<book>
  <chapter id="1">
    <mishna id="1">If a mavoy [an alleyway onto which courtyards open] - that [has an entrance with an opening that] is higher than twenty amot [a specific unit of length], one must lower [it in order to separate the mavoy from the public domain]. Rabbi Yehuda says it is not necessary. And if it is wider than ten amot, one must narrow [it in order to separate the mavoy from the public domain]. If there is a tsurat hapetach [two uprights and a crossbar, however slight, halachically effecting a doorway], even though [the entrance] is wider than ten amot, it is not necessary to narrow it.</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">The required preparation of a mavoy [to consider its fourth side as separated from the public domain]: Beit Shammai says, "A lechi [A vertical strip at the side of an entrance to a mavoy which permits carrying on Shabbat in the mavoy] and a beam [on top of the entrance]." Beit Hillel says, "A lechi or a beam." Rabbi Eliezer says, "Two lechi." In the name of Rabbi Yishmael, said one student in front of Rabbi Akiva, "Beit Shammai and Beit Hillel did not disagree about [an entrance of] a mavoy that is narrower than four amot, that it is [adequately separated] with either a lechi or a beam. About what did they disagree? About [an entrance of a mavoy] that is from four to ten amot; Beit Shammai says, '[It needs] a lechi and a beam,' but Beit Hillel says, 'Either a lechi or a beam.'" Rabbi Akiva says, "They disagreed about this and that."</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">The beam that they spoke [about, must be] wide enough to hold an ariach, and an ariach is half a brick [with a whole brick having the width] of three tefachim [a specific unit of length]. It is enough for the beam to be a tefach wide so that it can hold an ariach sideways.</mishna>
    <mishna id="4">[The beam must be] wide enough to hold an ariach and strong enough to hold an ariach. Rabbi Yehuda says, "[It  must only be] wide [enough], even though it is not strong [enough to hold an ariach]."</mishna>
    <mishna id="5">If [the beam] is [made of] stubble or reeds, we view it as if it were [made out of] metal. [If it is] bent, we view it as if it were straight. [If it is] rounded, we view it as if it were squared off. Anything [round] that has a circumference of three tefachim has a width of one tefach.</mishna>
    <mishna id="6">The lechayayin that they spoke [about], their height [must be] ten tefachim, and their width and thickness can be anything. Rabbi Yose says, "Their width must be three tefachim."</mishna>
    <mishna id="7">We can make a lechi from anything - even out of a living thing but Rabbi Yose forbids [doing that]. And [a living thing that is used as a grave cover] imparts impurity according to [the laws of] a grave cover, but Rabbi Meir renders it pure. We [can] write a bill of divorce on [a living animal] but Rabbi Yose Haglili disqualifies [such a bill of divorce].</mishna>
    <mishna id="8">If a caravan is camped in a valley and they encircled [the camp] with animal tack; we can carry within [that perimeter], but only if the fence [made from the tack] is ten tefachim  high and the gaps aren't more than the walls. Any gap that is [up to] ten amot is permitted because it is like an opening [doorway]; larger than that is forbidden.</mishna>
    <mishna id="9">We may surround [an area] with three ropes, one on top of the other, but only if there is not [a gap of] three tefachim  between one rope and another. The required size of the ropes and their width must be more than a tefach, so that the whole thing be ten tefachim.</mishna>
    <mishna id="10">We surround an area with reeds, but only if there is not [a gap of] three tefachim  between one reed and another. They spoke [about allowing these leniencies specifically] concerning a caravan - so says Rabbi Yehuda. The Sages say, "They were only talking about a caravan in the present case [as an example]." Any mechitza [legal partition] which is not [made of] vertical and horizontal [parts] is not a mechitza - so says Rabbi Yose ben Rabbi Yehuda. The Sages say, "[Only] one of [those] two things [is required]." [The Rabbis] gave dispensation for four things in an army camp: We can take wood from any place, we are exempt from hand-washing; from [the prohibition to eat] demai [produce from which it is uncertain whether tithes were already taken]; and from the requirement to make an eruv [halachic merging of separate domains by means of setting aside an amount of food in a designated place][in order to carry within the camp].</mishna>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="2">
    <mishna id="1">We [may] make pasin [L-shaped quasi-partitions which permit drawing water from wells in the public domain]  for wells [in order for the the well and the area around it to be considered a single domain: the pasin must be made of] four double boards, [placed at the corners of the well so] that [they] appear like eight - so says Rabbi Yehuda. Rabbi Meir says, "Eight [boards must be used], which appear like twelve, [namely] four double boards and four single ones." Their height must be ten tefachim [a specific unit of length] and their width six [tefachim], and their thickness anything and [the gap] between them [must not be wider] than the width of two teams of cattle, each team consisting of three cattle - so says Rabbi  Meir. Rabbi Yehuda says, "[Each team] of four." [The width is the space taken by cattle] yoked together and not unyoked, [in such a way that when] one [team] enters, [the other] one exits.</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">It is permitted to move the [pasin] closer to the well, but only if the cow's head and the greater part of its body is within [them] as it drinks. It is permitted to move [the pasin] away from the well, but only if one adds more pasin.</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">Rabbi Yehuda said, "[The distance from the well, at which it is permitted to place the pasin is] up until beit se'atayim [a measure of area, equivalent to that area of land large enough to require a  se'atayim of seeds to sow it]." [The Sages] said to him, "They didn't say beit se'atayim except concerning a garden or a karpef [an enclosed area outside of a town or village], but if [the area that was being enclosed] was a pen or a fold or a field [behind the house] or a yard [in front of the house], even if is five beit kor [the same as a beit se'atayim but for a  kor of seeds], even if it is ten beit kor, it is permissible [to set up pasin around it]. It is permitted to distance [the pasin] any amount, but only if one adds more pasin."</mishna>
    <mishna id="4">Rabbi Yehuda said, "If a public thoroughfare intersects the pasin, one should move it to [one of] the sides." The sages say, "It is not necessary." It is the same [if it is a] public cistern or a public well  or a private well, we [only need to] make pasin for them; but for a private cistern, we make a [full] mechitza [legal partition] of ten tefachim [a specific unit of length] - so says Rabbi Akiva. Rabbi Yehuda ben Baba says, "We can only make pasin for a public well, but for all others we [are required to] make a [full] partition ten tefachim high."</mishna>
    <mishna id="5">Rabbi Yehuda ben Baba also said, "If a garden or karpef be  seventy amot [specific unit of length] and a bit [long] by seventy amot and a bit  [wide and] is encircled by a fence ten amot high, we [may] move [carry things] within it, but only if there is a guardbooth or dwelling within it, or if it is close to the town." Rabbi Yehuda said, "Even if there is nothing within it except a cistern or a ditch or a cave, we [may] move [carry things] within it." Rabbi Akiva says, "Even if there is not [even] one of all these [items] within it, we [may] move [carry things] within it, but only if it [is no more than] seventy amot and a bit [long] by seventy amot and a bit  [wide]." Rabbi Eliezer said, "If its length exceeds its width by even a single amah, we do not move [carry things] within it [as it would be forbidden]."  Rabbi Yose says, "Even if its length is twice its width, we [may] move [carry things] within it."</mishna>
    <mishna id="6">Rabbi Elai said, "I heard from Rabbi Eliezer, 'Even [if a garden or a karpef is as large as] a beit kor [it is permitted to move things within it].' I also heard from him, 'If one of the householders of a courtyard had forgotten, and did not [participate in] the eruv [halachic merging of separate domains by means of setting aside an amount of food in a designated place], it is forbidden for him to carry any thing out of, or into, his house; but for them [the other residents of the courtyard] it is permitted  [to do so].' I also heard from him, 'We [may] fulfill our obligation [to eat bitter herbs] on Passover with akrvanim [a type of green].' And I searched among all his disciples and sought a companion [who had likewise heard him expound these positions], but I could not find [any one]."</mishna>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="3">
    <mishna id="1">We may use all [food and drink] to make an eruv [halachic merging of separate domains by means of setting aside an amount of food in a designated place] or a shituf [ the same as an eruv when connecting different alleys and streets], exception for water and except for salt. And all [food and drink] may be bought with money [that must be used on food or drink in place] of ma'aser [sheni] [the second tithe of produce, which must be taken to Jerusalem and consumed there],  except for water and except for salt. Someone who has vowed [to abstain] from food is permitted [to partake] of water and salt. We [may] make an eruv for a nazir [a person who vows to avoid corpse impurity, refrain from cutting his hair and abstain from all grape products] with wine [even though he is prohibited from drinking it], and for a [common] Israelite with terumah [a portion of a crop given to a Kohen which becomes holy upon separation, and can only be consumed by Kohanim or their household][even though he is prohibited from eating it]. Sumchos said, "[We can only make an eruv for an Israelite] with chulin [produce or food permitted for general consumption]." And [we may place the eruv] of a Kohen [member of priestly caste, subgroup of tribe of Levi, uniquely responsible for maintaining and carrying out the sacrificial services in the Temple] in a Beit Haperas [a field in which a grave has been plowed over]. Rabbi Yose says, "[We can] even [place it]  in a graveyard, because he [the Kohen] may go outside [the graveyard] and eat [it]."</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">We may make an eruv with demai [produce from which it is uncertain whether tithes were already taken]; and with ma'aser rishon [the first tithe of produce, which must be given to the Levi] from which terumah  has been taken; and with ma'aser sheni and hekdesh [property, living or inanimate, devoted by its owner for sacred purposes, by which action he ceases to be its owner] which have been redeemed; and for Kohanim with challah [a portion of a batch of bread dough given to a Kohen which becomes holy upon separation, and can only be consumed by Kohanim or their household], and with terumah. But [we may] not [make an eruv] with tevel [produce from which the various tithes have not yet been separated]; and not with ma'aser rishon, from which terumah has not been taken; or with ma'aser sheni and hekdesh which have not been redeemed. If someone sends his eruv via the hand of a deaf and dumb person, a mental retard, a minor or one who does not acknowledge [the legal validity of] an eruv, it is not [considered] an eruv: but if he has told another person [not of the categories just mentioned] to receive it from [his messenger from those categories], behold it is [considered] an eruv.</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">If he has put [his eruv] in a tree, if [the eruv was placed] higher than ten tefachim [a specific unit of length] [from the ground], it is not [considered] an eruv; [but if he puts it] lower than ten tefachim, it is [considered] an eruv. If he has put it into a pit, even if it is a hundred amot [a specific unit of length] deep, his eruv is [considered] an eruv. If he put it on the top of a cane or pole, in the case that it is detached [from actually growing in the ground but] is stuck [therein], even [if it is] a hundred amot high, behold it is [considered] an eruv. If he put it into a closet [which he locked] and lost the key, behold it is [considered] an eruv. Rabbi Eliezer says, "If he does not know that the key is in its place, it is not [considered] an eruv."</mishna>
    <mishna id="4">If the eruv rolled out of the techum [the area around a person or community within which it is permissible to travel on Shabbat], or if a heap [of stones] fell on it, or if it got burned, or if [it was] terumah and became impure; [if any of these happen] while [it is] yet day, [before the Shabbat comes in], it is not [considered] an eruv; [but if it happens] after it got dark, behold it is [considered] an eruv. If there is a doubt [about the time when it happened], Rabbi Meir and Rabbi Yehuda say, "This is [like at once driving] an ass [and leading a] camel [which make the person get stuck between them]." Rabbi Yose and Rabbi Shimon say, "An eruv about which there is a doubt is [considered] valid." Rabbi Yose further said, "Avtulmos testified, in the name of five elders, that an eruv about which there is a doubt is [considered] valid."</mishna>
    <mishna id="5">A man may make his eruv conditional and say, "If [hostile] gentiles come from the east, my eruv [shall extend my techum] to the west; [if they come] from the west, my eruv [shall extend my techum] to the east; if they come from both directions, I [will be permitted to] go to the place [direction] that I want; [if] they don't come from either direction, I am like [the rest of] my townsmen [concerning the preexisting techum]; should a sage come from the east, my eruv [shall extend my techum] to the east; [should one come] from the west, my eruv [shall extend my techum] to the west; [if one] come from each direction, I [will be permitted to] go to the place [direction] that I want; [if] none [come] from either direction, I am like the rest of my townsmen [concerning the preexisting techum]." Rabbi Yehuda says, "If one of them [the two sages who come] was his teacher, he goes to his teacher; and if both were his teachers, he [will be permitted to] go to the place [direction] that he wants."</mishna>
    <mishna id="6">Rabbi Eliezer says, "[In the case of] a festival that is adjacent to a Shabbat, whether [it is] before it or after it, a man may set two eruvin, and say, 'My first eruv [shall extend my techum] to the east, and the second [one] to the west; the first [one] to the west, and the second [one] to the east; my eruv [is for] the first [day], and the second [day I am] like my townsmen; my eruv [is  for] the second [day], and the first [day I am] like my townsmen.'" But the sages say, "He can [only] set his eruv for one direction, or he can not set his eruv at all; he can [only] set his eruv for both days, or he can not set his eruv at all. How should he do [it]? He carries it [the eruv] out [to the place where he means to set it] on the [eve of the] first [day], and remains with it until dark and [then] he takes it and comes [back]; he [brings the eruv out again] on the second [day], remains with it until dark, and then eats it. It comes out [that in this way] he gains in his walking [beyond the preexisting techum], and he gains in [eating] his eruv. If [his eruv] is eaten on the first [day] his eruv is [considered an eruv] for the first [day], but is not [considered] an eruv for the second [day]." Rabbi Eliezer said to them, "[That means that] you admit to me that [an adjacent holiday and Shabbat] are two [distinct] realms of holiness."</mishna>
    <mishna id="7">Rabbi Yehuda says, "If one is afraid that Rosh Hashana will be extended [to two days], he may make two eruvin and say, 'My first eruv [shall extend my techum] to the east, and the second [one] to the west; the first [one] to the west, and the second [one] to the east; my eruv [is for] the first [day], and the second [day I am] like my townsmen; my eruv [is  for] the second [day], and the first [day I am] like my townsmen.'" But the Sages did not concede to him.</mishna>
    <mishna id="8">And Rabbi Yehuda also said, "A man may conditionally [tithe] the basket [of tevel produce] on the first festival day [of Rosh HaShanah], and eat it on the second [day]; and so too, an egg which is laid on the first [day] may be eaten on the second." But the Sages did not concede to him.</mishna>
    <mishna id="9">Rabbi Dosa ben Harkinus says, "He who [stands] before the reading-desk [to lead the prayers] on the [first] festival day of Rosh Hashana, should say, 'Strengthen [support] us, Lord our God, on this day of Rosh Chodesh, whether today or tomorrow [be the true one].' And on the next day he says [the same prayer, with the variation], 'whether this day or yesterday [be the true one].'" But the Sages did not concede to him.</mishna>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="4">
    <mishna id="1">If [hostile] gentiles, or an evil spirit [a fit of insanity], caused a man to go out [of the techum - the area around a person or community within which it is permissible to travel on Shabbat], he must not [when recovering his own free agency] move further than four amot [a specific unit of length]; if they [the gentiles or the fit] bring him back [within the techum], it is as if he had not gone out. If they carried him into another town, or put him into a pen or fold [for cattle], Rabban Gamaliel, and Rabbi Eliezer ben Azariah say, "He may walk [throughout] all of it." But Rabbi Yehoshua and Rabbi Akiva say, "He only has  four amot within which to move." It once happened that they [these four sages] came from Perendisin, and their ship went out to sea [on Shabbat]: Rabban Gamliel and Rabbi Eliezer ben Azariah walked [throughout] all of [the vessel]; but Rabbi Yehoshua and Rabbi Akiva did not move beyond four amot, since they wanted to be strict upon themselves.</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">Once [on a Shabbat-eve] they [the above Sages were on board a ship that] did not enter the harbor until it became dark; they said to Rabban Gamaliel, "What are we [to do, regarding] descending [from the ship]?" He said [back] to them, "You are permitted; for I already observed that we had entered [within] the techum before it got dark."</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">He who went out [of the techum] with permission [of the Rabbis on an important matter], and they said to him, "The thing has already been done," has [is allowed to go] two thousand amot in any direction. If he was still within the techum, it is as if he had not gone out; since all those who go out to save [lives] are [permitted to] return to their place [on Shabbat].</mishna>
    <mishna id="4">He who sat down on the road [towards dusk on the Shabbat-eve], and [then] stood up and saw, behold, he is near a town, since it had not been his intention to [enter the town], he may not enter - so says Rabbi Meir; Rabbi Yehuda says, "He may enter." Rabbi Yehuda said, "It once happened that Rabbi Tarfon entered [a town], without [the] intention  [to do so]."</mishna>
    <mishna id="5">He who fell asleep on the road [towards dusk on the Shabbat-eve], and did not know that it had become dark [night had set in], has [the right to move] two thousand amot in any direction. - so says Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri. The Sages say, "He only has [the right to move within] four amot." Rabbi Eliezer says, "And he is in [forms] the center [of these four amot]." Rabbi Yehuda says, "He can go [four amot] in whichever direction he pleases." But Rabbi Yehuda conceded, that if he [that person] chose [a direction] for himself, he may not [afterwards] go back upon it [and change his mind].</mishna>
    <mishna id="6">If there were two [people situated in such a way] that part of the four amot [permitted] to each are within the limits of the other, they may take and eat their meal in the middle [within their joint space]; but only if neither of them take out [his food] from his [limits] and into those of his fellow. If there were three [people so situated], and [the four amot belonging to] the middle one is subsumed by them [forms part of the limits belonging to each of the two outer ones], he is permitted [to bring food to a common space and eat] with them, and they are permitted  [to bring food to a common space and eat] with him; but the two outer ones are forbidden [to bring food together to a common space and eat] with each other. Rabbi Shimon says, "What is this like? [It is like] three courtyards that open into each other and [also] open into the public domain; if the two [outer] ones have made an eruv [halachic merging of separate domains by means of setting aside an amount of food in a designated place] with the middle one, [the middle courtyard] is permissible to [carry to and from] them, and them [from and into] it; but the two outer ones are forbidden one to the other."</mishna>
    <mishna id="7">He who came upon the road, and it was becoming dark [on the Shabbat eve], if he recognized [singled out] a tree or hedge, and said, "Under it [I will take] my Shabbat rest," [it is as if] he did not say anything. [But if he said], "At its trunk [I will take] my Shabbat rest," he may go from the spot of his feet [where he is standing] to its trunk, [up to] two thousand amot, and from its trunk to his home two thousand amot [more]; it comes out that, after it got dark, he may go four thousand amot.</mishna>
    <mishna id="8">If he did not recognize [single out a tree or a hedge], or is not conversant with the halacha, and says, "[I will take] my Sabbath rest on my place [where I stand]," the place [where he stands] obtains for him two thousand amot in every direction; in a circle - so says Rabbi Hanina ben Antigonus. But the Sages say, "[Those two thousand amot are] squared [off] like a square table, in order that he gains the angles [the corners].</mishna>
    <mishna id="9">This is what [the Rabbis meant when they] said  a poor person may make an eruv with his feet. Rabbi Yehuda says, "Both a poor person and a wealthy one [may do so]; they did not say that we may make an eruv with bread except in order to unencumber the wealthy person, that he need not go out and make an eruv with his feet [by walking to it.]"</mishna>
    <mishna id="10">He who [on the eve of Shabbat has been dispatched by his townsmen and] goes out to another town that is usually combined to his by means of an eruv [in order to set the eruv] and is brought back [advised to return] by his fellow [before he has completed his errand], he is permitted to go [to the second town]; but all his townsmen are forbidden [to go there] - so says Rabbi Yehuda. Rabbi Meir says, "Whoever can make an eruv but does not make an eruv is [like at once driving] an ass [and leading a] camel [which make the person get stuck between them]."</mishna>
    <mishna id="11">He who went out [beyond] the techum, even [the distance of] one amah, may not re-enter [the techum]. Rabbi Eliezer says, "[If he has gone] two amot [beyond the techum] he may re-enter; [but if] three, he may not re-enter." Rabbi Shimon says, "Even [if he goes] fifteen amot [beyond the techum] he may re-enter, since the land-surveyors [who fix the techum] are not very exact in the measurements, because [they are concerned about] those who err [and might otherwise overshoot the techum."</mishna>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="5">
    <mishna id="1">How can the boundaries of a town be enlarged [extended]? If one house recede and [another] house jut out, or one attachment recede and [another] attachment jut out, or fragments of a wall ten tefachim [a specific unit of length] high [that jut out], or if there be any bridges or monuments [a section of which juts out], with dwelling-houses thereon, the measurement of the town goes out in front of [their outermost point]; and we make [the area that extends to its sides]  like a type of square table ,in order that it gains the angles [the corners].</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">We give [an allowance for] a karpef [an enclosed area outside of a town or village] to [extend the boundaries of] a town - so says Rabbi Meir. But the Sages say, "[The Rabbis] didn't say [that there is an allowance for a] karpef  except [when it would be] between two towns; if the one has [up to] seventy and a fraction amot [a specific unit of length] outside of it and the other one [also] has [up to] seventy and a fraction amot outside of it [such that there is one hundred and forty one and a third amot from the end of one town to the other; in that case] one makes [the allowance of] a karpef for both of them, so that they become as one."</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">And so too, if three villages form a triangle, and the two outer ones have one hundred and forty one and a third amot between them, the [third] one between them [makes] the three of them become as one.</mishna>
    <mishna id="4">They are not to measure [the techum - the area around an individual or community within which it is permissible to carry on Shabbat], except with a rope [exactly] fifty amot, not shorter and not longer; and he [who measures] must not measure except from in front of his heart [his chest]. If he was measuring and reached a valley or [an obstruction], he incorporates it [by measuring above it in a straight line] and resumes his [standard procedure of] measurement; if he reached a mountain, he incorporates it [by measuring above it in a straight line] and resumes his [standard procedure of] measurement, so long as he does not step out of the techum [in doing so]. If he cannot incorporate it [by measuring above it in a straight line because it is too high], Rabbi Dostai bar Yannai said of such [a circumstance] in the name of Rabbi Meir, "I have heard that they [who measure] cut straight through mountains."</mishna>
    <mishna id="5">We don't measure except [by using] an expert [surveyor. If the techum has been measured] farther in one place, and closer in another, we follow the farther [measurement]. If one [surveyor has measured the limit] farther and another [has measured it] closer, we follow the farther [measurement]. Even a slave or a maidservant is [considered] reliable [if either] say, "Until here is the techum of Shabbat;" for the Rabbis did not say the matter [the laws of techumim] to be strict but [rather] to be lenient.</mishna>
    <mishna id="6">If a town [originally the property] of a single individual, becomes [the property] of the many, we make an eruv for all of it [meaning that all of the householders residing there should participate in making it. If a town originally the property] of the many, becomes [the property] of one individual, we don't make an eruv for all of it [meaning the householders residing there may not participate in making it], unless [a number of dwellers who live adjacent] be left out, [that number being] like the town, Chadasha in Yehuda, in which there are fifty dwellings - so says Rabbi Yehuda. Rabbi Shimon says, "[It is sufficient if] three courtyards of two houses [each are left out]."</mishna>
    <mishna id="7">He who was [on the eve of Shabbat] to the east [of his habitation], and says to his son, "Place my eruv to the west;" or [being] to the west [of his habitation], and says to his son, "Place my eruv to the east;" if there is from him [the place where he is standing] to his home [no more than] two thousand amot, and if there is more than that to his eruv, he is permitted [to use the techum of] his house, but forbidden [to use the techum of] his eruv; [if the distance] to his eruv is [no more than] two thousand amot, and if there is more than that to his home, he is permitted [to use the techum of] his eruv, but forbidden [to use the techum of] his home. If he placed his eruv within the extension of the town, he has not done [anything], and it is not anything; if he has placed it [the eruv] out of the techum, even one amah, whatever [extent of ground] he gains [in this direction], he loses [in the opposite one].</mishna>
    <mishna id="8">The inhabitants of a large town may traverse the whole of a small town [that lies within their techum], but the inhabitants of the small [town] may not traverse the whole of the large town [that is only partially within their techum]. How is this? He who was in the large town and placed his eruv in the small town, or in the small town and placed his eruv in the large town, may traverse all of the town wherein he has placed his eruv and two thousand amot beyond it. Rabbi Akiva says, "He only has [the right to walk] two thousand amot from the place where he deposited his eruv."</mishna>
    <mishna id="9">Rabbi Akiva said to them [the Sages], "Will you not concede to me, [in the case of] he who places his eruv in a cave, that he has not [the right to walk] further than two thousand amot [from his eruv]?" They said to him "[True; but] when is this the case? If there are no dwellings within [the cave]; but if there are dwellings within it, he may traverse the whole of the cave and [also] two thousand amot outside of it. It comes out that the [law pertaining to the] interior [of a cave] is more lenient than the [law pertaining to the the space] above it. As to the one who measures [a techum of  two thousand amot] that they spoke about, he is only allowed two thousand amot [from the place where he started], even though the end of his measurement should terminate in a cave."</mishna>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="6">
    <mishna id="1">Someone who dwells [together] in a courtyard with a gentile, or with someone who does not acknowledge [the validity of] an eruv [the halachic merging of separate domains by means of setting aside an amount of food in a designated place], behold [the residence there of] such [an individual] forbids hims [from carrying there] - so says Rabbi Meir. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaacov says, "[Truly such an individual's residence] does not forbid him, until there are [also]  two Israelites [the residence of which] forbid each other."</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">Said Rabban Gamliel, "It happened that a Sadducee dwelt with us in a mavoy [an alleyway onto which courtyards open] in Jerusalem; and father said to us [on the Shabbat eve], 'Hurry and take out all the vessels into the mavoy, before [the Sadducee] brings out [his], and [by so doing] forbids it to you [to carry there].'" Rabbi Yehudah says [it] with a variation in the language: "Hurry and do [take care of] your needs in  the mavoy, before [the Sadducee] brings out [his vessels], and [by so doing] forbids it to you [to carry there].'"</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">If one of the householders of a courtyard forget, and not join in the eruv, it is forbidden for him and for them [the other residents of the courtyard] to carry into or out of his home; but their [homes] are permissible for him and for them [to carry into and out of]; if they [the other residents] gave him their [rights to the courtyard], he is permitted [to carry in and out of it], but they are forbidden [to do so]. If there were two [householders who have neglected to join in the eruv], they [by so doing] forbid each other [from carrying to  and from their homes], since one [individual] can give [his rights to the courtyard], and can acquire [the rights of others to the courtyard]; but two [though they can jointly] give [their rights], cannot [jointly] acquire [the rights of others to the use of the courtyard].</mishna>
    <mishna id="4">[Until] when may we give [our rights to the courtyard]? Beit Shammai says, "While it is still day [before the onset of Shabbat]." But Beit Hillel says, "[Even] from dusk." He who gives his [rights to the courtyard], and [afterwards] carries out [into or from the courtyard], whether inadvertently or intentionally, behold [by so doing] he forbids [the other residents of the courtyard from carrying into or out of it] - so says Rabbi Meir. Rabbi Yehuda says, "[If he does it] intentionally, he forbids [it for them]; inadvertently, he does not forbid [it]."</mishna>
    <mishna id="5">If a householder was a partner in [one cask of] wine with two of his neighbors [residing in the same  mavoy], they are not required to make an eruv [technically, a shituf, which is its equivalent, in order to carry into the mavoy]; if he is [a partner] with one in wine, and with one in oil, they are required to make an eruv. Rabbi Shimon says, "In the one [case] as in the other, they do not require an eruv."</mishna>
    <mishna id="6">If five [different] groups took their Shabbat-rest in one chamber [large hall], Beit Shammai says, "A [separate] eruv should be made for each and every group." But Beit Hillel says, "One eruv [is sufficient] for [them] all." And [Beit Hillel] concedes, that when some of these groups occupy distinct rooms, or attics, [then] they require a [separate] eruv for each and every group.</mishna>
    <mishna id="7">If brothers or partners eat at their father's [or at one] table, but [each] sleep in their [separate] homes [in the same courtyard], they are each and every one required to [individually participate in the] eruv. Therefore, if one of them forgot, and did not [participate in the] eruv, he [should] nullify his [rights to the common courtyard]. When [is this the case?] When they place their eruv in another place; but if the eruv has come to [have been placed with] them, or if there are no other dwellings in the courtyard, they need not [participate in or] make an eruv.</mishna>
    <mishna id="8">If five courtyards open into one another, and [also] open into the mavoy, if they [the householders therein] made eruvin for the courtyards, but did not make a shituf [an eruv used to join together alleys and streets] for the  mavoy, they are permitted [to carry to and from] the courtyards, but are prohibited [to do so] in the mavoy; but if they made a shituf in the mavoy, they are permitted in both [the courtyards and the mavoy]. If they made an eruv for the courtyards and a shituf for the mavoy, if one of the householders of the courtyards forgot and did not participate in the eruv, they are [nevertheless] permitted [to carry] in both [the courtyards and the mavoy]; if one of the householders of the mavoy forgot to participate in the shituf, they are permitted [to carry] in the courtyards, but are forbidden [to do so] in the mavoy, since the mavoy is [in the same relation] to the courtyards, as the courtyards [are] to the homes [within them].</mishna>
    <mishna id="9">If there are two courtyards, one which is behind the other, if the [residents of the] inner courtyard made an eruv, and [those of] the outer courtyard did not make an eruv, [the residents of] the inner courtyard are permitted [to carry to and from it], but [those of] the outer courtyard are forbidden [to do so]; if [those of] the outer [courtyard made an eruv], but [those of] the inner [courtyard did] not, both [courtyards] are prohibited; if each made its own eruv, the [residents of] each are permitted [to carry to and from] its own [courtyard]. Rabbi Akiva forbids the outer courtyard [in that case], since the right of thoroughfare [possessed by the inner courtyard] forbids it. But the Sages say, "The right of thoroughfare does not forbid [the outer courtyard]."</mishna>
    <mishna id="10">If one [of the householders] of the outer courtyard forgot and did not participate in the eruv, the inner courtyard is permitted, but the outer courtyard is prohibited; if [one of the householders] of the inner courtyard [forgot and] did not participate in the eruv, both are prohibited. If [both courtyards] place their eruv in one place, and one [of the householders], whether from the inner or from the outer [courtyard], forgot and did not participate in the eruv,  both are prohibited. And if [each courtyard] belong to [single] individuals, they do need to make an eruv [in order to carry into and from their own courtyards].</mishna>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="7">
    <mishna id="1">If there is a window [opening] between two courtyards [that is] four [tefachim - a specific unit of length] by four [tefachim], and within ten [tefachim from the ground, the residents of each courtyard may] make two [separate] eruvin [the halachic merging of separate domains by means of setting aside an amount of food in a designated place]; or if they want, they may make one  eruv [together]. If the window be less than four by four, or above ten, they may make two  eruvin and may not make one eruv [together].</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">If there is a wall between two courtyards [that is] ten [tefachim] high and four [tefachim] wide, they [the residents of each courtyard] may make two  [separate] eruvin and may not make one eruv [together]. If there were fruit on top of [the wall], the [residents] from each side may go up and eat [them], but only if they don't bring [the fruit] down [from off the wall]. If the wall is breached [and has a gap] up until ten amot [a specific unit of length], they may make two eruvin; or if they want, they may make one  eruv [together], because it [the breach] is considered as an opening [doorway]. [Should the breach be] wider than this, they may make one eruv [together] and may not make two eruvin. </mishna>
    <mishna id="3">If there was a ditch between two courtyards [that is] ten [tefachim] deep, and four [tefachim] wide, they [the residents of each courtyard] may make two  [separate] eruvin and may not make one eruv [together], even if [the trench] is filled with stubble or with straw. If it is [however] filled with dirt or rocks, they may make one eruv [together] and may not make two eruvin. </mishna>
    <mishna id="4">If one places a board four tefachim wide over [the ditch], and likewise [if one does so between] two projecting balconies that face each other, [the residents of the courtyards] may make two eruvin; or if they want, they may make one  eruv [together; but if the board be] less [wide] than this, they may make two  eruvin and may not make one eruv [together]. </mishna>
    <mishna id="5">If there was a heap of straw between two courtyards ten tefachim high, [the residents of the courtyards] may make two  eruvin and may not make one eruv [together]. They may feed [their animals] from both sides. If the heap becomes lessened from being ten tefachim, they may make one eruv [together] and may not make two eruvin. </mishna>
    <mishna id="6">How do we make a shituf [an eruv used to join together alleys and streets] for a mavoy [an alleyway onto which courtyards open]? One places a cask of wine [in a designated place] and says, "Behold, this is [the possession] of all the residents of the mavoy;" and he may give them rights [to the wine] through [the agency of] his grown-up son or daughter, through his Hebrew slave or maid-servant, or through his wife; but he may not give them rights [to the wine] through [the agency of] his minor son or daughter, or through his Canaanite slave or maid-servant, because their hand [agency] is [limited to be] like his [and so they cannot acquire anything from him].</mishna>
    <mishna id="7">If the [quantity of] food [required for the shituf] becomes lessened, he may  [himself] add [to it], and give [the other residents] rights [to this addition], and he need not inform [them]; if [new residents of the courtyard] were added to [the previous ones], he may  [himself] add [sufficient food to make up the quantity required], and give them rights [to this addition], and he must inform [them].</mishna>
    <mishna id="8">How much is [the] required quantity [of food to make a shituf]? When they [the residents] are numerous, nourishment [that is sufficient] for [one person eating] two meals [is sufficient] for all of them; when they are few, the size of a dried fig - [which is also the quantity of food prohibited] to carry out on Shabbat - for each and every one of them.</mishna>
    <mishna id="9">Rabbi Yose said, "To what does this [preceding law] apply? To the beginning of the eruv [when it is first made]; but to remnants of the eruv [later when some of it has been lessened], any quantity [is sufficient]." And the Rabbis did not say to make an eruv for [several] courtyards [where it is already subsumed by a shituf], except so that the children not forget [the concept of an eruv].</mishna>
    <mishna id="10">We may use all [food and drink] to make an eruv or a shituf, except for water and except for salt - these are the words of Rabbi  Eliezer. Rabbi Yehoshua says, "[Nothing but] a [whole] loaf of bread is [considered an] eruv. Even if one bakes a [whole] se'ah [a specific unit of volume of flour] but it is a portion [and not a whole loaf], we may not make an eruv with it; [whereas] a [small] loaf made from [flour bought with] an issar [a specific unit of money], and it is whole, we may make an eruv with it."</mishna>
    <mishna id="11">A man may give [money] to a storekeeper or baker, in order that [the latter] acquire him rights in the eruv - so says Rabbi Eliezer. But the Sages say, "His money did not acquire him rights [in the eruv]." But they concede that [if he has given] his money to any other person [to be his agent], it will acquire for him rights [in the eruv; though in the case of a shopkeeper or baker it will not be effective] since we cannot [participate in] an eruv for [another] man without his knowledge. Rabbi Yehuda said, "To what does this [preceding law] apply? In eruvin of techumim [areas around  individuals or communities within which it is permissible to travel on Shabbat]; but in eruvin of courtyards, we may [participate in] an eruv [for another man] with his knowledge or without his knowledge; since we may confer rights on a man not in his presence, whereas, we may not confer obligations on a man not in his presence"</mishna>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="8">
    <mishna id="1">How are techumin [the area around a person or community within which it is permissible to travel on Shabbat] to be combined? A man places a cask [of wine, oil or food], and says, "Behold this is for all my townsmen, for all who go to the house of mourning, or to the house of feasting." Whoever accepted upon himself [to make use of this and carry in the combined techumim] while it is yet day [before Shabbat], is permitted [to carry in the enlarged area; but if he does so ] after dark, he is forbidden [from doing so], because one cannot create an eruv [halachic merging of separate domains by means of setting aside an amount of food in a designated place] after dark.</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">How much is its legal quantity [of food required to effect the combination of techumim]? Food for two meals for every one [who participates], for weekday meals, but not for Shabbat meals – so says Rabbi Meir. Rabbi Yehuda says, “For Shabbat meals, but not for weekday meals;” and both intend to render lenient decisions. Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka says, “[It is sufficient to effect the combination if each person has] a loaf [that is sold] for a fundyon [a specific amount of money], when the price of four se'in [a specific unit of volume] of flour is one sela [a specific amount of money].” Rabbi Shimon says, “two-thirds of a loaf [such as is produced when making] three [loaves] with one kav [a specific unit of volume] of flour. [The time it takes to eat] half [of such a loaf is the time that it takes for someone’s clothes to become impure] in a leprous house; and [impure food that is] the half of a half [of the quantity needed to make such a loaf will suffice] to make the body [of a priest] unfit [for the consumption of terumah – a portion of a crop given to a Kohen which becomes holy upon separation, and can only be consumed by Kohanim or their household].”</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">If the [other]  inhabitants of a courtyard and the inhabitants of a gallery [in the courtyard] forgot to make an eruv [the halachic merging of separate domains by means of setting aside an amount of food in a designated place], whatever is above ten tefachim high [from the ground] is considered as belonging to the gallery; and whatever is less than ten tefachim high [from the ground] is considered as belonging to the courtyard. [If either] the ring of [dirt surrounding] a cistern, or a stone [be] ten tefachim high, [it belongs] to the gallery; [but if] less than this [it belongs] to the courtyard. When is this the case [that the ring or stone can be considered as belonging to the gallery]? When [the ring or stone is] close [to the gallery], but if [they are] separated, even though it is ten tefachim high, [it belongs] to the courtyard. What is [considered as] close? Whatever is less distant than four tefachim.</mishna>
    <mishna id="4">One who places his eruv [in order to permit carrying in the courtyard] in a gateway [porter's lodge], in a portico [entry hall], or in a gallery, it is not [considered] an eruv; and if one lives there [even if has not joined in the eruv], he cannot forbid [the courtyard] to [its owner, meaning he does not prevent the courtyard’s other resident or residents from carrying within it. If one places his eruv] in a straw warehouse, in a barn, in a wood-shed, or in a granary, it is [considered] an eruv; and if one lives there [if he has not joined in the eruv], he forbids the courtyard to [its owner to carry there]. Rabbi Yehuda says, "If the owner [of the courtyard] has reserved to himself the right of keeping his utensils there [in such a space that is being rented out], he [the renter who does not participate in the eruv] does not forbid the courtyard to [its owner to carry there]."</mishna>
    <mishna id="5">If a person leaves his house, and goes to spend Shabbat in another town [without joining in the eruv], whether he be a gentile or an Israelite, he forbids the courtyard [for the other residents to carry in] – so says Rabbi Meir. Rabbi Yehuda says, "He does not forbid it." Rabbi Yose says, "A gentile forbids it [in such a case], but an Israelite does not, as it is not the custom of an Israelite to return on the Shabbat." Rabbi Shimon says, "Even though he has left his house, and went to spend Shabbat with his daughter in the same town, he does not forbid [the courtyard], since he has in thought renounced [habitation in his house for that Shabbat]."</mishna>
    <mishna id="6">If a cistern is between two courtyards, we may not draw water from it on Shabbat, unless there is a mechitza [legal partition] ten tefachim high, either above [at the top of the cistern] or below [within the water], or in the basin. Rabbi Shimon ben Gamliel says, "Beit Shammai says, '[The mechitza must be made] below [within the water];' but Beit Hillel says, 'Above [on top the well].'" Said Rabbi Yehuda, "The mechitza is not greater [more effective] than the wall which is between [the two courtyards]."</mishna>
    <mishna id="7">If a streamlet of water runs through a courtyard, we may not draw water from it, unless there is a mechitza ten tefachim high, where it [the streamlet] flows in [to the courtyard], and [another] where it flows out [again]. Rabbi Yehudah says, "The wall above it is to be considered a mechitza." Rabbi Yehuda [further] said, "It so happened, that, in [the town of] Ebal, they drew water from a streamlet on Shabbat, with the sanction of the Elders." [The Sages] said [back] to him, "[That was] because it did not hold the legal size [of a karmelit – a rabbinically-defined domain which is neither a Biblically-defined public or private domain, in which and into which it is forbidden to carry on Shabbat]."</mishna>
    <mishna id="8">If there is a balcony over the water, we may not draw from it on Shabbat, unless a mechitza is made for it [that is] ten tefachim high, either above or below [the balcony]. And so too [is the law], if there are two balconies, one above the other. If [a mechitza] was made for the upper [balcony], but not for the lower [one], both are forbidden [to draw water], until they make  an eruv [and so combine the two areas].</mishna>
    <mishna id="9">If a courtyard is less than four [square] amot [a specific unit of length], we may not pour any water into it on Shabbat, unless a sewer be made that is capable of holding two seah below the outlet, either outside of, or within, the courtyard. If [however the sewer] be outside, it must be vaulted [over; whereas if it is] inside, it need not be vaulted [over].</mishna>
    <mishna id="10">Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says, "If a gutter is vaulted over [the length of] four amot in the public domain, we may pour into it on Shabbat." But the Sages say, "Even though the courtyard or the roof be one hundred amot long [and the gutter pass through that entire length], one may not pour [directly] into the gutter; but one may pour out from one roof to another, [so that] the water descends into the gutter." The portico [entrance hall] may be added to the [courtyard in computing the] four amot [mentioned in the preceding Mishna].</mishna>
    <mishna id="11">And so too, if there are two row houses facing each other [in one courtyard], and the residents of the one [row house] have made a sewer, but the residents of the other have not [joined in making it], those who made the sewer are permitted [to pour water down into the courtyard]; but those who did not make it are forbidden [from doing so]. </mishna>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="9">
    <mishna id="1">All the roofs of a town [form] one domain, so long as there isn't a roof, ten [tefachim - a specific unit of length] higher or ten [tefachim] lower [than the rest] - so says Rabbi Meir. But the Sages say, "Each and every [roof] is a domain by itself." Rabbi Shimon says, "Roofs, as well as courtyards as well as karpefot [enclosed areas outside of a town or village] are [considered] one domain for [the carrying of] all [such] utensils [as were actually] therein [when] the Shabbat [began], but not for those utensils [which were] in the house [when] the Shabbat [began]."</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">If a large roof adjoins onto a small one, the large [roof] is permitted [to carry from it to the house and from the house to it], but the small [roof] is prohibited  [to do so]; if a large courtyard is breached [and now opens] onto a small one,[the residents of] the large [courtyard] are permitted [to continue carrying to and from the courtyard], but [the residents of] the small [courtyard] are prohibited [to do so], because it [the breach] is considered as an opening [doorway] to the large [courtyard or roof]. If a courtyard is breached [and now opens] onto the public domain, one who carries from [the courtyard] into a private domain, or from a private domain into [the courtyard] is guilty [of violating a Torah prohibition] - so says Rabbi Eliezer. But the Sages say, "[One who carries] from [the courtyard] into the public domain, or from the public domain into [the courtyard] is absolved [from having violated a Torah prohibition]; since [now as a result of the breach] the courtyard is like a karmelit [A rabbinically-defined domain which is neither a Biblically-defined public or private domain, in which and into which it is forbidden to carry on Shabbat]."</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">If a courtyard is breached [on Shabbat and now opens onto the public domain] on two sides; or also if a house is breached [on Shabbat and now opens onto the public domain] on two sides; or also the entrance of a  mavoy [an alleyway onto which courtyards open], the beams and lechayayim [A vertical strip at the side of an entrance to a mavoy which permits carrying on Shabbat in the mavoy] of which have been removed [and so remove the separation between it and the public domain], it is permitted [to continue carrying to and from these places] on that [particular] Shabbat; but it is prohibited [to do so] for the future, [on any subsequent Shabbat] - so says Rabbi Yehuda. But Rabbi Yose says, "If they are permitted on that [particular] Sabbath, they are [also] permitted for the future; and if they are prohibited for the future, they are also prohibited on that [particular] Sabbath."</mishna>
    <mishna id="4">One who builds an attic over two houses [situated across from each other]; or also bridges which are open at both ends, we may carry under them on Shabbat - so says Rabbi Yehuda. But the Sages forbid it. And Rabbi Yehuda further said, "We can make an eruv [the halachic merging of separate domains by means of setting aside an amount of food in a designated place] in a mavoy that is open at both ends." But the Sages forbid it.</mishna>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="10">
    <mishna id="1">One who finds tefillin [on the road on Shabbat], must bring them in [into the town or village], one pair [consisting of one for the head and one for the arm] at a time. Rabban Gamliel says, "He must bring them in two pairs at a time." To what does this [previous law] apply? To old ones [such as have been already tied], but [if they be] new ones, he is absolved [from the obligation to bring them in to the town or village]. If he found [many tefillin] in pairs or all tied together, he must  remain with them until dusk  [when Shabbat ends], and [then] bring them [in]; but in [a time of] danger, he must [only] cover them and may [then continue to] walk on.</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">Rabbi Shimon says, "He must hand them to his fellow [who is next to him], and his fellow [hands them] to his fellow [who is next to him, and so on, from hand to hand], until [the tefilllin] reach the outmost courtyard [of the town or village]; and also, his child, [if, for example, it is born on the field or road on Shabbat], he must hand it to his fellow [who is next to him], and his fellow [hands it] to his fellow [who is next to him, and so on], even [if it have to pass through] a hundred [sets of hands]." Rabbi Yehuda says, "A man may hand a cask to his fellow [who is next to him], and his fellow [hands it] to his fellow [who is next to him, and so on], even beyond the techum [the area around a person or community within which it is permissible to travel on Shabbat]." The Sages said [back] to him, "[The cask] cannot move further than the allowance of its owners."</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">If one was reading from a book [a scroll] on the threshold [of the house], and the book [unrolls] from his hand, he may roll it [back] towards him. If he was reading on top of the roof [of the house], and the book unrolls from his hand; until it reaches ten tefachim [a specific unit of length][from the ground], he may roll it [back] towards him; from when it reaches ten tefachim, he must turn over the written side [downwards, to the wall, and leave it until nightfall]. Rabbi Yehuda says, "Even if it is [only] removed from the ground [a distance] like the breadth of a needle, he may roll it [back] towards him." Rabbi Shimon says, "Even if it is on the ground itself, he may roll it [back] towards him, since no shevut [restrictions established by the Sages regarding Shabbat to prevent violation of Torah-level Shabbat prohibitions, and to increase its sanctity] stands in front of [is not trumped by the respect due to] the Holy Writings."</mishna>
    <mishna id="4">If there is a ledge outside of a window [opening], we may place [things from the house there] and remove them [and bring them into the house] on Shabbat. A man may stand in the private domain, and [reach in and] move [things that are] in the public domain; [or he may stand] in a public domain, and [reach in and] move [things that are] in the private domain; so long as he [who is moving things in the public domain] not move them beyond four amot [a specific unit of length].</mishna>
    <mishna id="5">A man may not stand in a private domain and urinate into the public domain, [nor may he stand] in the public domain and urinate into a private domain. And also, he may not [stand in one domain and] spit [into another]. Rabbi Yehuda says, "Even from when the spit has been separated in his mouth, he may not walk four amot before he spits."</mishna>
    <mishna id="6">A man may not stand in a private domain and drink in the public domain, [nor stand] in the public domain and drink in a private domain, unless he places his head and the greater part of his body into the place where he drinks. And so also is [the law with respect] to a wine press. A man may collect [water dropping] from a drain spout below ten tefachim from the ground; but from a projecting spout [pipe], he may drink in any place [or way].</mishna>
    <mishna id="7">If there is a cistern that is in the public domain and its ring [of earth surrounding it] is ten tefachim high, if there is a window [opening] that is above it, we may draw water from [the cistern] on Shabbat. A dunghill in the public domain, which is ten tefachim high, if there is a window [opening] that is above it, we may pour water [onto the dunghill] on Shabbat.</mishna>
    <mishna id="8">If [branches of] a tree [droop], and cover the ground [around it], if the branches are not three tefachim from the ground, we may carry beneath it. If its roots [project and] are taller than three tefachim high from the ground, one may not sit on them. The door of a storage space, or thorn bunches [that are used to put] into gaps [in the wall to fill them up], or reed mats, may not be shut, unless they are [situated somewhat] above the ground.</mishna>
    <mishna id="9">A man may not stand in a private domain and [use a key] to open [a door] in the public domain, [nor may he stand] in the public domain, and [use a key] to open [a door] in a private domain, unless he has previously made a mechitza [legal partition] ten tefachim high [around the spot on which he stands] - so says Rabbi Meir. [The Sages] said [back] to him, it so happened in the stall-feeders’ market in Jerusalem, that they would lock up [their shops], and place the key in the window [opening] above the opening [doorway]." Rabbi Yose says, "It was in the wool-market."</mishna>
    <mishna id="10">If there is a loose bolt, with a knob to it, Rabbi Eliezer forbids [one to use it to lock the door of a building on Shabbat]: but Rabbi Yose permits [it]. Rabbi Eliezer said, "It happened in the synagogue in Tiberias that they were accustomed to [treat] it as permitted, until Rabban Gamliel and the elders came and forbade [it] to them." Rabbi Yose said, "[On the contrary;] as forbidden they were accustomed to [treat] it , until Rabban Gamliel and the elders came and permitted [it] to them."</mishna>
    <mishna id="11">If there is a loose bolt that [is fastened to a rope and part of it] drags [on the ground], we may [use it to] lock [a door] in the Temple, but not in the [rest of the] country; but a bolt that rests [completely on the floor] is forbidden in either place. Rabbi Yehuda says, "[Even] one that rests is permitted in the Temple, and one that drags [is permitted also] in the [rest of the] country."</mishna>
    <mishna id="12">We may refasten the lower hinge [of a door] in the Temple, but not in the [rest of the] country; but [to refasten] the upper [hinge] is forbidden in either place. Rabbi Yehuda says, "[Even] the upper one [may be refastened] in the Temple, and the lower one [also] in [the rest of the] country."</mishna>
    <mishna id="13">We may refashion a bandage [dressing] in the Temple, but not  in the [rest of the] country. [To put a new bandage] to begin with, is forbidden in either place. We may tie a string [of an instrument, which broke on Shabbat] in the Temple, but not in the [rest of the] country. [To tie a new string] to begin with, is forbidden in either place. We may cut [off] a wart in the Temple, but not  in the [rest of the] country. But if [we cut it off] with an instrument, [it is] forbidden in either place.</mishna>
    <mishna id="14">If a Kohen [member of the priestly caste, a subgroup of tribe of Levi, which is uniquely responsible for maintaining and carrying out the sacrificial services in the Temple] is injured on his finger, he may bind reeds upon [this wound] in the Temple [on the Shabbat], but not in the [rest of the] country. If [he does so] to squeeze out blood, [it] is forbidden in either place. We may strew salt on the ramp [of the altar on Shabbat], so that they [the ministering priests] don't slip; and we may draw water from the Golah Cistern and from the Large Cistern, with a rolling wheel, [even] on Sabbat, and from the Cold Well on a festival day [but not on Shabbat].</mishna>
    <mishna id="15">If a [dead] sheretz [a specific type of small animal, such as some insects, reptiles, or rodents, which move by scurrying, creeping, slithering, etc., the vast majority of which are prohibited for consumption] is found in the Temple [on Shabbat], the Kohen removes it with his belt, so as not to prolong the impurity [within the Temple] - so says Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka. Rabbi Yehuda says, "[He should remove it] with wooden pincers, so as not to increase [create more contamination from] the impurity." From where [in the Temple] must we remove it? From the sanctuary, from the vestibule, and from between the vestibule and the altar - so says Rabbi Shimon ben Nanas. Rabbi Akiva said, "Every place, [in which if we entered while impure], if intentionally, we would be liable to be cut off; and if inadvertently, to bring a sin-offering, from there it must be removed. In all other places, it, we must cover it with a copper vessel [until after Shabbat, when it is removed]." Rabbi Shimon says, "[Whatever] the Sages permitted, they [only] gave you [permission to do] what is yours [not forbidden by the Torah]; since they only permitted you [that which is] a shevut [restrictions established by the Sages regarding Shabbat to prevent violation of Torah-level Shabbat prohibitions, and to increase its sanctity]."</mishna>
  </chapter>
</book>