<book>
  <chapter id="1">
    <mishna id="1">Five [types of people] may not set aside Terumah [produce consecrated for priestly consumption], and if they did set aside Terumah, their Terumah is not [valid] Terumah: the deaf person, and the fool, and the minor, and one who sets aside Terumah from what does not belong to him. If a non-Jew who set aside Terumah from what belongs to a Jew even with permission, [the non-Jew's] Terumah is not [valid] Terumah. </mishna>
    <mishna id="2">A deaf person who can speak but cannot hear may not set aside Terumah. But if one did set aside Terumah, one's Terumah is valid Terumah. A deaf person that the Sages refer to in all cases can neither hear nor speak.</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">Regarding a minor who has not brought forth two [pubic] hairs, Rabbi Yehudah says that his Terumah is [valid] Terumah. Rabbi Yosi says, if he has not reached an age of [responsibility for his] vows, his Terumah is not [valid] Terumah. When he reaches an age [of responsibility for his] vows, his Terumah is [valid] Terumah. </mishna>
    <mishna id="4">One may not set aside Terumah from olives for oil, and not from grapes for wine. If one did set aside Terumah [from olives for oil or grapes for wine], the school of Shammai rules that their own Terumah [that was required of the grapes or wine] is among them, and the school of Hillel rules that one's Terumah is not [valid] Terumah.</mishna>
    <mishna id="5">One may not set aside Terumah from the Leket [fallen gleanings given to the poor], or from the Shikhecha [forgotten sheaves given to the poor], or from the Pe'ah [corner of the field that must be given to the poor], or from the Hefker [ownerless], and not from the first tithe whose Terumah has already been taken, or from Ma'aser Sheni [second tithe, which must be eaten in Jerusalem] or Hekdesh [consecrated donation] that has been redeemed, and not from that which is obligated [in Terumah] for that which is not obligated, and not from that which is not obligated to that which is obligated, and not from the picked to the unpicked, and not from the unpicked to the picked, and not from the Chadash [grain from the current year that one is forbidden to eat] for the Yashan [grain from the previous year that one is permitted to eat], and not from the Yashan for the Chadash, and not from the fruits of the Land [of Israel] for fruits from outside the Land, and not from fruits outside the Land for fruits of the Land. And if one did set aside Terumah [from these types of produce], one's Terumah is not [valid] Terumah.</mishna>
    <mishna id="6">Five [types of people] may not set aside Terumah, and if they did set aside Terumah, their Terumah is not [valid] Terumah: the mute, the drunkard, the naked, the blind, and a Ba'al Keri [one who had a nocturnal emission] may not set aside Terumah, and if they did set aside Terumah, their Terumah is [valid] Terumah.</mishna>
    <mishna id="7">One may not set aside Terumah by measure, by weights, or by number. However, one may set aside Terumah from that which has been measured, weighed, or counted. One may not set aside Terumah in a basket or container with a known measure. However, one may set aside Terumah in them [by only filling them] a half or a third. One may not set aside Terumah in [a container that holds one] Seah [specific unit of volume, by only filling it] a half, since half of it is a measure.</mishna>
    <mishna id="8">One may not set aside Terumah from oil for crushed olives, nor from wine for trodden grapes. If one has already set aside Terumah, one's Terumah is [valid] Terumah, but one must again set aside Terumah. The first [set of Terumah] will render on its own [another substance that it falls into] Demai [produce from which it is uncertain if tithes are already taken] and requires a fine of a fifth [of its value if eaten by an Israelite], but not so with the second [set of Terumah].</mishna>
    <mishna id="9">One may set aside Terumah from oil for pickled olives, and wine for grapes that will be made into raisins. If one set aside Terumah from oil for olives that will be eaten, or wine for grapes that will be eaten, or grapes for grapes that will be eaten, and he decided to press them, one does not need to set aside Terumah [again].</mishna>
    <mishna id="10">One may not set aside Terumah from substances whose preparations have been finished for substances whose preparations have not been finished, and not from substances whose preparations have not been finished for substances whose preparations have been finished, and not from substances whose preparations have not been finished for [other] substances whose preparations have not been finished. But if they have already set aside Terumah, their Terumah is [valid] Terumah.</mishna>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="2">
    <mishna id="1">One may not set aside Terumah [produce set aside for priestly consumption] from the pure for the impure. And if they set the Terumah aside, their Terumah is [valid] Terumah. Truly they said, the fig round, some of which has been made impure, one may set aside Terumah from the pure that is in it for the impure that is in it. And so too with a bundle of greenery, and so too with a pile. If there were two rounds, two bundles, or two piles--one impure and one pure--one may not set aside Terumah from one for the other. Rabbi Eliezer says: one may set aside Terumah from the pure for the impure.</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">One may not set aside Terumah from the impure for the pure. And if he accidentally set the Terumah aside, their Terumah is [valid] Terumah. If intentionally, [it is as if] he has done nothing. And so too with a Levite who had tithes from which Terumah had not been taken, and was continuously designating [parts of these impure tithes as the Terumah of other tithes]: if accidentally, what he did is done [with validity]. If intentionally, [it is as if] he has done nothing. Rabbi Yehudah said, if he knew that it was [impure] in the beginning, even if he [forgot and designated] accidentally, [it is as if] he has done nothing.</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">One who immerses vessels on the Sabbath accidentally may use them. Intentionally - he may not use them. One who tithes or cooks on the Sabbath accidentally may eat of it. Intentionally - he may not eat of it. One who plants on the Sabbath accidentally may allow it to grow. Intentionally - he must uproot [the plant]. If it is during the Sabbatical year, whether it was accidental or intentional - he must uproot.</mishna>
    <mishna id="4">One may not set aside Terumah from one species for a different species. And if he set the Terumah aside, his Terumah is not [valid] Terumah. All species of wheat are [considered] one [species]. All species of figs and dried figs and pressed figs are one, and one may set aside Terumah from one for the other. Any place where there is a Kohen [member of priestly caste], the Terumah should be set aside from the finer species. And any place where there is not a Kohen, the Terumah should be set aside from the longer lasting species. Rabbi Yehudah said, he should always set the Terumah aside from the finer species.</mishna>
    <mishna id="5">One should set aside as Terumah a whole small onion, rather than half of a large onion. Rabbi Yehudah said: not so, rather half of a large onion. And thus did Rabbi Yehudah say, one should set aside as Terumah onions from within the towns for [onions from within] the villages, but not [onions] from within the villages for [onions from within] the towns, because it is the food of the aristocracy.</mishna>
    <mishna id="6">One should set aside Terumah oil olives for pickled olives but not pickled olives for oil olives, and unboiled wine for boiled wine but not boiled wine for unboiled wine. The rule is that for any species that is considered Kilayim [forbidden mix of two species] with another species, one should not set aside Terumah from one [species] for the other [species], even from the good [species] for the bad [species]. And any species that is not considered Kilayim with another species, one may set aside Terumah from the good [species] for the bad [species], but not from the bad [species] for the good [species]. But if one set aside Terumah from the bad for the good, his Terumah is valid Terumah, except for from darnel [a poisonous rye grass] for wheat, since [darnel] is not a food. The gourd and the cucumber are one species. Rabbi Yehudah says [they are] two species.</mishna>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="3">
    <mishna id="1">If one set aside a gourd as Terumah [produce consecrated for priestly consumption] and it was found to be bitter, a melon and it was found to be rotten, it is [considered valid] Terumah but he must again give Terumah. If one set aside a barrel of wine as Terumah and it was found to be vinegar, if it was known to be vinegar before he set it aside as Terumah, is is [not considered valid] Terumah. But if it had become vinegar after he had given it as Terumah, behold it is Terumah. In a case of doubt, it is Terumah but he must again give Terumah. The first [set of Terumah] will not render on its own [another substance that it falls into] Demai [produce from which it is uncertain if tithes are already taken] and does not require a fine of a fifth [of its value if eaten by an Israelite], and so too with the second [set of Terumah].</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">If one of them fell into Chulin [non-sacred produce], it does not render [the Chulin] Demai. If the second fell into a different place, it does not render [that place] Demai. If both fell into the same place, it renders it Demai according to [whether] the smaller one [is large enough to render the mixture Demai].</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">Partners who set aside Terumah, the one after the other: Rabbi Akiva says: the Terumah of both of them is [valid] Terumah. But the Sages say: [only] the Terumah of the first is Terumah. Rabbi Yosi says: if the first set aside Terumah according to the prescribed amount, the Terumah of the second is not Terumah, but if the first did not set aside Terumah according to the prescribed amount, the Terumah of the second is Terumah.</mishna>
    <mishna id="4">To what does this apply? Only if one did not confer [with the other], but if one permits a member of his household, or his male slave or female slave to set aside Terumah [for him], this Terumah is [considered valid] Terumah. If he annulled [this permission]: If he annulled it before he set aside Terumah, the Terumah is not [valid] Terumah. But if he annulled it after he set aside Terumah, the Terumah is Terumah. Workers have no permission to give Terumah, except for those who tread [grapes] for they immediately make the winepress impure.</mishna>
    <mishna id="5">If one says: "The Terumah of this pile is within it", or, "its tithes are within it", or, "the Terumat Ma'aser [a portion of the tithes that are given to the priest] is within it", Rabbi Shimon says: he has [thereby] designated it [as Terumah, tithes, or Terumat Ma'aser]. But the Sages say: not unless he said, "It is in the north or south of it". Rabbi Elazar Chisma says: if one says, "The Terumah of this pile is taken from it for it", he has [thereby] designated it. Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says: if one says, "The tenth part of this tithe is made into Terumat Ma'aser for it", he has [thereby] designated it.</mishna>
    <mishna id="6">If one sets aside Terumah before Bikurim [first-fruits that must be given to the priest], or Ma'aser Rishon [first tithe, which must be given to the Levite] before Terumah, or Ma'aser Sheni [second tithe, which must be eaten in Jerusalem] before Ma'aser Rishon, although he transgresses a negative commandment, that which he has done is done, for it is said: "You shall not delay your grain harvests and your grape harvests" (Exodus 22:28).</mishna>
    <mishna id="7">From where [do we derive] that [the setting aside of] Bikurim must precede Terumah, seeing that this one is called "Terumah" and "the first" and the other is [also] called "Terumah" and "the first"? Rather Bikurim take precedence since they are the first-fruits of all produce. And Terumah precedes Ma'aser Rishon because it is called "first". And Ma'aser Rishon precedes Ma'aser Sheni because it includes that which is called "first" [Terumat Ma'aser].</mishna>
    <mishna id="8">He who intends to say ‘Terumah’ and says ‘tithe’, [or] ‘tithe’ and says ‘Terumah’ [or who intends to say] ‘Olah’ [burnt-offering] and he says ‘Shelamim’ [burnt offering, or] ‘Shelamim’ and he says ‘Olah’ [or who intends to vow that] ‘I will not enter this house,’ and says, ‘that house,’ [or] ‘That I will not give any benefit to this [man],’ and says ‘to that [man],’ he has said nothing until his mouth and mind are equivalent.</mishna>
    <mishna id="9">A non-Jew and a Cuthite, their Terumah is [considered valid] Terumah and their tithes are [valid] tithes and their Hekdesh [consecrated donations] is [valid] Hekdesh. Rabbi Yehudah says: the non-Jew does not have Kerem Revai [fruits in the four year after their planting, which are considered sacred]. But the Sages say: he does have it. The Terumah of a non-Jew makes [produce into which it falls into] Demai and [one who eats it unintentionally] is obligated [to pay back an extra] fifth. But Rabbi Shimon exempts him.</mishna>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="4">
    <mishna id="1">One who sets aside only part of [the] Terumah [produce consecrated for priestly consumption] and tithes [that are in one place], may take from [that place the rest of the] Terumah for that [place], but not for another place. Rabbi Meir says: he may also take from Terumah and tithes for another place.</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">If one had his produce in a storehouse, and he gave a Se'ah [specific unit of volume] to a Levite and a Se'ah to a poor person, he may set aside another eight Se'in [from the storehouse] and eat them, the words of Rabbi Meir. But the Sages say: he may only set aside according to the account [when Terumah and tithes have been given for all the produce in the storehouse].</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">The amount of Terumah: A fair-eyed [generous amount]: one out of forty. Beit Shammai say: out of thirty. The average [amount]: out of fifty. A stingy [amount]: out of sixty. If he set aside Terumah and found that it was only one out of sixty, [it is valid] Terumah and he need not set aside [more] Terumah. If he does go back and add [more Terumah], [the extra amount] requires tithing. If he found that it was only one out of sixty-five [it is valid] Terumah, but he must set aside Terumah again according to his habitual practice, in measure, weight or number. Rabbi Yehudah says: [he may] even [set aside Terumah] not from the surrounding [produce].</mishna>
    <mishna id="4">One who says to his messenger: "Go and set aside Terumah [for me]", [the messenger] should set aside Terumah according to the mind of the owner. If he does not know the mind of the owner, he gives according to the average [amount]—one out of fifty. If he gave ten [parts] less or ten [parts] more, his Terumah is [valid] Terumah. If his intention was to add even one part more, his Terumah is not [valid] Terumah.</mishna>
    <mishna id="5">One who gives more Terumah: Rabbi Eliezer says: [he may give up to] one out of ten, as in the case of Terumat Ma'aser [a portion of the tithes that is given to the priest]. [If he gave] more than this, he must make [the extra into] Terumat Ma'aser for other produce. Rabbi Yishmael says: [he may give up until the mixture is] half Chulin [non-sacred produce] and half Terumah. Rabbi Tarfon and Rabbi Akiva say: [he may give] as long as there remains [enough to carry] the name of Chulin. </mishna>
    <mishna id="6">On three occasions they measure the contents of the basket [to determine how much Terumah must be given]: At the time of the first ripe fruits, and of the late summer fruits, and in the middle of the summer. He who counts [the fruit] is praiseworthy, and he who measures it is more praiseworthy than him, and he who weighs them is the most praiseworthy of all three.</mishna>
    <mishna id="7">Rabbi Eliezer says: Terumah can be removed [if it falls into a mixture] of one hundred and one [times its size]. Rabbi Joshua says: in a hundred and more, and this 'more' has no definite measure. Rabbi Yosi ben Meshullam says: this 'more' must be a Kav [specific unit of volume] to a hundred Se'ah, a sixth [of the Se'ah] renders [the mixture] as Demai [produce from which it is uncertain if tithes were already taken].</mishna>
    <mishna id="8">Rabbi Yehoshua says: black figs can be counted together with the white [to remove a white fig that is Terumah and fell into a mixture of black and white figs], and the white can be counted together with the black [to remove a black fig]. In the case of cakes of figs, the large can be counted together with the small, and the small can be counted together with the large. The round [cakes of figs] can be counted together with the square [cakes], and the square can be counted together with the round. Rabbi Eliezer prohibits this. Rabbi Akiva says: if it is known what [kind] fell in, then the one [kind] cannot be counted together with the other, but if it is not known what [kind] fell in, then the one [kind] can be counted together with the other.</mishna>
    <mishna id="9">How [does Rabbi Akiva decide]? If there were fifty black figs and fifty white, and a black [fig] fell in, the black are forbidden, but the white are permitted; and if a white [fig] fell in, the white are forbidden and the black are permitted. If it is not known what [kind] fell in, then the one [kind] can be counted together with the other. In this [case], Rabbi Eliezer is stringent and Rabbi Yehoshua is lenient.</mishna>
    <mishna id="10">But in this [following case], Rabbi Eliezer is lenient and Rabbi Yehoshua stringent. If one was pressing a litra of cut figs [of Terumah] by a jar and he did not know which [jar was used]: Rabbi Eliezer says: they [the cut figs] are to be regarded as if they are separate, so that the lower [figs] can be counted together with the higher. Rabbi Yehoshua says: the Terumah cannot be removed unless there are a hundred jars there.</mishna>
    <mishna id="11">A Se'ah of Terumah which fell on top of a stockpile and stays on the surface: Rabbi Eliezer says: if at the surface there are one hundred Se'ah, it can be removed [since the mixture is] one hundred and one [times its size]. But Rabbi Yehoshua says: it cannot be removed. A Se'ah of Terumah which fell on top of a stockpile, he must skim it off. If so, why did they say that Terumah can be removed in [a mixture] one hundred and one [times its size]? [This applies] if it is not known whether they have become mixed up or where they have fallen.</mishna>
    <mishna id="12">Two baskets or two stockpiles, and a Se'ah of Terumah has fallen into one of them and it is not known into which it has fallen, then the one [kind] can be counted together with the other. Rabbi Shimon says: even if they are in two cities, the one [kind] can be counted together with the other.</mishna>
    <mishna id="13">Rabbi Yosi said: A case once came before Rabbi Akiva concerning fifty bundles of vegetables into which a bundle had fallen, half of which was Terumah. And I said in front of him, that it can be removed, not because Terumah can be removed in [a mixture that is] fifty-one [times its size], but because there were one hundred and two halves there.</mishna>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="5">
    <mishna id="1">If a Se'ah [specific unit of volume] of impure Terumah [produce consecrated for priestly consumption] fell into less than a hundred [Se'ah] of Chulin [non-sacred produce], or into Ma'aser Rishon [first tithe, which must be given to the Levite], or into Ma'aser Sheni [second tithe, which must be eaten in Jerusalem], or into Hekdesh [consecrated donation], whether these were impure or pure, they must all [be left to] rot. If the Se'ah [of Terumah] was pure, [the mixture] should be sold to priests at the price of Terumah, excluding the value of that Se'ah [itself]. If it fell into Ma'aser Rishon, he should declare Terumat Ma'aser [a portion of the tithes that is given to the priest]. And if it fell into Ma'aser Sheni or into Hekdesh, they must be redeemed. If the Chulin was impure, it may be eaten in small quantities, or roasted, or kneaded with fruit juice, or divided into pieces of dough so that there is not in any one place [a piece of dough] the size of an egg.</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">If a Se'ah of impure Terumah fell into a hundred [Se'ah] of pure Chulin, Rabbi Eliezer says: [a Se'ah] must be set aside as Terumah and burned, for I say that the Se'ah that fell in is the Se'ah that was brought up. But the Sages say: it may be brought up and eaten in small quantities, or roasted, or kneaded with fruit juice, or divided into pieces of dough so that there is not in any one place [a piece of dough] the size of an egg.</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">If a Se'ah of pure Terumah fell into a hundred [Se'ah] of impure Chulin, it may be eaten in small quantities, or roasted, or kneaded with fruit juice, or divided into pieces of dough so that there is not in any one place [a piece of dough] the size of an egg.</mishna>
    <mishna id="4">If a Se'ah of impure Terumah fell into a hundred Se'ah of pure Terumah: Beit Shammai prohibits, but Beit Hillel permits. Beit Hillel said to Beit Shammai: since pure [Terumah] is forbidden to non-priests and impure [Terumah is forbidden] to priests, then just as pure [Terumah] may be brought up, so too may impure [Terumah] be brought up. Beit Shammai answered them: No! If lenient Chulin, which is permitted to non-priests, may allow us to bring up pure [Terumah that fell into it], does stringent Terumah, which is forbidden to non-priests, allow us to bring up impure [Terumah that fell into it]? After they agreed, Rabbi Eliezer said: it should be set aside as Terumah and burned. But the Sages say: it has disappeared on account of its being a minor [portion of the mixture].</mishna>
    <mishna id="5">If a Se'ah of Terumah fell into a hundred [of Chulin], and he lifted it out and it fell into [Chulin] elsewhere: Rabbi Eliezer says: it renders [the mixture] Demai [produce from which it is uncertain if tithes were already taken] as though it were certainly Terumah. But the Sages say: it render Demai only according to proportion.</mishna>
    <mishna id="6">If a Se'ah of Terumah fell into less than a hundred [of Chulin], and rendered [the mixture] Demai, and part of the Demai mixture [then] fell into another place: Rabbi Eliezer says: it renders [that place] Demai as if certain Terumah [had fallen in]. But the Sages say: the Demai mixture renders [another mixture] Demai only according to proportion. And that which is leavened [with Terumah] renders other dough leavened [as if with Terumah] only according to proportion. And drawn water disqualifies a Mikvah [ritual bath] also only according to proportion.</mishna>
    <mishna id="7">If a Se'ah of Terumah fell into a hundred [of Chulin] and he lifted [a Se'ah] out and then another fell in, and he lifted another out and another fell in, this is permitted until the amount of Terumah exceeds that of the Chulin.</mishna>
    <mishna id="8">If a Se'ah of Terumah fell into a hundred [of Chulin], and before he could take it out another fell in, this is forbidden. Rabbi Shimon permits it.</mishna>
    <mishna id="9">If a Se'ah of Terumah fell into a hundred [of Chulin], and they were ground up and reduced [in bulk], just as the Chulin was reduced so too the Terumah was reduced, and it is permitted. If a Se'ah of Terumah fell into less than a hundred [of Chulin] and they were ground up and increased in bulk, just as the Chulin increased so too the Terumah increased, and it is forbidden. If it is known that the kernels of Chulin were better than those of Terumah, it is permitted. If a Se'ah of Terumah fell into less than a hundred [of Chulin], and [more] Chulin fell in afterwards, if it was unintentional it is permissible, but if intentional it is forbidden.</mishna>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="6">
    <mishna id="1">One who eats Terumah [produce consecrated for priestly consumption] unintentionally must repay its principal value and a fifth [of its value, regardless of] whether he eats it or drinks it, or anoints himself with it, or whether the Terumah is pure or the Terumah is impure, he must pay its fifth and a fifth of that fifth [if he ate the fifth]. He may not repay with Terumah, but rather with tithed Chulin [non-sacred produce], which becomes Terumah. And the Tashlumin [payments for what was wrongfully eaten] also become Terumah and if the priest wishes to forego [the payments], he cannot forego.</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">A daughter of an Israelite who ate Terumah and afterwards was married to a priest: If she ate Terumah that had not yet been acquired by a [particular] priest, she can repay to herself the principal value and the fifth. But if she ate Terumah that a priest had already acquired, she must repay the principal value to the owners, but [she can repay] the fifth to herself, because they said that one who eats Terumah unintentionally must pay the principal value to the owners and the fifth to anyone he wants.</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">If one feeds his workers or his guests Terumah, he must pay the principal value and they must pay the fifth, the words of Rabbi Meir. But the Sages say: they must pay both the principal value and the fifth, and he must pay them the price of their meal.</mishna>
    <mishna id="4">If one stole Terumah but did not eat it, he must pay Tashlumei Kefel [a double payment] of the price of the Terumah. If he ate it, he must pay two principal values plus a fifth, one principal value and a fifth from Chulin [non-sacred produce], and one principal value at the price of Terumah. If one stole Terumah of Hekdesh [consecrated donation] and ate it, he must pay two fifths and the principal value, for Tashlumei Kefel does not apply to Hekdesh. </mishna>
    <mishna id="5">One may not pay from Leket [fallen gleanings given to the poor], from Shikhecha [forgotten sheaves given to the poor], from Pe'ah [corner of a field that must be given to the poor], or from the Hefker [ownerless property], and not Ma'aser Rishon [first tithe, which must be given to the Levite] from which Terumah has been taken, nor from Ma'aser Sheni [second tithe, which must be eaten in Jerusalem] and Hekdesh [consecrated donation] that have been redeemed, because Kodesh [consecrated material] may not be used to redeem Kodesh, the words of Rabbi Meir. But the Sages permit [payment] with these.</mishna>
    <mishna id="6">Rabbi Eliezer says: one may pay from one species for another species, provided that it is from superior [produce] for inferior [produce]. Rabbi Akiva says: one may pay only from one species for its own species. Hence if a man ate cucumbers of the pre-Sabbatical year, he must wait for the cucumbers of the post-Sabbatical year and pay with them. From the place where Rabbi Eliezer is lenient [derives his leniency], from there Rabbi Akiva is stringent, for it says: "And he shall give the priest the Kodesh" (Leviticus 22:14). [This implies] whatever is appropriate for being Kodesh, the words of Rabbi Eliezer. But Rabbi Akiva says: "And he shall give the priest the Kodesh" [implies] the Kodesh that he ate.</mishna>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="7">
    <mishna id="1">One who eats Terumah [produce consecrated for priestly consumption] intentionally must pay the principal value but need not pay the [additional] fifth. The Tashlumin [payments for what was wrongfully eaten] are Chulin [non-sacred produce, and] if the priest wishes to forego [the payments], he may forego.</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">A daughter of a priest who married an Israelite and afterwards ate Terumah, she must pay the principal value but does not pay the [additional] fifth. Her death [penalty if she commits adultery] is by burning. If she married one of the ineligible [to marry a daughter of a priest], she must pay the principal value and the fifth, and her death [penalty] is by strangulation. These are the words of Rabbi Meir. The Sages say that both cases must pay the principal value but not pay the fifth, and their deaths are by burning.</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">One who feeds Terumah to his young children, or to his slaves, whether they are adult or young, as well as one who eats Terumah of Chutz LaAretz [outside of the Land of Israel], and one who eats less than an olive-bulk of Terumah, must repay the principal value, but need not pay the fifth. The Tashlumin are Chulin, [and] if the priest wishes to forego [the payments], he may forego.</mishna>
    <mishna id="4">This is the general principle: whenever one has to pay both the principal value and the fifth, the Tashlumin are Terumah, [and] if the priest wishes to forego [the payments], he may not forego. But whenever one has to pay the principal value and not pay the fifth, the Tashlumin remain Chulin, [and] if the priest wishes to forego [the payments], he may forego.</mishna>
    <mishna id="5">If there were two baskets, one of Terumah and one of Chulin, and a Se'ah [specific unit of volume] of Terumah fell into one of them, but it is not known into which it fell, behold I can assume that it had fallen into that of the Terumah. [If] it is not known which was of Terumah and which of Chulin, if he eats from one of them he is exempt, and the second [basket] is treated as [if it were] Terumah and requires Challah [dough that must be set aside for the priest], the words of Rabbi Meir. But Rabbi Yosi exempts. If another person eats from the second basket he is exempt. If one man ate of both, he must repay according to [the value of] the smaller of the two.</mishna>
    <mishna id="6">If one of these [baskets] fell into Chulin, it does not render it Demai [produce from which it is uncertain if tithes were already taken], and the second [basket] is treated as [if it were] Terumah and requires Challah, the words of Rabbi Meir. Rabbi Yosi exempts. If the second [basket] falls into another place [that is Chulin], it does not render [that other place] Demai. If both of them fall into one place, they render it Demai according to [the proportion of] the smaller of the two.</mishna>
    <mishna id="7">One who used one of these [baskets] as seed, he is exempt, and the second is treated as if it were Terumah and requires Challah, the words of Rabbi Meir. But Rabbi Yosi exempts. If another person uses the second as seed, he is exempt. If one man uses both as seed, if it is of a kind whose seed disintegrates [in the ground] it is permitted, but if it is of the kind whose seed does not disintegrate it is prohibited.</mishna>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="8">
    <mishna id="1">If a woman was eating Terumah [produce consecrated for priestly consumption] and someone came and told her, "your husband died", or "[he] divorced you", and also if a slave was eating Terumah and someone came and told him, "your master has died", or "[he] sold you to an Israelite [non-priest, whose slaves may not eat Terumah]", or "[he] gave you as a gift", or "[he] made you a freeman", and also if a Kohen [priest] was eating Terumah and it became known that he is [not eligible to eat Terumah because he is] the son of a divorcee or of a Chalutzah [a childless widow whose brother-in-law has performed a divorce ceremony so as not to fulfill his requirement of marrying her], Rabbi Eliezer obligates him to pay the principle value and the fifth. Rabbi Yehoshua exempts him. If he was standing and sacrificing on the altar, and it became known that he is the son of a divorcee or a Chalutzah, Rabbi Eliezer says all the sacrifices that he offered on the altar are invalid. Rabbi Yehoshua deems them valid. If, [alternatively], it became known that he possesses a physical defect, his offering is invalid.</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">And in all of these cases, if there was Terumah in their mouths, Rabbi Eliezer says they may swallow [it]. Rabbi Yehoshua says they must spit [it] out. If someone tells him, "you have just become impure and the Terumah has just become impure", Rabbi Eliezer says he may swallow [it]. Rabbi Yehoshua says he must spit [it] out. [If someone tells him,] "you were already impure and the Terumah was already impure", or if it became known that it is untithed produce or Ma'aser Rishon [first tithe, which must be given to the Levite] from which no Terumah [produce consecrated for priestly consumption] was taken, or Ma'aser Sheni [second tithe, which must be eaten in Jerusalem] or Hekdesh [consecrated donation] that were not redeemed, or if he tasted the taste of an insect in his mouth, he must spit out [the Terumah].</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">If someone was eating a grape cluster and entered from the garden into the courtyard, Rabbi Eliezer says he may finish [the cluster]. Rabbi Yehoshua says he may not finish. If Shabbat evening darkens [while he is eating], Rabbi Eliezer says he may finish. Rabbi Yehoshua says he may not finish.</mishna>
    <mishna id="4">If wine that is Terumah is left uncovered, it must be poured out. It is not necessary to say this if it is Chulin [non-sacred produce]. Three kinds of liquids become forbidden if left uncovered: water, wine, and milk. All other liquids [even if left uncovered] are permitted. How long must they be left [uncovered] for them to become forbidden? As long as [it would take] for a snake to come out from a nearby place and drink [from it].</mishna>
    <mishna id="5">The amount of water that may be left uncovered [without being rendered forbidden] is [greater than or equal to] the amount that can neutralize in it the poison. Rabbi Yosi says, in vessels, all [quantities of water are forbidden], and in the ground, forty Se'ah [specific unit of volume, is the minimum quantity of water that may be left uncovered and still be permitted].</mishna>
    <mishna id="6">Bite marks in figs, grapes, cucumbers, pumpkins, melons or cucumber-melons, even if they [the fruit] are as [much as] a Kikar, either large or small, either uprooted or rooted, all that contain moisture are forbidden. [An animal] bitten by a snake is forbidden on account of the danger to life.</mishna>
    <mishna id="7">A filter [used as a cover] for wine, [the wine] becomes forbidden if left uncovered. Rabbi Nekhemiah permits it.</mishna>
    <mishna id="8">A vessel of Terumah that has developed in it a chance that it is impure: Rabbi Eliezer says, if it had been deposited in a neglected place, one should deposit it in a hidden place; and if it was uncovered, one should cover it. Rabbi Yehoshua says, if it had been deposited in a hidden place, one should deposit it in a neglected place; and if it was covered, one should uncover it. Rabban Gamliel says, one should not do anything new to it. </mishna>
    <mishna id="9">A vessel [of Terumah] that was broken in the upper vat [of a wine-press], and the lower vat was impure: Rabbi Eliezer and Rabbi Yehoshua agree that if one can save at least a Revi'it [specific unit of volume] of it in purity, one should save it. But if not: Rabbi Eliezer says: let it flow down and become impure [of its own accord], and let him not defile it with his own hands.</mishna>
    <mishna id="10">Similarly, a vessel of [Terumah] oil that spilled: Rabbi Eliezer and Rabbi Yehoshua agree that if one can save at least a Revi'it of it in purity, one should save it. But if not: Rabbi Eliezer says: let it flow down and be absorbed, and let him not absorb it with his own hands.</mishna>
    <mishna id="11">Concerning [both] this case and that case, Rabbi Yehoshua said: This is not [the kind of] Terumah over which I am cautioned from defiling it, but rather from eating it. And "Do not defile it" applies in what case? If one was passing from place to place with loaves of Terumah  in his hand and a non-Jew said to him: "Give me one of these and I will defile it; for if not, I will defile them all". Rabbi Eliezer says, let him defile them all, and do not give him one of them to defile. But Rabbi Yehoshua says: he should place before him one of them on a rock.</mishna>
    <mishna id="12">Similarly, women who have been told by non-Jews, "Give us one of you that we may defile her; for if not, we will defile you all", let [the non-Jews] defile them all, and do not hand over to them one soul from Israel.</mishna>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="9">
    <mishna id="1">One who plants Terumah [produce consecrated for priestly consumption], if unintentionally, must overturn it. If intentionally, he must allow it to remain. If it had already produced a third [of its full size], whether unintentionally or intentionally, he must allow it to remain. But in the case of flax, [even if planted] intentionally he must overturn it.</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">And [Terumah that has been planted is] obligated in Leket [fallen gleanings given to the poor], Shikhecha [forgotten sheaves given to the poor], and Pe'ah [corner of a field that must be given to the poor]. The poor of the Israelites and the poor of the priests may glean them, but the poor of the Israelites must sell theirs to the priests for the price of Terumah and the money is theirs. Rabbi Tarfon says: none may glean except the poor of the priests, lest [Israelite gleaners] forget and put it into their mouths. Rabbi Akiva said to him: if so, then none may glean except the pure.</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">And  [Terumah that has been planted is] obligated in tithes and the poor man’s tithe. The poor of the Israelites and the poor of the priests may take them, but the poor of the Israelites must sell theirs to the priests for the price of Terumah and the money is theirs. He who beats [the grain with sticks] is praiseworthy. But he who threshes it [with an animal], how should he do it? He should suspend baskets from the neck of the animal and place in them [grain] from the same kind [as that being threshed], with the result that he will neither muzzle the animal nor feed [it] the Terumah.</mishna>
    <mishna id="4">The growths of Terumah [seeds] are Terumah, but the growths of their growths are Chulin [non-sacred produce]. But non-tithed produce, and Ma'aser Rishon [first tithe, which must be given to the Levite], and after-growths from the Sabbatical year, and Terumah grown in Chutz La'Aretz [outside the Land of Israel], and mixtures that are Demai [produce from which it is uncertain if tithes were already taken] and Bikurim [first-fruits that must be given to the priest]—their growths are Chulin. The growths of Hekdesh [consecrated donation] and Ma'aser Sheni [second tithe, which must be eaten in Jerusalem] are Chulin, and one redeems them at the time when they are planted.</mishna>
    <mishna id="5">A hundred rows of Terumah [seeds] and one of Chulin, they are all permitted, in [the case of] a kind whose seed disintegrates. But in a kind whose seed does not disintegrate, even if there be a hundred [rows] of Chulin and one of Terumah, they are all prohibited.</mishna>
    <mishna id="6">Non-tithed produce, its growths are permissible in a kind whose seed disintegrates. But in a kind whose seed does not disintegrate, [even] the growths of its growths are forbidden. Which is a kind whose seed does not disintegrate? For instance, Luf [plant], garlic, and onions. Rabbi Yehudah says: onions are like barley.</mishna>
    <mishna id="7">One who weeds with a non-Jew in leek-plants, even though its fruits are non-tithed, he may eat from them in a casual fashion. Saplings of Terumah which have become impure, if planted [again], they become pure from their impurity. But they may not be eaten until the edible [parts] have been lopped off [and regrown]. Rabbi Yehudah says: until they have been lopped off and repeated [lopped off a second time]. </mishna>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="10">
    <mishna id="1">An onion [of Terumah, produce consecrated for priestly consumption] that was placed into lentils: if [the onion was] whole, it is permissible; but if cut up, [it is forbidden if it] imparts a flavor. In the case of all other dishes, whether [the onion is] whole or cut up, [it is forbidden if it] imparts a flavor. Rabbi Yehudah permits it in the case of brined fish, because it is used only to remove the unpleasant flavor.</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">An apple [of Terumah] that was chopped and placed in dough [of Chulin, non-sacred produce] so that it leavened it, [the dough] is forbidden. Barley [of Terumah] that fell into a cistern of water, though putrefied [by the barley], the waters are permissible.</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">One who removes warm bread from an oven and places it on the mouth of a barrel of Terumah wine: Rabbi Meir forbids it. Rabbi Yehudah permits it. Rabbi Yosi permits [if the bread is] of wheat and forbids if of barley, because barley absorbs.</mishna>
    <mishna id="4">An oven that was heated with cumin of Terumah and [bread was] baked in it, the bread is permitted, because it retains not the flavor of cumin, but the smell of the cumin.</mishna>
    <mishna id="5">Fenugreek that fell into a vat of wine, in [the case of] Terumah or in Ma'aser Sheni [second tithe, which must be eaten in Jerusalem], if there is in the seed enough to impart a flavor [even] without the stalk, [it is forbidden]. But if it was Sabbatical year produce or Kilayim [forbidden mix of two species] of the vineyard, or Hekdesh [consecrated donation], [it is forbidden] if there is in both seed and stalk enough to impart a flavor.</mishna>
    <mishna id="6">Someone who had bunches of fenugreek that are Kilayim of the vineyard, they must be burned. If he had bunches of fenugreek that are non-tithed produce, he must beat them and calculate how much seed there is in them and set aside [Terumah] from the seed, but he need not to set aside from the stalks. But if he did set aside [Terumah from the stalks], he must not say: "I will beat [the seed] and take the stalks and give [only] the seed [as Terumah]", but rather he must give the stalks together with the seed.</mishna>
    <mishna id="7">Olives of Chulin that were pickled with olives of Terumah, [whether these were] crushed [olives] of Chulin [pickled together] with crushed [olives] of Terumah, or crushed [olives] of Chulin with whole [olives] of Terumah, or in liquid of Terumah, they are forbidden. But whole [olives] of Chulin pickled with crushed [olives] of Terumah, they are permitted.</mishna>
    <mishna id="8">Impure fish that was pickled with pure fish, any jug that can hold two Se'ah [specific unit of volume], if it contains the weight of ten Zuz [specific unit of weight] in [the measure of] Judea, which is five Selah [specific unit of weight] in [the measure of] Galilee, of impure fish, its brine is forbidden. Rabbi Yehudah says: [the ratio is] a Revi'it [specific unit of volume] in two Se'ah. Rabbi Yosi says: one-sixteenth of it.</mishna>
    <mishna id="9">Impure locusts that were pickled with pure locusts, they did not make their brine forbidden. Rabbi Tzadok testified regarding the brine of impure locusts, that it is pure.</mishna>
    <mishna id="10">All [vegetables] that are pickled together are permitted, except [when pickled] with a leek-plant. A leek-plant of Chulin [pickled] with a leek-plant of Terumah, or [another] vegetable of Chulin with a leek-plant of Terumah, [these are] forbidden. But a leek-plant of Chulin with a vegetable of Terumah, [this is] permitted.</mishna>
    <mishna id="11">Rabbi Yosi says: All overcooked vegetables with [Terumah] beets are forbidden, because they impart a flavor. Rabbi Shimon says: cabbage from an artificially irrigated field with [Terumah] cabbage from a rain-watered field is forbidden because it absorbs. Rabbi Akiva says: all [foods] that are cooked together are permitted, except [when cooked] with meat. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri says: liver renders other things forbidden, but does not become forbidden, because it gives off [flavor] but does not absorb.</mishna>
    <mishna id="12">An egg that is cooked in forbidden spices, even its yolk is forbidden, because it absorbs. The liquid of overcooked vegetables and the liquid of pickled vegetables that are Terumah, [these are] forbidden to non-priests.</mishna>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="11">
    <mishna id="1">One may not put a pressed fig cake or dried figs [that are Terumah, produce consecrated for priestly consumption] into fish brine, since it ruins them. But one may place [Terumah] wine into fish brine. One may not spice [Terumah] oil, but one may put honey and pepper into wine. One may not cook Terumah wine, because it decreases it. Rabbi Yehudah permits this, because it improves it.</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">[A non-priest who drank] honey of date, wine of apples, vinegar of winter grapes, and all other kinds of fruit juice of Terumah, Rabbi Eliezer makes him liable in [paying their] principal value and the fifth. Rabbi Yehoshua exempts. Rabbi Eliezer declares [these] susceptible to impurity as liquids. Rabbi Yehoshua says: the Sages did not count seven liquids as those that count spices, but rather stated: seven liquids make [things] susceptible to impurity, whereas all other liquids do not make susceptible.</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">One must not make dates into honey, apples into wine, winter grapes into vinegar, or change any other kind of fruit from their natural state in [a case where they are] Terumah or Ma'aser Sheni [second tithe, which must be eaten in Jerusalem], except olives and grapes alone. One does not receive forty lashes on account of Orlah [fruits in the first three years after their planting, which may not be eaten], except for that which comes out of olives and out of grapes. One may not bring liquids as Bikurim [first-fruits that must be given to the priest], except for that which comes out of olives and out of grapes. And it [fruit juice] is not susceptible to impurity as liquids, except for that which comes out of olives and out of grapes. And [fruit juice] cannot be offered on the altar, except for that which comes out of olives and out of grapes.</mishna>
    <mishna id="4">The stems of fresh figs and dried figs and Kelisim [type of fruit] and carobs of Terumah are forbidden to non-priests.</mishna>
    <mishna id="5">Seeds of Terumah [fruit]: When he gathers them in, they are forbidden [to non-priests]. But if he throws them away, they are permitted. Similarly, the bones of holy things: When he gathers them in, they are forbidden. But if he throws them away, they are permitted. Coarse bran is permitted. Bran-flour of Chadash [grain from the current year that one is forbidden to eat] is forbidden, and Yashan [grain from the previous year that one is permitted to eat] is permitted. One may act with regard to Terumah as one does with regard to Chulin [non-sacred produce]. One who sifts a Kav [specific unit of volume] or two [of fine flour] from a Se'ah [specific unit of volume] of wheat, should not ruin the rest, but rather should put it in a hidden place.</mishna>
    <mishna id="6">A store-chamber that was cleared of Terumah wheat, one should not require him to be sitting and collecting each and every [grain], but rather he may sweep it in his usual manner and then deposit Chulin in it.</mishna>
    <mishna id="7">Similarly, a jar of oil that was spilled, one should not require him to be sitting and scooping it up [with his fingers], but rather he may deal with it as he would in a case of Chulin.</mishna>
    <mishna id="8">One who pours from jar to jar and drips three drops, he may place in it Chulin. But if he tilted the jar and gathered [the drops], it is Terumah. How much Terumat Ma'aser [a portion of the tithes that is given to the priest] of Demai [produce from which it is uncertain if tithes were already taken] must there be for him to take it to the priest? One eighth of a Sheminit [specific unit of volume].</mishna>
    <mishna id="9">Vetches of Terumah, they may be fed to cattle, to wild beasts or to chickens. An Israelite who hired a cow from a priest, he may feed it vetches of Terumah. But a priest who hired a cow from an Israelite, even though the responsibility of its food is his, he may not feed it vetches of Terumah. An Israelite who undertakes the care of a cow from a priest by [splitting the growth in its] appraised value, he may not feed it vetches of Terumah. But a priest who undertakes the care of a cow from an Israelite by appraised value, he may feed it vetches of Terumah.</mishna>
    <mishna id="10">One may burn oil that has to be burnt [because it is contaminated Terumah] in synagogues, houses of study, dark alleys, and for sick people with permission of a priest. The daughter of an Israelite who is married to a priest and regularly goes to her father’s house, her father may burn [such oil] with her permission. One may burn [such oil] in the house of celebration but not in the house of mourning, the words of Rabbi Yehudah. Rabbi Yosi says: in the house of mourning, but not in the house of celebration. Rabbi Meir forbids [both] here and here. Rabbi Shimon permits here and here.</mishna>
  </chapter>
</book>