<book>
  <chapter id="1">
    <mishna id="1">One who plants [a fruit tree] to serve as a fence or for beams, it is exempt from [the laws of] Orlah [the fruit of a tree during the first three years after its planting, the consumption or usage of which is forbidden]. Rabbi Yose says, even if he intended the inner side to be for fruit and the outer side to be a fence, the inside fruit is subject [to Orlah] while the outside is exempt.</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">At the time that our forefathers came into the Land [of Israel], [and they] found [a tree] already planted, it was exempt [from the laws of Orlah]. If they planted [a fruit tree], even though [the Land] had not yet been conquered, it was subject. If one planted [a tree] for public use, it is subject. Rabbi Yehudah exempts it. If one planted [a tree] on public property, or if a non-Jew planted [a tree], or if a thief planted [a tree on property that was not his], or if one planted on a boat, or if it grew on its own, it is subject to Orlah.</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">A tree that was uprooted together with its rock-soil [the hard soil which is wrapped around the roots], [or] was swept away in a flood by a river together with its rock-soil, [and one added more soil and it started growing again], if it could have lived [just from the rock-soil] it is exempt; if not, it is subject. Rock-soil that became detached from one side, or that a plow shook it off, or that he shook it off until it [the rock soil] turned into loose soil, [and one added more soil and it started growing again], if it could have lived it is exempt; if not, it is subject.</mishna>
    <mishna id="4">A tree that was uprooted but one root remained is exempt. And how large must that root be? Rabban Gamliel says in the name of Rabbi Elazar the son of Yehudah of Bertota, as a stretching pin.</mishna>
    <mishna id="5">A tree that was uprooted and it had a rooted shoot [a low lying branch which was bent and planted into the ground] and the tree is now deriving nourishment [only] from the [new] shoot, the old tree now assumes the status of the shoot. If one [bent and] rooted [a series of branches] year after year, and it [the first shoot] became detached, one counts [the number of years for the laws of Orlah] from the time it became detached. [As for] grafted shoots of vines, and grafted vine shoots growing on other grafted, vine shoots, even though he rooted them in the ground, they are permitted. Rabbi Meir says, in a case where the strength [of the graft] is great, it is permitted; but where the strength [of the graft] is lacking it is prohibited. (So too) regarding a [rooted] shoot which has become detached and it is full of fruit, if [the fruit] increased [in size] one two-hundredth part [after its detachment] it is prohibited.</mishna>
    <mishna id="6">A shoot of Orlah or a shoot of Kilayim [a general term for the product of forbidden crossbreeding or working of certain animals with one another, planting together certain plants, or interweaving certain fibers] that became mixed up with [other] shoots - these, he must not gather. If he did gather them, it becomes neutralized in [a mixture of] two hundred and one, provided that he did not intentionally gather them. Rabbi Yose says, even if he gathered them deliberately [in order to neutralize them], it [still] becomes neutralized in two hundred and one.</mishna>
    <mishna id="7">Leaves, sprouts, the sap of vines and vine buds, are permitted regarding [the laws of] Orlah, Revai [the fruit of a tree in the fourth year after its planting, which must be taken to Jerusalem and consumed there] and to a Nazirite, but are prohibited regarding [the laws of] Asherah [idolatrous tree of which all benefit is prohibited]. Rabbi Yose says, vine-buds are prohibited, because they are [considered] a fruit. Rabbi Eliezer says, if one curdles milk with the resin of Orlah, it is prohibited. Rabbi Yehoshua said, I have heard explicitly [i.e., I have a received tradition] that if one curdles with resin of leaves or the resin of roots, it is permitted; with the resin of unripe fruit, it is forbidden, because they are [considered] a fruit.</mishna>
    <mishna id="8">Defective grapes, grape pits, grape skins, and wine made from [soaking] them [in water], the outer skin of the pomegranate and its sprout [at the top], nutshells, and fruit pits, are prohibited regarding Orlah, Asherah, and to a Nazirite, while they are permitted regarding Revai. Fruit that fell before becoming ripe are prohibited with regard to all [of the aforementioned laws].</mishna>
    <mishna id="9">Rabbi Yose says, we may plant a shoot from an Orlah [tree], but we may not plant a nut from an Orlah, because it is a fruit. And one may not graft using palm branches [with dates] of an Orlah.</mishna>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="2">
    <mishna id="1">Terumah [a portion of a crop given to a Kohen, priest, pl. Kohanim, which becomes holy upon separation, and can only be consumed by Kohanim or their household] and Terumat Ma'aser [a tenth of the tithe given to a Levi, Levite, which must, in turn, be given to a Kohen and which becomes holy upon separation, and can only be consumed by Kohanim or their household] of Demai [produce from which it is uncertain whether tithes were already taken], Challah [a portion of a batch of bread dough given to a Kohen which becomes holy upon separation, and can only be consumed by Kohanim or their household] and Bikkurim [first-fruits that must be brought to the Temple in Jerusalem and given to the Kohen] are nullified in one hundred and one parts, and they are mixed together and require elevation. Orlah [the fruit of a tree during the first three years after its planting, the consumption or usage of which is forbidden] and Kilayim [the product of forbidden crossbreeding] of the vineyard are nullified in two hundred and one parts, and they are mixed together, and they do not require elevation. Rabbi Shimon says, they are not mixed together. Rabbi Eliezer says, they are mixed with the giver of flavor, but not to forbid.</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">Terumah can [add volume to achieve the minimum to] neutralize Orlah, and Orlah can [add volume to achieve the minimum to] neutralize Terumah. How so? A Se'ah [a specific unit of volume] of Terumah which fell into one hundred [Se’ah of normal foodstuff], and afterwards three Kavin of Orlah or three Kavin of mixed seed in the vineyard fell in; this is [an instance] where Terumah can neutralize Orlah, and Orlah can neutralize Terumah. </mishna>
    <mishna id="3">Orlah can neutralize Kilayim, and Kilayim [neutralize] Orlah, and Orlah [neutralize] Orlah. How so? A Se’ah of Orlah which falls into two hundred [Se’ah of normal foodstuff] and afterwards more than a  Se’ah of Orlah [falls in], or more than a Se’ah of Kilayim of the vineyard; this is [a case] where Orlah can neutralize Kilayim, and Kilayim [can neutralize] Orlah, and Orlah [can neutralize] Orlah. </mishna>
    <mishna id="4">All that cause fermentation, or season, or make a mixture Meduma [mixture of Chullin, permitted foodstuff, and Terumah that is forbidden to non-Kohanim] when mixed with Terumah or with Orlah or with Kilayim of the vineyard, is prohibited. Bet Shammai say, it also defiles. But Bet Hillel say, it does not defile unless it has [the volume of] an egg.</mishna>
    <mishna id="5">Dostai, of the village of Yitmah, was one of the disciples of Bet Shammai, and he said, I received a tradition from Shammai the elder who said, it [one of the items mentioned above] never defiles unless it contains [the volume of an] egg. </mishna>
    <mishna id="6">And concerning what they said, All that cause fermentation, or season, or make a mixture Meduma when is [the rule applied] stringently? [In the case of] a species [mixed] with its [like] species. [When is the rule applied sometimes] leniently and [sometimes] stringently? [In the case of] a species [mixed] with a different kind of species. How so? If leaven of wheat fell into wheat dough and there is enough to cause leavening, whether there is enough to neutralize in one hundred and one, or there is not enough to neutralize in one hundred and one, it is prohibited. If there is not enough to neutralize in one hundred and one, whether there is enough to cause leavening or there is not enough to cause leavening, it is prohibited. </mishna>
    <mishna id="7">How is [this teaching of "All that cause fermentation, or season, or make a mixture Meduma" applied to yield both] a lenient and a strict ruling, [in the case of] one kind [of produce] mixed with [produce] of the same kind? Crushed beans [of Terumah] that were cooked with lentils [which are not Terumah], and they contain enough to impart flavor [to the lentils], whether there was [enough Terumah] to be neutralized in one hundred and one, or whether there is not [enough Terumah] to be neutralized in one hundred and one, it is forbidden [and this is the strict ruling]; if there is not enough of them to impart flavor [to the lentils], whether there was [enough Terumah] to be neutralized in one hundred and one, or whether there is not [enough Terumah] to be neutralized in one hundred and one, it is permitted [and this is the lenient ruling].</mishna>
    <mishna id="8">If leaven of Chullin has fallen into dough, and there is enough to make it ferment, and after that leaven of Terumah or Kilayim of the vineyard [fell in], and there was enough to cause leavening, [the dough] is prohibited.</mishna>
    <mishna id="9">If leaven of Chullin has fallen into dough and caused it to ferment, and after that leaven of Terumah or Kilayim of the vineyard fell in, and there was enough to cause leavening, [the dough] is prohibited. [But,] Rabbi Shimon permits it. </mishna>
    <mishna id="10">Spices of two or three [categories of prohibitions], of one species, or of three different species of spices [of one category of prohibition], render a mixture prohibited by combining together. Rabbi Shimon says, the mixture of two or three categories of prohibition of one species, or two species of one category of prohibition do not combine together.</mishna>
    <mishna id="11">Leaven of Chullin, and of Terumah that fell into a dough and individually, each does not have a sufficient quantity to cause fermentation, but taken together, they did cause fermentation: Rabbi Eliezer says, I go after the last one that fell; but the Sages say, regardless of whether the forbidden leaven fell in first, or last, never does the dough become prohibited, unless there is a sufficient amount to cause fermentation on its own.  </mishna>
    <mishna id="12">Yoezer, a man of Birah, was one of the disciples of the House of Shammai, and he said, I asked Rabban Gamliel the Elder, as he was standing at the Eastern Gate, and he said, regardless of whether the forbidden fell in first, or last, never does the dough become prohibited, unless there is a sufficient amount to cause fermentation on its own.  </mishna>
    <mishna id="13">Vessels that were oiled [in order to soften them], with impure oil, and were then later re-oiled with pure oil, or they were first oiled with pure oil, and afterwards, were oiled them with impure oil: Rabbi Eliezer says, I go after the first, while the Sages say, [its status follows] after the last.</mishna>
    <mishna id="14">If leaven of Terumah and leaven of Kilayim of the vineyard fell into a dough and each individually does not have enough of a quantity to effect fermentation, but together, they did cause fermentation, the dough is prohibited to non-Kohanim, and permitted to Kohanim. Rabbi Shimon allows to both non-Kohanim and Kohanim. </mishna>
    <mishna id="15">If spices of the Terumah and if Kilayim of the vineyard have fallen into a pot, and each individually does not have a sufficient quantity to properly season, but together, they did cause proper seasoning, it is forbidden to non-Kohanim, but permitted to Kohanim. Rabbi Shimon allows it to both Kohanim and non-Kohanim.</mishna>
    <mishna id="16">If a piece of the flesh of Kodshei Kodashim [sacrifices of the highest degree of sanctity, they may be slaughtered only on the north-west corner of the altar, and consumed only within the Temple compound by male priests, or burnt entirely.], [or] of Pigul [sacrifice made unfit because of improper intentions], [or] of Notar [sacrifice made unfit because it was left too long uneaten] that was cooked with pieces [of permissible flesh], it is forbidden to non-Kohanim, but permissible to Kohanim. Rabbi Shimon allows it to both Kohanim and non-Kohanim.</mishna>
    <mishna id="17">If flesh of Kodshei Kodashim and flesh of Kodashim Kalim [sacrifices of a lesser degree of sanctity, they may be slaughtered anywhere in the Temple courtyard and consumed by most anyone, anywhere in Jerusalem] have been cooked together with non-sanctified [permissible] flesh, it is forbidden to the impure, but permitted for the pure.  </mishna>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="3">
    <mishna id="1">A garment that has been dyed using peels of an Orlah [the fruit of a tree during the first three years after its planting, the consumption or usage of which is forbidden] must be burnt. If [this garment] got mixed in with other [garments], they must all be burnt; these are the words of Rabbi Meir. And the Sages say, it becomes neutralized in [a pile of] two hundred and one [other such garments].</mishna>
    <mishna id="2">One who dyes [a thread] the length of m'lo hasit [distance between the splayed thumb and forefinger] with peels of an Orlah tree, and then wove them into a garment, but doesn't know which [thread] it is: Rabbi Meir says, one must burn the garment, and the Sages say, it becomes neutralized in [a pile of] two hundred and one [other such garments].</mishna>
    <mishna id="3">One who weaves [a thread] the length of a Sit from the wool a firstborn animal into a garment, must burn the garment. And [if the thread was from] the hair of a Nazirite or from a firstborn donkey [which needs redemption and he sewed it] into a sack, one must burn the sack. And [with regards to] holy items, they sanctify [whatever they are sewed into], independent of the quantity.</mishna>
    <mishna id="4">A cooked item which is cooked with the peels of an Orlah must be burnt. If [the cooked item] gets mixed with other [such cooked items], it becomes neutralized in two hundred and one [other such cooked items].</mishna>
    <mishna id="5">An oven which was lit with shells of Orlah, and bread was baked in it, the bread should be burned. If that bread was mixed with others, it is neutralized in two hundred and one.</mishna>
    <mishna id="6">One who has bundles of fenugreek which come from a Kilayim [the product of forbidden crossbreeding] of the vineyard must burn them. If [these bundles] got mixed with other [such bundles], they must all be burnt; these are the words of Rabbi Meir. And the Sages say, they are neutralized in two hundred and one. </mishna>
    <mishna id="7">As Rabbi Meir used to say, if it is the normal way to count [an object, individually], then it renders everything as holy [and thereby forbidden]. But the Sages say that only six things render everything as holy; while Rabbi Akiva says there are seven. They are: nuts with brittle shells, and Badan pomegranates, and sealed jars, and beet shoots, and cabbage heads, and Greek gourds. Rabbi Akiva says, also loaves of bread of homeowners. That which is fit for the [laws of] Orlah is Orlah. That which is fit for [the laws of]  Kilayim of the vineyard is  Kilayim of the vineyard.</mishna>
    <mishna id="8">(How so?) If nuts split, pomegranates separate, barrels open, gourds are cut, loaves of bread are crumbled, they are neutralized in two hundred and one.</mishna>
    <mishna id="9">If there is a doubt about [whether or not a certain fruit is] Orlah: in Israel it is forbidden [to have benefit from it], and in Syria it is permitted, and outside the Land [of Israel], one may go down [to the market] and buy it, as long as one doesn't see the gathering. A vineyard that has vegetables planted in it [rendering them Kilayim] and the vegetables are sold outside [of Israel]: in Israel they are forbidden, and in Syria they are permitted, and outside the Land one can go down [to the market] and buy them as long as one doesn't gather them directly. New [wheat] is forbidden by law of the Torah everywhere. But Orlah [is forbidden] by traditional law ascribed to Moshe and Kilayim [is forbidden] by Rabbinic law. </mishna>
  </chapter>
</book>