<book><chapter id="1"><pasuk id="1">There was a man in the land of Uz whose name was Job, and that man was sincere and upright, God-fearing and shunning evil.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Now seven sons and three daughters were born to him.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">His livestock consisted of seven thousand sheep, three thousand camels, five hundred yoke of cattle, five hundred she- donkeys, and very much production; and the man was greater than all the children of the East.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Now his sons would go and make a feast in each one's house on his day, and they would send and invite their three sisters to eat and drink with them.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Now it would come about when the cycle of the feasting days would be over, that Job would send and summon them, and offer up burnt-offerings early in the morning burnt- offerings according to the number of all of them, for Job said, "Perhaps my sons have sinned and blasphemed God in their hearts." So would Job do all the days.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Now the day came about, and the angels of God came to stand beside the Lord, and the Adversary, too, came among them.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The Lord said to the Adversary, "Where are you coming from?" And the Adversary answered the Lord and said, "From going to and fro on the earth and from walking in it."</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Now the Lord said to the Adversary, "Have you paid attention to My servant Job? For there is none like him on earth, a sincere and upright man, God-fearing and shunning evil."</pasuk><pasuk id="9">And the Adversary answered the Lord and said, "Does Job fear God for nothing?</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Haven't You made a hedge around him, his household, and all that he has on all sides? You have blessed the work of his hands, and his livestock has spread out in the land.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">But now, stretch forth Your hand and touch all that he has, will he not blaspheme You to Your face?"</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Now the Lord said to the Adversary, "Behold, all that he has is in your hands; only upon him do not stretch forth your hand." Now the Adversary left the presence of the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Now the day came about that his sons and daughters were dining and drinking wine at the home of their firstborn brother,</pasuk><pasuk id="14">and a messenger came to Job and said, "The cattle were plowing, and the she-donkeys were grazing beside them,</pasuk><pasuk id="15">and Sheba fell upon them and took them, and they slew the youths by the sword, and only I alone escaped to tell you."</pasuk><pasuk id="16">This one was still talking, and another one came and said, "A tremendous fire fell from heaven and burned the flocks and the youths and consumed them; only I alone escaped to tell you."</pasuk><pasuk id="17">This one was still talking, and another one came and said, "Chaldeans formed three bands, spread out on the camels and took them, and slew the youths with the sword, and only I alone escaped to tell you."</pasuk><pasuk id="18">While this one was still talking, another one came and said, "Your sons and daughters were dining and drinking wine at the home of their firstborn brother,</pasuk><pasuk id="19">when, behold, a great wind came from the other side of the desert, and struck the four corners of the house; it fell upon the youths, who died, and only I alone escaped to tell you."</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Then Job stood up, and rent his robe and tore his hair; then he fell to the ground and prostrated himself.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">And he said, "From my mother's womb, I emerged naked, and I will return there naked. The Lord gave and the Lord took; may the name of the Lord be blessed."</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Despite all this, Job did not sin, neither did he ascribe unseemliness to God.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="2"><pasuk id="1">Now the day came about that the angels of God came to stand beside the Lord, and the Adversary too came among them to stand beside the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Now the Lord said to the Adversary, "Where are you coming from?" And the Adversary replied to the Lord and said, "From going to and fro on the earth and from walking in it."</pasuk><pasuk id="3">And the Lord said to the Adversary, "Have you paid attention to My servant Job? For there is none like him in the earth, a sincere and upright man, God-fearing and shunning evil, and he still maintains his sincerity. Yet you enticed Me against him."</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Now the Adversary replied to the Lord and said, "Skin for skin, and whatever a person has he will give for his life.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">But, stretch forth Your hand now and touch his bones and his flesh, will he not blaspheme You to Your face?"</pasuk><pasuk id="6">And the Lord said to the Adversary, "Here he is in your hands, but preserve his life."</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Now the Adversary departed from the presence of the Lord, and he smote Job with severe boils from the sole of his foot to the crown of his head.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Then he took himself a potsherd to scratch himself with, and he sat down in the midst of the ashes.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Then his wife said to him, "Do you still maintain your sincerity? Blaspheme God and die!"</pasuk><pasuk id="10">And he said to her, "You talk as one of the disgraceful women talks. Shall we also accept the good from God, and not accept the evil?" Despite all this, Job did not sin with his lips.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Now Job's three friends heard about all this evil that befell him, and they came, each one from his place; Eliphaz the Temanite, Bildad the Shuhite, and Zophar the Naamathite, and they met together to come to bemoan him and console him.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Now they lifted their eyes [and looked] from afar but they did not recognize him; so they raised their voices and wept, and each one rent his robe, and they threw earth on their heads towards heaven.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Now they sat down with him on the ground for seven days and seven nights, but no one said a word to him because they perceived that the pain was very severe.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Afterwards, Job opened his mouth and cursed his day.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="3"><pasuk id="1">Now Job raised his voice and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"Would the day in which I was to be born be lost, and the night when one said, 'A man has impregnated.'</pasuk><pasuk id="3">May that day be dark; let God not seek it from above, and let no light shine upon it.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">May darkness and the shadow of death defile it; let pitch darkness dwell upon it; let them frighten it like demons of the day.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">That night-may pitch darkness take it; it shall not rejoice among the days of the year; in the number of months it shall not come.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Behold that night shall be lonely; no joyful singing shall come therein.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">May those who curse the day, curse it-those destined to be childless in their union.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">May the stars of its evening be darkened; it shall hope for light but have none, neither shall it see the rays of dawn.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">For He did not shut the doors of my womb, neither did He hide trouble from my eyes.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Why did I not die from the womb? [Why did I not] emerge from the belly and perish?</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Why did knees receive me and why [were there] breasts that I should suck?</pasuk><pasuk id="12">For now, I would be lying tranquilly; I would sleep, then it would be restful for me.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">With kings and counselors of the earth, who build ruins for themselves,</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Or with princes who have gold, who fill their houses with silver.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Or [why] was I not like a hidden stillborn child, like infants who did not see the light?</pasuk><pasuk id="16">There the wicked cease from anger, and there the weary rest.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Together prisoners are tranquil; they hear not the voice of the taskmaster.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Small and great are there, and a slave is free from his master.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Why does He give the toiler light and life to those of bitter spirit?</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Who await death and it is not here, and they spy after it more than after hidden treasures.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Those who are happy over joyous occurrences, rejoice when they find a grave</pasuk><pasuk id="22">for a man whose way is hidden, and God hedged him in.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">For before my meal comes my sigh, and my moans pour like water.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">For the thing I feared has befallen me, and what I dreaded is coming upon me.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">I was not at ease, neither was I quiet, and I did not rest, yet trouble came.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="4"><pasuk id="1">Now Eliphaz the Temanite raised his voice and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"Because He tested you with [one] thing, should you weary? Who can withhold words?</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Behold, you have chastised many, and you have strengthened weak hands.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Your words would pick up the stumbler, and you would strengthen buckling knees.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Now when it comes to you, you weary; it touches you and you are frightened.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Surely, your fear was your foolishness, your hope and the sincerity of your ways.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Remember now, who was innocent that perished, and where were the upright destroyed?</pasuk><pasuk id="8">As I have seen, those who plow violence and sow mischief will reap it.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">From the breath of God they will perish, and from the wind of His nostrils they will be destroyed.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">The roar of an old lion, the voice of a young lion, and the teeth of lion cubs were misled.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">A lion perishes without prey, and the young of the lion will scatter.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Now a word was conveyed secretly to me, and my ear grasped a bit of it.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">In the thoughts of the visions of night, when slumber falls on people,</pasuk><pasuk id="14">terror and quaking befell me, and He frightened most of my bones.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">And a spirit passed by my face; it made the hair of my flesh stand on end.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">It was standing, but I did not recognize its appearance, this image before my eyes; I heard a faint voice.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Can a mortal be more righteous than God, or can a man be purer than his Maker?</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Behold, He does not trust His servants and He casts reproach upon His angels.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Surely those who dwell in mud houses, whose foundation is in dust; they crush them before the worms.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">From morning to evening they are crushed without giving [a thought]; they perish to eternity.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Their haughtiness, which is absorbed within them-does it not leave [them]? They die, and not with wisdom.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="5"><pasuk id="1">Now call; will anyone answer you? To which of the holy ones will you turn?</pasuk><pasuk id="2">For anger will kill a fool, and wrath will kill a naive person.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">I have seen a fool taking root, and suddenly I cursed his dwelling.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">May his sons distance themselves from salvation, and may they be crushed in the gate without a rescuer.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">The hungry shall eat his harvest, and he will take it for the one saved from his weapons, and one of the thirsty shall swallow their riches.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">For not from the dust does ruin emerge, and not from the soil does trouble spring,</pasuk><pasuk id="7">because man is born for trouble, but flying creatures fly upward.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">But I would seek of God, and to God I would commit my cause,</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Who does things great and unsearchable, wonders without number,</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Who gives rain upon the face of the land and sends water upon the face of outside places,</pasuk><pasuk id="11">to place the humble on high, and those blackened are exalted by salvation.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">He frustrates the plans of the crafty, so that their hands do not carry out their plans.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">He takes the wise in their own craftiness, and the counsel of the crooked is hasty.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">By day, they meet darkness, and they grope at noon as at night.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">And He saved [them] from the sword of their mouth, and the needy from the hand of the mighty.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">So it was hope for the poor, and libel shut its mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Behold, fortunate is the man whom God reproves; so do not despise the chastening of the Almighty.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">For He brings pain and binds it; He wounds, and His hands heal.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">In six troubles He will save you, and in the seventh no harm will touch you.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">In famine, He redeemed you from death, and in war, from the power of the sword.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">You shall be hidden from the scourging tongue, and you shall not fear plunder when it comes.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">You shall mock plunder and hoarding, and you shall not fear the beasts of the land.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">But you have a treaty with the stones of the field, and the beasts of the field made peace with you.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">Then you shall know that there is peace in your tent, and you shall visit your habitation and miss nothing.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">And you shall know that your seed shall be many, and your offspring [as numerous] as the grass of the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">You shall come to the grave at a ripe old age, as the grain stack is taken away in its time.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">Behold this; we have inquired into it, so it is. Listen to it, and you-know for yourself. "</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="6"><pasuk id="1">Now Job replied and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"If only my anger and my calamity were weighed, placed together on a scale,</pasuk><pasuk id="3">for now, it would be heavier than the sand of the seas; therefore, my words stammer.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">For the Almighty's arrows are with me, whose venom my spirit drinks; the terrors of God wage war with me.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Does a wild donkey bray when it has grass or does an ox low over its fodder?</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Can bland food be eaten without salt, or is there a taste in the saliva of strong-tasting food?</pasuk><pasuk id="7">What my body refused to touch-they are as cloths for my food.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Would that my request were granted, and God would give what I hope for.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">And may God desire and crush me, enlarge His hand and finish me off.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Then should I yet have comfort, and I will beg, shuddering, that he have no pity, for I have not denied the words of the Holy One.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">What is my strength that I should wait and what is my end that I should restrain my desire?</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Is my strength the strength of stones or is my flesh copper?</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Have I no help, or is counsel lost to me?</pasuk><pasuk id="14">By one who withholds kindness from his friend and who abandons the fear of the Almighty?</pasuk><pasuk id="15">My brethren have betrayed [me] like a stream; like the source of streams they pass,</pasuk><pasuk id="16">which wrinkle from the ice-upon them snow is hidden.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">At the time they become warm, they retreat; when it heats up, they jump from their place.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">The paths of their way are held [by them]; they go up in waste and are lost.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">They look at the paths of Tema; they make a line for the roads of Sheba.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">They are ashamed because they had hoped; they came to it and were disgraced.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">For now you are like it; you fear ruin; yea you fear.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Did I say, "Give me," or "Offer a bribe for me from your wealth"?</pasuk><pasuk id="23">And "Rescue me from an enemy," and "Ransom me from the hands of tyrants"?</pasuk><pasuk id="24">Instruct me and I will be silent, and allow me to understand where I have erred.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">How clear are words of uprightness, but what does your proof prove?</pasuk><pasuk id="26">Do you think to clarify words? They are like wind, words of futility.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">You cast wrath upon an orphan, and you dig [a pit] for your friend.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">But now, agree and turn to me and [see] whether I lie to your face.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">Return now; there will be no injustice, and return again [to see that] my cause is righteous.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">Is there injustice in my tongue, or will my palate not understand wickedness?</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="7"><pasuk id="1">Is not man on earth for a limited time, and are his days [not] like the days of a hireling?</pasuk><pasuk id="2">As a slave, who longs for the shadow, and as a hireling who hopes for his wages,</pasuk><pasuk id="3">so was I made to possess months of futility, and they appointed wearisome nights for me.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">If I would lie down, I would say, 'When shall I arise, and [when will] the evening depart?' And I was sated with restlessness until twilight.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">My flesh is clothed with worms and clods of earth; my skin wrinkled and melted.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">My days are swifter than a weaver's shuttle and are spent without hope.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Remember that my life is wind; my eye will not return to see good.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">The eye of him who sees me shall see me no more; set Your eyes upon me and I will be here no longer.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Just as a cloud is consumed and goes away, so will one who descends to the grave not ascend.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">He shall never again return to his house, neither shall his place recognize him again.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Neither will I restrain my mouth; I will speak with the anguish of my spirit, I will complain with the bitterness of my soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Am I a sea or a sea monster, that You place a watch over me?</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Should I say that my bed shall comfort me, that my couch shall bear my speech</pasuk><pasuk id="14">You terrify me with dreams, and You frighten me with visions,</pasuk><pasuk id="15">so that my soul chooses strangling; death rather than these my bones.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">I despised [my life]; I will not live forever; desist from me for my life is futility.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">What is man that You should give him importance, or that You should pay attention to him?</pasuk><pasuk id="18">That you should visit him every morning and try him every moment.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">How long will You not desist from me, will You not let me go until I swallow my spit?</pasuk><pasuk id="20">I have sinned; what do I do to You? O watcher of man, why have You made me as a mark for You, so that I have become a burden to myself?</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Now why do You not forgive my transgression and remove my iniquity, for now I will lie on the dust; and You shall seek me but I am not here.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="8"><pasuk id="1">Now Bildad the Shuhite replied and said:</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"How long will you speak such things, seeing that the words of your mouth are [like] a mighty wind?</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Does God pervert judgment, or does the Almighty pervert justice?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">If your children sinned against Him, He sent them away in the hands of their transgression.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">If you seek God and supplicate the Almighty,</pasuk><pasuk id="6">if you are pure and upright, He shall arouse [your merit] over you, and will complete your righteous home.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">And your beginning shall be small, but your end shall increase exceedingly.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">For inquire now about the past generation and apply yourself to what their fathers have searched out,</pasuk><pasuk id="9">For we are of yesterday and know nothing, because our days on earth are like a shadow.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Will they not instruct you and tell you, and utter words out of their heart?</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Can papyrus shoot up without a marsh? Can the reed-grass grow without water?</pasuk><pasuk id="12">When it is still in its greenness, it will not be plucked, but before any other grass, it will dry up.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">So are the ways of all those who forget God, and the hope of the flatterer shall be lost,</pasuk><pasuk id="14">whose confidence shall be cut off, and whose trust is a spider's web.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">He leans on his house but it does not stand; he grasps it but it does not endure.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">It is fresh before the sun, and on its garden its tender branch emerges.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Beside the fountain, its roots are entwined; he sees a stone house.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">If one destroys him from his place, then it shall deny him, [saying] 'I have not seen you.'</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Behold this is the joy of his way, and from the earth, others will spring forth.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Behold God will not reject the innocent, nor will he uphold evildoers.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Until He fills your mouth with laughter and your lips with shouting.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Your enemies will be clothed with shame, and the tent of the wicked shall be no more."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="9"><pasuk id="1">Then Job replied and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"Indeed, I know that it is so, but why should a man be righteous with God?</pasuk><pasuk id="3">If he would wish to contend with Him He would not answer him one out of a thousand.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">He is wise in heart and mighty in strength; who hardened [his heart] against Him and remained whole?</pasuk><pasuk id="5">He Who moved mountains but they knew not that He had overturned them in His wrath;</pasuk><pasuk id="6">He Who causes the earth to quake from its place, and its pillars shudder;</pasuk><pasuk id="7">He Who spoke to the sun and it did not shine, and He sealed up the stars;</pasuk><pasuk id="8">He Who alone stretched out the heavens and treads on the high places of the sea;</pasuk><pasuk id="9">He Who made the Bear, Orion, and the Pleiades, and the chambers of the south;</pasuk><pasuk id="10">He Who performs great deeds without limit, and wonders until they have no number</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Behold, He goes by me but I do not see [Him]; and He passes but I do not perceive Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Behold, He strikes suddenly, and who can hold Him back; who will say to Him, 'What are You doing?'</pasuk><pasuk id="13">God will not hold back His wrath; all the helpers of Rahab stoop under Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Surely, that I should answer Him; that I should choose my words with Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">For if I am right, I will not reply; will I supplicate my Judge?</pasuk><pasuk id="16">If I call and He answers me, I will not believe that He would hearken to my voice</pasuk><pasuk id="17">He Who would crush me with a tempest and multiply my wounds for nought;</pasuk><pasuk id="18">He Who would not let me catch my breath, for he would sate me with bitterness.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">If it is a trial of strength- behold He is mighty; and if of judgment-who will summon me?</pasuk><pasuk id="20">If I am innocent, my mouth will condemn me; if blameless, it will make me crooked.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">I am blameless, but I do not know how to find rest; I despise my life.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">It is all one; therefore I said, 'He destroys both the innocent and the wicked.'</pasuk><pasuk id="23">If the scourge kills suddenly, he will mock at the calamity of the innocent.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">The earth has been given into the hands of a wicked one; he covers the faces of its judges. If not, then who is he?</pasuk><pasuk id="25">My days are swifter than a runner; they fled, they saw no good.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">They passed with the ships of Ebeh, like an eagle that swoops upon food.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">If I say, 'Let me forget my complaint, I will abandon my anger and restrain myself.'</pasuk><pasuk id="28">I will gather in all my sadness, I know that You will not declare me innocent.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">If I am wicked, why should I toil in vain?</pasuk><pasuk id="30">I washed myself with snow water and cleansed my hands with purity.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">Then You will plunge me in the ditch, and my garments shall abhor me.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">For He is not man like me, that I should answer Him, 'Let us come together in debate.'</pasuk><pasuk id="33">There is no arbiter between us, who will place his hand on both of us.</pasuk><pasuk id="34">Let Him take His rod off me, and let His terror not frighten me.</pasuk><pasuk id="35">I will speak and I will not fear Him, for I am not so with myself.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="10"><pasuk id="1">My soul quarrels with my life; I will leave my speech with me; I will speak with the bitterness of my life.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">I will say to God, 'do not condemn me; let me know why You quarrel with me.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Is it good to You that You should oppress, that You should reject the toil of Your hands, and shine upon the counsel of the wicked?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Do You have eyes of flesh, or do You see as a man sees?</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Are Your days like the days of a mortal, or are Your years like the days of a man,</pasuk><pasuk id="6">that You should search for my iniquity and seek my sin?</pasuk><pasuk id="7">It is in Your knowledge that I will not be condemned, but no one can save [me] from Your hand.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Your hands shaped me and made me; [Your hosts are] together round about, and You destroy me.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Remember now that You made me like clay, and You will return me to dust.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Did You not pour me like milk and curdle me like cheese?</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Clothe me with skin and flesh and cover me with bones and sinews?</pasuk><pasuk id="12">You have granted me life and kindness, and Your providence watched my spirit.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">But You hid these in Your heart; I knew that it was with You.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">If I sinned, You watched me, and would not cleanse me of my iniquity,</pasuk><pasuk id="15">If I dealt wickedly, woe is to me; and if I am righteous I will not raise my head, sated with disgrace and seeing my affliction.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">And it is so great that You hunt me like a lion, and You repeatedly pronounce a verdict upon me.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">You renew Your witnesses against me, and You increase Your anger with me; shifts with set times are with me.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Now why did You take me out of the womb? Would that I had died and no eye had seen me.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Then I would have been as though I had not existed; would that I was brought from the womb to the grave.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Are not my days few? So desist and withdraw from me, and I will strengthen myself a little,</pasuk><pasuk id="21">before I go and do not return, to a land of darkness and the shadow of death,</pasuk><pasuk id="22">a land of darkness like darkness itself; the shadow of death without orders, and where the light is as darkness.' "</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="11"><pasuk id="1">Now Zophar the Naamathite replied and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"Should not a multitude of words be answered, or should a talkative person be accounted right?</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Your fabrications may silence men, and you mock with no one to embarrass you.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">You said, 'My doctrine is pure, and I was clean in your eyes.'</pasuk><pasuk id="5">But, would that God would speak and open His lips with you,</pasuk><pasuk id="6">and tell you mysteries of wisdom for the wisdom is double, and know that God lends you of your iniquity.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Can you find out the mystery of God; can you find out the limit of the Almighty?</pasuk><pasuk id="8">[In] the heights of heaven, what will you do? Deeper than the grave, what do you know?</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Longer than the earth is its measure, and wider than the sea.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">If He passes and confines and assembles, who can hinder Him?</pasuk><pasuk id="11">For He knows deceitful people; when He sees iniquity, He does not consider it.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">But an empty man will gain understanding, and [from] a wild donkey a man will be born.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">If you prepare your heart and spread out your hands to Him,</pasuk><pasuk id="14">if there is iniquity in your hand, distance it, and do not allow injustice to dwell in your tents.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">For then you will lift your face without a blemish, and you shall be strong and shall not fear,</pasuk><pasuk id="16">for you shall forget trouble; like water that has passed shall you remember.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">And your luck shall rise more than midday; your darkness shall be like the morning.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">And you shall trust for there is hope, and you shall dig [around yourself] and lie in safety.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">And you shall lie down and no one will frighten you, and great men will supplicate you.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">And the eyes of the wicked shall fail, and they shall have no way to flee, and their hope shall result in intense grief."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="12"><pasuk id="1">Now Job replied and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"Indeed you are a people, and wisdom shall perish with you.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">[But] I too have intelligence like you; I am not inferior to you, and with whom are there none comparable to these?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">I am as one who is a laughingstock to his friend, one who calls to God and He answers him that the completely righteous will have laughter.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">A brand of contempt is for the thought of the tranquil, is prepared for those whose foot has slipped.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">The tents of robbers prosper, and those who provoke God are secure, to whomever God brought it with His hand.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">But now inquire of the beasts and they will instruct you, and of the fowl of the heavens and they will tell you.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Or speak to the earth and it will instruct you, and the fishes of the sea will tell you.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Who does not know of all these? For the hand of the Lord has done this,</pasuk><pasuk id="10">in Whose hand is the soul of all living and the spirit of all human flesh.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Does not the ear discern words and the palate taste its food?</pasuk><pasuk id="12">In elders there is wisdom and in longevity there is understanding.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">With Him is wisdom and might; He has counsel and understanding.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Behold, He breaks down and it cannot be rebuilt; He shuts up a man and there can be no opening.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Behold He withholds the water and it dries up; He sends it away and it overturns the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">With Him is might and counsel; His are the misled and the misleader.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">He leads counselors away with madness and He makes judges into fools.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">He loosens the bond of kings and He binds a girdle to their loins.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">He leads princes away with madness and He overthrows the mighty.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">He removes the speech from trusty men, and takes away the sense of the elders.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">He pours contempt upon princes and loosens the belt of the strong.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">He uncovers deep things out of darkness and brings to light the shadow of death.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">He makes nations great and destroys them; He spreads out the nations and leads them.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">He takes away the intelligence of the heads of the people of the land, and He causes them to wander in a wasteland [that is] not a road.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">They grope in the darkness without light, and he causes them to wander like a drunkard.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="13"><pasuk id="1">Behold my eye has seen everything; my ear has heard and understood it.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">I know as much as you; I too am not inferior to you.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">But I would speak to the Almighty, and I wish to reason with God.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">But you combine lies; all of you are quacks.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Would that you kept silent, and it would be accounted as wisdom for you.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Hearken now to my reasoning, and listen to the contentions of my lips.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Will you speak unjustly for God, and will you speak deceitfully for Him?</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Will you show Him favor? Will you contend for God?</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Will it be good when He searches you out? Will you mock Him as one mocks a mortal?</pasuk><pasuk id="10">He will surely reprove you- will you secretly show favor?</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Will not His majesty terrify you? Will [not] His fear fall upon you?</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Your memorials are compared to ashes; your eminences are like eminences of clay.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Keep your peace and leave me alone, so that I will speak, and let come upon me what may.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">For what reason shall I bring my flesh up into my teeth, and take my life into my hand?</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Behold, let Him kill me, I will hope for Him; but I will prove my ways to His face.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">He is also my salvation, because a hypocrite cannot come before Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Hearken to my word, and to my speech in your ears.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Behold now I have set up judgment; I know that I will be accounted innocent.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Who will contend with me, for now I will be silent and perish.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">But do not do two things to me; then I will not hide from before You.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Distance Your compulsion from upon me, and let Your fear not terrify me.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">But call, and I will answer, or I will speak and You answer me.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">How many iniquities and sins do I have? Let me know my transgression and my sin.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">Why do You hide Your face and regard me as Your enemy?</pasuk><pasuk id="25">Will You frighten a rattling leaf? Will You pursue dry stubble?</pasuk><pasuk id="26">That You should write disobediences against me and cause me to inherit the iniquities of my youth?</pasuk><pasuk id="27">And that You should put my feet in the stocks and guard all my ways; You engrave my footsteps.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">And it is like rot that decays like a moth-eaten garment.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="14"><pasuk id="1">Man, born of woman, short of days and full of fear.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">As a blossom, he emerges and is cut off; he flees like a shadow and does not stand.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Do You open Your eyes also on this one and bring me into judgment with You?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean one? Not one.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">If his days are limited, and the number of his months is with You, You set his bounds and he cannot cross.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Turn away from him that he may rest, until, like a hireling, he desires his day.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">For a tree has hope; if it is cut it will again renew itself, and its bough will not cease.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">If its root ages in the earth, and in the dust its trunk dies,</pasuk><pasuk id="9">from the smell of water it will blossom, and it will produce a branch like a sapling.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">But a man will die and he is weakened; man perishes and where is he?</pasuk><pasuk id="11">As the waters fail from the sea, and the river is drained dry.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">So does a man lie down and not rise; until the heavens are no more, they will not awaken, nor will they be aroused from their sleep.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Would that You hide me in the grave, that You would keep me secret, until Your wrath has subsided; give me a set time and remember me.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">If a man dies, will he live? All the days of my lifespan, I will hope, until the coming of my passing.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Call and I will answer You; You desire the work of Your hands.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">But now, You count my steps; You do not wait for my sin.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">My transgression is sealed up in a bundle, and You have attached Yourself to my iniquity.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">And surely the falling mountain gives forth produce and the rock that moves from its place.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Stones [which] the water eroded; it washes away into dust its aftergrowth, but the hope of man You have destroyed.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">You overpower him to eternity and he goes away, [You] change his countenance and You send him away.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">His sons become wealthy but he does not know it; and they become poor but he does not understand.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">But his flesh causes him pain, and his soul mourns for him."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="15"><pasuk id="1">Now Eliphaz the Temanite answered and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"Shall a wise man raise his voice with opinions of wind, and does he fill his belly with the east wind?</pasuk><pasuk id="3">To debate over a matter from which he derives no benefit and words in which there is no avail?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Surely you will do away with fear and increase speech before God.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">For your iniquity teaches your mouth, but you should have chosen the tongue of the crafty.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Let your own mouth condemn you and not I, and let your own lips testify against you.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Were you born before Adam? Were you created before the hills?</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Did you listen to the counsel of God and increase wisdom to yourself?</pasuk><pasuk id="9">What do you know that we do not know? [What do] you understand that is not with us?</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Both old and ancient are among us, who have more days than your father.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Are God's consolations little for you, and the thing that He gave you gently?</pasuk><pasuk id="12">What does your heart teach you and what do your eyes hint?</pasuk><pasuk id="13">That you should return your wind to God and let words come out of your mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">What is man that he should be innocent, and that one born of woman should be just?</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Lo! He does not believe in His holy ones, and the heavens are not pure in His eyes.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Surely [not] one who is abominable and impure, a man who drinks injustice like water.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">I will tell you, listen to me; and this I saw and I will tell.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">That the wise men tell and do not hide from their fathers.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">To them alone the land was given, and no stranger passed in their midst.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">All the days of a wicked man, he mourns, even the number of years that are laid up for the oppressor.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">The voice of terrors is in his ears; in peace a robber will come upon him.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">He will not believe that he shall return from darkness, and he is destined to the sword.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">He wanders for bread, where is it? He knows that the day of darkness is ready at his hand.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">Distress and anguish frighten him; it overpowers him like a king destined for the inferno,</pasuk><pasuk id="25">for he stretched his hand to God and showed his strength against the Almighty.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">He runs toward Him with his neck upright, with the thickness of the body of his shields.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">For he has covered his face with his fat, and he has made collops of fat on his loins.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">And he dwelt in ruined cities, in houses that could not be inhabited, that were destined to become heaps.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">He will not become wealthy, and his possessions will not remain; neither will the gratification of their desire bend to the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">He will not turn away from darkness; a flame will dry out his young branches, and he will turn away by the breath of His mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">He who was misled by futility will not believe that his recompense shall be futility.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">Before his time it will be completed, and his branches will not be green.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">He will cast off his unripe grapes like a vine, and he will throw off his blossom like an olive tree.</pasuk><pasuk id="34">Because the company of a hypocrite is lonely, and a fire consumes the tents of bribery.</pasuk><pasuk id="35">They conceive trouble and bear iniquity, and their belly prepares deceit."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="16"><pasuk id="1">Now Job replied and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"I have heard such [things] many [times]; you are all troublesome consolers.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Is there an end to words of wind? Or what will bring clarity to you that you should answer?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">I, too, could speak like you; if your soul were instead of my soul, I would join words together against you and shake my head at you.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">I would encourage you with my mouth, and the movement of my lips would cease.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Should I speak, my pain will not cease, and should I stop, what will leave me?</pasuk><pasuk id="7">but now, it has wearied me; you have silenced all my company.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">You have shrivelled me up; it has become a witness. My leanness has risen against me; it testifies before me.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">His wrath has torn me; yea, He hates me, He has gnashed His teeth at me. My Adversary sharpens his eyes upon me.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">They open their mouth at me, with disdain they strike my cheeks; united they assemble against me.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">God delivers me to a fool and heals me through the hands of the wicked.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">I was tranquil, but he crumbled me to pieces; He held me by my nape and shattered me, and stood me up as a target for him.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">His archers surround me; he splits my kidneys and does not have compassion. He spills out my gall upon the ground.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">He breached me [with] breach upon breach; he runs toward me like a mighty warrior.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">I sewed sackcloth on my scabs and sullied my radiance in the dust.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">My face became shrivelled from crying, and upon my eyelids is the shadow of death.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">But not because of any violence in my hands, and my prayer is pure.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">O earth! do not cover my blood, and let there be no place for my cry.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Even now, behold my Witness is in heaven and He Who testifies for me is on high.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">My intercessors, my friends, to God my eye pours out tears.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Would that a man could reason with God as a man with his fellow.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">For numbered years will come, and I will go on a way from which I will not return.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="17"><pasuk id="1">My spirit has been destroyed, my days flicker; graves are ready for me,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">even if there were no mockers with me, and in their provocation my eye [did not] abide.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Pay heed now, give me surety with You, for who is it who will shake hands with me?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">For You have hidden their hearts from understanding; therefore, You will not be exalted.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">He who speaks to his friends with flattery-his children's eyes will fail.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">And it set me up as a byword for peoples, and I will be [like] a drum before them.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">And my eye is dimmed from anger, and my limbs are all like a shadow.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">The upright will be appalled by this, and an innocent one will be aroused against a hypocrite.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Yet the righteous holds on his way, and the one whose hands are clean grows stronger and stronger.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">But all of them, [I say] you shall return and come now, and I will not find any wise man among you.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">My days have passed, yea my purposes; the thoughts of my heart have been broken off.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">They turn night into day; the light is short because of the darkness.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Since I hope for the grave as my house, in the darkness I have spread out my couch.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">To the pit I have called, 'You are my father'; 'My mother,' and 'My sister,' to the worms.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Where then is my hope? And as for my hope, who shall see it?</pasuk><pasuk id="16">The limbs of the grave shall descend, even together they rest on the dust."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="18"><pasuk id="1">Now Bildad the Shuhite answered and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"How long? Make an end to the words. Consider, and afterwards we will speak.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Why are we considered like an animal? and reputed dull in your sight?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">One who destroys his soul in his anger! Shall the earth be abandoned for your sake, and shall the Rock be removed from His place?</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Yea, the light of the wicked shall be put out and the spark of his fire shall not light.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">The light shall become dark in his tent, and his candle that is over him shall go out.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The steps of his strength shall be straitened, and his counsel shall cast him down.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">For he shall be sent into a net with his feet, and he shall walk on the toils.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">A trap shall seize him by the heel; He shall strengthen the thirsty ones over him.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">A noose is hidden for him in the ground, and a trap for him on the path.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">All around, terrors frighten him, and beat him off his feet.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">His son shall be hungry, and a misfortune shall be ready for his wife.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">He shall eat the branches of his body; the prince of death shall devour his branches.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">He shall be torn away from his wife who trusted him, and she will send him to the king of terrors.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">She shall dwell in his tent, not being his; brimstone shall be scattered upon his dwelling.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">From beneath, his roots shall dry up, and from above, his branch shall be cut off.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">His remembrance shall be lost from the earth, and he has no name in the street.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">They shall drive him from light into darkness and chase him from the world.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">He shall have neither son nor grandson in his people, and there shall be no survivor in his dwelling places.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Concerning his day-the later people shall be astonished, and the earlier ones shall be seized by quaking.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">These are [fit] only [for] the dwellings of the unrighteous, and this [for] the place of him who did not know God."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="19"><pasuk id="1">Now Job answered and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"How long will you grieve my soul and crush me with words?</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Already ten times you humiliate me; you are not ashamed to alienate yourselves from me.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">And even if I have indeed erred, let my error stay with me.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">If indeed, you are added to my [troubles], and prove against me my reproach.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Know then that God has perverted my cause, and He has encompassed me with His net.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Behold, I cry out [concerning] violence but I am not answered; I cry aloud but there is no justice.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">He has fenced in my way so that I cannot pass, and He places darkness on my paths.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">He has stripped me of my honor, and removed the crown from my head.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">He has broken me down all around and I have gone away; He has uprooted my hope like a tree.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">He has kindled His wrath against me, and He has regarded me as [one of] His enemies.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Together His troops advance; they build their road against me, and camp around my tent.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">He has distanced my brothers from me, and my friends became strange to me.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">My relatives are gone, and my familiar friends have forgotten me.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Those who live in my house and my maidservants consider me a stranger; in their sight I am a foreigner.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">I call my servant and he does not respond; with my mouth I appeal to him.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">My breath is strange to my wife, and I appeal to the children of my body.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Even children despised me; I get up and they talk about me.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">All my intimate friends abhor me; and those whom I loved turned against me.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">My bones cleaved to my skin and to my flesh, and I escaped by the skin of my teeth.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Have pity on me, have pity on me, you, my friends, for God's hand has touched me.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Why do you persecute me like God, and why are you not sated with my flesh?</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Would then that my words be written; would that they were inscribed in a book!</pasuk><pasuk id="24">With an iron pen and lead, forever on the rock they should be hewn.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">But I know that my Redeemer lives, and the last on earth, He will endure.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">And after my skin, they have cut into this, and from my flesh I see judgment.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">That I see for myself, and my eyes have seen and not a stranger; my kidneys are consumed within me.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">Shall you say, 'Why should we persecute him?' And what is the root of the matter found in me?</pasuk><pasuk id="29">Fear the sword, for the wrath of iniquities is the sword, in order that you know the plunder."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="20"><pasuk id="1">Now Zophar the Naamathite answered and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"Therefore my thoughts will cause me to answer me, and because of my silence that is within me,</pasuk><pasuk id="3">the chastisement of my disgrace I hear, and a spirit of my understanding will answer me.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Do you know this from time immemorial, since man was placed on the earth,</pasuk><pasuk id="5">that the triumph of the wicked is short, and the joy of the flatterers is but a moment?</pasuk><pasuk id="6">If his height ascends to the heavens and his head reaches the clouds,</pasuk><pasuk id="7">like his dung, he shall perish forever; those who see him will say, 'Where is he?'</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Like a dream, he will fly away and they will not find him; and he will wander away like a vision of the night.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">The eye that glimpsed him will do so no more, and his place will see him no longer.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">His sons will placate the poor, and his hands will return his plunder.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">His bones are full of his youth, and it will lie on the dust with him.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Though evil be sweet in his mouth, though he hide it under his tongue;</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Though he spare it and will not let it go, but keep it on the middle of his palate;</pasuk><pasuk id="14">His food will turn into the venom of cobras within him.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">He swallowed up wealth and vomited it out, and from his belly God will cast it.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">He will suck the venom of cobras; the tongue of the carpet viper will kill him.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">He will not see the rivulets, the flowing rivers of honey and cream.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">He will return that which he labored for and he will not swallow it; when his gain becomes vast wealth, he will not rejoice.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">When he oppressed, he abandoned the poor; he stole a house, which he did not build.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">For he did not know any rest in his stomach; with his beauty he will not save anything.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Nothing remains of his food; therefore his goods shall not prosper.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">When his desire has been filled sufficiently, he will be in straits; the hand of every laborer will come upon him.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">It shall come to pass that to fill his belly, He shall send upon him His burning wrath and rain upon them with His battle.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">He shall flee from iron weapons; a copper bow shall pierce him.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">One drew it and it emerged from its sheath and its glittering blade shall come forth from its bitterness, [bringing] terrors upon him.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">All darkness is hidden for what awaits him; fire that was not blown shall consume him; harm shall befall the survivor in his tent.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">The heavens shall reveal his iniquity and the earth shall rise up against him.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">The produce of his house shall go into exile; [his goods] shall flow away on the day of His wrath.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">This is the lot of a wicked man, from God; and the inheritance appointed him by God."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="21"><pasuk id="1">Now Job answered and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"Listen closely to my word, and this shall be your consolations.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Bear with me and I will speak, and after my speech you may mock.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Am I speaking to man? Why then should I not be short of breath?</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Turn to me and be silent, and place your hand upon your mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Now when I remember, I become frightened, and my flesh is seized with shuddering.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Why do the wicked live on, grow strong and powerfully rich?</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Their children are well established in their sight with them, and their children's children are before their eyes.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Their houses have peace from fear, and God's rod is not upon them.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">His bull impregnates and does not fail; his cow bears young and does not abort.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">They send forth their infants like sheep, and their children dance.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">They raise [their voice] with the tambourine and the harp, and they rejoice to the sound of the flute.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">They end their days in prosperity, and in a moment they descend to the grave.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">They said to God, 'Turn away from us; we do not wish to know Your ways.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">What is the Almighty that we should serve Him, and what will it avail us that we should pray to Him?'</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Behold, is not their prosperity in their hand? The counsel of the wicked has distanced itself from me.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">How long? May the lamp of the wicked be snuffed out, and may their ruin befall them; may He distribute lots in His anger.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">they shall be like straw before the wind and like chaff that the tempest has stolen.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Should God lay away his pain for his sons? Let Him requite him so that he should know.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Let his eyes see his ruin, and let him drink of God's wrath.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">For what does He care about his house after him since the number of his months has been cut off?</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Can anyone teach knowledge for God? But He judges high-handedly.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">This one dies in his full strength, completely tranquil and peaceful.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">His pails are full of milk, and the marrow of his bones is moist.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">And this one dies with a bitter spirit, having partaken of no good.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">Together on the earth they lie, and the worms cover them.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">Lo, I know your thoughts and the devices that you wrongfully think against me.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">For you will say, 'Where is the house of the prince, and where is the tent [and] the dwellings of the wicked?'</pasuk><pasuk id="29">Have you not asked the wayfarers? Then do not make their signs strange [to yourselves].</pasuk><pasuk id="30">That the wicked man is reserved for the day of calamity; they are brought for the day of wrath.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">Who will tell His way to His face? He did, and who will requite Him?</pasuk><pasuk id="32">But he will be borne to the grave and he will hasten to be beside the stacks of grain.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">The clods of the valley will be sweet to him, and all men draw after him as there were innumerable ones before him.</pasuk><pasuk id="34">Now how do you comfort me with futility, and [only] betrayal remains of your replies."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="22"><pasuk id="1">Now Eliphaz the Temanite answered and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"Does a man benefit God when he teaches them wisdom?</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Does the Almighty care if you are righteous, or is there any gain if you perfect your ways?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Will He reason with you because He fears you? Will He come with you to judgment?</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Is not your evil great, and are not your iniquities without end?</pasuk><pasuk id="6">For you take a pledge from your brothers for nought, and you strip them naked of their clothes.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">You gave the faint no water to drink, and you withheld bread from the hungry.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Does a strong man own the earth, and does a respected one remain therein?</pasuk><pasuk id="9">You sent widows away empty-handed, and the arms of the orphans are crushed.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Therefore, around you are traps, and sudden fear terrifies you.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Or darkness so that you do not see; or an abundance of water covers you.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Is not God in the height of heaven, and [does He not] behold the topmost of the stars, which are lofty?</pasuk><pasuk id="13">And you say, 'What does God know? Does He judge through the dark cloud?</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Thick clouds are a concealment for Him, and He does not see, and He walks on the circle of the heavens.'</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Will you keep the old way, upon which iniquitous people trod?</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Who were cut off when it was not their time, when a river was poured into their foundation?</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Who say to God, 'Turn away from us,' and 'What will the Almighty do to them?'</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Yet He filled their houses with good, but the counsel of the wicked was beyond me.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">The righteous see and rejoice, and an innocent one mocks them.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Whether their substance was cut off, and their pride consumed by the fire.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Accustom yourself now to be with Him and you will be complete; with them good will come to you.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Now learn Torah from His mouth, and lay His words in your heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">If you return to the Almighty, you shall be built up; you shall distance injustice from your tents.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">Then you shall make a fortification on the earth, and on the rocks of the valleys, [the gold of] Ophir.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">And the Almighty shall be [the Judge] of your adversaries, and you shall have abundant silver.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">For then you shall delight in the Almighty and lift your countenance to God.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">Pray to Him and He will listen to you, and you will pay your vows.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">You will make a decision, and it will be accomplished for you, and light will shine on all your ways.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">If they are humble, you will say, "Raise up!" and He will save a humble person.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">He shall deliver one who is not innocent, and he will be delivered because of the purity of your hands."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="23"><pasuk id="1">Now Job replied and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"Even today my speech is bitter; my wound is heavier than my sigh.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Would that I knew and I would find Him; I would come to the place prepared for Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">I would set out [my] case before Him, and I would fill my mouth with arguments.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">I would know the words that He would answer me, and I would understand what He would say to me.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Will He contend with me with much power? He will not place coercion upon me.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">There [my] integrity will be proven with Him, and I will extricate [myself] forever from my Judge.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Behold, I go to the east and He is not here, and to the west and I perceive Him not.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">In the north, when He made it I do not see; He wraps up the south and I cannot see.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Because He knows the way that is with me; He has tested me that I will emerge like gold.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">My foot has held to His path; I have kept His way and do not turn away.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">[I kept] the commandment of His lips and I do not remove [it]; more than my daily bread I kept the words of His mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">But He is One, and who will answer Him? [Therefore,] whatever His soul desires He does.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">For He will complete my sentence, and there are many such things with Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Therefore, I am startled by Him; I ponder and am frightened of Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Yea, God has made my heart faint, and the Almighty has startled me.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Because I was not cut off from before the darkness, and [because He did not] cover the thick darkness from before me.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="24"><pasuk id="1">Why were the times not hidden from the Almighty? And He Who knows him should not see his days.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">[There are some who] remove the landmarks; they violently take away a flock and pasture them.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">They lead away the orphan's donkey; they take the widow's ox for a pledge.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">They make the needy turn off the road; the poor of the land hide together.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Behold, [as] wild donkeys in the desert, they go out to their work, seeking prey; the wilderness yields bread for his young men.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">In the field, they reap his produce, and the wicked gather the plants of the vineyard.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">They make them lie all night naked without clothing and without a cover in the cold.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">From the stream of the mountains they become wet, and without shelter they embrace the rocks.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">They rob from the breast of the orphan, and they take a pledge from a poor man.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">They made [him] go naked without clothing and [from] the hungry they carried off the sheaves.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Between their rows they make oil; they tread the winepresses but they are thirsty.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">From the city people groan, and the soul of the slain cries out; yet God does not impute it for unseemliness.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">They were among those who rebelled because of rain; they did not recognize His ways, neither did they sit in His paths.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Should one rise in daylight, he would murder, he would slay the poor and the needy, and at night he would be like a thief.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">And the eye of the adulterer awaits evening, saying, "No eye will see me," and he puts a mask on his face.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">In the dark, he digs under houses; by day, they lock themselves in; they know no light.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">For together morning is to them [as] the shadow of death, for he recognizes the terrors of the shadow of death.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">He is light upon the face of the water; their portion in the earth is cursed; he does not turn by the way of the vineyards.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Dryness and heat they steal away, [also] snow water; [they descended to] the grave [because] they had sinned.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">The womb forgets him; he is sweet to the worms; he will no longer be remembered. Injustice was broken like a tree.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">He feeds the barren woman who will not bear, but he does not adorn the widow.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">And He draws the mighty men with His strength; he rises and does not believe in his life.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">He grants him safety and he relies [upon it], but His eyes are on their ways.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">They are taken away in a second and he is no more, and they are crushed; like all they are gathered in, and like the tip of an ear of grain they will be cut off.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">And if it is not so, then who will prove me a liar and make my words as nought?"</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="25"><pasuk id="1">Now Bildad the Shuhite answered and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"Dominion and fear are with Him; He makes peace in His heights.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Have His troops a number, and on whom does His light not shine?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">How then can man be just with God, and how can one born of woman be clean?</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Behold, He removes the moon and it will not shine, and the stars are not pure in His eyes.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">How much less, man, who is a worm, and the son of man, who is a maggot!"</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="26"><pasuk id="1">Then Job replied and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"How have you helped the powerless, saved the one who has no strength in his arm?</pasuk><pasuk id="3">How have you advised the one without wisdom, and plentifully declared sound knowledge?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Whom did you tell these words, and whose breath emerged from you?</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Gehinnom is hollow beneath the water and its denizens.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Sheol is naked before Him, and there is no cover for Abaddon.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">He stretches out the north over chaos; He suspends the earth on nothing.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">He binds water in His clouds, and the cloud does not split beneath it.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">He closes in the face of His throne; He spreads His cloud over it.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">He encircled a boundary on the face of the water, until the ending of light with darkness.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">The pillars of the heavens trembled and are astonished from His rebuke.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">With His strength, the sea wrinkled, and with His understanding, He smote Rahab.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">By His breath He made the heavens a tent; His hand caused pain to the bar- like serpent.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Behold these are the outskirts of His ways, and what implication of any matter can be understood therein, and who understands the thunder of His mighty deeds?"</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="27"><pasuk id="1">Then Job again took up his parable and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"As God lives, Who has taken away my right, and the Almighty has embittered my soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">For as long as my soul is within me and the spirit of God is in my nostrils,</pasuk><pasuk id="4">my lips will speak no injustice and my tongue will utter no deceit.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Far be it from me that I should justify you; until I die, I will not give up my innocence.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">I have maintained my righteousness, and I will not let it go; my heart will not reproach [me] because of my days.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">My enemy shall be like a wicked man and he who rises up against me like an unjust one.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">For what is the hope of a flatterer who robs, when God casts off his soul?</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Will God hearken to his cry when trouble befalls him?</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Or will he delight with the Almighty? Will he call God at all times?</pasuk><pasuk id="11">I will instruct you [what is] in God's hand; what is with the Almighty I will not conceal.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Behold all of you have seen; now why do you become altogether vain?</pasuk><pasuk id="13">This is the portion of a wicked man with God, and the inheritance of the powerful, which they receive from the Almighty.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">If his sons increase, they will be for the sword, and his grandchildren will not be sated with bread.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">His survivors will be buried in death, and his widows will not weep.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">If he gathers money like dust and prepares clothing like clay,</pasuk><pasuk id="17">he will prepare, and a righteous man will wear [them], and He will distribute [his] money to the innocent.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">He builds his house as a moth, and as a booth that a watchman made.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">He dies rich and will not be gathered in; he opened his eyes and he is not here.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Terrors shall overtake him like water; at night a tempest snatches him away.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">The east wind carries him off and he goes away, and it sweeps him out of his place.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">And he will cast upon him and not have compassion; from his hand he will flee.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">They clap their hands over them, and those of his place hiss over him.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="28"><pasuk id="1">For silver has a mine, and gold has a place where it is refined.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Iron is taken from earth and copper is smelted from stone.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">He made an end to darkness, and every end He fathoms-a stone of darkness and the shadow of death.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">A stream burst forth from the place of its flow; those who cause the foot to be forgotten are removed, yea, from man they are lifted up.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">A land from which bread emerged, and its place was as though turned into fire.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Its stones [were] a place of sapphire, and it had gold dust.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">A path unknown to brigands and which the eye of a vulture did not see.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Proud beasts did not tread it, neither did a lion pass by it.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">He stretched His hand upon the flinty rock; He turned it over from the root of the mountains.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">In the rocks, He split rivers, and His eye saw all precious things.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">He bound up the depths of the rivers, and [from] Taalumah He brings out light.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">But wisdom-whence will it be found, and where is the place of understanding?</pasuk><pasuk id="13">No mortal knows its value, and it will not be found in the land of the living.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">The deep says, "It is not in me," and the sea says, "It is not with me."</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Fine gold cannot be given in its place, neither can silver be weighed out as its price.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">It cannot be praised with jewelry of Ophir, with precious onyx and sapphire.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Neither gold nor glass can equal it, nor is a pure golden vessel its exchange.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Coral and crystal cannot be mentioned, and the striving for wisdom [is more precious] than pearls.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">The topaz of Kush cannot equal it; it cannot be praised with jewelry of pure gold.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Now whence does wisdom come, and where is the place of understanding?</pasuk><pasuk id="21">It is hidden from the eyes of all living, and it is concealed from the winged creatures of the heavens.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Destruction and death said, "With our ears we heard its report."</pasuk><pasuk id="23">God understood its way, and He knew its place.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">For He looks to the ends of the earth, and He sees under all the heavens.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">To make a weight for the wind, and He meted out the water with a measure,</pasuk><pasuk id="26">when He made a decree for the rain and a way for the clouds [and] the thunders.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">Then He saw and counted it, prepared it, yea, searched it out.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">And He said to man, 'Behold, the fear of the Lord is wisdom and shunning evil is understanding.' "</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="29"><pasuk id="1">Then Job again took up his parable and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"Would that I were as [in] my early months, as [in] the days that God watched over me,</pasuk><pasuk id="3">when He lit His candle over my head; by His light I would go through the darkness.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">As I was in my early days, when God's counsel was upon my tent.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">When the Almighty was still with me, [and] my young men were around me;</pasuk><pasuk id="6">When I washed my feet with cream, and the rock that was with me would pour forth rivulets of oil;</pasuk><pasuk id="7">When I would go out to the gate upon the ceiling; in the square I would prepare my seat.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Youths saw me and hid, and old men rose and stood.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Princes refrained from talking and laid [their] hand on their mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">The voice of nobles was hushed, and their tongues stuck to their palates.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">For the ear [that] heard praised me, and the eye [that] saw bore witness for me.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">For I would deliver the poor who cried out, and the orphan, and one who had no one to help him.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">The blessing of the lost one would come upon me, and I would make the widow's heart sing for joy.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">I put on righteousness and it clothed me; like a coat and a turban was my judgment.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">I was eyes for the blind, and I was feet for the lame.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">I was a father to the needy, and a cause that I did not know, I would investigate.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">I broke the fangs of the unjust, and plucked the prey out of his teeth.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">And I said, I will perish with my nest, and I will multiply days as the phoenix.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">My root will be open to water, and dew will lodge in my branches.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">My honor which is with me will be renewed, and my bow will become stronger in my hand.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">They listened to me and waited, and kept silence for my counsel.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">After my word, they would not ask again, and my speech would drip upon them.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">And they waited for me as for rain, and they opened their mouth after a long time.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">If I would jest with them, they would not believe it, and they would not cast down the light of my countenance.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">I would choose their way and sit at the head, and I would dwell as a king in the troop, as one consoles mourners.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="30"><pasuk id="1">But now, those younger in days than I laugh at me; those whose fathers I despised, to put them with the sheep dogs.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Moreover, why did I need the strength of their hands; old age was wasted on them.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Because of want and because of hunger, they sat in solitude; they would flee to desolation, to the darkness of waste and desolation.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">They pluck salt-wort on shrubs, and the roots of juniper bushes were their fare.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">They are driven forth from the midst [of the city], they shout at them as [at] a thief.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">To dwell in the crevices of the valleys, in holes of earth and rocks.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Among the shrubs they bray; under the nettles they gather.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Sons of churls, sons of ignoble men were broken from the land.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">But now I have become their song, and I have become their conversation piece.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">They abhor me, they have distanced themselves from me, and from my face they have spared no spittle.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">For He untied my bowstring and afflicted me, and they have cast off the bridle before me.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">On my right, "little sprouts" stand; they push away my feet and they cast up against me their ways of destruction.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">They break up my path; they serve to increase my calamity, although they derive no help therefrom.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">As [through] a wide breach they come; under [cover of] darkness they roll upon [me].</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Terrors turned upon me; they pursue my nobility as a spirit, and my salvation passed by like a cloud.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">And now, my soul pours out upon me; days of affliction seize me.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">At night, my bones are picked off me and my sinews have no rest.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">By great force is my garment changed; like the opening of my shirt it girds me.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">It directed me to the mud, and I was compared to dust and ashes.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">I cry out to You but You do not answer me; I stood, and You ponder me.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">You became cruel to me; with the strength of Your hand You manifest hatred to me.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">You lift me up to the spirit, You cause me to ride [on it], and weakness melts me away.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">For I knew that You would return me to death and to the meeting place of all living.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">But not with destruction does He stretch forth his hand; if with His misfortune, He would dandle them.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">whether I did not weep for one who had a difficult time, or whether my soul was [not] grieved for the needy.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">For I hoped for good and evil came, and I looked forward to light and pitch darkness came.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">My innards seethed and did not become silent; days of affliction came before me.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">I went blackened without the sun; I rose in the congregation and I would cry out.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">I was a brother to jackals and a companion to ostriches.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">My skin, which was upon me, was blackened, and my bones dried out from the heat.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">And my harp became mournful, and my flute [turned] into the voice of weepers.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="31"><pasuk id="1">I made a covenant with my eyes, and why should I gaze upon a virgin?</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Now what is the portion of God from above and the heritage of the Almighty from on high?</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Is not misfortune for the unjust and deliverance for workers of iniquity?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Will He not see my ways and count all my steps?</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Whether I went with falsehood, and my foot hastened upon deceit.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">May He weigh me with a just scale and may God know my innocence!</pasuk><pasuk id="7">If my foot has turned away from the road and my heart has gone after my eyes and any wrong has clung to my hands,</pasuk><pasuk id="8">may I sow and another eat, and produce be uprooted.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">If my heart was enticed to a woman, and if I lurked at my neighbor's doorway,</pasuk><pasuk id="10">may my wife grind for someone else, and may others kneel over her.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">For that is lewdness, and it is iniquity deserving punishment.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">For it is fire; it consumes to destruction, and it uproots all my grain.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">If I rejected the judgment of my slave or my bondwoman in their cause with me,</pasuk><pasuk id="14">then what will I do when God arises and when He visits what will I answer Him?</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Did not my Maker make him in the womb, and [did not] One form us both in the womb?</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Did I refrain from the desire of the poor, or did I cause the eyes of a widow to fail?</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Did I eat my morsel alone and did no orphan eat therefrom?</pasuk><pasuk id="18">For, from my youth it raised me like a father, and from my mother's womb I led it.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Did I see a person perishing without a garment or that a needy person had no covering?</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Did not his loins bless me, and with the fleece of my lambs [did he not] warm himself?</pasuk><pasuk id="21">If I raised my hand against an orphan because I saw my help in the gate,</pasuk><pasuk id="22">may my shoulder fall from its shoulder-blade and may my arm be broken from its bone.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">For the misfortune from God is fear to me, and I cannot bear its weight.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">If I put my hope in gold, and to jewelry I said, 'My confidence,'</pasuk><pasuk id="25">If I rejoiced because my wealth was great and because my hand found much;</pasuk><pasuk id="26">If I saw light shining and the moon becoming brighter,</pasuk><pasuk id="27">And my heart was secretly enticed, and my mouth kissed my hand,</pasuk><pasuk id="28">this too is iniquity that bears punishment, for I would have denied God above.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">If I rejoiced with the misfortune of my enemy, and was aroused because harm had befallen him,</pasuk><pasuk id="30">but I did not allow my palate to sin, to ask his soul through an oath.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">If the people of my tent did not say, 'Who will give [us] of his flesh? We will not be sated.'</pasuk><pasuk id="32">A stranger did not lodge outside; my doors I would open to the road.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">Did I, like men, cover my transgressions, to conceal my iniquity in my hiding place?</pasuk><pasuk id="34">For I would subdue a great multitude, and the most contemptible of families frighten me; yet I remain silent and do not go outside the doorway.</pasuk><pasuk id="35">Would that I were given one who will listen to me; behold my inscription; may the Almighty bear witness for me and may my opponent write a book.</pasuk><pasuk id="36">Would I not carry him on my shoulder, bind it to me as crowns?</pasuk><pasuk id="37">I will tell him the number of my steps; I will draw him near, as a prince.</pasuk><pasuk id="38">If my soil complains about me, and its furrows weep together,</pasuk><pasuk id="39">if I consumed its strength without money, and I caused pain to its owner,</pasuk><pasuk id="40">instead of wheat, thistles shall emerge, and instead of barley, noisome weeds. Job's words are ended."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="32"><pasuk id="1">Now these three men ceased to answer Job because he considered himself righteous.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Then Elihu the son of Barachel the Buzite of the family of Ram became angry; he became angry with Job because he thought himself [more] righteous than God.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">He became angry with his three friends because they found no answer and condemned Job.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Now Elihu waited [to reply] to Job with words because they were older than he in days.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Then Elihu saw that there was no answer in the mouth of the three men, and he became angry.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Then Elihu the son of Barachel the Buzite raised his voice and said, "I am young in days and you are very old; therefore, I was awestricken, and I feared to declare my opinion to you.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">I said, 'Days speak, and many years impart wisdom.'</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Indeed, it is a spirit in man, and the breath of the Almighty permits them to understand.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Neither do great men gain wisdom, nor do elders understand judgment.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Therefore, I said, 'Listen to me; I will express my opinion, yea I too.'</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Behold I have awaited your words; I have hearkened for your reasons, until you search out the words.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Yea, I attended to you, and behold, there is no one of you to convince Job, to answer words appropriate for him.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Lest you say, 'We have found wisdom; God will crush him, and not a man.'</pasuk><pasuk id="14">He did not set up words against me; I would not reply to him with your sayings.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">They were dismayed; they answered no more. Words have removed themselves from them.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">And I waited for they did not speak, for they remained silent; they no longer answered.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">I, too, will answer my share; I, too, will express my opinion.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">For I am full of words; the wind of my stomach distresses me.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Behold my belly is like wine that is not opened, like new wineskins, which will burst.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Let me speak so that I will be relieved; let me open my lips and reply.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">I pray you, let me not respect any man's person, neither will I euphemize toward any man.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">For I do not know how to euphemize; or else my Maker would carry me away.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="33"><pasuk id="1">But listen to my words, Job, I pray you, and hearken to all my speech.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Behold now I have opened my mouth; my tongue has spoken with my palate.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">My words are [with] the uprightness of my heart, and with knowledge my lips speak clear [words].</pasuk><pasuk id="4">The spirit of God made me, and the breath of the Almighty keeps me alive.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">If you can, answer me; set up before me and stand.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Behold I am like your mouth to God; I was also formed out of clay.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Behold my awe will not terrify you, and my coercion will not weigh heavily upon you.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">You spoke but in my hearing, and the voice of [your] words I have heard.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">'I am innocent without transgression; I am clean, and I have no iniquity.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Behold He finds pretenses against me; He considers me His enemy.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">He puts my feet into the stocks; He watches all my ways.'</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Behold this. 'You are not right,' I will answer you, for God exceeds man.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Why do you contend with Him because He does not answer any of his matters?</pasuk><pasuk id="14">For God answers in one way and in two, to one who does not see it.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">In a dream, a vision of the night, when sound sleep falls upon men, in the slumbers on the bed.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Then He opens the ear of men, and with their chastisement He seals [them].</pasuk><pasuk id="17">To restrain man from a deed; and He covers haughtiness from man.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">He withholds his soul from the pit, and his life from perishing by the sword.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">And he is chastised with pain on his bed, and most of his bones, [since he is] strong.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">And his living spirit causes him to abhor food, and his soul choice morsels.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">His flesh is consumed from sight, and his bones are dislocated to unsightliness.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">And his soul approaches the pit, and his life to the destroyers.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">If there is an angel over him, an intercessor, one out of a thousand, to declare for a man his uprightness,</pasuk><pasuk id="24">He is gracious to him, and He says, 'Redeem him from descending to the pit. I have found ransom.'</pasuk><pasuk id="25">His flesh is more tender than in childhood; he will be restored to the days of his youth.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">He entreats God and placates Him, and he sees His countenance in prayer, and He requites man [according to] his righteousness.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">He makes a row of men and says, 'I sinned, and I perverted what was straight, but I did not profit.'</pasuk><pasuk id="28">He redeemed his soul from perishing in the pit, and his living spirit shall see the light.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">Behold God does all these, twice or thrice with man.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">To bring back his soul from the pit to be enlightened with the light of life.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">Mark well, Job; listen to me. Be still and I will speak.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">If you have words, answer me; speak, because I wish to justify you.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">If not, you listen to me; be silent and I will teach you wisdom.' "</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="34"><pasuk id="1">Now Elihu raised his voice and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"You wise men, hearken to my words, and you knowledgeable ones, give ear to me.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">For the ear tests words, as the palate tastes food.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Let us choose judgment for ourselves; let us know among ourselves what is good.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">For Job said, 'I am righteous, and God has deprived me of my right.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Because of my sentence, I call [Him] a liar. My wound is incurable without transgression.'</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Who is a man like Job, who drinks derision like water?</pasuk><pasuk id="8">[Who] went on the road to accompany workers of iniquity, and to go with men of wickedness?</pasuk><pasuk id="9">For he said, 'A man derives no benefit when he desires [to go] with God.'</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Therefore, men of understanding, hearken to me; far be it for God [to commit] wickedness or for the Almighty to [commit] injustice.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">For He recompenses man for his deed, and according to man's way He causes him to find.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Surely God does not condemn and the Almighty does not pervert justice.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Who gave Him a charge over the earth, and who disposed the entire world?</pasuk><pasuk id="14">If He puts His heart to it, His spirit and His soul He would gather in to Himself.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">All flesh would perish together, and man would return to the dust.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">And if you wish, understand; hearken to this, lend your ears to the sound of my words.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Will He heal even one who hates judgment? Will you accuse even a very righteous One?</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Is it proper to say of a king, 'scoundrel'; 'wicked,' of nobles?</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Who did not respect princes, and a prince was not recognized before a poor man, for they are all the work of His hands.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">In a moment, they die, and at midnight a nation quakes and passes away; they remove their strength-it is not in their hands.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">For His eyes are upon man's ways, and He sees all his steps.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">There is neither darkness nor the shadow of death wherein workers of iniquity may hide.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">For He will not place additional [guilt] on a man to go to God in judgment.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">He shatters the mighty without number and He stands others in their stead.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">Because He recognizes their deeds; He turns night [upon them] and they are crushed.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">In the place of the wicked He smote them, in the place of viewers</pasuk><pasuk id="27">Because they turned away from following Him, and they did not understand any of His ways</pasuk><pasuk id="28">To bring upon Him the cry of the poor, and He hears the cry of the afflicted.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">When He quiets [them], who will deal wickedly? When He hides His face, who will see Him?-whether [it be done] to a nation or to a man, alike.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">That a flattering man shall not reign, because of the snares of the people.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">For to God should be said, 'I will bear it; I will not destroy [myself].</pasuk><pasuk id="32">Besides what I see, You instruct me; if I have committed injustice, I will not continue.'</pasuk><pasuk id="33">From you[r counsel] should He pay it, for you despised [your life]? Should you choose and not I? And what you know, speak?</pasuk><pasuk id="34">Men of understanding will say to me, and a wise man will listen to me,</pasuk><pasuk id="35">Job does not speak with knowledge, and his words are without sense.</pasuk><pasuk id="36">My Father! May Job be tried to eternity, so that there be repentances among men of iniquity.</pasuk><pasuk id="37">For he adds transgression to his sin; among us he speaks loquaciously and multiplies his words to God."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="35"><pasuk id="1">Then Elihu raised his voice and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"Do you consider this to be customary, what you said,-'My righteousness is greater than [that of] God'?</pasuk><pasuk id="3">That you say, 'What will it benefit you? What profit will I have more than if I had sinned?'</pasuk><pasuk id="4">I will give you a reply, and your companions with you.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Gaze at the heavens and see, and view the skies, which are higher than you.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">If you sinned, what do you do to Him, and if your transgressions are many, what do you do to Him?</pasuk><pasuk id="7">If you are righteous, what do you give Him? Or what does He take from your hand?</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Your wickedness [affects] a man like yourself, and your righteousness a son of man.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Because of the many oppressed ones, they cause [people] to cry out; they cry for help from the arm of the mighty.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">And he did not say, 'Where is God, my Maker, Who deals destruction at night,</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Who teaches us [more] than the beasts of the earth, and Who makes us wiser than the birds of the skies?'</pasuk><pasuk id="12">There they cry out and He does not answer, because of the pride of the wicked.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Indeed, God will not hear vanity, neither will the Almighty see it.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Surely you who say [that] you do not see Him should present your case before Him and wait for Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">And now, what He visited [of] His wrath is nothing, and He did not know because of the great multiplicity.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">As for Job, he opens his mouth with vanity; he increases words without knowledge."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="36"><pasuk id="1">Then Elihu continued and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"Wait awhile for me and I will tell you, for God has more words.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">I will take up my knowledge from afar, and to my Maker I will ascribe righteousness.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">For indeed, my words are not false; you have perfect knowledge.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Behold God is great and will not despise; He is great in strength of heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">He does not preserve the life of the wicked, but He gives the poor their right.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">He does not withdraw His eyes from the righteous, and with kings on the throne He seats them to eternity and they are exalted.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">And if they are bound with chains, are caught with ropes of poverty,</pasuk><pasuk id="9">He tells them their deed and their transgressions, for they increase.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">He opens their ears to discipline and commands that they repent of iniquity.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">If they understand and worship [Him], they will complete their days with goodness and their years with pleasantness.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">And if they do not take heed, they will pass away by the sword and perish because of lack of knowledge.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">But the wicked of heart bring about wrath; they do not beg mercy when He binds them.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Their soul shall die by strangulation, and their living spirit among the profligate.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">He extricates a poor man in his poverty and opens their ear through oppression.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Moreover, it allured you from the narrow mouth, that is wide, not cramped below; and the bedecking of your table shall be full of fatness.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">And if you have had your fill of the sentence of the wicked, the judgment and the sentence will support [you].</pasuk><pasuk id="18">For [there shall be] wrath, lest it entice you to multiply [words], and great ransom will not turn you away.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Will you set up your prayer so that no trouble [befall you], nor any forces of strength?</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Do not yearn for the night when peoples are taken away [as they stand] in their place.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Beware, do not turn to iniquity, for you chose this over poverty.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Behold God deals loftily in His power; who is a teacher like Him?</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Who charged Him with His way, and who said, 'You have performed an injustice'?</pasuk><pasuk id="24">Mention [this] for you will magnify His work, which men have seen.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">All men have seen it; mortal man looks from afar.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">Behold God is great and we do not know; the number of His years is unfathomable.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">For He increases drops of water; they pour rain into His cloud.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">That the heavens drip; yea, they drip because of a great man.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">Or will one understand the spreading of a cloud, the darkness of His pavilion?</pasuk><pasuk id="30">Behold He spread His rain over it, and He covered the roots of the sea.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">For He judges the nations therewith; He gives food to one who has many [children].</pasuk><pasuk id="32">Over the clouds He covers the rain, and He commands it through one who prays.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">Their beloved one preaches to them; [this is] the acquisition, for it also ascends on high.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="37"><pasuk id="1">From this too does my heart quake and spring from its place.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Hear attentively the noise of His voice and the sound that emanates from His mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Beneath the entire heaven I have seen it, and His light is upon the ends of the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">In its wake, a voice roars; it thunders with the voice of its pride, and He will not cut them off for his voice will be heard.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">God thunders with His voice wondrous [thunders]; He performs great deeds, but we do not know.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">For He says to the snow, 'Be upon the earth'; likewise to the shower of rain and to the showers of His mighty rain.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">By the hand of every man he seals so that every man should know his deed.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">The beasts go into ambush, and in their dens they dwell.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">From the Chamber comes a tempest, and from Mezarim the cold.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">From the breath of God He gives forth ice and the breadth of waters in a flood.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Aph Beri burdens the cloud; he scatters His rain cloud.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">And he turns around in circuits by His guidance for their work; whatever He commands them upon the face of the habitable world,</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Whether for the rod, whether for His land, or for kindness that He cause it to come.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Hearken to this, Job; stand still and ponder the wonders of God.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Do you know how God places upon them and the rain of His cloud appears?</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Do you know about the revelations of the clouds, of the wonders of Him Who is perfect in knowledge?</pasuk><pasuk id="17">How your garments are warm when the earth is silenced from the south wind?</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Did you spread out the skies with Him, which are as strong as a molten mirror?</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Let us know what we shall say to Him; we cannot set up [judgment] because of darkness.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Need it be told to Him when I speak, or need a man tell what is kept a secret?</pasuk><pasuk id="21">And now, they did not see the rain; it is [like] bright [clouds] in the skies, and a wind came and cleared them away.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Gold[en splendor] comes from the north; on God there is an awesome glory.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">We have not found the Almighty great in power, and with judgment and much righteousness He does not afflict.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">Therefore, men fear Him; He does not look upon any wise of heart."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="38"><pasuk id="1">Then the Lord answered Job from the tempest and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"Who is this who gives dark counsel, with words, without knowledge?</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Now gird your loins like a man, and I will ask you and [you] tell Me.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Where were you when I founded the earth? Tell if you know understanding.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Who placed its measures if you know, or who extended a line over it?</pasuk><pasuk id="6">On what were its sockets sunk, or who laid its cornerstone?</pasuk><pasuk id="7">When the morning stars sing together, and all the angels of God shout?</pasuk><pasuk id="8">And [who] shut up the sea with doors when it broke forth and issued out of the womb?</pasuk><pasuk id="9">When I made the cloud its raiment and the dark cloud its wrapping?</pasuk><pasuk id="10">And broke for it My prescribed limit, and placed a bar and doors?</pasuk><pasuk id="11">And said, 'Until here you may come but no further, and here [your strength] shall place your waves with pride.'</pasuk><pasuk id="12">In [all] your days, did you command the morning? Did you tell the dawn its place?</pasuk><pasuk id="13">To grasp the corners of the earth so that the wicked shall be shaken from it?</pasuk><pasuk id="14">The seal changes like clay and they shall stand like a garment.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">And their light shall be withheld from the wicked, and the high arm shall be broken.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Have you come until the locks of the sea, and have you walked in the searching out of the deep?</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Have the gates of death been revealed to you, and do you see the gates of the shadow of death?</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Do you understand [everything] until the breadths of the earth? Tell if you know it all.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Which is the way to [the place] where the light dwells, and as for darkness-where is its place?</pasuk><pasuk id="20">That you should take it to its border and that you should understand the paths of its house?</pasuk><pasuk id="21">You knew- for then you were born, and the number of your days would be many.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Have you come to the treasures of snow, and did you see the treasures of hail?</pasuk><pasuk id="23">That I saved for a time of trouble, for a day of battle and war?</pasuk><pasuk id="24">Which way is the light parted, [which way] does the eastern one spread it over the earth?</pasuk><pasuk id="25">Who has separated a place for the hair and a way for the cloud of the thunderclaps?</pasuk><pasuk id="26">To rain on the earth where no man is; a desert in which there is no man.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">To sate darkness and desolation and to cause a source of grass to sprout.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">Has the rain a father, or who begot the waves of dew?</pasuk><pasuk id="29">From whose womb did the ice emerge, and the frost of the heaven-who bore it?</pasuk><pasuk id="30">Like a stone, the water hides, and the face of the deep is caught.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">Can you tie the chains of the Pleiades or loose the straps of Orion?</pasuk><pasuk id="32">Can you take out the constellations each in its time, and can you console Ayish for her children?</pasuk><pasuk id="33">Do you know the ordinances of heaven; can you place his dominion upon the earth?</pasuk><pasuk id="34">Can you lift up your voice to the cloud, or will an abundance of water cover you?</pasuk><pasuk id="35">Will you send forth lightning bolts so that they should go and say to you, 'Here we are'?</pasuk><pasuk id="36">Who placed wisdom in the inward parts or who gave the rooster understanding?</pasuk><pasuk id="37">Who charges the skies with wisdom, and who brings down the bottles of heaven?</pasuk><pasuk id="38">When the dust was poured into a mass and the clods cleaved together?</pasuk><pasuk id="39">Do you hunt the prey for the old lion, or do you fill the appetite of the young lions?</pasuk><pasuk id="40">When they crouch in their dens, they abide in the covert to lie in wait?</pasuk><pasuk id="41">Who prepares for the raven his prey, when his young cry out to God, they wander for lack of food?</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="39"><pasuk id="1">Do you know the time for the mountain goats to give birth? Do you wait for the hinds to calve?</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Do you count the months when they will be filled, and do you know the time of their birth?</pasuk><pasuk id="3">They kneel; they bring forth their young; they send forth their pangs.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Their children grow strong; they grow up on the grain; they go forth and do not return to them.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Who sent the wild donkey free, or who loosed the bands of the wild donkey?</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Whose house I have made the wilderness, and whose dwellings the salt land.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">He mocks the tumult of the city; he does not hearken to the shouts of the driver.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">He spies out the mountains for his pasture, and he searches after every green thing.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Does the wild ox wish to serve you; will it lodge by your manger?</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Can you tie a wild ox to a furrow with his rope or will he harrow the valleys after you?</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Will you rely on him because his strength is great, or will you leave your toil for him?</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Will you believe him that he will return your seed or that he will gather in your threshing floor?</pasuk><pasuk id="13">The wing of the renanim rejoices, or the winged stork or the nozah.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">For she leaves her eggs on the ground, and she warms herself on the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">She forgets that a foot will crack it, and the beast of the field will step on it.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">She is hardened against her young ones as though they were not hers; though her toil is in vain, she has no fear.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">For God caused her to forget wisdom, and He did not give her a share of understanding.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Like the time that she goes off on high; she scorns the horse and its rider.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Did you give the horse his strength? Did you clothe his neck with fierceness?</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Do you make him leap like a locust? The glory of his snorting is terrible.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">They spy in the valley and rejoice with strength; he goes forth toward the arms.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">He scorns fear and is not dismayed; neither does he retreat because of the sword.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">The quiver upon him rattles, the blade of the spear and the javelin.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">With tumult and shaking he hollows out the ground, and he does not believe that it is the sound of a shofar.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">To many shofaroth he says, 'Hurrah!' He smells battle from afar, the thunder of princes and shouting.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">Is it because of your understanding that the hawk grows a wing, that it spreads out its wings to the south?</pasuk><pasuk id="27">Or is it by your order that the eagle flies high, and that he lifts up his nest?</pasuk><pasuk id="28">He dwells on the rock and lodges, on the crag of the rock and the stronghold.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">From there he searches for food; his eyes behold it afar off.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">And his eaglets gulp down blood; and where there are slain, there he is."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="40"><pasuk id="1">Now the Lord answered Job and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"Will one who contends with the Almighty make himself master? He who argues with God, let him answer it."</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Now Job answered the Lord and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="4">"Behold I am of small account; what shall I answer You? I put my hand to my mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">I said one [thing] and I will not answer, and two, and I will not add.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Now the Lord answered Job from a tempest and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="7">"Now gird your loins like a man; I will ask you and [you] tell Me.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Will you even make void My judgment? Will you condemn Me in order that you be justified?</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Do you have an arm like God, or do you thunder like Him with [your] voice?</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Bedeck yourself now with pride and excellence, and clothe yourself with glory and beauty.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Scatter your raging anger, see any haughty man and humble him.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">See any haughty man and subdue him, and crush the wicked in their place.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Hide them in the dust together; bind up their faces in a hidden place.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">I too will confess to you that your right hand will save you.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Behold now the behemoth that I have made with you; he eats grass like cattle.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Behold now his strength is in his loins and his power is in the navel of his belly.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">His tail hardens like a cedar; the sinews of his testicles are knit together.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">His limbs are as strong as copper, his bones as a load of iron.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">His is the first of God's ways; [only] his Maker can draw His sword [against him].</pasuk><pasuk id="20">For the mountains bear food for him, and all the beasts of the field play there.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Does he lie under the shadows, in the covert of the reeds and the swamp?</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Do the shadows cover him as his shadow? Do the willows of the brook surround him?</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Behold, he plunders the river, and [he] does not harden; he trusts that he will draw the Jordan into his mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">With His eyes He will take him; with snares He will puncture his nostrils.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">Can you pull the leviathan with a harpoon, or press down his tongue with a rope?</pasuk><pasuk id="26">Can you insert a fishhook into his nose, or pierce his jaw with a barb?</pasuk><pasuk id="27">Will he offer much supplication to you, or will he speak soft words to you?</pasuk><pasuk id="28">Will he make a covenant with you? Will you take him as a lifelong slave?</pasuk><pasuk id="29">Will you play with him like a bird or tie him to your maidens?</pasuk><pasuk id="30">Will charmers dig pits for him? Will they divide him among the merchants?</pasuk><pasuk id="31">Will you fulfill [your desire] to make a tent of his skin or a shade of fishes of his head?</pasuk><pasuk id="32">Put your hand over him; remember the battle, do not stop.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="41"><pasuk id="1">Behold his hope is in vain; shall not one be cast down even at the sight of him?</pasuk><pasuk id="2">There is no one so fierce that he can stir him up, and who is he who can stand before Me?</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Who came to meet Me? I will pay [his reward]. Everything under the heavens is Mine.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">I will not be silent concerning his sons, either for his acts of heroism or the arrangement of his supplication.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Who exposed the face of his raiment? Who can come within his double bridle?</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Who can open the doors of his face? Around his teeth is terror.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">There is pride in his strong shields, closed with a narrow seal.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">They are so close to each other that no air comes between them.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">One adheres to the other; they stick together and cannot be separated.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">His sneezes flash forth light, and his eyes are like the rays of dawn.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">From his mouth go firebrands; sparks of fire go forth like foam.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">From his nostrils smoke goes forth, like a bubbling pot and an earthenware vessel.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">His breath kindles coals, and flame goes forth from his mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Strength lodges in his neck, and sadness rejoices before him.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">The flakes of his flesh are joined together, poured out upon it, not to move.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">His heart is as strong as stone, and as strong as a lower millstone.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">From his fear the mighty are frightened; the breakers fail.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">He who overtakes him with a sword-it will not remain, [neither will] a spear, a slingshot, nor a coat of mail.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">He regards iron as straw, and copper as rotten wood.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">No arrow can put him to flight; slingstones turn into stubble for him.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Catapult [stones] are regarded as straw, and he plays at the noise of the harpoon.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Under him are rays of the sun; where he lies is gold upon the mire.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">He makes the deep seethe like a pot; he makes the sea like a seething mixture.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">He makes a path shine after him; he considers the deep to be hoary.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">On the dust there is none that rules over him, which is not made to be dismayed.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">He looks at all high things; he is king over all proud beasts."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="42"><pasuk id="1">Then Job answered God and said,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">"I knew that You can do everything and no design is restrained from You.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Who is this who hides counsel without knowledge? Therefore, I told but I did not understand; they are hidden from me and I did not know.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Hearken now and I will speak; I will ask You and [You] inform me.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">I have heard of You by the hearing of the ear, and now, my eye has seen You.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Therefore I despise [my life], and I will be consoled on dust and ashes."</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Now it came to pass after the Lord had spoken these words to Job, that the Lord said to Eliphaz the Temanite, "My wrath is kindled against you and your two companions because you did not speak correctly, as did My servant Job.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">And now, take to yourselves seven bulls and seven rams and go to My servant Job and offer up a burnt offering for yourselves, and Job My servant will pray for you, for I will favor him not to do anything unseemly to you, for you did not speak to Me correctly, as did My servant Job."</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Now Eliphaz the Temanite, Bildad the Shuhite, and Zophar the Naamathite went and did as the Lord had spoken to them, and the Lord favored Job.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Now the Lord returned Job's captivity when he prayed for his friends, and the Lord gave Job twice as much as he had had before.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Now all his brothers and all his sisters and all his previous acquaintances came to him and ate a meal in his house, and they bemoaned him and consoled him concerning all the evil that the Lord had brought upon him, and they gave him, each one one piece of money and each one one golden nose ring.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Now the Lord blessed Job's end more than his beginning, and he had fourteen thousand flocks and six thousand camels and a thousand yoke of cattle and a thousand she-donkeys.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">And he had fourteen sons and three daughters.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">And he named the first Jemimah, the second Keziah, and the third Keren-happuch.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Nowhere in the land were women as beautiful as Job's daughters to be found, and their father gave them an inheritance among their brothers.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Now Job lived thereafter one hundred and forty years, and he saw his sons and his sons' sons for four generations.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Then Job died, being old and sated with days.</pasuk></chapter></book>