<book><chapter id="1"><pasuk id="1">The praises of a man are that he did not follow the counsel of the wicked, neither did he stand in the way of sinners nor sit in the company of scorners.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">But his desire is in the law of the Lord, and in His law he meditates day and night.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">He shall be as a tree planted beside rivulets of water, which brings forth its fruit in its season, and its leaves do not wilt; and whatever he does prosper.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Not so the wicked, but [they are] like chaff that the wind drives away.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Therefore, the wicked shall not stand up in judgment, nor shall the sinners in the congregation of the righteous.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">For the Lord knows the way of the righteous, but the way of the wicked shall perish.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="2"><pasuk id="1">Why have nations gathered and [why do] kingdoms think vain things?</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Kings of a land stand up, and nobles take counsel together against the Lord and against His anointed?</pasuk><pasuk id="3">"Let us break their bands and cast off their cords from us."</pasuk><pasuk id="4">He Who dwells in Heaven laughs; the Lord mocks them.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Then He speaks to them in His wrath; and He frightens them with His sore displeasure.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">"But I have enthroned My king on Zion, My holy mount."</pasuk><pasuk id="7">I will tell of the decree; The Lord said to me, "You are My son; this day have I begotten you.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Request of Me, and I will make nations your inheritance, and the ends of the earth your possession.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">You shall break them with an iron rod; like a potter's vessel you shall shatter them."</pasuk><pasuk id="10">And now, [you] kings, be wise; be admonished, [you] judges of the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Serve the Lord with fear, and rejoice with quaking.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Arm yourselves with purity lest He become angry and you perish in the way, for in a moment His wrath will be kindled; the praises of all who take refuge in Him.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="3"><pasuk id="1">A song of David, when he fled from Absalom his son.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">O Lord, how many have my adversaries become! Great men rise up against me.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Great men say concerning my soul, "He has no salvation in God to eternity."</pasuk><pasuk id="4">But You, O Lord, are a shield about me, my glory and He Who raises up my head.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">With my voice, I call to the Lord, and He answered me from His holy mount to eternity.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">I lay down and slept; I awoke, for the Lord will support me.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">I will not fear ten thousands of people, who have set themselves against me all around.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Arise, O Lord, save me, my God, for You have struck all my enemies on the cheek; You have broken the teeth of the wicked.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">It is incumbent upon the Lord to save, and it is incumbent upon Your people to bless You forever.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="4"><pasuk id="1">To the conductor with melodies, a song of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">When I call, answer me, O God of my righteousness; in my distress You have relieved me, be gracious to me and hearken to my prayer.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Sons of man, how long will my honor be disgraced? [How long] will you love futility? [How long] will you constantly seek lies?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">You shall know that the Lord has set apart the pious man for Himself; the Lord shall hear when I call out to Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Quake and do not sin; say [this] in your heart on your bed and be forever silent.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Offer up sacrifices of righteousness and trust in the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Many say, "Who will show us goodness?" Raise up over us the light of Your countenance, O Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">You gave joy into my heart from the time that their corn and their wine increased.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">In peace together, I would lie down and sleep, for You, O Lord, would make me dwell alone in safety.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="5"><pasuk id="1">To the conductor, on nehiloth, a song of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Give ear to my words, O Lord; consider my meditation.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Hearken to the voice of my cry, my King and my God, for I will pray to You.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">O Lord, in the morning You shall hearken to my voice; in the morning I shall arrange [my prayer] to You, and I shall look forward.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">For You are not a God Who desires wickedness; evil does not abide with You.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Confused people shall not stand before Your eyes; You hate all workers of iniquity.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">You destroy speakers of lies; the Lord abhors a man of blood and deceit.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">But I, with Your great loving-kindness, shall enter Your House; I shall prostrate myself toward Your Holy Temple in the fear of You.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">O Lord, lead me in Your righteousness; because of those who lie in wait for me, make Your way straight before me.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">For there is no sincerity in his mouth; there is malice in their heart; their throat is an open grave; they make their tongue smooth.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Condemn them, O God; let them fall by their own counsels; cast them down in the multitude of their transgressions for they have rebelled against You.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">And let all who take refuge in You rejoice; may they ever shout for joy, and You shall shelter them, and let all who love Your name exult in You.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">For You, O Lord, shall bless the righteous; You shall encompass him with will like a shield.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="6"><pasuk id="1">To the conductor with melodies on the sheminith, a song of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">O Lord, do not rebuke me in Your anger, and do not chastise me in Your wrath.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Be gracious to me, O Lord, because I languish; heal me, O Lord, because my bones are frightened.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">And my soul is very frightened, and You, O Lord, how long?</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Return, O Lord, rescue my soul; save me for the sake of Your loving- kindness.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">For there is no memory of You in death; in the grave, who will thank You?</pasuk><pasuk id="7">I am weary from my sighing; every night I sully my bed; I wet my couch with my tears.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">My eye is dimmed from anger; it has aged because of all my adversaries.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Turn away from me, all you workers of iniquity, for the Lord has hearkened to the voice of my weeping.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">The Lord has hearkened to my supplication; the Lord has accepted my prayer.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">All my enemies shall be ashamed and very frightened; they shall return and be ashamed in a moment.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="7"><pasuk id="1">A shiggayon of David, which he sang to the Lord concerning Cush the Benjamite.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">O Lord, my God, I have taken refuge in You; save me from all my pursuers and deliver me.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Lest he tear my soul like a lion, rending it to pieces with no one to save [me].</pasuk><pasuk id="4">O Lord, my God, if I have done this, if there is any injustice in my hands;</pasuk><pasuk id="5">if I repaid the one who did evil to me, and I stripped my adversary into emptiness,</pasuk><pasuk id="6">may the enemy pursue my soul and overtake [me] and trample my life to the ground, and cause my soul to rest in the dust forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Arise, O Lord, with Your wrath; exalt Yourself with anger upon my adversaries, and awaken for me the judgment that You commanded.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">And [if] a congregation of kingdoms surrounds You, return on high over them.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">May the Lord judge the peoples; judge me, O Lord, according to my righteousness and according to my innocence, which is upon me.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">May evil destroy the wicked, and may You establish the righteous, for the righteous God tests the hearts and the reins.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">My shield is upon God, Who saves the upright in heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">God is a righteous judge, and God is incensed every day.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">If he does not repent, He will whet His sword; He has trodden His bow and made it ready.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">And He has prepared deadly weapons for him; He will make arrows for pursuers.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Behold, he travails with iniquity; he conceives mischief, and gives birth to lies.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">He dug a pit and deepened it, and he fell into the pit that he made.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">His mischief will return upon his head, and his violence will descend upon his crown.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">I will thank the Lord according to His righteousness, and I will sing praise to the name of the Lord Most High.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="8"><pasuk id="1">To the conductor, on the gittith, a song of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">O Lord, our Master, how mighty is Your name in all the earth, for which You should bestow Your majesty upon the heavens.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Out of the mouth of babes and sucklings You have established strength because of Your adversaries, in order to put an end to enemy and avenger.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">When I see Your heavens, the work of Your fingers, the moon and stars that You have established,</pasuk><pasuk id="5">what is man that You should remember him, and the son of man that You should be mindful of him?</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Yet You have made him slightly less than the angels, and You have crowned him with glory and majesty.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">You give him dominion over the work of Your hands; You have placed everything beneath his feet.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Flocks and cattle, all of them, and also the beasts of the field;</pasuk><pasuk id="9">the birds of the sky and the fish of the sea, he traverses the ways of the seas.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">O Lord, our Master, how mighty is Your name in all the earth!</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="9"><pasuk id="1">To the conductor, to brighten the youth, a song of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">I will thank the Lord with all my heart; I will tell all Your wonders.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">I will rejoice and exult with You; I will sing praises to Your most high name.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">When my enemies draw backward, they stumble and are destroyed from before You.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">For You have performed my judgment and my cause; You sat on the throne, O Judge of righteousness.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">You rebuked nations, You destroyed a wicked man; You erased their name forever and ever.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The enemy has been destroyed; swords exist forever, and You have uprooted the cities-their remembrance is lost.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">But the Lord shall sit forever; He has established His throne for judgment.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">But He judges the world with righteousness, kingdoms with equity.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">And the Lord shall be a fortress for the crushed, a fortress for times of distress.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">And those who know Your name shall trust in You, for You have not forsaken those who seek You, O Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Sing praises to the Lord, Who dwells in Zion; relate His deeds among the peoples.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">For He Who avenges blood remembers them; He has not forgotten the cry of the humble.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Be gracious to me, O Lord, see my affliction from my enemies, You Who raise me up from the gates of death,</pasuk><pasuk id="15">in order that I tell all Your praises; in the gates of the daughter of Zion I will rejoice in Your salvation.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Nations have sunk in the pit they have made; in this net that they have concealed, their foot has become trapped.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">The Lord is known for the judgment that He performed; with the act of His hand, the wicked man stumbles. Let us meditate over this forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">May the wicked return to the grave, all nations who forget God.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">For the needy shall not be forgotten forever, neither shall the hope of the poor be lost to eternity.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Arise, O Lord; let man have no power. May the nations be judged for Your anger.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">O Lord, place mastery over them; let the nations know that they forever are mortal man.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="10"><pasuk id="1">O Lord, why do You stand from afar? [Why do] You hide in times of distress?</pasuk><pasuk id="2">With the haughtiness of the wicked man, he pursues the poor man. They are caught in the plots that they have devised.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">For the wicked man boasts about the desire of his soul, and the robber congratulates himself for having blasphemed the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">A wicked man at the height of his anger; "He will not seek; there is no God," [say] all his thoughts.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">His ways prosper at all times; Your judgments are far removed from him. All his adversaries-he blows at them.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">He says to himself, "I will not fall; for all generations I will not be in adversity."</pasuk><pasuk id="7">His mouth is full of oaths and deceits and guile; under his tongue is mischief and iniquity.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">He sits in the lurking-places of the villages; in hidden places he slays the innocent; his eyes spy on Your army.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">He lurks in a hidden place; like a lion in his den, he lurks to seize a poor man; he seizes a poor man when he draws his net.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">He crouches, he bows down, and an army of broken people shall fall by his signals.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">He says in his heart, "God has forgotten; He has hidden His face, He never sees."</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Arise, O Lord God, lift up Your hand; do not forget the humble.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Why did a wicked man blaspheme God? He said in his heart that You do not seek.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">You saw, for You look at mischief and provocation to give with Your power; upon You Your army leaves [its burden]; You would help the orphan.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Break the arm of the wicked, but as for the evil one-You will seek his wickedness and not find [it].</pasuk><pasuk id="16">The Lord is King forever and ever; nations perish from His land.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">You shall hear the desire of the humble, O Lord; may You prepare their heart, may Your ear hearken.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">To judge the orphan and the crushed one, that he no longer continue to break the weak from the earth.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="11"><pasuk id="1">To the conductor, of David; I took refuge in the Lord. How do you say to my soul, "Wander from your mountain, [you] bird"?</pasuk><pasuk id="2">For behold the wicked tread the bow, they set their arrow on the bowstring to shoot in the dark at the upright of heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">For the foundations were destroyed; what did the righteous man do?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">The Lord is in His Holy Temple. The Lord-His throne is in Heaven; His eyes see, His pupils try the sons of men.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">The Lord tries the righteous, but His soul hates the wicked and the one who loves violence.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">He shall rain upon the wicked charcoal, fire, and brimstone, and a burning wind is the portion of their cup.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">For the Lord is righteous; He loves [workers of] righteousness, whose faces approve of the straight [way].</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="12"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor on the sheminith, a song of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Save, O Lord, for the pious are gone, for the faithful have vanished from the sons of men.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">One speaks to another with falseness, smooth talk; they speak with a double heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">May the Lord cut off all smooth lips, the tongue that speaks great things.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Who said, "With our tongue we will overpower; our lips are with us. Who is lord over us?"</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Because of the plunder of the poor, because of the cry of the needy, Now I will rise, the Lord shall say; I will grant them salvation, He shall speak concerning them.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The sayings of the Lord are pure sayings, like silver refined, exposed to the earth, clarified sevenfold.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">You, O Lord, shall guard them; You shall guard him from this generation forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Wicked men walk on all sides when the [one who appears] basest to the sons of men is elevated.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="13"><pasuk id="1">To the conductor, a song of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">How long, O Lord? Will You forget me forever? How long will You hide Your face from me?</pasuk><pasuk id="3">How long will I take counsel in my soul, having sorrow in my heart by day; how long will my enemy have the upper hand over me?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Look and answer me, O Lord my God; enlighten my eyes lest I sleep the sleep of death.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Lest my enemy say, "I have overwhelmed him"; my adversaries will rejoice when I totter.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">But I trusted in Your loving-kindness, my heart will rejoice in Your salvation; I will sing to the Lord for He has bestowed [it] upon me.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="14"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, of David; The fool said in his heart, "There is no God"; they have dealt corruptly; they have committed abominable deeds; no one does good.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">The Lord in Heaven looked down upon the sons of men to see whether there is a man of understanding, who seeks the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">All have turned away; together they have spoiled; no one does good, not even one.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Did not all the workers of iniquity know? Those who devoured My people partook of a feast; they did not call upon the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">There they were in great fear, for God is in the generation of a righteous man.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">You put to shame the counsel of the poor, for the Lord is his refuge.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">O that the salvation of Israel would come out of Zion; when the Lord returns the captivity of His people, Jacob shall rejoice, Israel shall be glad.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="15"><pasuk id="1">A song of David; O Lord, who will sojourn in Your tent, who will dwell upon Your holy mount?</pasuk><pasuk id="2">He who walks uprightly and works righteousness, and speaks truth in his heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">He did not slander with his tongue; he did his neighbor no harm, neither did he take up reproach upon his kinsman.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">A base person is despised in his eyes, and he honors the God-fearing; he swears to [his own] hurt and does not retract.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">He did not give his money with interest, nor did he accept a bribe against the innocent; he who does these shall not falter forever.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="16"><pasuk id="1">A michtam of David; O God, guard me for I have taken refuge in You.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">You should say to the Lord, "You are my Master; my good is not incumbent upon You.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">For the holy ones who are in the earth, and the mighty ones in whom is all my delight.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">May the sorrows of those who hasten after another [deity] increase; I will not pour their libations of blood, nor will I take their names upon my lips.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">The Lord is my allotted portion and my cup; You guide my destiny.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Portions have fallen to me in pleasant places; even the inheritance pleases me."</pasuk><pasuk id="7">I will bless the Lord, Who counseled me; even at night my conscience instructs me.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">I have placed the Lord before me constantly; because [He is] at my right hand, I will not falter.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Therefore, my heart rejoiced, and my soul was glad; even my flesh shall dwell in safety.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">For You shall not forsake my soul to the grave; You shall not allow Your pious one to see the pit.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">You shall let me know the way of life, the fullness of joys in Your presence. There is pleasantness in Your right hand forever.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="17"><pasuk id="1">A prayer of David; Hearken, O Lord, to righteousness, listen to my cry, lend an ear to my prayer, [which is] without deceitful lips.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">May my judgment come forth from before You; may Your eyes see [my] upright acts.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">You have tried my heart; You have visited [upon me] at night. You have refined me and not found; If I think, let it not pass my mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">As for man's deeds, because of the word of Your lips, I kept [myself] from the ways of the profligate.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">To support my feet in Your paths, lest my feet falter.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">I called to You because You shall answer me, O God. Bend Your ear to me; hearken to my saying.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Distinguish Your kind acts to save, with Your right hand, those who take refuge [in You] from those who rise up [against them].</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Guard me as the apple of the eye; in the shadow of Your wings You shall hide me.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Because of the wicked who have robbed me; my mortal enemies who encompass me.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">[With] their fat, they closed themselves up; their mouths spoke with haughtiness.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">[By] our footsteps they surround us now, they set their eyes roaming over the land.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">His likeness is like a lion, which yearns for prey, and as a young lion, which lurks in hidden places.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Arise, O Lord, confront him; bring him down to his knees; rescue my soul from the wicked, Your sword.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Of those who die by Your hand, O Lord, of those who die of old age, whose share is in life, and whose belly You will fill with Your hidden treasure, who have children in plenty and leave their abundance to their babes.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">I will see Your face with righteousness; I will be satisfied with Your image upon the awakening.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="18"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor; of the servant of the Lord, of David, who spoke to the Lord the words of this song on the day that the Lord saved him from the hand of all his enemies and from the hand of Saul.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">And he said, "I love You, O Lord, my strength.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">O Lord, my rock and my fortress and my rescuer; my God, my rock, I will take refuge in Him; my shield and the horn of my salvation, my refuge.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">With praise I call to the Lord, and from my enemies I will be saved.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Bands of death have encompassed me, and streams of scoundrels would affright me.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Bands of the nether world have surrounded me; the snares of death confronted me.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">When I am in distress, I call upon the Lord; yes, I cry out to my God; out of His temple He hears my voice, and my cry comes before Him in His ears.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">The earth shook and quaked, the foundations of the mountains did tremble; and they were shaken when He was angered.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Smoke went up in His nostrils, and fire out of His mouth did devour; coals flamed forth from Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">And He bent the heavens, and He came down, and thick darkness was under His feet.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">And He rode on a cherub and did fly; He swooped on the wings of the wind.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">He made darkness His hiding-place about Him as His booth; the darkness of waters, thick clouds of the skies.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">From the brightness before Him, His thick cloud passed, hail and coals of fire.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">The Lord thundered from Heaven; and the Most High gave forth His voice with hail and coals of fire.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">And He sent out arrows and He scattered them; He shot lightning and He discomfited them.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">And the depths of the water appeared; the foundations of the world were laid bare by Your rebuke, O Lord, by the blast of the breath of Your nostrils.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">He sent forth from on high [and] He took me; He drew me out of many waters.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">He delivered me from my mighty enemy, and from those that hated me, for they were too powerful for me.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">They confronted me on the day of my calamity, but the Lord was a support to me.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">And He brought me forth into a wide space; He delivered me because He took delight in me.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">The Lord rewarded me according to my righteousness; according to the cleanness of my hands He recompensed me.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">For I have kept the ways of the Lord and have not wickedly departed from [the commandments of] my God.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">For all His ordinances were before me; and His statutes I will not remove from myself.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">And I was single-hearted with Him, and I kept myself from my iniquity.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">And the Lord has recompensed me according to my righteousness, according to the cleanness of my hands before His eyes.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">With a kind one, You show Yourself kind, with a sincere man, You show Yourself sincere.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">With a pure one, You show Yourself pure, but with a crooked one, You deal crookedly.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">For You deliver a humble people, and You humble haughty eyes.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">For You light my lamp; the Lord, my God, does light my darkness.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">For by You I run upon a troop, and by my God I scale a wall.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">[He is] the God Whose way is perfect; the word of the Lord is refined; He is a shield to all who trust in Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">For who is God save the Lord? And who is a Rock, save our God?</pasuk><pasuk id="33">The God is He Who girds me with strength; and He makes my way perfect.</pasuk><pasuk id="34">He makes my feet like hinds, and sets me upon my high places.</pasuk><pasuk id="35">He trains my hands for war so that a copper bow is bent by my arms.</pasuk><pasuk id="36">You have given me the shield of Your salvation; Your right hand has supported me, and You have treated me with great humility.</pasuk><pasuk id="37">You have enlarged my step[s] beneath me, and my ankles have not slipped.</pasuk><pasuk id="38">I have pursued my enemies and overtaken them, never turning back until they were consumed.</pasuk><pasuk id="39">I have crushed them so that they cannot rise; yea, they are fallen under my feet.</pasuk><pasuk id="40">For You have girded me with strength for the battle; You have subdued under me those that rose up against me.</pasuk><pasuk id="41">And of my enemies, You have given me the back of their necks; those that hate me, that I may cut them off.</pasuk><pasuk id="42">They pray but no one saves them; [even] to the Lord, but He answered them not.</pasuk><pasuk id="43">Then I ground them as dust before the wind; as the mud in the streets I did pour them.</pasuk><pasuk id="44">You allowed me to escape from the contenders of the people; You shall make me the head over nations; may a people that I do not know serve me.</pasuk><pasuk id="45">As soon as they hear they shall obey me; foreigners shall lie to me.</pasuk><pasuk id="46">Foreigners shall wither, and they shall fear their imprisonments.</pasuk><pasuk id="47">The Lord lives, and blessed be my Rock, and exalted be the God of my salvation.</pasuk><pasuk id="48">The God Who grants me vengeance and destroys peoples instead of me.</pasuk><pasuk id="49">Who delivers me from my enemies; even above those that rise against me You have lifted me; from the violent man You deliver me.</pasuk><pasuk id="50">Therefore, I will give thanks to You, O Lord, among the nations, and to Your name I will sing praises.</pasuk><pasuk id="51">He gives great salvations to His king, and He performs kindness to His anointed; to David and to his seed forever.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="19"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, a song of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">The heavens recite the glory of God, and the sky tells of the work of His hands.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Day to day utters speech, and night to night tells knowledge.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">There is neither speech nor words; their voice is not heard.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Their line goes forth throughout the earth, and their words are at the end of the world; for the sun He made a tent therein.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">And it is like a bridegroom emerging from his chamber; it rejoices like a mighty man running a course.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">From the end of the heavens is its source, and its circuit is to their ends, and none is hidden from its heat.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">The law of the Lord is perfect, restoring the soul; the testimony of the Lord is faithful, making the simple one wise.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">The orders of the Lord are upright, causing the heart to rejoice; the commandment of the Lord is clear, enlightening the eyes.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">The fear of the Lord is pure, existing forever; the judgments of the Lord are true, altogether just.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">They are to be desired more than gold, yea more than much fine gold, and are sweeter than honey and drippings of honeycombs.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Also Your servant was careful with them; for in observing them there is great reward.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Who understands errors? Cleanse me of hidden [sins].</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Also withhold Your servant from willful sins; let them not rule over me; then I will be perfect and I will be cleansed of much transgression.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">May the sayings of my mouth and the meditations of my heart be acceptable before You, O Lord, my Rock and my Redeemer.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="20"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, a song of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">May the Lord answer you on a day of distress; may the name of the God of Jacob fortify you.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">May He send your aid from His sanctuary, and may He support you from Zion.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">May He remember all your meal offerings and may He accept your fat burnt offerings forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">May He give you as your heart [desires], and may He fulfill all your counsel.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Let us sing praises for your salvation, and let us assemble in the name of our God; may the Lord fulfill all your requests.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Now I know that the Lord saved His anointed; He answered him from His holy heavens; with the mighty acts of salvation from His right hand.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">These trust in chariots and these in horses, but we-we mention the name of the Lord our God.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">They kneel and fall, but we rise and gain strength.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">O Lord, save [us]; may the King answer us on the day we call.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="21"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, a song about David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">O Lord, may the king rejoice with Your strength, and how greatly does he exult with Your salvation!</pasuk><pasuk id="3">You gave him his heart's desire, and the speech of his lips You have never withheld.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">For You have preceded him with the blessings of the good man; You have placed a gold crown on his head.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">He asked You for life; You gave it to him, length of days forever and ever.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">His glory is great in Your salvation; majesty and beauty You place upon him.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">For You make him blessings forever; You shall make him happy with joy before You.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">For the king trusts in the Lord and in the loving- kindness of the Most High, that he should not falter.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Your hand shall suffice for all Your enemies; Your right hand shall suffice for those who hate You.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">You shall place them as a fiery furnace at the time of Your anger; may the Lord destroy them with His wrath and may fire consume them.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">You shall destroy their fruit from the earth and their seed from the sons of man.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">For they have directed evil against You; they have devised a plot that they cannot [execute].</pasuk><pasuk id="13">For You shall place them as a portion; with Your bowstrings You shall set [Your arrows] toward their faces.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Exalt Yourself, O Lord, with Your strength; let us sing and chant of Your might.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="22"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, on the ayeleth hashachar, a song of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">My God, my God, why have You forsaken me? [You are] far from my salvation [and] from the words of my moaning.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">My God, I call out by day and You do not reply, and at night I do not keep silent.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">But You are holy; You await the praises of Israel.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Our ancestors trusted in You; they trusted and You rescued them.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">They cried out to You and they escaped; they trusted in You and they were not shamed.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">But I am a worm and not a man; a reproach of man, despised by peoples.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">All who see me will mock me; they will open their lips, they will shake their head.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">One should cast his trust upon the Lord, and He will rescue him; He will save him because He delights in him.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">For You drew me from the womb; You made me secure on my mother's breasts.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Upon You, I was cast from birth; from my mother's womb You are my God.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Do not distance Yourself from me, for distress is near; for there is none to help.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Great bulls have surrounded me; the mighty ones of Bashan encompassed me.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">They opened their mouth against me [like] a tearing, roaring lion.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">I was spilled like water, and all my bones were separated; my heart was like wax, melting within my innards.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">My strength became dried out like a potsherd, and my tongue cleaves to my palate; and You set me down in the dust of death.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">For dogs have surrounded me; a band of evildoers has encompassed me, like a lion, my hands and feet.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">I tell about all my bones. They look and gloat over me.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">They share my garments among themselves and cast lots for my raiment.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">But You, O Lord, do not distance Yourself; my strength, hasten to my assistance.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Save my soul from the sword, my only one from the grip of the dog.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Save me from the lion's mouth, as from the horns of the wild oxen You answered me.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">I will tell Your name to my brothers; in the midst of the congregation I will praise You.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">You who fear the Lord, praise Him; all the seed of Jacob, honor Him, and fear Him, all the seed of Israel.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">For He has neither despised nor abhorred the cry of the poor, neither has He hidden His countenance from him; and when he cried out to Him, He hearkened.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">Because of You is my praise in the great congregation; I pay my vows in the presence of those who fear Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">The humble shall eat and be sated; they shall praise the Lord, those who seek him; your hearts shall live forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">All the ends of the earth shall remember and return to the Lord, and all the families of the nations shall prostrate themselves before You.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">For the kingship is the Lord's, and He rules over the nations.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">They shall eat all the best of the earth and prostrate themselves; before Him shall all those who descend to the dust kneel, and He will not quicken his soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">The seed that worships Him; it shall be told to the generation concerning the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">They shall come and tell His righteousness to the newborn people, that which He has done.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="23"><pasuk id="1">A song of David. The Lord is my shepherd; I shall not want.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">He causes me to lie down in green pastures; He leads me beside still waters.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">He restores my soul; He leads me in paths of righteousness for His name's sake.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Even when I walk in the valley of darkness, I will fear no evil for You are with me; Your rod and Your staff-they comfort me.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">You set a table before me in the presence of my adversaries; You anointed my head with oil; my cup overflows.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">May only goodness and kindness pursue me all the days of my life, and I will dwell in the house of the Lord for length of days.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="24"><pasuk id="1">Of David, a song. The land and the fullness thereof are the Lord's; the world and those who dwell therein.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">For He founded it upon seas and established it upon rivers.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Who will ascend upon the Lord's mount and who will stand in His Holy place?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">He who has clean hands and a pure heart, who has not taken My name in vain and has not sworn deceitfully.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">He shall receive a blessing from the Lord and charity from the God of his salvation.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">This is the generation of those who seek Him, who seek Your presence-Jacob, forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">[You] gates, lift your heads and be uplifted, [you] everlasting portals, so that the King of Glory may enter.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Who is this King of Glory? The Lord, Who is strong and mighty, the Lord Who is a mighty warrior.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">[You] gates, lift your heads and lift up, [you] everlasting portals, so that the King of Glory may enter.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Who is this King of Glory? The Lord of Hosts-He is the King of Glory forever.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="25"><pasuk id="1">Of David. To You, O Lord, I will lift up my soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">My God, I trusted in You; let me not be ashamed. Nor shall my enemies rejoice over me.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Neither shall any of those who hope for You be ashamed; let those who betray [to the extent of] destitution be ashamed.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">O Lord, let me know Your ways; teach me Your paths.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Direct me with Your truth and teach me, for You are the God of my salvation; I hope for You all day long.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Remember Your mercies, O Lord, and Your kindnesses, for they have been since time immemorial.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The sins of my youth and my transgressions, do not remember; what is worthy of Your kindness, You remember for me, for the sake of Your goodness, O Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">The Lord is good and upright; therefore, He leads sinners on the road.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">He leads the humble with just rules and He teaches the humble His way.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">All the Lord's ways are kindness and truth for those who keep His covenant and His testimonies.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">For Your name's sake, O Lord, You shall forgive my iniquity, for it is great.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Who is this man who fears the Lord? He will guide him on the road that he chooses.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">His soul shall abide in prosperity, and his seed shall inherit the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">The secret of the Lord is with those who fear Him, and His covenant is to let them know [it].</pasuk><pasuk id="15">My eyes are always to God for He will take my feet out of the net.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Turn to me and be gracious to me, for I am alone and poor.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">The troubles of my heart have increased; deliver me from my straits.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">See my affliction and my toil, and forgive all my sins.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">See my enemies for they have increased, and they hate me with unjust hatred.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Guard my soul and save me; let me not be shamed for I have taken refuge in You.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Sincerity and uprightness shall guard me, for I have hoped for You.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">O God, redeem Israel from all its troubles.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="26"><pasuk id="1">Of David. Judge me, O Lord, for I have walked with sincerity, and I trusted in the Lord; I shall not falter.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Test me, O Lord, and try me; refine my reins and my heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">For Your kindness is before my eyes, and I walked in Your truth.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">I did not sit with dishonest men, neither did I go with hypocrites.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">I hated the congregation of the evildoers, and I did not sit with the wicked.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">I washed my hands with cleanliness, and I encompassed Your altar, O Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">To proclaim thanksgiving with a loud voice and to recite all Your wonders.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">O Lord, I love the dwelling of Your house and the place of the residence of Your glory.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Gather not my soul with sinners nor my life with men of blood,</pasuk><pasuk id="10">in whose hands are plots and whose right hand is full of bribery.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">But I walk with sincerity; redeem me and be gracious to me.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">My foot stood on a straight path; I will bless the Lord in assemblies.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="27"><pasuk id="1">Of David. The Lord is my light and my salvation; whom shall I fear? The Lord is the stronghold of my life; from whom shall I be frightened?</pasuk><pasuk id="2">When evildoers draw near to me to devour my flesh, my adversaries and my enemies against me-they stumbled and fell.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">If a camp encamps against me, my heart shall not fear; if a war should rise up against me, in this I trust.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">One [thing] I ask of the Lord, that I seek-that I may dwell in the house of the Lord all the days of my life, to see the pleasantness of the Lord and to visit His Temple every morning.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">That He will hide me in His tabernacle on the day of calamity; He will conceal me in the secrecy of His tent; He will lift me up on a rock.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">And now, my head will be raised over my enemies around me, and I will sacrifice in His tent sacrifices with joyous song; I will sing and chant praise to the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Hearken, O Lord, to my voice [which] I call out, and be gracious to me and answer me.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">On Your behalf, my heart says, "Seek My presence." Your presence, O Lord, I will seek.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Do not hide Your presence from me; do not turn Your servant away with anger. You were my help; do not forsake me and do not abandon me, O God of my salvation.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">For my father and my mother have forsaken me, but the Lord gathers me in.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Instruct me, O Lord, in Your way, and lead me in the straight path because of those who lie in wait for me.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Do not deliver me to the desires of my adversaries, for false witnesses and speakers of evil have risen against me.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Had I not believed in seeing the good of the Lord in the land of the living!</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Hope for the Lord, be strong and He will give your heart courage, and hope for the Lord.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="28"><pasuk id="1">Of David. To You, O Lord, I call. My Rock, do not be deaf to me, lest You be silent to me, and I will be likened to those who descend into the Pit.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Hearken to the voice of my supplications when I cry out to You, when I lift my hands towards Your Holy Sanctuary.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Do not cause me to be drawn with the wicked or with those who work iniquity, who speak peace with their friends but evil is in their heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Give them according to their deeds and according to the evil of their endeavors; according to the work of their hands give to them; return their recompense to them.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">For they do not understand the works of the Lord or the deeds of His hands. He shall break them down and not build them up.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Blessed is the Lord, for He has heard the voice of my supplication.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The Lord is my strength and my shield; my heart trusted in Him and I was helped; my heart rejoiced and I will thank Him with my song.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">The Lord is strength to them and He is the stronghold of the salvations of His anointed.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Save Your people and bless Your inheritance, and tend them and elevate them forever.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="29"><pasuk id="1">A song of David. Prepare for the Lord, [you] sons of the mighty; prepare for the Lord glory and might.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Prepare for the Lord the glory due His name; prostrate yourselves to the Lord in the place beautified with sanctity.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">The voice of the Lord is upon the waters; the God of glory thunders; the Lord is over the vast waters.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">The voice of the Lord is in strength; the voice of the Lord is in beauty.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">The voice of the Lord breaks the cedars, yea, the Lord breaks the cedars of Lebanon.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">He causes them to dance like a calf, Lebanon and Sirion like a young wild ox.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The voice of the Lord cleaves with flames of fire.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">The voice of the Lord causes the desert to quake; the Lord causes the desert of Kadesh to quake.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">The voice of the Lord will frighten the hinds and strip the forests, and in His Temple everyone speaks of His glory.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">The Lord sat [enthroned] at the flood; the Lord sat as King forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">The Lord shall grant strength to His people; the Lord shall bless His people with peace.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="30"><pasuk id="1">A psalm; a song of dedication of the House, of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">I will exalt You, O Lord, for You have raised me up, and You have not allowed my enemies to rejoice over me.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">O Lord, I have cried out to You, and You have healed me.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">O Lord, You have brought my soul from the grave; You have revived me from my descent into the Pit.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Sing to the Lord, His pious ones, and give thanks to His holy name.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">For His wrath lasts but a moment; life results from His favor; in the evening, weeping may tarry, but in the morning there is joyful singing.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">And I said in my tranquility, "I will never falter."</pasuk><pasuk id="8">O Lord, with Your will, You set up my mountain to be might, You hid Your countenance and I became frightened.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">To You, O Lord, I would call, and to the Lord I would supplicate.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">"What gain is there in my blood, in my descent to the grave? Will dust thank You; will it recite Your truth?</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Hear, O Lord, and be gracious to me; O Lord, be my helper."</pasuk><pasuk id="12">You have turned my lament into dancing for me; You loosened my sackcloth and girded me with joy.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">So that my soul will sing praises to You and not be silent. O Lord, my God, I will thank You forever.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="31"><pasuk id="1">To the conductor, a song of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">I took refuge in You, O Lord; let me not be shamed forever; rescue me with Your righteousness.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Incline Your ear to me, quickly rescue me; be a rock of strength to me, a stronghold to save me.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">For You are my Rock and my Stronghold, and for Your name's sake, You shall lead me and guide me.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">You shall free me from this net which they have hidden for me, for You are my stronghold.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">In Your hand I entrust my spirit; You have redeemed me, O Lord, God of truth.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">I hated those who await worthless vanities, but I hoped for the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">I will exult and rejoice in Your kindness, for You have seen my affliction; You have known the troubles of my soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">And you did not deliver me into the hands of an enemy; You have placed my feet in a broad place.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Be gracious to me, O Lord, for I am in distress; my eye is dimmed from anger, my soul and my belly.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">For my life is spent in grief and my years in sighing; my strength has failed because of my iniquity, and my bones have decayed.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">From all my tormentors I have become a reproach-and very much so to my neighbors-and fright to my acquaintances; those who see me outside avoid me.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">I was forgotten like a dead person, out of mind; I was like a lost utensil.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">For I heard the gossip of many, terror from all sides when they take counsel together against me; they plotted to take my soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">But I trusted in You, O Lord; I said, "You are my God."</pasuk><pasuk id="16">My times are in Your hands; rescue me from the hands of my enemies and from my pursuers.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Cause Your countenance to shine upon Your servant; save me with Your kindness.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">O Lord, let me not be shamed because I called out to You; let the wicked be shamed, let them be silenced to the grave.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Let lying lips become mute, those that speak against a righteous man falsely, with haughtiness and disdain.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">How great is Your goodness that You have laid away for those who fear You, that You have worked for those who take refuge in You, in the presence of the sons of men!</pasuk><pasuk id="21">You shall hide them in the secrecy of Your countenance, from bands of men; protect them in a shelter from the strife of tongues.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Blessed is the Lord for He has been wondrously kind to me in a besieged city.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">But I said in my haste, "I have been cut off from before Your eyes," but You heard the voice of my supplications when I cried out to You.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">Love the Lord, all His pious ones. The Lord guards those who believe [in Him] and He pays with a bowstring him who works with haughtiness.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">Strengthen yourselves, and He will give your heart courage, all who hope to the Lord.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="32"><pasuk id="1">
Of David, a maskil Praiseworthy is he whose transgression is forgiven, whose sin is concealed.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Praiseworthy is the man to whom the Lord ascribes no iniquity and in whose spirit there is no guile.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">When I was silent, my bones decayed with my moaning all day long.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">For [both] day and night Your hand is heavy upon me; my freshness was transformed as in the droughts of summer, forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">I would inform You of my sin, and I did not conceal my iniquity; I said, "I will confess my transgressions to the Lord," and You forgave the iniquity of my sin forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">For this let every pious man pray to You at the time that You are found, only about a flood of vast waters [that] should not reach him.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">You are a shelter for me, from an adversary You guard me; with songs of deliverance You encompass me forever,</pasuk><pasuk id="8">"I will enlighten you and instruct you which way [to go]; I will wink My eye to you."</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Be not like a horse, like a mule that does not discern; whose mouth must be held with bit and bridle, so that when he is being groomed, he does not come near you.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Many are the pains of the wicked, but as for him who trusts in the Lord- kindness will encompass him.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Rejoice with the Lord and exult, You righteous, and cause all those of upright hearts to sing praises.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="33"><pasuk id="1">Sing praises to the Lord, O you righteous; for the upright, praise is fitting.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Give thanks to the Lord with a harp; with a lyre of ten melodies make music to Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Sing to Him a new song; play well with joyful shouting.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">For the word of the Lord is upright, and all his deeds are with faith.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">He loves charity and justice; the earth is full of the Lord's kindness.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">By the word of the Lord, the heavens were made, and with the breath of His mouth, all their host.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">He gathers in the water of the sea as a mound; He puts the deeps into treasuries.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Let all the earth fear the Lord; let all the inhabitants of the world stand in awe of Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">For He said and it came about; He commanded and it endured.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">The Lord frustrated the counsel of nations; He put the plans of peoples to nought.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">The counsel of the Lord shall endure forever; the plans of His heart to all generations.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Praiseworthy is the nation whose God is the Lord, the people that He chose as His inheritance.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">The Lord looked from heaven; He saw all the sons of men.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">From His dwelling place He oversees all the inhabitants of the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">He Who forms their hearts together, Who understands all their deeds.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">The king is not saved with a vast army; a mighty man will not be rescued with great strength.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">A horse is a false hope for victory, and with his power, he will not escape.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Behold the eye of the Lord is to those who fear Him, to those who hope for His kindness,</pasuk><pasuk id="19">to rescue their soul from death and to sustain them in famine.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Our soul waits for the Lord; He is our help and our shield.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">For our heart will rejoice in Him, because we hoped in His holy name.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">May Your kindness, O Lord, be upon us, as we hoped for You.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="34"><pasuk id="1">Of David, when he disguised his sanity before Abimelech, whereupon he drove him out and he departed.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">I will bless the Lord at all times; His praise is always in my mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">My soul boasts of the Lord; may the humble hear and rejoice.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Declare the greatness of the Lord with me, and let us exalt His name together.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">I sought the Lord and He answered me, and He delivered me from all my terrors.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">They looked to Him and they became radiant, and their faces will not be ashamed.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">This poor man called and the Lord heard, and He saved him from all his troubles.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">An angel of the Lord is stationed around those who fear Him, and He saved them.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Comprehend and see that the Lord is good; praiseworthy is the man who takes shelter in Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Fear the Lord, His holy ones; for there is no want to those who fear Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Young lions suffer want and are hungry, but those who seek the Lord lack no good.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Come, children, hearken to me; I will teach you the fear of the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Who is the man who desires life, who loves days to see goodness?</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Guard your tongue from evil and your lips from speaking deceitfully.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Shun evil and do good, seek peace and pursue it.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">The eyes of the Lord are to the righteous, and His ears are to their cry.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">The face of the Lord is against evildoers, to cut off their remembrance from the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">They cry out and the Lord hearkens, and He saves them from all their troubles.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">The Lord is near to the broken-hearted, and He saves those of crushed spirit.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Many evils befall the righteous, but the Lord saves him from them all.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">He guards all his bones; not one of them was broken.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Evil will kill the wicked, and those who hate the righteous shall be accounted guilty.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">The Lord redeems the soul of His servants, and all who take refuge in Him shall not be accounted guilty.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="35"><pasuk id="1">Of David. O Lord, strive with those who strive against me, battle my foes.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Grasp a shield and encircling armor, and rise to my assistance.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">And arm Yourself with a spear and bar the way before my pursuers; say to my soul, "I am your salvation."</pasuk><pasuk id="4">May those who seek my life be shamed and embarrassed; may those who plan my harm draw backward and be abashed.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Let them be as chaff before the wind, with an angel of the Lord thrusting them.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">May their way be dark and slippery, with an angel of the Lord pursuing them.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">For without cause they have hidden for me a pit, yea a net; without cause they have dug it for my soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">May darkness that he does not know come upon him, and his net that he hid shall ensnare him; in the darkness may he fall into it.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">And my soul shall exult in the Lord; it shall rejoice in His salvation.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">All my bones shall say, O Lord, who is like You, Who saves a poor man from one stronger than he and a poor man and a needy one from one who robs him.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">False witnesses rise up; they ask me of things that I know not.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">They recompense me with evil instead of good, death to my soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">But, as for me, when they were ill, my attire was sackcloth; I afflicted myself with fasting, and may my prayer return upon my bosom.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">I walked about as though it were a friend or as though it were my own brother; I was bowed with gloom as the mourning of a mother.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">And, when I limped, they rejoiced and gathered; lame people gathered about me, [why,] I do not know. Were they to tear, they would not draw blood.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Because of the flattery of scorn for food, they gnash their teeth at me.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">O Lord, how long will You look on? Return my soul from their darkness, my only one from young lions.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">I will thank You in a large assembly; in a mighty people I will praise You.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Let them not rejoice over me, those who are my enemies for an unjust cause, neither shall those who hate me for nought wink their eyes.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">For they do not speak peace, and against the crushed people of the earth they think words of deceit.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">And they opened their mouth wide against me and they said, "Aha! Aha! Our eyes have seen [what we desired]."</pasuk><pasuk id="22">You saw, O Lord, do not be silent; O Lord, do not distance Yourself from me.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Arouse Yourself and awaken to my judgment, my God and my Lord, to my cause.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">Judge me according to Your righteousness, O Lord, my God, and let them not rejoice over me.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">Let them not say in their hearts, "Our soul rejoices." Let them not say, "We have swallowed him up."</pasuk><pasuk id="26">Let them be ashamed and abashed together, those who rejoice at my misfortune; let them be clothed in shame and disgrace, those who raise themselves haughtily over me.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">Let those who desire my vindication sing praises and rejoice, and let them constantly say, "May the Lord, Who desires the peace of His servant, be magnified."</pasuk><pasuk id="28">And my tongue shall utter Your righteousness, Your praise all day long.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="36"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor. Of the servant of the Lord, of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">The word of the transgression to the wicked man, in the midst of my heart, is that there is no fear of God before his eyes.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">For it smoothed the way before him in his eyes, to find his iniquity to hate [him].</pasuk><pasuk id="4">The words of his mouth are iniquity and deceit; he refrained from learning to improve.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">He thinks iniquity on his couch; he stands on a way that is not good; he does not reject evil.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">O Lord, Your kindness is in the heavens; Your faith is until the sky.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Your charity is like the mighty mountains; Your judgments are [like] the vast deep. You save both man and beast, O Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">How precious is Your kindness, O God, and the sons of man will take refuge in the shadow of Your wings.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">They will be sated from the fat of Your house, and with the stream of Your delights You give them to drink.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">For with You is the source of life; in Your light we will see light.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Extend Your kindness to those who know You, and Your charity to the upright of heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Let the foot of haughtiness not come with me, neither shall the hand of the wicked cause me to wander.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">There the workers of iniquity have fallen; they have been thrust away and were unable to rise.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="37"><pasuk id="1">Of David. Do not compete with the evildoers; do not envy those who commit injustice.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">For they will be speedily cut off like grass and wither like green vegetation.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Trust in the Lord and do good; dwell in the land and be nourished by faith.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">So shall you delight in the Lord, and He will give you what your heart desires.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Commit your way to the Lord, and trust in Him and He will act.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">And He will reveal your righteousness like the light, and your judgments like noon.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Wait for the Lord and hope for Him; do not compete with one whose way prospers, with a man who executes malicious plans.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Desist from anger and forsake wrath; do not compete only to do evil.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">For evildoers shall be cut off, and those who hope for the Lord-they will inherit the land.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">A short while longer and the wicked man is not here, and you shall look at his place and he is not there.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">But the humble shall inherit the land, and they shall delight in much peace.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">The wicked man plots against the righteous and gnashes his teeth at him.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">The Lord will scoff at him because He saw that his day will come.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">The wicked initiated war and bent their bow to cast down the poor and the needy, to slay those who walk on a straight path.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Their sword shall enter their heart, and their bows shall be broken.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">The few of the righteous are better than the multitude of many wicked men.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">For the arms of the wicked shall be broken, but the Lord supports the righteous.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">The Lord knows the days of the innocent, and their inheritance will be forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">They will not be ashamed in time of calamity, and in days of famine they shall still be satisfied.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">For the wicked will perish, and the enemies of the Lord are like disappearing light on the plains; they are consumed in smoke, yea they are consumed.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">A wicked man borrows and does not pay, but the Righteous one is gracious and gives.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">For those blessed by Him will inherit the land, and those cursed by Him will be cut off.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">From the Lord a mighty man's steps are established, for He delights in his way.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">If he falls, he will not be cast down, for the Lord supports his hand.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">I was young, I also aged, and I have not seen a righteous man forsaken and his seed seeking bread.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">All day long he is gracious and lends, and his seed is due for a blessing.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">Shun evil and do good, and dwell forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">For the Lord loves justice, and He shall not forsake His pious ones; they will be guarded forever, but the seed of the wicked shall be cut off.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">The righteous shall inherit the land and dwell forever in it.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">The righteous man's mouth utters wisdom, and his tongue speaks judgment.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">The law of his God is in his heart; his feet do not falter.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">The wicked man watches for the righteous man and seeks to put him to death.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">The Lord shall not leave him in his hands, and He shall not condemn him [the righteous] when he [the wicked] is judged.</pasuk><pasuk id="34">Hope to the Lord and keep His way; He will exalt you to inherit the land, and you will witness the destruction of the wicked.</pasuk><pasuk id="35">I saw a wicked man, powerful, well-rooted as a native who is fresh.</pasuk><pasuk id="36">And he passed away and behold! he is not here, and I sought him and he was not found.</pasuk><pasuk id="37">Observe the innocent and see the upright, for there is a future for the man of peace.</pasuk><pasuk id="38">But transgressors were destroyed together; the future of the wicked was cut off.</pasuk><pasuk id="39">But the salvation of the righteous is from the Lord, their stronghold in time of distress.</pasuk><pasuk id="40">The Lord helped them and rescued them; He rescued them from the wicked and saved them because they took refuge in Him.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="38"><pasuk id="1">A song of David, to make remembrance.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">O Lord, do not reprove me with Your anger, nor chastise me with Your wrath.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">For Your arrows have been shot into me, and Your hand has come down upon me.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">There is no soundness in my flesh because of Your fury; there is no peace in my bones because of my sin.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">For my iniquities passed over my head; as a heavy burden they are too heavy for me.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">My boils are putrid; they fester because of my folly.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">I am very much stunned and bowed; all day I go around in gloom.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">For my loins are full of self-effacement; there is no soundness in my flesh.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">I passed out and was very crushed; I moaned from the turmoil in my heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">O Lord, all my desire is before You, and my sigh is not hidden from You.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">My heart is engulfed; my strength has left me, and the light of my eyes- they too are not with me.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">My lovers and my friends stand aloof from my affliction, and those close to me stood afar.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">And those who seek my life lay traps, and those who seek my harm speak treachery, and all day long they think of deceits.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">But I am as a deaf person, I do not hear, and like a mute, who does not open his mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">And I was as a man who does not understand and in whose mouth are no arguments.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Because I hoped for You, O Lord; You shall answer, O Lord, my God.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">For I said, "Lest they rejoice over me; when my foot faltered, they magnified themselves over me."</pasuk><pasuk id="18">For I am ready for disaster, and my pain is always before me.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">For I relate my iniquity; I worry about my sin.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">But my enemies are in the vigor of life, and those who hate me for false reasons have become great.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">And they repay evil for good; they hate me for my pursuit of goodness.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Do not forsake me, O Lord, my God; do not distance Yourself from me.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Hasten to my aid, O Lord, my salvation.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="39"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, to Jeduthun, a song of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">I said, "I will guard my ways from sinning with my tongue; I will guard my mouth [as with] a muzzle while the wicked man is still before me.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">I made myself dumb in silence; I was silent from good although my pain was intense.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">My heart is hot within me; in my thoughts fire burns; I spoke with my tongue,</pasuk><pasuk id="5">O Lord, let me know my end, and the measure of my days, what it is; I would know when I will cease.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Behold You made my days as handbreadths, and my old age is as nought before You; surely all vanity is in every man; this is his condition forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Man walks but in darkness; all that they stir is but vanity; he gathers yet he knows not who will bring them in.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">And now, what have I hoped, O Lord? My hope to You is;</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Save me from all my transgressions; do not make me the reproach of an ignoble man.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">I have become mute; I will not open my mouth because You have done it.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Remove Your affliction from me; from the fear of Your hand I perish.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">With rebukes for iniquity You have chastised man; You have caused his flesh to decay as by a moth. Surely all man is vanity forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Hear my prayer, O Lord, and hearken to my cry. Be not silent to my tears, for I am a stranger with You, a dweller as all my forefathers.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Turn away from me that I may recover, before I go and am here no longer."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="40"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, of David a song.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">I have greatly hoped for the Lord, and He extended [His ear] to me and heard my cry.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">And He drew me up out of the roaring pit, from the thick mire, and He set my feet upon a rock, He established my steps.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">He put a new song into my mouth, a praise to our God, so that many may see and fear, and trust in the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Praiseworthy is the man who made the Lord his trust, and did not turn to the haughty and those who turn to falsehood.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">You have done great things, You, O Lord my God. Your wonders and Your thoughts are for us. There is none to equal You; were I to tell and speak, they would be too many to tell.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">You desired neither sacrifice nor meal offering; You dug ears for me; a burnt offering or a sin offering You did not request.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Then I said, "Behold I have come," with a scroll of a book written for me.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">O God, I desired to do Your will and [to have] Your law within my innards.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">I brought tidings of righteousness in a great assembly. Behold, I will not withhold my lips, O Lord, You know.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">I did not conceal Your charity within my heart; I stated Your faith and Your salvation-I did not withhold Your kindness and truth-to a great assembly.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">You, O Lord, do not withhold Your mercies from me; may Your kindness and Your truth always watch me.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">For countless evils have encompassed me; my iniquities have overtaken me and I could not see [them because] they are more numerous than the hairs of my head, and my heart has forsaken me.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">O Lord, be willing to save me; O Lord, hasten to my help.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">May those who seek my soul to destroy it be shamed and embarrassed together; may those who seek to harm me retreat and be humiliated.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">May they be bewildered afterwards because of their shame, those who say about me, "Aha! Aha!"</pasuk><pasuk id="17">All who seek You shall exult and rejoice; those who love Your salvation shall constantly say, "May the Lord be magnified."</pasuk><pasuk id="18">But I am poor and needy; may the Lord think of me. You are my help and my rescuer, my God; do not delay.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="41"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, a song of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Praiseworthy is he who looks after the poor; on a day of calamity the Lord will rescue him.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">The Lord will preserve him and keep him alive, and he will be praised in the land, and You will not deliver him into the desire of his enemies.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">The Lord will support him on his sickbed; when You have transformed his entire restfulness in his illness.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">I said, "O Lord, be gracious to me; heal my soul because I have sinned against You."</pasuk><pasuk id="6">My enemies speak evil of me; "When will he die and his name be lost?"</pasuk><pasuk id="7">And if he comes to see [me], he speaks falsely; his heart gathers iniquity for him; when he goes outside, he talks.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">All my enemies whisper together about me; concerning me, they think evil.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">"An evil thing shall be poured into him, and once he lies down, he will no longer rise."</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Even my ally, in whom I trusted, who eats my bread, developed an ambush for me.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">But You, O Lord, be gracious to me and raise me up, so that I may repay them.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">With this I shall know that You desired me, when my enemy does not shout joyfully over me.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">As for me, because of my innocence You shall support me, and stand me up before You forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Blessed is the Lord, the God of Israel from all times past and to all times to come. Amen and amen.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="42"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, a maskil of the sons of Korah.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">As a hart cries longingly for rivulets of water, so does my soul cry longingly to You, O God.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">My soul thirsts for God, for the living God; when will I come and appear before God?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">My tears were my bread day and night when they say to me all day long, "Where is your God?"</pasuk><pasuk id="5">These things I will remember, and I will pour out my soul [because of the pain which is] upon me, how I passed on with the throng; I walked slowly with them until the house of God with a joyful shouting and thanksgiving, a celebrating multitude.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Why are you downcast, my soul, and why do you stir within me? Hope to God, for I will yet thank Him for the salvations of His presence.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">My God, my soul is downcast upon me; therefore, I will remember You from the land of Jordan and the peaks of Hermon, from the young mountain.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Deep calls to deep to the sound of Your water channels; all Your breakers and waves passed over me.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">By day, may the Lord command His kindness, and at night, may His resting place be with me, a prayer to the God of my life.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">I will say to God, my Rock, "Why have You forgotten me? Why should I walk in gloom under the oppression of the enemy?"</pasuk><pasuk id="11">With murder in my bones, my oppressors have reproached me by saying to me all day long, "Where is your God?"</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Why are you downcast, my soul, and why do you stir within me? Hope to God, for I will yet thank Him for the salvations of my countenance and my God.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="43"><pasuk id="1">Avenge me, O God, and plead my cause against an unkind nation, from a man of deceit and justice You shall rescue me.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">For You are the God of my strength, why have You abandoned me? Why should I walk in gloom under the oppression of the enemy.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Send Your light and Your truth, that they may lead me; they shall bring me to Your Holy Mount and to Your dwellings.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">And I will come to the altar of God, to the God of the joy of my exultation, and I will thank You with a lyre, O God, My God.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Why are you downcast, my soul, and why do you stir within me? Hope to God, for I will yet thank Him for the salvations of my countenance and my God.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="44"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, of the sons of Korah, a maskil.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">O God, with our ears we heard, our forefathers told us; You performed a deed in their days, in days of old.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">You-[with] Your hand You drove out nations and planted them; You inflicted harm on kingdoms and sent them away.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">For not by their sword did they inherit the land, neither did their arm save them, but Your right hand and Your arm and the light of Your countenance, for You favored them.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">You are my King, O God; command the salvations of Jacob.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">With You, we will gore our adversaries; with Your name, we will trample those who rise up against us.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">For I do not trust in my bow, neither will my sword save me.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">For You saved us from our adversaries and You put our enemies to shame.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">We praised [ourselves] with God all day long, and we will forever thank Your name, yea forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Even if You have forsaken us and put us to shame, and You do not go out in our hosts;</pasuk><pasuk id="11">You make us retreat from the adversary, and our enemies plunder for themselves;</pasuk><pasuk id="12">You deliver us as sheep to be eaten, and You scatter us among the nations.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">You sell Your people without gain, and You did not increase their price;</pasuk><pasuk id="14">You make us a reproach to our neighbors, a scorn and a derision to those around us;</pasuk><pasuk id="15">You make us a byword among the nations, a [cause for] shaking the head among the kingdoms.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">All day long, my disgrace is before me, and the shame of my face has covered me.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">From the voice of the one who taunts and blasphemes, because of an enemy and an avenger.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">All this has befallen us and we have not forgotten You, neither have we betrayed Your covenant.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Our heart has not turned back, nor have our steps turned away from Your path</pasuk><pasuk id="20">-even when You crushed us in a place of serpents, and You covered us with darkness.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">If we forgot the name of our God and spread out our palms to a strange god,</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Will God not search this out? For He knows the secrets of the heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">For it is for Your sake that we are killed all the time, [that] we are considered as sheep for the slaughter.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">Awaken! Why should You sleep, O Lord? Arouse Yourself, forsake not forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">Why do You hide Your countenance? [Why do] You forget our affliction and oppression?</pasuk><pasuk id="26">For our soul is cast down to the dust, our belly clings to the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">Arise to assist us and redeem us for the sake of Your kindness.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="45"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor on shoshannim, of the sons of Korah, a maskil a song of loves.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">My heart is astir with a good theme; I say, "My works are for a king; my tongue is a pen of an expert scribe."</pasuk><pasuk id="3">You are more handsome than [other] men; charm is poured into your lips. Therefore, God blessed you forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Gird a sword on your thigh, O mighty one, your majesty and your glory.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">And your glory is that you will pass and ride for the sake of truth and righteous humility, and it shall instruct you so that your right hand shall perform awesome things.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Your arrows are sharpened, nations shall fall under you, in the heart of the king's enemies.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Your throne, O judge, [will exist] forever and ever; the scepter of equity is the scepter of your kingdom.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">You loved righteousness and you hated wickedness; therefore God, your God, anointed you with oil of joy from among your peers.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Myrrh and aloes and cassia are all your garments; more than ivory palaces, those that are Mine will cause you to rejoice.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">The daughters of kings will visit you; the queen will stand at your right [bedecked] with golden jewelry from Ophir.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Hearken, daughter, and see, and incline your ear, and forget your people and your father's house.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">And the King shall desire your beauty, for He is your Lord, and prostrate yourself to Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">And the daughter of Tyre shall seek your presence with tribute, those who are the richest of the people.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">All honor [awaits] the King's daughter who is within; her raiment is superior to settings of gold.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">With embroidered garments, she will be brought to the King; and virgins in her train who are her companions will be brought to You.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">They shall be brought with joy and exultation; they shall come forth into the King's palace.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Instead of your forefathers will be your sons; you shall appoint them as princes throughout the land.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">I will mention Your name in every generation; therefore peoples shall thank You forever and ever.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="46"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, a song of the sons of Korah, on alamoth.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">God is for us a shelter and a strength, a help in troubles; He is very accessible.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Therefore we will not fear when the earth changes and when mountains totter into the heart of seas.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">His waters shall stir and be muddied; mountains shall quake from His pride forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">But as for the river-its rivulets shall cause the city of God, the holy place of the dwellings of the Most High, to rejoice.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">God is in its midst that it should not totter; God shall help it as morning approaches.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Nations have stirred, kingdoms have tottered; He let out His voice, the earth shall melt.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">The Lord of Hosts is with us; the God of Jacob is our fortress forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Go and see the works of the Lord, that He has wrought devastation in the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">He puts a stop to wars until the end of the earth; He will break the bow and cut the spear [to pieces]; wagons He will burn with fire.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Desist, and know that I am God; I will be exalted among the nations, I will be exalted upon the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">The Lord of Hosts is with us; the God of Jacob is our fortress forever.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="47"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor; of the sons of Korah, a song.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">All peoples, clap hands; shout to God with a voice of praise.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">For the Lord is Most High; yea, feared; a great King over all the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">He shall plague peoples in our stead and kingdoms under our feet.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">He shall choose our inheritance for us, the pride of Jacob, which He loves forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">God shall be exalted with the trumpet blast; the Lord, with the sound of the shofar.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Sing to God, sing; sing to our King, sing.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">For God is the King of all the earth; sing a song composed with wisdom.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">God has reigned over nations; God has sat upon His holy throne.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">The volunteers of the peoples have assembled, the people of the God of Abraham, for God has the shields of the earth; He is exceedingly exalted.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="48"><pasuk id="1">A song, a psalm of the sons of Korah.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">The Lord is great and very much praised, in the city of our God, the Mount of His Sanctuary.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">The fairest of branches, the joy of the entire earth- Mount Zion, by the north side, the city of a great king.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">God is in its palaces; He is known as a stronghold.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">For behold, the kings have assembled; they have passed together.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">They saw, so they wondered; they were startled, yea, they were bewildered.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">A quaking seized them there, pangs like [those of] a woman in confinement.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">With an east wind, [with which] You break the ships of Tarshish.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">As we have heard, so have we seen in the city of the Lord of Hosts, in the city of our God; God shall establish it forever and ever.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">We hoped, O Lord, for Your kindness in the midst of Your Temple.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">As is Your name, O God, so is Your praise upon the ends of the earth; Your right hand is full of righteousness.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Mount Zion shall rejoice; the daughters of Judah shall exult for the sake of Your judgments.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Encompass Zion and surround it, count its towers.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Give heed to its walls, raise its palaces, in order that you may tell a later generation.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">For this is God, our God forever and ever; He shall lead us as in youth.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="49"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, by the sons of Korah, a song.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Hear this, all you peoples; hearken, all You inhabitants of the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Both the sons of "adam," and the sons of "ish," together rich and poor.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">My mouth shall speak wisdoms and the thoughts of my heart are understanding.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">I will bend my ear to a parable; with a lyre, I will solve my riddle.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Why should I fear in days of misfortune? The iniquity of my heels surrounds me.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Those who rely on their possessions and boast of their great wealth,</pasuk><pasuk id="8">-a brother cannot redeem a man, he cannot give his ransom to God.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">The redemption of their soul will be too dear, and unattainable forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Will he live yet forever and not see the Pit?</pasuk><pasuk id="11">For he sees that wise men die, together a fool and a boorish man perish, and leave over their possessions to others.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">In their heart, their houses are forever, their dwellings are for every generation; they call by their names on plots of land.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">But man does not repose in his glory; he is compared to the silenced animals.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">This is their way; folly is theirs, and after them they will tell with their mouth forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Like sheep, they are destined to the grave; death will devour them, and the upright will rule over them in the morning, and their form will outlast the grave as his dwelling place.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">But God will redeem my soul from the power of the grave, for He shall take me forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Fear not when a man becomes rich, when the honor of his house increases,</pasuk><pasuk id="18">For he will not take anything in his death; his glory will not ascend after him.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Because in his lifetime he blesses himself, but [all] will praise you, for you will benefit yourself.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">You shall come to the generation of his forefathers; to eternity they will not see light.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Man is in his glory but he does not understand; he is compared to the silenced animals.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="50"><pasuk id="1">A song of Asaph; God, God the Lord, spoke and called to the earth, from the rising of the sun until its setting.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">From Zion, the finery of beauty, God appeared.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Our God shall come and not be silent; fire shall devour before Him, and around Him it storms furiously.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">He shall call to the heavens above and to the earth to avenge His people.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Gather to Me My devoted ones, who made a covenant with Me over a sacrifice.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">And the heavens will tell His righteousness, for He is a God Who judges forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Hearken, My people, and I will speak, Israel, and I will admonish you; God, even your God am I.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">I will not reprove you concerning your sacrifices, neither are your burnt offerings before Me constantly.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">I will not take from your household a bull, from your pens any goats.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">For all the beasts of the forest are Mine, the behemoth of the thousand mountains.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">I know all the fowl of the mountains, and the creeping things of the field are with Me.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">If I were hungry I would not tell you, for the world and its fullness are Mine.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Will I eat the flesh of bulls or do I drink the blood of he-goats?</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Slaughter for God a confession and pay the Most High your vows.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">And call to Me on a day of distress; I will rescue you and you will honor Me.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">But to the wicked man God said, "For what reason do you recount My statutes, and bring up My covenant on Your mouth?</pasuk><pasuk id="17">For you hated discipline and threw My words behind you.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">If you saw a thief, you agreed [to be] with him, and with adulterers is your portion.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">You let loose your mouth for evil, and you accustomed your tongue to deceit.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">You sit and talk against your brother; you slander your mother's son.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">You did these and I remained silent; you thought that I would be like you. I will contend with you and set up before your eyes.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Understand this now, you who forget God, lest I tear [you] to pieces, and there will be no one to save [you].</pasuk><pasuk id="23">One who slaughters a confession sacrifice honors Me, and [I will] prepare the way; I will show him the salvation of God."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="51"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, a song of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">When Nathan the prophet came to him when he went to Bath-sheba.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Be gracious to me, O God, according to Your kindness; according to Your great mercies, erase my transgressions.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Wash me thoroughly of my iniquity, and purify me of my sin.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">For I know my transgressions, and my sin is always before me.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Against You alone have I sinned, and I have done what is evil in Your sight, in order that You be justified in Your conduct, and right in Your judgment.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Behold, with iniquity I was formed, and with sin my mother conceived me.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Behold, You desired that truth be in the hidden places, and in the concealed part You teach me wisdom.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Purify me with a hyssop, and I will become pure; wash me, and I will become whiter than snow.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Make me hear joy and gladness; let the bones that You crushed exult.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Hide Your countenance from my sins, and erase all my iniquities.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Create for me a pure heart, O God, and renew a steadfast spirit within me.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Do not cast me away from before You, and do not take Your holy spirit from me.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Restore to me the joy of Your salvation, and let a noble spirit support me.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">I will teach transgressors Your ways, and sinners will return to You.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Save me from blood, O God, the God of my salvation; let my tongue sing praises of Your charity.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">O Lord, You shall open my lips, and my mouth will recite Your praise.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">For You do not wish a sacrifice, or I should give it; You do not desire a burnt offering.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">The sacrifices of God are a broken spirit; O God, You will not despise a broken and crushed heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">With Your will, do good to Zion; build the walls of Jerusalem.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Then You will desire sacrifices of righteousness, a burnt offering and a whole offering; then they will offer up bulls on Your altar.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="52"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, a maskil of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">When Doeg the Edomite came and told Saul and said to him, "David came to the house of Ahimelech."</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Why do you boast of evil, you mighty man? God's kindness is constant.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Your tongue plots destruction, as a sharpened razor, working deceit.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">You loved evil more than good, falsehood more than speaking righteousness forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">You loved all destructive words, a deceitful tongue.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">God, too, shall tear you down forever; He will break you and pluck you from [your] tent, and uproot you from the land of the living forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">And righteous men will see and fear, and laugh at him.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">"Behold the man who does not place his strength in God and trusts his great wealth; he strengthened himself in his wickedness."</pasuk><pasuk id="10">But I am like a fresh olive tree in the house of God; I have trusted in the kindness of God forever and ever.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">I will thank You forever and ever when You have done [this], and I will hope for Your name, for it is good, in the presence of Your devoted ones.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="53"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, on machalath, a maskil of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">The fool said in his heart, "There is no God"; they have dealt corruptly; they have committed abominable injustice; no one does good.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">God looked down from heaven upon the sons of men to see whether there is a man of understanding, who seeks God.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">They are all dross; together they have spoiled; no one does good, not even one.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Did not the workers of iniquity know? Those who devoured My people partook of a feast; they did not call upon the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">There they were in great fear; there was never such fear, for God scattered the bones of those who camp around you; You have put them to shame, for God rejected them.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">O that the salvations of Israel would come out of Zion; when God returns the captivity of His people, Jacob will rejoice, Israel will be glad.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="54"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, on neginoth, a maskil of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">When the Ziphim came and said to Saul, "Is not David hiding with us?"</pasuk><pasuk id="3">O God, with Your name save me, and with Your might avenge me.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">O God, hearken to my prayer, incline Your ear to the words of my mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">For strangers rose upon me and violent men sought my soul; they did not place God before them forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Behold, God is my Helper; the Lord is [help] to those who support my soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">He will return the evil to those who lie in wait for me; cut them off with Your truth.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">With generosity, I will slaughter sacrifices to You; I will thank Your name, O Lord, because it is good.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">For He saved me from every distress, and my eye saw my enemies.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="55"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, on neginoth, a maskil of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Incline Your ear, O God, to my prayer and do not disregard my supplication.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Hearken to me and answer me; I lament in my speech and I moan,</pasuk><pasuk id="4">From the voice of the enemy, because of the distress of the wicked; for they accuse me of iniquity and they hate me with a vengeance.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">My heart shudders within me, and terrors of death have fallen upon me.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Fear and trembling come upon me, and horror overcomes me.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">And I said, "If only I had wings like a dove! I would fly away and be at rest.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Behold I would wander far away; I would lodge in the desert forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">I would quickly find myself a refuge from a sweeping wind, from a tempest."</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Destroy, O Lord, divide their tongue, for I have seen violence and strife in the city.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Day and night they surround it on its walls, and iniquity and sin are in its midst.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Destruction is within it, and blows and deceit do not move out of its square.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">For no enemy reviled me that I should bear it; my enemy did not open his mouth wide against me, that I should hide from him.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">And you are a man of my equal, my prince and my esteemed one.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">That together we would devise counsel; in the house of God we would walk with a multitude.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">May He incite Death upon them; may they descend to the grave alive, for there are evils in their dwelling, in their midst.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">I shall call to God, and the Lord will save me.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Evening, morning, and noontime, I speak and moan, and He hearkened to my voice.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">He redeemed my soul with peace from the battle that came upon me, because of the many [people who] were with me.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">May God hear and answer them, and the One who dwells from time immemorial forever, for there is no passing for them, and they did not fear God.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">He stretched forth his hands against him who was at peace with him; he profaned his covenant.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Smooth were the buttery words of his mouth but his heart was set on war; his words were softer than oil, but they are curses.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Cast your burden on the Lord, and He will bear you; He shall never allow a righteous man to falter.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">But You, O God, shall lower them to the Pit of Destruction; men of blood and deceit shall not live half their days, but I will trust in You.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="56"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, on yonath elem rehokim, of David a michtam, when the Philistines seized him in Gath.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Be gracious to me, O God, because men yearn to swallow me; all day long the warrior oppresses me.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Those who eye me have yearned to swallow me all day long, for many fight against me, O Most High.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">The day I fear, I will hope to You.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">With God, I will praise His word; in God I trusted, I will not fear. What can flesh do to me?</pasuk><pasuk id="6">All day long, my words grieve [me]; all their thoughts about me are for evil.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">They lodge, they hide, they watch my steps, when they hope for my life.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">For iniquity, they expect rescue. Bring down nations with anger, O God.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">You counted my wanderings; place my tears in Your flask. Is it not in Your accounting?</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Then my enemies will retreat on the day that I call. Thereby I will know that I have a God.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">With God['s justice] I will praise a word; with the Lord['s kindness] I will praise a word.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">In God I trusted, I will not fear. What can man do to me?</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Upon me, O God, are Your vows; I will pay thanksgiving offerings to You.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">For You saved my soul from death, even my feet from stumbling, to walk before God in the light of life.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="57"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, al tashcheth, of David a michtam, when he fled from before Saul in the cave.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Be gracious to me, O God, be gracious to me, because my soul took refuge in You, and in the shadow of Your wings I will take refuge until the destruction passes.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">I will call upon the Most High God, upon the God Who completes [what He promised] for me.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">He will send from Heaven and save me from the disgrace of him who yearns to swallow me up forever; God will send His kindness and His truth.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">My soul is among lions; I lie among men who are aflame; their teeth are [like] spears and arrows, and their tongue is [like] a sharp sword.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Be exalted above the heavens, O God; over all the earth be Your glory.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">They prepared a net for my steps, he bent down my soul; they dug a pit before me, they will fall into it forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">My heart is steadfast with God, my heart is steadfast; I will sing, yea, I will sing praises.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Awaken, my honor; awaken [me], lyre and harp; I will awaken the dawn.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">I will thank You among the peoples, O Lord; I will sing Your praises among the kingdoms.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">For Your kindness is great up to the heavens, and Your truth is up to the skies.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Be exalted above the heavens, O God, over all the earth be Your glory.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="58"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, al tashcheth; of David a michtam.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Is it true that You were silent about the righteousness that You should have spoken, the equities [with which] You should have judged the children of men?</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Even in your heart, you plot injustice; in the earth, you weigh down the violence of your hands.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">The wicked become estranged [even] from the womb; those who speak lies go astray from birth.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">They have venom like the venom of a serpent, like a deaf cobra that closes its ear,</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Which will not hear the voice of charmers, the most cunning caster of spells.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">O God, smash their teeth in their mouth; break the molars of lions, O Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Let them be rejected; let them walk as [through] water; He will aim His arrows as though they are cut down.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Like a snail, which continuously melts, a mole [and a] stillbirth, which did not see the sun.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Before your tender briars develop into hardened thorns, with vigor, with wrath, He will drive them away as a storm wind.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">The righteous man will rejoice because he saw revenge; he will bathe his feet in the blood of the wicked.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">And man will say, "Truly, the righteous man has reward; truly there is a God Who judges on earth."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="59"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, al tashcheth; of David a michtam, when Saul sent and they guarded the house to slay him.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Save me from my enemies, my God; strengthen me against those who rise up against me.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Save me from workers of iniquity, and rescue me from bloodthirsty men.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">For behold, they lurked for my soul; strong men lodge against me, neither [for] my transgression nor [for] my sin, O Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Without iniquity, they run and prepare themselves; awaken towards me and see.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">And You, O Lord, God of Hosts, God of Israel, arise to visit upon all the nations; be not gracious to any treacherous workers of iniquity forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">They return in the evening, they howl like a dog and encircle the city.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Behold, they spew forth with their mouth; [they have] swords in their lips, for who hears?</pasuk><pasuk id="9">But You, O Lord, will scoff at them; You will mock all the nations.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">[Because of] his strength, I hope for You, for God is my fortress.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">The God of my kindness will precede me; God will allow me to see in those who watch me.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Do not kill them, lest my people forget; remove them from their possessions with Your power and bring them down, O Lord our Shield.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">The sin of their mouth is the word of their lips, and they will be seized because of their haughtiness, because of the curse and the lies that they tell.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Destroy [them] with wrath so that they will be no longer, and they will know that God rules over Jacob to the ends of the earth forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">And they will return in the evening, they will howl like dogs, and they will encircle the city.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">They will roam about to eat if they are not sated, so that they will lodge.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">And I will sing of Your power, and I will sing praises of Your kindness in the morning, for You were my stronghold and a refuge on a day that I was in straits.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">My strength! To You will I sing for God is my stronghold, O God of my kindness.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="60"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, on shushan eduth, a michtam of David, to teach.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">When he fought with Aram-Naharaim and with Aram-Zobah, and Joab returned and smote twelve thousand of Edom in the valley of salt.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">O God, You have forsaken us; You have breached us; You were angry with us. You shall restore us.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">You caused the land to quake; You split it; heal its breaches for it has faltered.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">You have shown Your people harshness; You have given us to drink wine of bewilderment.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">You have given those who fear You trials with which to be tested, in order to beautify [Your behavior] forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">In order that Your beloved ones should be rescued, save Your right hand and answer me.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">God spoke in His Sanctuary; I will exult, I will divide a portion, and I will measure the valley of Succoth.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Gilead is mine, and Manasseh is mine, and Ephraim is the strength of my head; Judah is my lawgiver.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Moab is my washbasin; on Edom I will throw my lock; Philistia, join me.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Who will bring me to a fortified city?-He Who led me to Edom?</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Is it not You, O God, Who has forsaken us, and [Who] does not go forth, O God, with our hosts?</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Give us aid against the adversary, but the salvation of man is futile.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Through God we shall gather might, and He will trample our adversaries.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="61"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, on neginath, of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Hearken, O God, to my request, listen to my prayer.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">From the end of the earth I call out to You when my heart becomes faint; on the rock that is higher than I, You lead me.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">For You were a shelter for me, a tower of strength in the face of the enemy.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">I shall dwell in Your tent to eternity; I will take shelter in the covert of Your wings forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">For You, God, have hearkened to my vows; You have given the heritage of those who fear Your name.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Add days to the days of the king, his years as every generation.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">May he dwell forever before God; kindness and truth should be prepared to guard him.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">So will I sing praises to Your name forever, when I pay my vows every day.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="62"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, on jeduthun, a song of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Only to God does my soul hope; from Him is my salvation.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Only He is my Rock and my salvation, my stronghold so that I shall not falter greatly.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">How long will you plan destruction to man? You shall be murdered, all of you, as a leaning wall, a tottering fence.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Only because of his loftiness have they plotted to topple him; they delight in lies; with his mouth they bless, but inwardly they curse forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Only to God should you hope, my soul, for my hope is from Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Only He is my Rock and my salvation; my stronghold, I shall not falter.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Upon God rests my salvation and my honor; [He is] the Rock of my strength, my shelter is in God.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Trust in Him at all times; people, pour out your hearts before Him. God is our shelter forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">The sons of men are but vanity, and men of distinction are deceitful; were they to be put on a scale, together they would equal vanity.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Do not trust in oppresion, and do not put vain hope in robbery; if wealth burgeons, pay it no heed.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">God spoke one thing, I heard two, for God has strength.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">And You, O Lord, have kindness, for You repay a man according to his deed.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="63"><pasuk id="1">A song of David when he was in the desert of Judah.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">O God, You are my God, I seek You. My soul thirsts for You; my flesh longs for You, in an arid and thirsty land, without water.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">As I saw You in the Sanctuary, [so do I long] to see Your strength and Your glory.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">For Your kindness is better than life; my lips will praise You.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Then I shall bless You in my lifetime; in Your name I shall lift my hands.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">[As] with choice foods and fat, my soul will be sated, when my mouth praises with expressions of song.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">When I remember You on my couch; in the watches I meditate about You.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">For You were my help, and in the shadow of Your wings I shall praise.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">My soul has clung after You; Your right hand has supported me.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">But they seek my soul to make it desolate; may they come into the depths of the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">May he be dragged by the sword; they will be the portion of foxes.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">And may the king rejoice with God; may all who swear by Him boast, for the mouth of those who speak lies will be closed.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="64"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, a song of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Hear, O God, my voice in my prayer; from fear of the enemy You shall guard my life.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">You shall hide me from the counsel of evildoers, from the gathering of workers of iniquity,</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Who whetted their tongue like the sword; who aimed a bitter word like their arrow,</pasuk><pasuk id="5">To shoot at the innocent in secret places; they shoot at him suddenly and do not fear.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">They strengthen the evil word for themselves; they tell to hide snares. They say, "Who will see us?"</pasuk><pasuk id="7">They seek pretexts; they have completed a diligent search, hidden within man and in the depths of the heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">And God cast them down; their wounds were [like] a sudden arrow.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">That which they hoped would make him stumble, their tongue brought upon them; all who see them will shake their heads.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Then all men feared, and they declared the work of God and understood His deed.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">The righteous will rejoice with God and take shelter in Him, and all upright of heart will boast.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="65"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, a psalm of David, a song.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Silence is praise to You, O God in Zion, and to You a vow is paid.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">You, Who hearken to prayer, to You all flesh shall come.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Words of iniquities have overcome me; as for our transgressions, You shall atone for them.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Praiseworthy is he whom You choose and draw near to dwell in Your courts; let us be sated with the goodness of Your house, the sanctity of Your Temple.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">With awesome deeds, through [Your] charity You shall answer us, God of our salvation, the trust of all the distant ends of the earth and the sea.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Who sets mountains with His strength, Who is girded with might.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Who humbles the roaring of the seas, the roaring of their waves, and the multitude of kingdoms.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">And the dwellers of the ends fear Your signs; with the emergence of morning and evening, You cause [them] to sing praises.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">You remember the earth and water it; You enrich it greatly with the stream of God which is full of water; You prepare their corn for so do You prepare it.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">To sate its furrows, to afford pleasure to its troops; with raindrops You dissolve it, You bless its plants.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">You crowned a year of Your goodness, and Your paths drip with fatness.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">They drip upon the dwellings of the desert, and hills gird themselves with joy.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Meadows are clothed with flocks, and valleys are enwrapped with corn; they shout for joy, yea, they sing.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="66"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, a song of praise; shout for joy to God, all the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Sing the glory of His name; make glorious His praise.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Say to God, "How awesome are Your deeds! Through the greatness of Your might, Your enemies will admit their lies to You.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">All the earth will prostrate themselves to You and sing praises to You; they will sing praises to Your name forever."</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Go and see the deeds of God, awesome in His deeds toward mankind.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">He turned the sea into dry land; in the river they crossed by foot; there we rejoiced with Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">With His might, He rules the world; His eyes oversee the nations; the rebellious ones will not exalt themselves, ever.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">O peoples, bless our God, and make the voice of His praise heard.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">He, Who kept our souls alive and did not let our foot falter.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">For You tested us, O God; You refined us as though refining silver.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">You brought us into a trap; You placed a chain on our loins.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">You caused man to ride at our head; we came in fire and water, and You took us out to satiety.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">I shall come to Your house with burnt offerings; I shall pay You my vows,</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Which my lips uttered and my mouth spoke in my distress.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Burnt offerings of fat animals I shall offer up to You with the burning of rams; I shall prepare cattle with he-goats forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Come, hearken and I shall tell all you who fear God what He did for my soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">My mouth called out to Him, and He was exalted under my tongue.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">If I saw iniquity in my heart, the Lord does not hear it.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">But God heard; He hearkened to the voice of my prayer.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Blessed be God, Who did not remove my prayer and His kindness from me.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="67"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, on neginoth; a psalm, a song.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">God will be gracious to us and bless us; He will cause His countenance to shine with us forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">That Your way should be known on earth, Your salvation among all nations.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Peoples will thank You, O God; peoples will thank You, yea, all of them.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Kingdoms will rejoice and sing praises, for You will judge peoples fairly, and the kingdoms-You will lead them on earth forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Peoples will thank You, O God; peoples will thank You, yea, all of them.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The earth gave forth its produce; God, our God, will bless us.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">God will bless us, and all the ends of the earth will fear Him.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="68"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, a psalm, a song of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">May God rise; His enemies scatter, and those who hate Him flee from before Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">As smoke is driven away, You will drive [them] away; as wax melts before fire, the wicked will perish from before God.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">And the righteous will rejoice, yea, they will exult before God and they will delight with joy.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">"Sing to God, sing praises to His name, praise Him Who rides in Aravoth by His name Yah, and rejoice before Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">O Father of orphans and Judge of widows, O God in His holy dwelling place."</pasuk><pasuk id="7">God settles the solitary in a house; He takes the prisoners out at the most opportune time, but the rebellious dwell in an arid land.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">O God, when You went out before Your people, when You marched through the wilderness, forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">The earth quaked, even the heavens dripped; this is Sinai, because of God, the God of Israel.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Generous rain You poured down, O God; Your heritage, which was weary, You established.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Your congregation dwelt therein; You prepare with Your goodness for the poor, O God.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">The Lord will give out a word; they will announce it to a great multitude.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Kings of hosts will wander, yea they will wander, and she who dwells in the house will divide the spoils.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">If you lie between the borders-the feathers of a dove covered with silver, and its pinions with brilliant gold.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">When the Almighty spreads out for kings therein, it will become as white as snow in darkness.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">The mountain of God is the mountain of Bashan; the mountain of peaks is the mountain of Bashan.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Why do you lurk, you lofty mountains, for the mountain that God desired for His dwelling? Even the Lord will dwell [there] forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">God's chariot is twice ten thousand times thousands of angels. The Lord was among them at Sinai in His holiness.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">You ascended on high, you took captives; you took gifts to be among men, and also rebellious ones for Yah God to dwell.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Blessed is the Lord; every day God lavishes upon us our salvation forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">God is to us the God of salvations, but God the Lord has the ways to death.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Indeed God will wound His enemies' head, the hairy pate of him who goes with his guilt.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">The Lord said, "I shall restore from Bashan; I shall restore from the depths of the sea.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">In order that your foot may wade through blood; the tongue of your dogs will have its portion from the enemies."</pasuk><pasuk id="25">They saw Your ways, O God, the ways of my God, my King in sanctity.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">Singers went first, minstrels afterwards, in the midst of maidens playing timbrels.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">In congregations bless God the Lord, from the womb of Israel.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">There Benjamin the youngest rules over them; the princes of Judah pelt them with stones, as do the princes of Zebulun and the princes of Naftali.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">Your God has commanded your strength; show this strength, O God, which You have wrought for us.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">From Your Temple, which is over Jerusalem, kings will bring You tribute.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">Rebuke the people of the forest, the congregation of mighty bulls among people like calves, submitting himself for pieces of silver; he scatters peoples, they always desire battles.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">Gifts will be brought from Egypt; Cush will cause his hands to run to God.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">Kingdoms of the earth, sing to God, sing praises to the Lord forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="34">To Him Who rides on the heaven of heavens of old; behold, He gives forth with His voice a voice of strength.</pasuk><pasuk id="35">Attribute strength to God; over Israel is His pride, and His strength is in the skies.</pasuk><pasuk id="36">You are feared, O God, from Your Sanctuary; the God of Israel-He gives strength and power to the people; blessed be God.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="69"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, on shoshannim, of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Save me, O God, for water has come up to my soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">I have sunk in muddy depths and there is no place to stand; I have come into the deep water, and the current has swept me away.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">I have become weary from calling out; my throat has become parched; my eyes fail while I wait for my God.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Those who hate me for nothing are more numerous than the hairs of my head; mighty are those who would cut me off, who are my enemies because of lies; what I did not steal, I will then return.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">O God, You know my folly, and my acts of guilt are not concealed from You.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Do not let those who hope for You be shamed through me, O Lord God of Hosts; let those who seek You not be disgraced through me, O God of Israel.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">For I have borne humiliation because of You; disgrace has covered my face.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">I was strange to my brothers, and alien to the sons of my mother.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">For the envy of Your house has consumed me, and the humiliations of those who blaspheme You have fallen upon me.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">And I bewailed my soul in fast, and it was a disgrace for me.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">And I made sackcloth my raiment, and I became a byword to them.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">They talk about me, those who sit in the gate, and [they make] melodies [about me] for those who imbibe strong drink.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">But, as for me, may my prayer to You, O Lord, be in an acceptable time. O God, with Your abundant kindness, answer me with the truth of Your salvation.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Save me from mud that I not sink, that I be saved from my enemies and from the depths of water.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Let neither the current of water sweep me away, nor the deep swallow me, and let a well not close its mouth over me.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Answer me, O Lord, for Your kindness is good; according to Your abundant mercies, turn to me.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">And do not hide Your face from Your servant, because I am distressed, hasten to answer me.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Come close to my soul, redeem it; because of my enemies, redeem me.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">You know my humiliation, my shame, and my disgrace; all my oppressors are before You.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Humiliation has broken my heart and I have become ill; I hoped for sympathy but there was none, and for comforters but I found none.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">They put gall into my food and for my thirst they gave me vinegar to drink.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">May their table before them become a trap, and [their hope] for peace become a snare.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">May their eyes become dark, so they cannot see; constantly cause their loins to slip.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">Pour out Your fury upon them, and may Your burning wrath overtake them.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">May their palace be desolate; in their tents let there be no dweller.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">For You-those whom You smote they pursued, and about the pain of those whom You wounded they tell.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">Add iniquity to their iniquity, and let them not come into Your charity.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">May they be erased from the book of life, and may they not be inscribed with the righteous.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">But I am poor and in pain; may Your salvation, O God, exalt me.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">I shall praise the name of God with song, and I shall magnify Him with a thanksgiving offering.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">And it will appeal to the Lord more than a young bull that is mature, with horns and hooves.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">When the humble see, they rejoice, yea, those who seek God, and your heart will be invigorated.</pasuk><pasuk id="34">For God hearkens to the needy, and He does not despise His prisoners.</pasuk><pasuk id="35">Heaven and earth will praise Him, the seas and everything that moves therein,</pasuk><pasuk id="36">When God saves Zion and builds the cities of Judah, and they dwell there and take possession of it.</pasuk><pasuk id="37">And the seed of His servants inherit it, and those who love His name dwell therein.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="70"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor; of David, to make mention.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">O God, [hasten] to save me; O Lord, hasten to my assistance.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">May those who seek my life be shamed and humiliated; may those who desire my harm turn back and be disgraced.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Let them return in the path of their shame, those who say, "Aha, aha."</pasuk><pasuk id="5">May all those who seek You exult and rejoice, and may those who love Your salvation say constantly, "May God be magnified."</pasuk><pasuk id="6">But I am poor and needy, O God, hasten to me; You are my aid and my rescuer, O Lord, do not delay.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="71"><pasuk id="1">In You, O Lord, have I taken refuge; let me never be ashamed.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">With Your charity, You shall save me and rescue me; extend Your ear to me and save me.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Be for me a sheltering rock in which to enter continually; You commanded [others] to save me because You are my rock and my fortress.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">My God, rescue me from the hands of the wicked, from the palm of him who treats unjustly and robs.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">For You are my hope, O Lord God, my trust since my youth.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">I relied on You from birth; from my mother's womb You drew me; my praise is always in You.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">I was an example for the multitude, but You were my strong shelter.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">My mouth will be filled with Your praise, all the days with Your glory.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Do not cast me away at the time of old age; when my strength fails, do not forsake me.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">For my enemies said of me, and those who watch for my soul took counsel together,</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Saying, "God has forsaken him; pursue and seize him, for there is no rescuer."</pasuk><pasuk id="12">O God, do not distance Yourself from me; my God, hasten to my assistance.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">The adversaries of my soul will be shamed and will perish; enwrapped in humiliation and disgrace will be those who seek to harm me.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">As for me, I shall constantly hope, and I shall add to all Your praise.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">My mouth will recite Your righteousness, all the days Your salvation, for I do not know their number.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">I shall come with the mighty deeds of the Lord God; I shall mention Your righteousness alone.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">O God, You have taught me since my youth, and until now I shall recite your wonders.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">And even until old age and hoary hairs, O God, do not forsake me, until I tell [of] Your strength to the generation, to everyone who comes-Your might</pasuk><pasuk id="19">And Your charity, O God, [which is] up to the heights, for You do great things. O God, who is like You?</pasuk><pasuk id="20">That You showed me great and evil troubles, You will revive me again, and from the depths of the earth You will again raise me up.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">You will increase my greatness, and You will turn and comfort me.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">I too shall thank You with a stringed instrument for Your truth, my God; I shall play music to You with a harp, O Holy One of Israel.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">My lips will sing praises when I play music to You, and my soul, which You redeemed.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">Also my tongue will utter Your righteousness all the days, for those who seek my harm are shamed, yea, for they are disgraced.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="72"><pasuk id="1">Concerning Solomon. O God, give Your judgments to a king and Your righteousness to a king's son.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">May he judge Your people justly, and Your poor people with justice.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">May the mountains bear peace for the people, and the hills-through righteousness.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">May he judge the poor of the people; may he save the children of the needy and crush the oppressor.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">May they fear You in the presence of the sun and before the moon for generations upon generations.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">May it descend as rain upon cut vegetation, as raindrops that drip upon the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">May the righteous flourish in his days, and much peace until there is no moon.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">And may he reign from sea to sea, and from the river to the ends of the land.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">May nobles kneel before him, and may his enemies lick the dust.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">May the kings of Tarshish and the isles return tribute; may the kings of Sheba and Seba approach with a gift.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">And all kings will prostrate themselves to him; may all nations serve him.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">For he will save a needy one who cries out, and a poor one who has no helper.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">He will have pity on the poor and needy, and he will save the souls of the needy.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">From blows and from robbery he will redeem their soul, and their blood will be dear in his eyes.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">And may he live, and He will give him of the gold of Sheba, and may He pray for him constantly; all the days may He bless him.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">May there be an abundance of grain in the land, on the mountain peaks; may its fruit rustle like Lebanon, and they will blossom forth from the city like the grass of the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">May his name be forever; before the sun, his name will be magnified, and [people] will bless themselves with him; all nations will praise him.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Blessed is the Lord God, the God of Israel, Who performs wonders alone.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">And blessed is His glorious name forever, and His glory will fill the entire earth. Amen and amen.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">The prayers of David the son of Jesse are completed.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="73"><pasuk id="1">A song of Asaph. Truly God is good to Israel, to the pure of heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">But as for me, my feet had almost turned away, in an instant my steps would have been swept away.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">For I envied the perverse; I would see the tranquility of the wicked.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">For there are no fetters to their death, and their health is sound.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">In the toil of mortal man they are not, neither are they plagued with mankind.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Therefore, they wear pride as a necklace; the robbery that they commit envelops their hips.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Because of their fat, their eyes bulge; they surpassed the imaginings of their heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">They consume, and speak wickedly about oppression; they speak about the Most High.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">They have set their mouth against Heaven, and their tongue walks through the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Therefore, His people will return here, and the waters of the full [stream] are drain water to them.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">And they say, "How does God know, and is there knowledge in the Most High?"</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Behold these are wicked, yet they are tranquil in the world and have increased wealth.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">But for nought I cleansed my heart and bathed my hands with cleanliness.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">And I was plagued all the days, and my chastisement was every morning.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">If I said, "I shall tell it as it is," behold I have made the generation of Your children into traitors.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">And when I ponder to know this, it is iniquity in my eyes.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Until I came to the sanctuaries of God, and I understood their end.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Only in slippery places do You set them; You cast them down to ruin.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">How they became desolate instantly! They were completely consumed by terrors.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">As a dream without awakening; O Lord, in the city You will despise their form.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">For my heart was in ferment, and my mind was on edge.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">But I was brutish and I did not know; I was [as] a beast with You.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Yet I was constantly with You; You grasped my right hand.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">With Your counsel You led me, and after[wards], You took me [for] glory.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">For whom do I have in heaven, and I desired no one with You on earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">My flesh and my heart yearn; God is the rock of my heart and my portion forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">For behold, those who have distanced themselves from You will perish; You have cut off anyone who strays from You.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">But as for me-God's nearness is my good; I have placed my refuge in the Lord God, to tell all Your mission.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="74"><pasuk id="1">A maskil of Asaph. Why, O God, have You forsaken forever? [Why] is Your wrath kindled against the flock of Your pasture?</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Remember Your congregation, which You acquired from time immemorial; You redeemed the tribe of Your heritage, Mount Zion on which You dwelt.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Raise Your blows to inflict eternal ruin, for all the evil that the enemy did in the Sanctuary.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Your adversaries roared in the midst of Your meeting place; they made their signs for signs.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">May he be known as though bringing [their blows] on high; the hatchets were in the thicket of the trees.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">And now, its entrances together, with hatchets and hammers they strike.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">They set Your Sanctuary afire; to the ground they profaned the dwelling place of Your name.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">They said in their heart, their rulers together; they burned all the meeting places of God in the land.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">We have not seen our signs; there is no longer a prophet, and no one with us knows how long.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">How long, O God, will the adversary blaspheme? Will the enemy disgrace Your name forever?</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Why do You withdraw Your hand, even Your right hand? Draw it out from within Your bosom.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">But God is my King from time immemorial, Who works salvations in the midst of the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">You crumbled the sea with Your might; You shattered the heads of the sea monsters on the water.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">You crushed the heads of Leviathan; You give it as food to the people in companies.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">You split fountain and stream; You dried up mighty rivers.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Day is Yours, even night is Yours; You established the luminary and the sun.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">You set all the boundaries of the earth; summer and winter-You formed them.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Remember how the enemy reviled the Lord and a villainous people blasphemed Your name.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Do not deliver to the company the soul of Your turtledove; the soul of Your poor ones do not ever forget.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Look to the covenant, for the dark places of the earth are filled with dwellings of violence.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Let not the poor turn back in disgrace; the poor and needy will praise Your name.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Arise, O God, plead Your own cause; remember Your disgrace from a villainous man all the days.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Do not forget the voice of Your adversaries, the tumult of those who rise up against You, which constantly ascends.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="75"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, al tashcheth, a psalm of Asaph, a song.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">We have thanked You, O God, we have thanked, and Your name is near; they have told Your wonders.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">When I take a festive day, I shall judge with fairness.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">When the earth and all its inhabitants were melting away, I established its pillars forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">I said to the perverse, "Do not behave perversely," and to the wicked, "Do not raise the horn."</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Do not raise your horn on high, [do not] speak with [your] fat neck.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">For it is not from the east or from the west, neither from the desert does elevation come.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">But God judges; He humbles this one and elevates that one.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">For a cup is in the hand of the Lord, and strong wine, a full mixture, and He pours out of this [cup], but all the wicked of the earth will drain and drink [it].</pasuk><pasuk id="10">And I shall recite forever; I shall sing [praises] to the God of Jacob.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">And all the horns of the wicked I shall cut off; the horns of the righteous will be upraised.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="76"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor on neginoth, a psalm of Asaph, a song.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">God is known in Judah; in Israel His name is great.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">His Tabernacle was in Salem, and His dwelling place in Zion.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">There He broke the arrows of the bow, shield and sword and war forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">You are destructive; mightier than the mountains of prey.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">The stout-hearted became mad; they slumbered in their sleep, and none of the men of the army found their hands.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">From Your rebuke, O God of Jacob, chariot and horse were stunned.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">You-awesome are You, and who can stand before You once You are angry?</pasuk><pasuk id="9">From heaven, You let judgment be heard; the earth feared and became calm.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">When God rises for judgment, to save all the humble of the earth forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">For man's anger will thank You; it will prevent the residue of wrath.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Vow and pay to the Lord your God; all those around Him will bring a gift to Him Who is to be feared.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">He will cut down the spirit of princes; He will be feared by the kings of the earth.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="77"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor on jeduthun, a song of Asaph.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">My voice is to God, and I shall cry out; my voice is to God, and hearken to me.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">On the day of my distress, I sought the Lord; my wound oozes at night and does not abate; my soul refuses to be comforted.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">I remember God and I stir; I speak and my spirit becomes faint, forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">You held fast the awakenings of my eyes; I throb and I do not speak.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">I think of days of yore, ancient years.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">I recall my music at night; I speak with my heart and my spirit searches.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">"Will the Lord forsake [me] forever and nevermore be appeased?</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Has His kindness ended forever? Has He issued a decree for all generations?</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Has God forgotten to be gracious? Has He, in anger, shut off His mercy forever?"</pasuk><pasuk id="11">And I said, "This is to terrify me, the change of the right hand of the Most High."</pasuk><pasuk id="12">I recall the deeds of Yah when I remember Your wonder from time immemorial.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">And I meditate over all Your works, and I speak of Your deeds.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">O God, Your way is in sanctity. Who is a power as great as God?</pasuk><pasuk id="15">You are the God Who works wonders; You made known Your might among the peoples.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">You redeemed Your people with Your arm, the sons of Jacob and Joseph forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">The waters perceived You, O God, the waters perceived You, they trembled, even the deeps quaked.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">They poured forth thick waters; the skies let out a voice, even your arrows went abroad.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">The sound of Your thunder is like a wheel; the lightning illuminated the world; the earth shook and quaked.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">In the sea was Your way, and Your path in the mighty waters, and Your steps were not known.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">You led Your people like sheep by the hand of Moses and Aaron.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="78"><pasuk id="1">A maskil of Asaph. Hearken, my people, to my instruction, extend your ear to the words of my mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">I shall open my mouth with a parable; I shall express riddles from time immemorial.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">That we heard and we knew them, and our forefathers told us.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">We shall not hide from their sons; to the last generation they will recite the praises of the Lord, and His might and His wonders, which He performed.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">And He established testimony in Jacob, and He set down a Torah in Israel, which He commanded our forefathers to make them known to their sons.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">In order that the last generation might know, sons who will be born should tell their sons.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">And they should put their hope in God, and not forget the deeds of God, and keep His commandments.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">And they should not be as their forefathers, a stubborn and rebellious generation, who did not prepare its heart and whose spirit was not faithful to God.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">The sons of Ephraim, armed archers, retreated on the day of battle.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">They did not keep the covenant of God, and they refused to follow His Torah.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">They forgot His deeds and His wonders, which He showed them.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Before their forefathers He wrought wonders, in the land of Egypt, the field of Zoan.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">He split the sea and took them across, He made the water stand as a heap.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">He led them with a cloud by day, and all night with the light of fire.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">He split rocks in the desert and gave them to drink as [from] great deeps.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">He drew flowing water from a rock and brought down water like rivers.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">But they continued further to sin against Him, to provoke the Most High in the desert.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">They tried God in their heart by requesting food for their craving.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">And they spoke against God; they said, "Can God set a table in the desert?</pasuk><pasuk id="20">True, He struck a rock and water flowed, and streams flooded. Can He give meat too? Can He prepare flesh for His people?"</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Therefore, God heard and was incensed; fire was kindled against Jacob, and also wrath ascended upon Israel.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Because they did not believe in God and did not trust in His salvation.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">And He had commanded the skies from above, and He had opened the portals of heaven.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">He had rained upon them manna to eat, and He had given them corn of heaven.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">Men ate the bread of the mighty; He sent them provisions for satisfaction.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">He caused the east wind to set forth in heaven, and He led the south wind with His might.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">He rained down flesh upon them like dust, and, like the sand of the seas, winged fowl.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">And He let it fall in the midst of their camp, around their dwellings.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">They ate and were very satisfied, and He brought them their desire.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">They were not estranged from their desire; while their food was still in their mouth,</pasuk><pasuk id="31">The wrath of God ascended upon them and slew [some] of their stoutest and caused the chosen of Israel to fall.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">Despite all this, they sinned again and did not believe despite His wonders.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">And He ended their days in vanity and their years in terror.</pasuk><pasuk id="34">When He slew them, they would seek Him, and they would repent and pray to God.</pasuk><pasuk id="35">And they remembered that God is their rock and the Most High God is their Redeemer.</pasuk><pasuk id="36">They beguiled Him with their mouth, and with their tongue they lied to Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="37">Their heart was not sincere with Him; they were not faithful in His covenant.</pasuk><pasuk id="38">But He is merciful, He expiates iniquity and does not destroy; many times He takes back His wrath and does not arouse all His anger.</pasuk><pasuk id="39">He remembers that they are flesh, a spirit that goes away and does not return.</pasuk><pasuk id="40">How often they provoked Him in the desert, vexed Him in the wasteland!</pasuk><pasuk id="41">They returned and tried God, and they sought a sign from the Holy One of Israel.</pasuk><pasuk id="42">They did not remember His hand, the day that He redeemed them from distress.</pasuk><pasuk id="43">Who placed His signs in Egypt and His wonders in the field of Zoan.</pasuk><pasuk id="44">He turned their canals into blood, and their flowing waters they could not drink.</pasuk><pasuk id="45">He incited against them a mixture of wild beasts, which devoured them, and frogs, which mutilated them.</pasuk><pasuk id="46">He gave their produce to the finishing locusts and their toil to the increasing locusts.</pasuk><pasuk id="47">He killed their vines with hail and their sycamore trees with locusts.</pasuk><pasuk id="48">He gave over their animals to the hail and their cattle to the fiery bolts.</pasuk><pasuk id="49">He dispatched against them the kindling of His anger-wrath, fury, and trouble, a delegation of evil messengers.</pasuk><pasuk id="50">He leveled a path for His anger; He did not withhold their soul from death, and He delivered their body to pestilence.</pasuk><pasuk id="51">He smote every firstborn in Egypt, the first fruit of their strength in the tents of Ham.</pasuk><pasuk id="52">Then He caused His people to journey like sheep, and He led them as a flock in the desert.</pasuk><pasuk id="53">He led them securely and they were not afraid, and the sea covered their enemies.</pasuk><pasuk id="54">He brought them to the border of His sanctuary, this mountain that His right hand had acquired.</pasuk><pasuk id="55">He drove out nations from before them, and allotted them an inheritance by line, and He caused the tribes of Israel to dwell in their tents.</pasuk><pasuk id="56">Yet they tried and provoked the Most High God, and did not keep His testimonies.</pasuk><pasuk id="57">They turned back and dealt treacherously as their forefathers; they turned around like a deceitful bow.</pasuk><pasuk id="58">They provoked Him with their high places, and with their graven images they angered Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="59">God heard and became incensed, and He utterly rejected Israel.</pasuk><pasuk id="60">And He abandoned the Tabernacle of Shiloh, the tent that He had stationed among men.</pasuk><pasuk id="61">He delivered His might into captivity, and His glory into the hand of the adversary.</pasuk><pasuk id="62">And He delivered His people to the sword, and He became incensed with His inheritance.</pasuk><pasuk id="63">Fire consumed his youths and his virgins were not married.</pasuk><pasuk id="64">His priests fell by the sword, but his widows did not weep.</pasuk><pasuk id="65">And the Lord awoke as one asleep, as a mighty man, shouting from wine.</pasuk><pasuk id="66">And He smote His adversaries from the rear; He gave them perpetual disgrace.</pasuk><pasuk id="67">He rejected the tent of Joseph and did not choose the tribe of Ephraim.</pasuk><pasuk id="68">He chose the tribe of Judah, Mount Zion, which He loved.</pasuk><pasuk id="69">And He built His Sanctuary like the high heavens, like the earth He established it forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="70">And He chose His servant David and took him from the sheepcotes.</pasuk><pasuk id="71">From behind the nursing ewes He brought him, to shepherd Jacob His people and Israel His heritage.</pasuk><pasuk id="72">And He shepherded them according to the integrity of his heart, and with the skill of his hands he led them.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="79"><pasuk id="1">A song of Asaph. O God! Nations have come into Your heritage, they have defiled Your Holy Temple, they have made Jerusalem into heaps.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">They have given the corpses of Your servants as food to the birds of the heaven, the flesh of Your pious ones to the beasts of the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">They have spilt their blood like water around Jerusalem, and no one buries [them].</pasuk><pasuk id="4">We were a disgrace to our neighbors, ridicule and derision to those around us.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">How long, O Lord? Will You be wroth forever? Will Your jealousy burn like fire?</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Pour out Your wrath upon the nations that do not know You and upon the kingdoms that did not call out in Your name.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">For they devoured Jacob and made his dwelling desolate.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Do not remember for us the early iniquities; may Your mercies quickly come before us for we have become very poor.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Help us, O God of our salvation, on account of the glory of Your name, and save us and atone for our sins for Your name's sake.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Why should the nations say, "Where is their God?" Let it be known among the nations before our eyes the revenge of the spilt blood of Your servants.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">May the cry of the prisoner come before You; according to the greatness of Your arm, set free the children of the mother who died.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">And return to our neighbors sevenfold into their bosom, their reproach with which they reproached You, O Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">But we, Your people and the flock of Your pasture, shall thank You forever; to all generations we shall recite Your praise.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="80"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, to the roses, a testimony, of Asaph a song.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">O Shepherd of Israel, hearken, He Who leads Joseph like flocks, He Who dwells between the cherubim, appear.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Before Ephraim, Benjamin, and Manasseh arouse Your might, and it is for You to save us.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">O God, return us; cause Your countenance to shine and we shall be saved.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">O Lord God of Hosts, how long have You been wroth at Your people's prayer?</pasuk><pasuk id="6">You have fed them bread of tears, and You have given them to drink tears in large measure.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">You have made us the target of strife to our neighbors, and our enemies mock themselves.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">O God of Hosts, return us; cause Your countenance to shine and we shall be saved.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">You uprooted a vine from Egypt; You drove out nations and planted it.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">You cleared [a place] before it; it took root and filled the land.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Mountains were covered [by] its shade, and its branches were great cedars.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">It sent forth its branches until the sea, and to the river its tender shoots.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Why have You breached its fences, so that all wayfarers have plucked its fruit?</pasuk><pasuk id="14">The boar from the forest gnaw at it, and the creeping things of the field graze on it?</pasuk><pasuk id="15">O God of Hosts, return now; look from heaven and see, and be mindful of this vine,</pasuk><pasuk id="16">And of the foundation that Your right hand has planted and over the son You have strengthened for Yourself.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Burned with fire [and] cut off; from the rebuke of Your countenance they perish.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">May Your hand be upon the man of Your right hand, upon the son of man whom You strengthened for Yourself.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">And let us not withdraw from You; grant us life, and we shall call out in Your name.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">O Lord God of Hosts, return us; cause Your countenance to shine, and we shall be saved.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="81"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, on the gittith, of Asaph.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Sing praises to the God Who is our might, sound the shofar to the God of Jacob.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Raise [your voice in] song and give forth [with] a timbrel, a pleasant harp with a lyre.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Sound the shofar on the New Moon, on the appointed time for the day of our festival.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">For it is a statute for Israel, the judgment of the God of Jacob.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">As a testimony for Jehoseph, He ordained it, when he went forth over the land of Egypt, [when] I understood a language that I had not known.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">I removed his shoulder from burdens; his hands were removed from the cauldron.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">In distress, you called and I released you; I answered you-[though you called] in secret- with thunder; I tried you by the waters of Meribah, forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Hearken, My people, and I shall admonish you, Israel, if you hearken to Me.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">No strange god shall be within you, neither shall you prostrate yourself to a foreign god.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">I am the Lord, your God, Who brought you up from the land of Egypt; open your mouth wide, and I shall fill it.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">But My people did not hearken to My voice, neither did Israel desire to [follow] Me.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">So I let them go after their heart's fantasies; let them go in their counsels.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">If only My people would hearken to Me, if Israel would go in My ways.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">In a short time I would subdue their enemies and upon their enemies I would return My hand.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">The enemies of the Lord would lie to Him, and their time would be forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Then He would feed them with the fat of wheat and I would sate you with honey from a rock.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="82"><pasuk id="1">A song of Asaph. God stands in the congregation of God; in the midst of the judges He will judge.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">How long will you judge unjustly and favor the wicked forever?</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Judge the poor and orphan; justify the humble and the impoverished.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Release the poor and the needy; save [them] from the hands of [the] wicked.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">They did not know and they do not understand [that] they will walk in darkness; all the foundations of the earth will totter.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">I said, "You are angelic creatures, and all of you are angels of the Most High."</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Indeed, as man, you will die, and as one of the princes, you will fall.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Arise, O God, judge the earth, for You inherit all the nations.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="83"><pasuk id="1">A psalm, a song of Asaph.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">O God, have no silence, do not be silent and do not be still, O God.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">For behold, Your enemies stir, and those who hate You raise their heads.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Against Your people they plot cunningly, and they take counsel against Your protected ones.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">They said, "Come, let us destroy them from [being] a nation, and the name of Israel will no longer be remembered."</pasuk><pasuk id="6">For they have taken counsel with one accord; against You they form a pact.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The tents of Edom and the Ishmaelites, Moab and the Hagrites.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Gebal, Ammon, and Amalek, Philistia with the inhabitants of Tyre.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Also Assyria joined them; they were the arm of the children of Lot forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Do to them as [to] Midian; as [to] Sisera, as [to] Jabin in the brook Kishon.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">They were destroyed in En-Dor; they were [as] dung on the ground.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Make them, their nobles, as Oreb and as Zeeb, and as Zebah and as Zalmuna all their princes,</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Who said, "Let us inherit for ourselves the dwellings of God."</pasuk><pasuk id="14">My God, make them like thistles, like stubble before the wind.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">As a fire that burns in a forest and as a flame that burns mountains.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">So will You pursue them with Your tempest, and with Your whirlwind You will terrify them.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Fill their faces with shame, and they will seek Your countenance, O Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Let them be ashamed and terrified forever; let them be disgraced and perish.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Let them know that You-Your name alone is the Lord, Most High over all the earth.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="84"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, on the gittith, of the sons of Korah, a song.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">How beloved are Your dwelling places, O Lord of Hosts!</pasuk><pasuk id="3">My soul yearns, yea, it pines for the courts of the Lord; my heart and my flesh pray fervently to the living God.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Even a bird found a house and a swallow her nest, where she placed her chicks upon Your altars, O Lord of Hosts, my King and my God.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Fortunate are those who stay in Your house; they will continually praise You forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Fortunate is the man who has strength in You, in whose heart are the highways.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Transgressors in the valley of weeping make it into a fountain; also with blessings they enwrap [their] Teacher.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">They go from host to host; he will appear to God in Zion.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">O Lord, God of Hosts, hearken to my prayer; bend Your ear, O God of Jacob, forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">See our shield, O God, and look at the face of Your anointed.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">For a day in Your courts is better than a thousand; I chose to sit on the threshold of the house of My God rather than dwell in tents of wickedness.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">For a sun and a shield is the Lord God; the Lord will give grace and glory; He will not withhold good from those who go with sincerity.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">O Lord of Hosts, fortunate is the man who trusts in You.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="85"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, a song of the sons of Korah.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">O Lord, You have appeased Your land; You have returned the Captivity of Jacob.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">You have forgiven the iniquity of Your people; You have concealed all their sin forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">You have taken in all Your wrath; You have retreated from the fierceness of Your anger.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Return us, O God of our salvation and revoke Your anger with us.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Will You be wroth with us forever? Will You extend Your anger to generation after generation?</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Will You not return and revive us so that Your people will rejoice with You?</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Show us, O Lord, Your kindness, and Your salvation You shall give to us.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">I shall hear what God will speak when He speaks peace to His people and to His pious men, and they will not return to folly.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Truly, His salvation is near those who fear Him, so that His glory dwell in our land.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Kindness and truth have met; righteousness and peace have kissed.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Truth will sprout from the earth, and righteousness will look down from heaven.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">God too will give good, and our land will give its produce.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Righteousness will go before him, and He will place it on the way of his steps.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="86"><pasuk id="1">A prayer of David. O Lord, incline Your ear; answer me for I am poor and needy.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Watch my soul for I am a pious man; save Your servant-You, my God-who trusts in You.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Be gracious to me, O Lord, for I call to You all the days.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Cause the soul of Your servant to rejoice, for to You, O Lord, I lift my soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">For You, O Lord, are good and forgiving, with much kindness to all who call You.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Lend Your ear, O Lord, to my prayer, and hearken to the voice of my supplications.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">On the day of my distress I shall call You, for You will answer me.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">There is none like You among the godly, O Lord, neither is there any like Your works.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">All nations that You made will come and prostrate themselves before You, O Lord, and glorify Your name.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">For You are great and perform wonders, You, O God, alone.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Teach me Your way, O Lord; I shall walk in Your truth. Unify my heart to fear Your name.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">I shall thank You, O Lord my God, with all my heart, and I shall glorify Your name forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">For Your kindness is great toward me, and You have saved my soul from the lowest depths of the grave.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">O God, willful transgressors have risen against me, and a company of mighty ones have sought my life, and they did not place You before themselves.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">But You, O Lord, are a compassionate and gracious God, slow to anger and with much kindness and truth.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Turn to me and be gracious to me; grant Your might to Your servant and save the son of Your maidservant.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Grant me a sign for good, and let my enemies see [it] and be ashamed, for You, O Lord, have helped me and comforted me.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="87"><pasuk id="1">Of the sons of Korah, a song with musical accompaniment, whose foundation is on the mountains of the Sanctuary.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">The Lord loves the gates of Zion more than all the dwellings of Jacob.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Glorious things are said about you, the city of God, forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">I will remind Rahab and Babylon of My beloved ones. Behold Philistia and Tyre with Cush, "This one was born there."</pasuk><pasuk id="5">And to Zion it will be said, "Man after man was born in her," and He will establish it on high.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">[When] the Lord counts in the script of the peoples forever, [He will say,] "This one was born there."</pasuk><pasuk id="7">And singers as well as flute players, all my innards are concerned with you.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="88"><pasuk id="1">A song with musical accompaniment of the sons of Korah, for the conductor, about the sick and afflicted one, a maskil of Heman the Ezrahite.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">O Lord, the God of my salvation! I cried by day; at night I was opposite You.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">May my prayer come before You; extend Your ear to my supplication.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">For my soul is sated with troubles, and my life has reached the grave.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">I was counted with those who descend into the Pit; I was like a man without strength.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">I am considered among the dead who are free, as the slain who lie in the grave, whom You no longer remember and who were cut off by Your hand.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">You have put me into the lowest pit, into dark places, into depths.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Your wrath lies hard upon me, and [with] all Your waves You have afflicted [me] constantly.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">You have estranged my friends from me; You have made me an abomination to them; [I am] imprisoned and cannot go out.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">My eye has failed because of affliction; I have called You every day, I have spread out my palms to You.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Will You perform a wonder for the dead? Will the shades rise and thank You forever?</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Will Your kindness be told in the grave, Your faith in destruction?</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Will Your wonder be known in the darkness, or Your righteousness in the land of oblivion?</pasuk><pasuk id="14">As for me, O Lord, I have cried out to You, and in the morning my prayer comes before You.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Why, O Lord, do You abandon my soul, do You hide Your countenance from me?</pasuk><pasuk id="16">I am poor, and close to sudden death; I have borne Your fear, it is well-founded.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Your fires of wrath have passed over me; Your terrors have cut me off.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">They surround me like water all the day; they encompass me together.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">You have estranged from me lover and friend; my acquaintances are in a place of darkness.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="89"><pasuk id="1">A maskil of Ethan the Ezrahite.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">The kindnesses of the Lord I shall sing forever; to generation after generation I shall make known Your faithfulness, with my mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">For I said, "Forever will it be built with kindness; as the heavens, with which You will establish Your faithfulness."</pasuk><pasuk id="4">I formed a covenant with My chosen one; I swore to David My servant.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Until eternity, I shall establish your seed, and I shall build your throne for all generations forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">And the heavens acknowledge Your wonder, O Lord, also Your faithfulness in the congregation of holy ones.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">For who in the heavens is equal to the Lord? [Who] resembles the Lord among the sons of the mighty?</pasuk><pasuk id="8">God is revered in the great council of the holy ones and feared by all around Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">O Lord, God of Hosts, who is like You, O Yah, Who are mighty? And Your faithfulness surrounds You.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">You rule over the pride of the sea; when it raises its waves, You humble them.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">You crushed Rahab like one slain; with the arm of Your might You scattered Your enemies.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">The heaven is Yours, even the earth is Yours; the inhabited earth and the fullness thereof-You founded them.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">North and south-You created them; Tabor and Hermon sing praises in Your name.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">You have an arm with might; Your hand is mighty, Your right hand is high.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Righteousness and judgment are the basis of Your throne; kindness and truth come before Your countenance.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Fortunate is the people that know the blasting of the shofar; O Lord, may they walk in the light of Your countenance.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">With Your name they rejoice every day, and with Your righteousness they are exalted.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">For You are the glory of their might, and with Your favor our horns will be raised.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">For our shield is [devoted] to the Lord, and our king to the Holy One of Israel.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Then You spoke in a vision to Your pious ones, and You said, "I placed help on a mighty man; I lifted up a chosen one from the people.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">I found David My servant, I anointed him with My holy oil.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">With whom My hand will be established, even My arm will strengthen him.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">No enemy will exact from him, neither will an unjust person afflict him.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">And I shall crush his adversaries from before him, and I shall strike his enemies.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">My faithfulness and My kindness will be with him, and with My name his horn will be raised.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">I shall place his hand over the sea, and his right hand over the rivers.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">He will call to Me, 'You are my Father, my God, and the Rock of my salvation.'</pasuk><pasuk id="28">I, too, shall make him a firstborn, the highest of the kings of the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">I will forever keep My kindness for him, and My covenant will remain true to him.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">And I shall make his seed endure forever, and his throne as the days of the heavens.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">If his sons forsake My Torah and do not walk in My judgments,</pasuk><pasuk id="32">If they profane My statutes and do not keep My commandments,</pasuk><pasuk id="33">I shall punish their transgression with a rod, and their iniquity with stripes.</pasuk><pasuk id="34">But I shall not cancel My kindness from him, and I shall not betray My faith.</pasuk><pasuk id="35">I shall not profane My covenant, neither shall I alter the utterance of My lips.</pasuk><pasuk id="36">One thing have I sworn by My holiness, that I will not fail David.</pasuk><pasuk id="37">His seed will be forever and his throne is like the sun before Me.</pasuk><pasuk id="38">Like the moon, which is established forever, and it is a witness in the sky, eternally true."</pasuk><pasuk id="39">But You abandoned and You rejected; You became wroth with Your anointed.</pasuk><pasuk id="40">You abrogated the covenant of Your servant; You profaned his crown to the ground.</pasuk><pasuk id="41">You breached all his fences; You made his fortifications a ruin.</pasuk><pasuk id="42">All wayfarers have plundered him; he was a disgrace to his neighbors.</pasuk><pasuk id="43">You raised the right hand of his adversaries; You caused all his enemies to rejoice.</pasuk><pasuk id="44">You even turned back the sharp edge of his sword, and You did not raise him up in battle.</pasuk><pasuk id="45">You have brought an end to his shining, and his throne You have cast down to earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="46">You have shortened the days of his youth; You have enwrapped him with shame forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="47">How long, O Lord? Will You hide forever? Will Your anger burn like fire?</pasuk><pasuk id="48">I am mindful what my old age is; for what futility have You created all the sons of man?</pasuk><pasuk id="49">Who is a man who will live and not see death, who will rescue his soul from the grasp of the grave forever?</pasuk><pasuk id="50">Where are Your former acts of kindness, O Lord, which You swore to David in your trust?</pasuk><pasuk id="51">Remember, O Lord, the disgrace of Your servants, which I bear in my bosom, [the disgrace] of all great nations.</pasuk><pasuk id="52">Which Your enemies disgraced, O Lord, which they disgraced the ends of Your anointed.</pasuk><pasuk id="53">Blessed is the Lord forever. Amen and Amen.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="90"><pasuk id="1">A prayer of Moses, the man of God. O Lord, You have been our dwelling place throughout all generations.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Before the mountains were born, and You brought forth the earth and the inhabited world, and from everlasting to everlasting, You are God.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">You bring man to the crushing point, and You say, "Return, O sons of men."</pasuk><pasuk id="4">For a thousand years are in Your eyes like yesterday, which passed, and a watch in the night.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">You carry them away as a flood; they are like a sleep; in the morning, like grass it passes away.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">In the morning, it blossoms and passes away; in the evening, it is cut off and withers.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">For we perish from Your wrath, and from Your anger we are dismayed.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">You have placed our iniquities before You, [the sins of] our youth before the light of Your countenance.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">For all our days have passed away in Your anger; we have consumed our years as a murmur.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">The days of our years because of them are seventy years, and if with increase, eighty years; but their pride is toil and pain, for it passes quickly and we fly away.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Who knows the might of Your wrath, and according to Your fear is Your anger.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">So teach the number of our days, so that we shall acquire a heart of wisdom.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Return, O Lord, how long? And repent about Your servants.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Satiate us in the morning with Your loving-kindness, and let us sing praises and rejoice with all our days.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Cause us to rejoice according to the days that You afflicted us, the years that we saw evil.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">May Your works appear to Your servants, and Your beauty to their sons.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">And may the pleasantness of the Lord our God be upon us, and the work of our hands establish for us, and the work of our hands establish it.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="91"><pasuk id="1">He who dwells in the covert of the Most High will lodge in the shadow of the Almighty.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">I shall say of the Lord [that He is] my shelter and my fortress, my God in Whom I trust.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">For He will save you from the snare that traps from the devastating pestilence.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">With His wing He will cover you, and under His wings you will take refuge; His truth is an encompassing shield.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">You will not fear the fright of night, the arrow that flies by day;</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Pestilence that prowls in darkness, destruction that ravages at noon.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">A thousand will be stationed at your side, and ten thousand at your right hand; but it will not approach you.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">You will but gaze with your eyes, and you will see the annihilation of the wicked.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">For you [said], "The Lord is my refuge"; the Most High you made your dwelling.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">No harm will befall you, nor will a plague draw near to your tent.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">For He will command His angels on your behalf to guard you in all your ways.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">On [their] hands they will bear you, lest your foot stumble on a stone.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">On a young lion and a cobra you will tread; you will trample the young lion and the serpent.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">For he yearns for Me, and I shall rescue him; I shall fortify him because he knows My name.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">He will call Me and I shall answer him; I am with him in distress; I shall rescue him and I shall honor him.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">With length of days I shall satiate him, and I shall show him My salvation.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="92"><pasuk id="1">A song with musical accompaniment for the Sabbath day.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">It is good to give thanks to the Lord, and to sing to Your name, O Most High.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">To declare in the morning Your kindness and Your faith at night.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Upon a ten-stringed harp and upon a psaltery, with speech upon a harp.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">For You have made me happy O Lord, with Your work; with the work of Your hands I shall exult.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">How great are Your works, O Lord! Your thoughts are very deep.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">A boorish man does not know; neither does a fool understand this.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">When the wicked flourish like grass, and all workers of violence blossom, only to be destroyed to eternity.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">But You remain on high forever, O Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">For behold Your enemies, O Lord, for behold Your enemies will perish; all workers of violence will scatter.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">But You have raised my horn like that of a wild ox; to soak me with fresh oil.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">My eye has gazed upon those who stare at me [with envy]; when evildoers rise up against me, my ears hear [them].</pasuk><pasuk id="13">The righteous one flourishes like the palm; as a cedar in Lebanon he grows.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Planted in the house of the Lord, in the courts of our God they will flourish.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">They will yet grow in old age; fat and fresh will they be.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">To declare that the Lord is upright, my rock in Whom there is no injustice.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="93"><pasuk id="1">The Lord has reigned; He has attired Himself with majesty; yea the Lord has attired Himself, He has girded Himself with might. The world also is established that it cannot be moved.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Your throne is established of old; You are from everlasting.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">The rivers have raised, O Lord, the rivers have raised their voice; the rivers have raised their depths.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">More than the voices of great waters and more than the mightiest breakers of the sea, is the Lord mighty on high.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Your testimonies are very faithful to Your house, the dwelling of holiness, O Lord, to the length of days.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="94"><pasuk id="1">O God of vengeance, O Lord; O God show vengeance.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Exalt Yourself, O Judge of the earth, render to the haughty their recompense.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">How long will the wicked, O Lord, how long will the wicked rejoice?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">They spout forth, they speak falsely; all workers of violence boast.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Your people, O Lord, they crush, and Your inheritance they afflict.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">They slay the widow and the stranger, and they murder the orphans.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">They say, "Yah will not see, nor will the God of Jacob understand."</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Understand, [you] most boorish of the people, and [you] fools, when will you gain intelligence?</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Will He Who implants the ear not hear or will He Who forms the eye not see?</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Will He Who chastises nations not reprove? [He is] the One Who teaches man knowledge.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">The Lord knows man's thoughts that they are vanity.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Fortunate is the man whom You, Yah, chastise, and from Your Torah You teach him.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">To grant him peace from days of evil, while a pit is a dug for the wicked.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">For the Lord will not forsake His people, nor will He desert His inheritance.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">For until righteousness will judgment return, and after it all those upright in heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Who will rise up for me against evildoers; who will stand up for me against workers of violence?</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Had not the Lord been my help, in an instant my soul would rest silent.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">If I said, "My foot has slipped," Your kindness, O Lord, supported me.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">With my many thoughts within me, Your consolations cheered me.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Will the throne of evil join You, which forms iniquity for a statute?</pasuk><pasuk id="21">They gather upon the soul of the righteous and condemn innocent blood.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">But the Lord was my fortress, and my God the rock of my refuge.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">And He returned upon them their violence, and for their evil, may He cut them off; may the Lord our God cut them off.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="95"><pasuk id="1">Come, let us sing praises to the Lord; let us shout to the rock of our salvation.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Let us greet His presence with thanksgiving; let us shout to Him with songs.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">For the Lord is a great God and a great King over all divine powers.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">In Whose hand are the depths of the earth, and the heights of the mountains are His.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">For the sea is His, He made it, and His hands formed the dry land.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Come, let us prostrate ourselves and bow; let us kneel before the Lord, our Maker.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">For He is our God, and we are the people of His pasture and the flocks of His hand, today, if you hearken to my voice.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Do not harden your heart as [in] Meribah, as [on] the day of Massah in the desert.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">When your ancestors tested Me; they tried Me, even though they had seen My work.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Forty years I quarreled with a generation, and I said, "They are a people of erring hearts and they did not know My ways."</pasuk><pasuk id="11">For which reason I swore in My wrath, that they would not enter My resting place.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="96"><pasuk id="1">Sing to the Lord a new song, sing to the Lord, all the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Sing to the Lord, bless His name, announce His salvation from day to day.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Tell of His glory among the nations, among all peoples His wonders.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">For the Lord is great and very much praised; He is feared over all divine powers.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">For all the gods of the peoples are nought, but the Lord made the heavens.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">[They ascribe] beauty and majesty before Him; might and glory in His sanctuary.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Ascribe to the Lord, [you] families of peoples, ascribe to the Lord glory and might.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Ascribe to the Lord the glory due His name; carry an offering and come to His courtyards.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Prostrate yourselves to the Lord in the majestic sanctuary; quake before Him, all the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Say among the nations, "The Lord has reigned." Also the inhabited world will be established so that it will not falter; He will judge peoples with equity.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">The heavens will rejoice and the earth will exult; the sea and the fullness thereof will roar.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">The field and all that is therein will jubilate; then all the forest trees will sing praises.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Before the Lord, for He has come, for He has come to judge the earth; He will judge the inhabited world justly and the peoples with His faith.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="97"><pasuk id="1">The Lord has reigned, the earth will exult; many islands will rejoice.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Cloud and thick darkness are around Him; righteousness and judgment are the foundation of His throne.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Fire will go before Him and will burn His enemies all around.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">His lightnings illuminated the world; the earth saw and quaked.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Mountains melted like wax from before the Lord, from before the Master of all the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">The heavens told His righteousness, and all the earth saw His glory.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">All worshippers of graven images will be ashamed, yea those who boast of idols; all gods, prostrate yourselves before Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Zion heard and rejoiced, and the daughters of Judah exulted, because of Your judgments, O Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">For You, O Lord, are Most High above all the earth; You are very much exalted above all gods.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">You who love the Lord, hate evil; He watches the souls of His pious ones, He rescues them from the hands of the wicked.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">A light is sown for the righteous, and for the upright of heart, joy.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Rejoice, you righteous, with the Lord, and give thanks to His holy name.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="98"><pasuk id="1">A song. Sing to the Lord a new song, for He performed wonders; His right hand and His holy arm have saved Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">The Lord has made known His salvation; to the eyes of the nations He has revealed His righteousness.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">He remembered His kindness and His faith to the house of Israel; all the ends of the earth have seen the salvation of our God.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Shout to the Lord, all the earth, open [your mouths] and sing praises and play music.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Play to the Lord with a harp, with a harp and a voice of song.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">With trumpets and the sound of a shofar, raise your voices before the King, the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The sea and the fullness thereof will roar, the inhabited world and the inhabitants thereof.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Rivers will clap hands; together mountains will sing praises.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Before the Lord, for He has come to judge the earth; He will judge the inhabited world justly and the peoples with equity.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="99"><pasuk id="1">The Lord has reigned, nations will quake; [before] Him Who dwells between the cherubim, the earth will falter.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">The Lord is great in Zion, and He is high over all the peoples.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">They will acknowledge Your great and awesome name, [that] it is holy,</pasuk><pasuk id="4">And the might of the King who loves judgment; You founded equity; judgment and righteousness You made in Jacob.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Exalt the Lord our God and prostrate yourselves to His footstool, it is holy.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Moses and Aaron among His priests, and Samuel among those who call in His name, would call out to the Lord, and He would answer them.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">In a pillar of cloud He would speak to them; they kept His testimonies and the statutes He gave them.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">O Lord, Our God, You answered them; You were a forgiving God for them but vengeful for their misdeeds.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Exalt the Lord our God and prostrate yourselves to the mount of His sanctuary, for the Lord our God is holy.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="100"><pasuk id="1">A song for a thanksgiving offering. Shout to the Lord, all the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Serve the Lord with joy, come before Him with praise.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Know that the Lord is God; He made us and we are His, people and the flock of His pasture.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Come into His gates with thanksgiving, [into] His courtyards with praise; give thanks to Him, bless His name.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">For the Lord is good; His kindness is forever, and until generation after generation is His faith.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="101"><pasuk id="1">Of David, a song. I shall sing of kindness and judgment; to You, O Lord, I shall sing.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">I shall concern myself with the way of integrity. When will it come to me? I shall walk with the innocence of my heart within my house.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">I do not place before my eyes any base thing; I hate doing wayward deeds; it does not cling to me.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">A perverse heart turns away from me; I know no evil.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">He who slanders his neighbor in secret, I cut him down; one whose eyes are raised up high and his heart is expansive, I cannot tolerate him.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">My eyes are upon the faithful of the land to dwell with me; he who goes on the way of the innocent, he will serve me.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">He will not dwell within my house; he who practices deceit, who speaks lies, will not be established before my eyes.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Betimes I cut down all the wicked of the earth; to cut down from the city of the Lord all workers of violence.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="102"><pasuk id="1">A prayer for a poor man when he enwraps himself and pours out his speech before the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">O Lord, hearken to my prayer, and may my cry come to You.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Do not hide Your countenance from me; on the day of my distress extend Your ear to me; on the day I call, answer me quickly.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">For my days have ended in smoke, and as a hearth my bones are dried up.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Beaten like grass and withered is my heart, for I have forgotten to eat my bread.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">From the sound of my sigh my bones clung to my flesh.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">I was like a bird of the wilderness; I was like an owl of the wasteland.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">I pondered, and I am like a lonely bird on a roof.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">All day long my enemies revile me; those who scorn me swear by me.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">For ashes I ate like bread, and my drinks I mixed with weeping.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Because of Your fury and Your anger, for You picked me up and cast me down.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">My days are like a lengthening shadow, and I dry out like grass.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">But You, O Lord, will be enthroned forever, and Your mention is to all generations.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">You will rise, You will have mercy on Zion for there is a time to favor it, for the appointed season has arrived.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">For Your servants desired its stones and favored its dust.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">And the nations will fear the name of the Lord, and all the kings of the earth Your glory.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">For the Lord has built up Zion; He has appeared in His glory.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">He has turned to the prayer of those who cried out, and He did not despise their prayer.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Let this be inscribed for the latest generation, and a [newly] created people will praise Yah.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">For He has looked down from His holy height; the Lord looked from heaven to earth,</pasuk><pasuk id="21">To hear the cry of the prisoner, to loose the sons of the dying nation;</pasuk><pasuk id="22">To proclaim in Zion the name of the Lord and His praise in Jerusalem.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">When peoples gather together, and kingdoms, to serve the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">He has afflicted my strength on the way; He has shortened my days.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">I say, "My God, do not take me away in the middle of my days, You Whose years endure throughout all generations.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">In the beginning You founded the earth, and the heavens are the work of Your hands.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">They will perish but You will endure, and all of them will rot away like a garment; like raiment You will turn them over and they will pass away.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">But You are He, and Your years will not end.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">The children of Your servants will dwell, and their seed will be established before You."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="103"><pasuk id="1">Of David. My soul, bless the Lord, and all my innards, His holy name.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">My soul, bless the Lord and do not forget any of His benefits.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Who forgives all your iniquity, Who heals all your illnesses.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Who redeems your life from the pit, Who crowns you with kindness and mercy.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Who sates your mouth with goodness, that your youth renews itself like the eagle.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">The Lord performs charitable deeds and judgment for all oppressed people.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">He makes His ways known to Moses, to the children of Israel His deeds.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">The Lord is merciful and gracious, slow to anger and with much kindness.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">He will not quarrel to eternity, and He will not bear a grudge forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">He has not dealt with us according to our sins, nor has He repaid us according to our iniquities.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">For, as the height of the heavens over the earth, so great is His kindness toward those who fear Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">As the distance of east from west, He distanced our transgressions from us.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">As a father has mercy on sons, the Lord had mercy on those who fear Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">For He knows our creation; He remembers that we are dust.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">As for man-his days are like grass; like a flower of the field, so does he sprout.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">For a wind passes over him and he is no longer here; and his place no longer recognizes him.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">But the Lord's kindness is from everlasting to everlasting, and His charity to sons of sons.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">To those who keep His covenant and to those who remember His commandments to perform them.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">The Lord established His throne in the heavens, and His kingdom rules over all.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Bless the Lord, His angels, those mighty in strength, who perform His word, to hearken to the voice of His word.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Bless the Lord, all His hosts, His ministers, those who do His will.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Bless the Lord, all His works, in all the places of His dominion; my soul, bless the Lord.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="104"><pasuk id="1">My soul, bless the Lord. My God, You are very great, You are attired with majesty and beauty.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">[You] enwrap Yourself with light like a garment; [You] extend the heavens like a curtain.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Who roofs His upper chambers with water; Who makes clouds His chariot, which goes on the wings of the wind.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">He makes winds His messengers, burning fire His ministers.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">He founded the earth on its foundations that it not falter to eternity.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">You covered the deep as [with] a garment; the waters stand on the mountains.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">From Your rebuke they fled; from the sound of Your thunder they hastened away.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">They ascended mountains, they descended into valleys to this place, which You had founded for them.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">You set a boundary that they should not cross, that they should not return to cover the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">He sends the springs into the streams; they go between the mountains.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">They water every beast of the field; the wild donkeys quench their thirst.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Beside them the fowl of the heavens dwell; from between the branches they let out their voices.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">He waters the mountains from His upper chambers; from the fruit of Your works the earth is sated.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">He causes grass to sprout for the animals and vegetation for the work of man, to bring forth bread from the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">And wine, which cheers man's heart, to make the face shine from oil, and bread, which sustains man's heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">The Lord's trees are sated, the cedars of Lebanon, which He planted.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Where birds nest; as for the stork-the high junipers are its home.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">The lofty mountains for the ibexes; the rocks a shelter for the hyraxes.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">He made the moon for the appointed seasons; the sun knows its setting.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">You make darkness and it is night, in which every beast of the forest moves about.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">The young lions roar for prey and to beg their food from God.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">When the sun rises they gather in and couch in their dens.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Man goes out to his work, to his labor until evening.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">How great are Your works, O Lord! You have made them all with wisdom; the earth is full of Your possessions!</pasuk><pasuk id="25">This sea-great and wide; there are creeping things and innumerable beasts, both small and large.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">There the ships go; You formed this leviathan with which to sport.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">They all look to You with hope, to give their food in its time.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">You give them that they may gather; You open Your hand that they may be sated with goodness.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">You hide Your countenance and they are frightened; You gather in their spirit and they perish and return to their dust.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">You will send forth Your spirit and they will be created, and You will renew the surface of the ground.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">The glory of the Lord will be forever; the Lord will rejoice with His works.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">He Who looks at the earth and it quakes; He touches the mountains and they emit smoke.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">I shall sing to the Lord while I am alive; I shall sing praises to my God as long as I exist.</pasuk><pasuk id="34">May my speech be pleasing to Him; I shall rejoice with the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="35">Sinners will be destroyed from the earth and the wicked will be no more; my soul, bless the Lord. Hallelujah.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="105"><pasuk id="1">Give thanks to the Lord, call out in His name; make His deeds known among the peoples.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Sing to Him, play music to Him, speak of all His wonders.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Boast of His holy name; may the heart of those who seek the Lord rejoice.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Search for the Lord and His might; seek His presence constantly.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Remember His wonders, which He performed, His miracles and the judgments of His mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">The seed of Abraham His servant, the children of Jacob, His chosen ones.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">He is the Lord our God; throughout all the earth are His judgments.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">He remembered His covenant forever, the word He had commanded to the thousandth generation,</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Which He had made with Abraham, and His oath to Isaac,</pasuk><pasuk id="10">And He set it up to Jacob as a statute, to Israel as an everlasting covenant,</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Saying, "To you I shall give the land of Canaan, the portion of your heritage."</pasuk><pasuk id="12">When they were few in number, hardly dwelling in it.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">And they walked from nation to nation, from one kingdom to another people.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">He let no man oppress them, and He reproved kings on their account.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">"Do not touch My anointed ones, and do not harm My prophets."</pasuk><pasuk id="16">He called a famine upon the land; He broke every staff of bread.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">He sent a man before them; Joseph was sold as a slave.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">They afflicted his foot with fetters; his soul was placed in irons.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Until His word came, the saying of the Lord purified him.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">A king sent and released him, a ruler of peoples [sent] and loosed his bonds.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">He made him the master of his household and the ruler over all his possessions.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">To bind up his princes with his soul, and he made his elders wise.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Israel came to Egypt, and Jacob sojourned in the land of Ham.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">And He made His people very fruitful, and He made it stronger than its adversaries.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">He turned their heart to hate His people, to plot against His servants.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">He sent Moses His servant, [and] Aaron whom He chose.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">They placed upon them the words of His signs and His miracles in the land of Ham.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">He sent darkness and it darkened, and they did not disobey His word.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">He turned their water into blood, and it killed their fish.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">Their land swarmed with frogs in the rooms of their monarchs.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">He commanded and a mixture of noxious beasts came, lice throughout all their boundary.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">He made their rains into hail, flaming fire in their land.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">And it struck their vines and their fig trees, and it broke the trees of their boundary.</pasuk><pasuk id="34">He spoke and locusts came, and nibbling locusts without number.</pasuk><pasuk id="35">And they consumed all grass in their land, and they consumed the produce of their soil.</pasuk><pasuk id="36">And He smote every firstborn in their land, the first of all their strength.</pasuk><pasuk id="37">And He took them out with silver and gold, and there was no pauper among their tribes.</pasuk><pasuk id="38">Egypt rejoiced with their departure for their fear had fallen upon them.</pasuk><pasuk id="39">He spread out a cloud for shelter, and fire to illuminate the night.</pasuk><pasuk id="40">They asked, and He brought quails, and the bread of heaven sated them.</pasuk><pasuk id="41">He opened a rock and water flowed; in the deserts ran rivers.</pasuk><pasuk id="42">For He remembered His holy word with Abraham His servant.</pasuk><pasuk id="43">And He took out His people with joy, His chosen ones with joyful singing.</pasuk><pasuk id="44">And He gave them lands of nations, and they inherited the toil of kingdoms.</pasuk><pasuk id="45">In order that they keep His statutes and observe His laws. Hallelujah.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="106"><pasuk id="1">Hallelujah. Give thanks to the Lord for He is good, for His kindness is forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Who can narrate the mighty deeds of the Lord? [Who] can make heard all His praise?</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Fortunate are those who keep justice, who perform righteousness at all times.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Remember me, O Lord, when You favor Your people; be mindful of me with Your salvation.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">To see the goodness of Your chosen ones, to rejoice with the joy of Your nation, to boast with Your inheritance.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">We sinned with our forefathers; we committed iniquity and wickedness.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Our forefathers in Egypt did not understand Your wonders; they did not remember Your manifold deeds of kindness, and they were rebellious by the sea, by the Sea of Reeds.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">And He saved them for His name's sake, to make known His might.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">And He rebuked the Sea of Reeds, and it dried up, and He led them in the depths as [in] a desert.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">He saved them from the hand of the enemy, and He redeemed them from the hand of the foe.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">And the water covered their adversaries; not one of them survived.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">And they believed His words; they sang His praise.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Quickly, they forgot His deeds; they did not await His counsel.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">They craved a lust in the desert, and they tried God in the wasteland.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">He gave them their request, but He sent emaciation into their soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">They angered Moses in the camp, Aaron, the holy man of the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">The earth opened up and swallowed Dathan and covered the congregation of Abiram.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">And fire burned in their congregation; a flame burned the wicked.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">They made a calf in Horeb and prostrated themselves to a molten image.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">They exchanged their glory for the likeness of an ox eating grass.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">They forgot God, their Savior, Who wrought great deeds in Egypt.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Wonders in the land of Ham, awesome deeds by the Sea of Reeds.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">He intended to destroy them [and would have] were it not that Moses, His chosen one, stood before Him in the breech to return His wrath from destroying.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">They rejected the desirable land; they did not believe His word.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">They complained in their tents; they did not hearken to the voice of the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">He raised His hand to them to cast them down in the desert,</pasuk><pasuk id="27">And to cast their seed among the nations and to scatter them in the lands.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">They became attached to Baal Pe'or and ate sacrifices of the dead.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">They provoked [God] with their deeds, and a plague broke out among them.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">Phinehas stood up and executed justice, and the plague was stopped.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">It was accounted for him as a merit, for generation to generation to eternity.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">They provoked [God] by the waters of Meribah, and Moses suffered because of them.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">For they rebelled against His spirit, and He uttered with His lips.</pasuk><pasuk id="34">They did not destroy the peoples whom the Lord had told them [to destroy].</pasuk><pasuk id="35">And they mingled with the nations and learned their deeds.</pasuk><pasuk id="36">They worshipped their idols, which became a snare for them.</pasuk><pasuk id="37">They slaughtered their sons and daughters to the demons.</pasuk><pasuk id="38">They shed innocent blood, the blood of their sons and daughters whom they slaughtered to the idols of Canaan, and the land became polluted with the blood.</pasuk><pasuk id="39">And they became unclean through their deeds, and they went astray with their acts.</pasuk><pasuk id="40">And the Lord's wrath was kindled against His people and He detested His inheritance.</pasuk><pasuk id="41">And He delivered them into the hands of nations, and their enemies ruled over them.</pasuk><pasuk id="42">And their foes oppressed them, and they were humbled under their hand.</pasuk><pasuk id="43">Many times He saved them, but they were rebellious with their counsel, and they were humbled because of their iniquity.</pasuk><pasuk id="44">But He looked upon their distress when He heard their cries.</pasuk><pasuk id="45">And He remembered His covenant for them, and He relented in accordance with His abundant kindness.</pasuk><pasuk id="46">And He caused them to be pitied by all their captors.</pasuk><pasuk id="47">Save us, O Lord, our God, and gather us from the nations, to give thanks to Your holy name, to boast with Your praise.</pasuk><pasuk id="48">Blessed be the Lord God of Israel from world to world, and all the people shall say, "Amen." Hallelujah!</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="107"><pasuk id="1">Give thanks to the Lord because He is good, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Those redeemed by the Lord shall say it, those whom He redeemed from the hands of an oppressor.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">And gathered them from lands, from the east and from the west, from the north and from the sea.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">They strayed in the desert, on a road of desolation; they did not find an inhabited city.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Hungry as well as thirsty, their soul enwraps itself in them.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">And they cried out to the Lord in their distress; from their straits He rescued them.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">And He led them on a straight road, to go to an inhabited city.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">They shall give thanks to the Lord for His kindness, and for His wonders to the children of men.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">For He sated a yearning soul, and a hungry soul He filled with goodness.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Those who sit in darkness and the shadow of death, prisoners of affliction and iron.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">For they rebelled against the words of God, and they scorned the counsel of the Most High.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">And He humbled their heart with toil; they stumbled with no one to help them.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">And they cried out to the Lord in their distress; from their straits He saved them.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">He took them out of darkness and the shadow of death, and He broke open their bonds.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">They shall give thanks to the Lord for His kindness, and for His wonders to the children of men.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">For He broke copper doors, and cut off iron bars.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Fools, because of the way of their transgression and because of their iniquities, are afflicted.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Their soul despises all food, and they reach the portals of death.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">And they cried out to the Lord in their distress; from their straits He saved them.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">He sent His word and healed them, and extricated them from their pit.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">They shall give thanks to the Lord for His kindness, and for His wonders to the children of men.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">And they shall slaughter sacrifices of thanksgiving, and they shall tell of His deeds with song.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Those who go down to the sea in ships, who do work in mighty waters.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">They saw the deeds of the Lord and His wonders in the deep.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">He spoke, and He set up a tempest, and it raised its waves.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">They went up to the heavens, they came down to the depths; their soul melted with trouble.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">They were frightened and staggered like a drunkard, and all their wisdom was destroyed.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">They cried out to the Lord from their distress, that He take them out of their straits.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">The tempest He had set up [settled] into a calm, and their waves were stilled.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">They rejoiced that they were stilled, and He led them to the region of their desire.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">They shall thank the Lord for His kindness, and for His wonders to the children of men.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">And they shall exalt Him in an assembly of people, and in a sitting of elders, praise Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">He makes rivers into a desert, and springs of water into an arid place;</pasuk><pasuk id="34">A fruitful land into a salty waste, because of the evil of its inhabitants.</pasuk><pasuk id="35">He makes a desert into a pool of water, and a wasteland into springs of water.</pasuk><pasuk id="36">And He settles the hungry there, and they establish an inhabited city.</pasuk><pasuk id="37">And they sow fields and plant vineyards, which produce fruits and grain.</pasuk><pasuk id="38">And He blessed them, and they multiplied exceedingly, and their animals did not decrease.</pasuk><pasuk id="39">Whereas they were few and they sank down from dominion, trouble, and sorrow.</pasuk><pasuk id="40">He pours contempt upon princes and leads them astray in a wasteland where there is no path.</pasuk><pasuk id="41">And He strengthened the needy from poverty and made him families like flocks.</pasuk><pasuk id="42">The upright see and rejoice, and all injustice shuts its mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="43">He who is wise will keep these in mind, and they will ponder the kind deeds of the Lord.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="108"><pasuk id="1">A song, a psalm of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">My heart is steadfast, O God; I shall sing and play music, even my glory.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Awaken, you psaltery and harp; I shall awaken the dawn.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">I shall thank You among the peoples, O Lord, and I shall play music to You among the kingdoms.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">For Your kindness is great above the heavens, and Your truth is until the skies.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Lift Yourself above the heavens, O Lord, and over all the earth is Your glory.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">In order that Your beloved ones be released, save with Your right hand and answer me.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">God spoke with His holiness, that I would rejoice, that I would allot a portion, and that I would measure the valley of Succoth.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Gilead is mine, Manasseh is mine, and Ephraim is the strength of my head; Judah is my prince.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Moab is my wash basin, on Edom I shall cast my shoe; on Philistia I shall shout.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Who will bring me to the fortified city? He Who led me up to Edom.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Is it not You, O God, Who has forsaken us, and does not go, O Lord, in our hosts?</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Give us help against the adversary, for man's salvation is futile.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">With God we shall gather strength and He will trample our adversaries.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="109"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor. Of David, a song. O God of my praise, be not silent.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">For the mouth of a wicked man and the mouth of a deceitful man have opened upon me; they spoke with me with a lying tongue.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">And with words of hatred they have surrounded me, and they have fought with me without cause.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Instead of my love, they persecute me, but I am at prayer.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">They have imposed upon me evil instead of good and hatred instead of my love.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Set a wicked man over him, and let an adversary stand at his right hand.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">When he is judged, let him emerge guilty, and let his prayer be accounted as a sin.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">May his days be few, and may someone else take his office of dignity.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">May his sons be orphans and his wife a widow.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">May his sons wander, and [people] should ask and search from their ruins.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">May a creditor search out all he has, and may strangers despoil his labor.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">May he have none who extends kindness, and may no one be gracious to his orphans.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">May his end be to be cut off; in another generation may their name be blotted out.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">May the iniquity against his forefathers be remembered by the Lord, and may the sin against his mother not be erased.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">May they be before the Lord constantly, and may He cut off their remembrance from the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Because he did not remember to do kindness, and he pursued a poor and needy man, and a broken-hearted one, to kill [him].</pasuk><pasuk id="17">And he loved a curse, and it came upon him; and he did not desire a blessing, and it distanced itself from him.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">And he donned a curse like his garment, and it came into his midst like water and into his bones like oil.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">May it be to him as a garment with which he envelops himself and as a girdle with which he constantly girds himself.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">This is the recompense of my adversaries from the Lord, and those who speak evil upon my soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">But You, O God, my Lord, do with me for Your name's sake, for Your kindness is good; save me.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">For I am poor and needy, and my heart has died within me.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Like a shadow when it lengthens, I was driven about; I was stirred up like a locust.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">My knees stumbled from fasting, and my flesh became emaciated from fat.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">And I was a disgrace to them; they would see me, they would shake their head.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">Help me, O Lord, my God; save me according to Your kindness.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">And they should know that this is Your hand; You, O Lord, have done it.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">Let them curse and You will bless; they rose up and were ashamed, but Your servant will rejoice.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">May my adversaries don disgrace and enwrap themselves with their shame like a cloak.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">I shall thank the Lord exceedingly with my mouth, and among many people I shall praise Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">For He will stand to the right of the needy to save [him] from those who judge his soul.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="110"><pasuk id="1">Of David a psalm. The word of the Lord to my master; "Wait for My right hand, until I make your enemies a footstool at your feet."</pasuk><pasuk id="2">The staff of your might the Lord will send from Zion; rule in the midst of your enemies.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Your people will volunteer on the day of your host, because of the beauty of holiness when you fell from the womb; for you, your youth is like dew.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">The Lord swore and will not repent; you are a priest forever because of the speech of Malchizedek.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">The Lord, on your right hand, has crushed kings on the day of His wrath.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">He will execute justice upon the nations [into] a heap of corpses; He crushed the head on a great land.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">From the stream on the way he would drink; therefore, he raised his head.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="111"><pasuk id="1">Hallelujah, I shall thank the Lord with all my heart with the counsel of the upright and [in] the congregation.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Great are the works of the Lord, available to all who desire them.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Majesty and splendor are His work, and His righteousness endures forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">He made a memorial for His wonders; the Lord is gracious and merciful.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">He gave food to those who fear Him; He remembers His covenant forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">The strength of His works He related to His people, to give them the inheritance of the nations.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The works of His hands are truth and justice; all His commandments are faithful.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Steadfast forever, made in truth and uprightness.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">He sent redemption to His people; He commanded His covenant forever; His name is holy and awesome.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">The beginning of wisdom is the fear of the Lord; good understanding to all who perform them; his praise endures forever.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="112"><pasuk id="1">Hallelujah. Praiseworthy is the man who fears the Lord, who greatly desires His commandments.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">His seed will be mighty in the land, a generation of upright ones, which shall be blessed.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Wealth and riches will be in his house, and his righteousness endures forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">He shone a light in the darkness for the upright, [for He is] gracious and merciful and righteous.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Good is the man who is gracious and lends, who conducts his affairs with moderation.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">For he will never falter; for an everlasting memorial will the righteous man be.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">He will not fear bad news; his heart is steadfast, trusting in the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">His heart is steadfast, he will not fear until he sees in his adversaries.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">He distributed, he gave to the needy; his charity endures forever, his horn will be raised with glory.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">A wicked man will see and become angry; he will gnash his teeth and melt; the desire of the wicked will be lost.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="113"><pasuk id="1">Hallelujah! Praise, you servants of the Lord, praise the name of the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">May the name of the Lord be blessed from now and to eternity.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">From the rising of the sun until its setting, the name of the Lord is praised.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">The Lord is high over all nations; upon the heavens is His glory.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Who is like the Lord, our God, Who dwells on high,</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Who lowers [His eyes] to look in the heavens and the earth?</pasuk><pasuk id="7">He lifts the pauper up from the dust, from the dungheap He raises up the needy,</pasuk><pasuk id="8">To seat [him] with princes, with the princes of His people.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">He seats the barren woman of the house as a happy mother of children. Hallelujah!</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="114"><pasuk id="1">When Israel left Egypt, the house of Jacob [left] a people of a strange tongue,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Judah became His holy nation, Israel His dominion.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">The sea saw and fled; the Jordan turned backward.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">The mountains danced like rams, hills like young sheep.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">What frightens you, O sea, that you flee? O Jordan, that you turn backward?</pasuk><pasuk id="6">You mountains, that you dance like rams; you hills, like young sheep?</pasuk><pasuk id="7">From before the Master, Who created the earth, from before the God of Jacob,</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Who transforms the rock into a pond of water, the flint into a fountain of water.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="115"><pasuk id="1">Not for us, O Lord, not for us, but for Your name give honor, for Your kindness and for Your truthfulness.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Why should the nations say, "Where is your God now?"</pasuk><pasuk id="3">But our God is in heaven; whatever He wishes, He does.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Their idols are silver and gold, the handiwork of man.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">They have a mouth but they do not speak; they have eyes but they do not see.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">They have ears but they do not hear; they have a nose but they do not smell.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Their hands-but they do not feel; their feet-but they do not walk; they do not murmur with their throat.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Like them shall be those who make them, all who trust in them.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Israel, trust in the Lord; He is their help and their shield.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">House of Aaron, trust in the Lord; He is their help and their shield.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Those who fear the Lord, trust in the Lord; He is their help and their shield.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">The Lord, Who remembered us, will bless; He will bless the house of Israel; He will bless the house of Aaron.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">He will bless those who fear the Lord, the small together with the great.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">May the Lord add upon you, upon you and upon your children.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Blessed are you to the Lord, the Maker of heaven and earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">The heavens are heavens of the Lord, but the earth He gave to the children of men.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Neither will the dead praise God, nor all those who descend to the grave.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">But we shall bless God from now until everlasting, Hallelujah!</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="116"><pasuk id="1">I wished that the Lord would hear my voice [in] my supplications.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">For He extended His ear to me, and I shall call out in my days.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">[When] bands of death surrounded me and the boundaries of the grave befell me, and I found trouble and grief,</pasuk><pasuk id="4">And I called out in the name of the Lord, "Please, O Lord, save my soul!</pasuk><pasuk id="5">The Lord is gracious and righteous, and our God is merciful.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">The Lord protects the simple; when I was poor, He saved me.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Return, my soul, to your rest, for the Lord has dealt bountifully with you.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">For You have rescued my soul from death, my eye from tears, and my foot from stumbling.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">I shall walk before the Lord in the lands of the living.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">I believed so that I spoke; I humble myself exceedingly.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">I said in my haste, "All men are liars."</pasuk><pasuk id="12">How can I repay the Lord for all His favors upon me?</pasuk><pasuk id="13">I shall lift up a cup of salvations, and I shall call out in the name of the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">I shall pay my vows to the Lord now in the presence of all His people.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Difficult in the eyes of the Lord is the death of His pious ones.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Please, O Lord, for I am Your servant; I am Your servant the son of Your maidservant; You have loosed my thongs.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">To You I shall slaughter a thanksgiving offering, and I shall call out in the name of the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">I shall pay my vows to the Lord now in the presence of all His people,</pasuk><pasuk id="19">In the courtyards of the house of the Lord, in your midst, O Jerusalem. Hallelujah!</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="117"><pasuk id="1">Praise the Lord, all nations, laud Him, all peoples.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">For His kindness has overwhelmed us, and the truth of the Lord is eternal. Hallelujah!</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="118"><pasuk id="1">Give thanks to the Lord because He is good, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Israel shall now say, "For His kindness is eternal."</pasuk><pasuk id="3">The house of Aaron shall now say, "For His kindness is eternal."</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Those who fear the Lord shall now say, "For His kindness is eternal."</pasuk><pasuk id="5">From the straits I called God; God answered me with a vast expanse.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">The Lord is for me; I shall not fear. What can man do to me?</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The Lord is for me with my helpers, and I shall see [revenge] in my enemies.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">It is better to take shelter in the Lord than to trust in man.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">It is better to take shelter in the Lord than to trust in princes.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">All nations surrounded me; in the name of the Lord that I shall cut them off.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">They encircled me, yea they surrounded me; in the name of the Lord that I shall cut them off.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">They encircled me like bees; they were extinguished like a thorn fire; in the name of the Lord that I shall cut them off.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">You pushed me to fall, but the Lord helped me.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">The might and the cutting power of God was my salvation.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">A voice of singing praises and salvation is in the tents of the righteous; the right hand of the Lord deals valiantly.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">The right hand of the Lord is exalted; the right hand of the Lord deals valiantly.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">I shall not die but I shall live and tell the deeds of God.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">God has chastised me, but He has not delivered me to death.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Open for me the gates of righteousness; I shall enter them and thank God.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">This is the Lord's gate; the righteous will enter therein.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">I shall thank You because You answered me, and You were my salvation.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">The stone that the builders rejected became a cornerstone.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">This was from the Lord; it is wondrous in our eyes.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">This is the day that the Lord made; we shall exult and rejoice thereon.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">Please, O Lord, save now! Please, O Lord, make prosperous now!</pasuk><pasuk id="26">Blessed be he who has come in the name of the Lord; we have blessed you in the name of the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">The Lord is God, and He gave us light. Bind the sacrifice with ropes until [it is brought to] the corners of the altar.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">You are my God and I shall thank You; the God of my father, and I shall exalt You.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">Give thanks to the Lord because He is good, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="119"><pasuk id="1">Praiseworthy are those whose way is perfect, who walk with the law of the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Praiseworthy are those who keep His testimonies; who seek Him wholeheartedly.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Not only have they committed no injustice, they walked in His ways.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">You commanded Your precepts, to keep diligently.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">My prayers are that my ways should be established, to keep Your statutes.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Then I shall not be ashamed when I look at all Your commandments.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">I shall thank You with an upright heart when I learn the judgments of Your righteousness.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">I shall keep Your statutes; do not forsake me utterly.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">In what manner should a youth purify his way? To observe according to Your word.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">With all my heart I searched for You; do not cause me to stray from Your commandments.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">In my heart I hid Your word, in order that I should not sin against You.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Blessed are You, O Lord; teach me Your statutes.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">With my lips I recited all the judgments of Your mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">With the way of Your testimonies I rejoiced as over all riches.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Concerning Your precepts I shall converse, and I shall look at Your ways.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">With Your statutes I shall occupy myself; I shall not forget Your speech.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Bestow kindness upon Your servant; I shall live and I shall keep Your word.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Uncover my eyes and I shall look at hidden things from Your Torah.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">I am a stranger in the land; do not hide Your commandments from me.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">My soul is crushed from longing for Your judgments at all times.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">You shall rebuke cursed willful sinners who stray from Your commandments.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Remove from me disgrace and contempt, for I kept Your testimonies.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Although princes sat and talked about me, Your servant conversed about Your statutes.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">Also, Your testimonies are my affairs, men of my counsel.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">My soul clung to the dust; revive me according to Your word.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">I told of my ways, and You answered me; teach me Your statutes.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">Make me understand Your precepts, and I shall speak of Your wonders.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">My soul drips from grief; sustain me according to Your word.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">Remove from me the way of falsehood, and favor me with Your Torah.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">I chose the way of faith; Your judgments I have set [before me].</pasuk><pasuk id="31">I clung to Your testimonies; O Lord; put me not to shame.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">[In] the way of Your commandments I shall run, for You will broaden my understanding.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">Instruct me, O Lord, [in] the way of Your statutes, and I shall keep it at every step.</pasuk><pasuk id="34">Enable me to understand and I shall keep Your Torah, and I shall keep it wholeheartedly.</pasuk><pasuk id="35">Lead me in the path of Your commandments for I desired it.</pasuk><pasuk id="36">Extend my heart to Your testimonies and not to monetary gain.</pasuk><pasuk id="37">Turn away my eyes from seeing vanity; with Your ways sustain me.</pasuk><pasuk id="38">Fulfill for Your servant Your word that is for Your fear.</pasuk><pasuk id="39">Remove my disgrace, which I feared, for Your judgments are good.</pasuk><pasuk id="40">Behold, I longed for Your precepts; with Your righteousness sustain me.</pasuk><pasuk id="41">And may Your acts of kindness befall me, O Lord, Your salvation according to Your word.</pasuk><pasuk id="42">And I shall answer a word to those who disgrace me, for I trusted in Your word.</pasuk><pasuk id="43">And do not take out utterly from my mouth a word of truth, because I hoped for Your words.</pasuk><pasuk id="44">And I shall keep Your Torah constantly, forever and ever.</pasuk><pasuk id="45">And I shall walk in widely accepted ways, for I sought Your precepts.</pasuk><pasuk id="46">And I shall speak of Your testimonies in the presence of kings, and I shall not be ashamed.</pasuk><pasuk id="47">And I shall engage in Your commandments, which I love.</pasuk><pasuk id="48">And I shall lift up my palms to your commandments, which I love, and I shall converse about Your statutes.</pasuk><pasuk id="49">Remember a word to Your servant, through which You gave me hope.</pasuk><pasuk id="50">This is my consolation in my affliction, for Your word has sustained me.</pasuk><pasuk id="51">Willful sinners derided me greatly; I did not turn away from Your Torah.</pasuk><pasuk id="52">I remembered Your judgments of old, O Lord, and I was consoled.</pasuk><pasuk id="53">Quaking gripped me because of the wicked men who abandoned Your Torah.</pasuk><pasuk id="54">Your statutes were to me as songs in the house of my sojournings.</pasuk><pasuk id="55">At night I remembered Your name, O Lord, and I kept Your Torah.</pasuk><pasuk id="56">This came to me because I kept Your precepts.</pasuk><pasuk id="57">"The Lord is my portion," I said, to keep Your words.</pasuk><pasuk id="58">I entreated You with all my heart; favor me according to Your word.</pasuk><pasuk id="59">I considered my ways, and I returned my feet to Your testimonies.</pasuk><pasuk id="60">I hastened and did not delay to keep Your commandments.</pasuk><pasuk id="61">Bands of wicked men robbed me; I did not forget Your Torah.</pasuk><pasuk id="62">At midnight, I rise to give thanks to You for Your just judgments.</pasuk><pasuk id="63">I am a companion to all who fear You and to those who keep your precepts.</pasuk><pasuk id="64">O Lord, the earth is full of Your kindness; teach me Your statutes.</pasuk><pasuk id="65">You have done good with Your servant, O Lord, according to Your word.</pasuk><pasuk id="66">The best of reason and knowledge, teach me for I believe in Your commandments.</pasuk><pasuk id="67">Before I recited, I erred, but now I keep Your word.</pasuk><pasuk id="68">You are good and You do good; teach me Your statutes.</pasuk><pasuk id="69">Willful sinners have heaped false accusations upon me, but I keep your precepts wholeheartedly.</pasuk><pasuk id="70">Thick like fat is their heart, but I engage in Your Torah.</pasuk><pasuk id="71">It is good for me that I was afflicted, in order that I learn Your statutes.</pasuk><pasuk id="72">The instruction of Your mouth is better for me than thousands of gold and silver.</pasuk><pasuk id="73">Your hands made me and fashioned me; enable me to understand, and I shall learn Your commandments.</pasuk><pasuk id="74">Those who fear You will see me and rejoice for I hoped for Your word.</pasuk><pasuk id="75">I know, O Lord, that Your judgments are just, and in faith You afflicted me.</pasuk><pasuk id="76">May Your kindness be [upon me] now to comfort me, as Your word to Your servant.</pasuk><pasuk id="77">May Your mercy come upon me so that I shall live, for Your Torah is my occupation.</pasuk><pasuk id="78">May the willful sinners be shamed for they condemned me falsely; I shall converse about Your precepts.</pasuk><pasuk id="79">May those who fear You and those who know Your testimonies return to me.</pasuk><pasuk id="80">May my heart be perfect in Your statutes in order that I not be shamed.</pasuk><pasuk id="81">My soul pines for Your salvation; for Your word I hope.</pasuk><pasuk id="82">My eyes pine for Your word, saying, "When will You console me?"</pasuk><pasuk id="83">For I have become like a wineskin in smoke; I have not forgotten Your statutes.</pasuk><pasuk id="84">How many are Your servant's days? When will You execute judgments upon my pursuers?</pasuk><pasuk id="85">Willful sinners have dug pits for me, which is not according to Your Torah.</pasuk><pasuk id="86">All Your commandments are faithful; they pursued me in vain; help me.</pasuk><pasuk id="87">They almost destroyed me on earth, but I did not forsake Your precepts.</pasuk><pasuk id="88">According to Your kindness, sustain me, and I shall keep the testimony of Your mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="89">Forever, O Lord, Your word stands in the heavens.</pasuk><pasuk id="90">Your faith is to every generation; You established the earth and it endures.</pasuk><pasuk id="91">For Your judgments they stand today, for all are Your servants.</pasuk><pasuk id="92">Were not Your Torah my occupation, then I would have perished in my affliction.</pasuk><pasuk id="93">I shall never forget Your precepts for through them You have sustained me.</pasuk><pasuk id="94">I am Yours; save me for I sought Your precepts.</pasuk><pasuk id="95">Concerning me: the wicked hoped to destroy me; I shall ponder Your testimonies.</pasuk><pasuk id="96">Of every finite thing I have seen the end; Your commandments are very broad.</pasuk><pasuk id="97">How I love Your Torah! All day it is my conversation.</pasuk><pasuk id="98">Each of Your commandments makes me wiser than my enemies, for it is always mine.</pasuk><pasuk id="99">From all my teachers I gained understanding, for Your testimonies are my conversation.</pasuk><pasuk id="100">From the wise elders I gain understanding, for I kept Your precepts.</pasuk><pasuk id="101">From every evil way I restrained my feet in order that I keep Your word.</pasuk><pasuk id="102">From Your judgments I did not turn away, for You guided me.</pasuk><pasuk id="103">How sweet are Your words to my palate, more than honey to my mouth!</pasuk><pasuk id="104">From Your precepts I shall gain understanding; therefore, I hate all ways of falsehood.</pasuk><pasuk id="105">Your words are a lamp for my foot, and light for my path.</pasuk><pasuk id="106">I swore and I fulfilled, to keep the judgments of Your righteousness.</pasuk><pasuk id="107">I have been exceedingly humbled; O Lord, sustain me according to Your word.</pasuk><pasuk id="108">The freewill offerings of my mouth accept now, O Lord, and teach me Your judgments.</pasuk><pasuk id="109">My soul is constantly in my hand, and I have not forgotten Your Torah.</pasuk><pasuk id="110">The wicked laid a snare for me, but I did not stray from Your precepts.</pasuk><pasuk id="111">I inherited Your testimonies forever, for they are the joy of my heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="112">I have inclined my heart to perform Your statutes forever on their paths.</pasuk><pasuk id="113">I hate those who harbor iniquitous thoughts, but Your Torah I love.</pasuk><pasuk id="114">You are my protection and my shield; I hoped for Your word.</pasuk><pasuk id="115">Go away from me, you evildoers, and I shall keep the commandments of my God.</pasuk><pasuk id="116">Support me as Your word, and I shall live, and do not put me to shame because of my hope.</pasuk><pasuk id="117">Sustain me and I shall be saved, and I shall constantly engage in Your statutes.</pasuk><pasuk id="118">You trampled all who stray from Your statutes, for their deceit is false.</pasuk><pasuk id="119">As dross, You cut off all the wicked of the earth; therefore I love Your testimonies.</pasuk><pasuk id="120">My flesh bristles from fear of You, and I dread Your judgments.</pasuk><pasuk id="121">I performed justice and righteousness; do not leave me to my oppressors.</pasuk><pasuk id="122">Be surety for Your servant for good; let the willful sinners not oppress me.</pasuk><pasuk id="123">My eyes pined for Your salvation and for the word of Your righteousness.</pasuk><pasuk id="124">Deal with Your servant according to Your kindness, and teach me Your statutes.</pasuk><pasuk id="125">I am Your servant; enable me to understand, and I shall know Your testimonies.</pasuk><pasuk id="126">A time to do for the Lord; they have made void Your Torah.</pasuk><pasuk id="127">Because I loved Your commandments more than gold, even more than fine gold.</pasuk><pasuk id="128">Because I considered all precepts of all things upright; [and] every false way I hated.</pasuk><pasuk id="129">Your testimonies are hidden; therefore, my soul kept them.</pasuk><pasuk id="130">The commencement of Your words enlightens; You make the simple understand.</pasuk><pasuk id="131">I opened my mouth and panted because I yearned for Your commandments.</pasuk><pasuk id="132">Turn to me and favor me as is Your custom with those who love Your name.</pasuk><pasuk id="133">Prepare my steps with Your word, and do not allow any iniquity to rule over me.</pasuk><pasuk id="134">Redeem me from the oppression of man, and I shall keep Your precepts.</pasuk><pasuk id="135">Cause Your countenance to shine upon Your servant and teach me Your statutes.</pasuk><pasuk id="136">Rivulets of water ran down from my eyes because they did not keep Your Torah.</pasuk><pasuk id="137">You are righteous, O Lord, and Your judgments are upright.</pasuk><pasuk id="138">You commanded Your testimonies, [which are] righteousness, and they are exceedingly faithful.</pasuk><pasuk id="139">My zeal incenses me, for my adversaries have forgotten Your words.</pasuk><pasuk id="140">Your word is very pure, and Your servant loves it.</pasuk><pasuk id="141">I am young and despised; I have not forgotten Your precepts.</pasuk><pasuk id="142">Your righteousness is perpetual righteousness, and Your Torah is true.</pasuk><pasuk id="143">Distress and anguish have overtaken me; Your commandments are my occupation.</pasuk><pasuk id="144">The righteousness of Your testimonies is eternal; enable me to understand and I shall live.</pasuk><pasuk id="145">I called with all my heart; answer me, O Lord; I shall keep Your statutes.</pasuk><pasuk id="146">I called to You; save me and I shall keep Your testimonies.</pasuk><pasuk id="147">I arose early, when it was still night, and I cried out; I hoped for Your word.</pasuk><pasuk id="148">My eyes preceded the watches to speak of Your word.</pasuk><pasuk id="149">Hearken to my voice according to Your kindness; O Lord, according to Your custom sustain me.</pasuk><pasuk id="150">Pursuers of lewdness have drawn near; from Your Torah they have distanced themselves.</pasuk><pasuk id="151">You are near, O Lord, and all Your commandments are true.</pasuk><pasuk id="152">From before, I knew from Your testimonies, for You established them to [the end of] the world.</pasuk><pasuk id="153">See my affliction and release me, for I have not forgotten Your Torah.</pasuk><pasuk id="154">Plead my cause and redeem me; for Your word sustains me.</pasuk><pasuk id="155">Salvation is far from the wicked, for they did not seek Your statutes.</pasuk><pasuk id="156">Your mercies, O Lord, are abundant; according to Your custom, sustain me.</pasuk><pasuk id="157">Many are my pursuers and my adversaries; from Your testimonies I did not turn away.</pasuk><pasuk id="158">I saw traitors and I quarreled [with them] because they did not keep your word.</pasuk><pasuk id="159">See that I love Your precepts, O Lord; according to Your kindness, sustain me.</pasuk><pasuk id="160">The beginning of Your word is true, and each of Your righteous judgments is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="161">Princes pursued me for nothing, but my heart feared Your word.</pasuk><pasuk id="162">I rejoice over Your word as one who finds great spoil.</pasuk><pasuk id="163">I hate falsehood, and I abominate [it], I love Your Torah.</pasuk><pasuk id="164">Seven times a day I praise You for Your righteous judgments.</pasuk><pasuk id="165">There is abundant peace to those who love Your Torah, and they have no obstacle.</pasuk><pasuk id="166">I hoped for Your salvation, O Lord, and I performed Your commandments.</pasuk><pasuk id="167">My soul kept Your testimonies, and I love them exceedingly.</pasuk><pasuk id="168">I kept Your precepts and Your testimonies, for all my ways are before You.</pasuk><pasuk id="169">May my song of prayer draw near before You, O Lord; according to Your word, enable me to understand.</pasuk><pasuk id="170">May my supplication come before You; according to Your word, save me.</pasuk><pasuk id="171">My lips will utter praise when You teach me Your statutes.</pasuk><pasuk id="172">My tongue will proclaim Your word, for all Your commandments are righteous.</pasuk><pasuk id="173">May Your hand be [ready] to help me, for I have chosen Your precepts.</pasuk><pasuk id="174">I yearned for Your salvation, O Lord, and Your Torah is my occupation.</pasuk><pasuk id="175">May my soul live and praise You, and may Your judgments help me.</pasuk><pasuk id="176">I went astray like a lost lamb; seek Your servant, for I did not forget Your commandments.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="120"><pasuk id="1">A song of ascents. In my distress I called to the Lord, and He answered me.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">O Lord, save my soul from false lips, from a deceitful tongue.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">What can He give you, and what can He add to you, you deceitful tongue?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Sharpened arrows of a mighty man with coals of brooms.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Woe is to me for I have sojourned in Meshech; I dwelt among the tents of Kedar.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">For a long time, my soul dwelt with those who hate peace.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">I am at peace, but when I speak, they [come] to [wage] war.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="121"><pasuk id="1">A song for ascents. I shall raise my eyes to the mountains, from where will my help come?</pasuk><pasuk id="2">My help is from the Lord, the Maker of heaven and earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">He will not allow your foot to falter; Your Guardian will not slumber.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Behold the Guardian of Israel will neither slumber nor sleep.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">The Lord is your Guardian; the Lord is your shadow; [He is] by your right hand.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">By day, the sun will not smite you, nor will the moon at night.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The Lord will guard you from all evil; He will guard your soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">The Lord will guard your going out and your coming in from now and to eternity.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="122"><pasuk id="1">A song of ascents of David. I rejoiced when they said to me, "Let us go to the house of the Lord."</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Our feet were standing within your gates, O Jerusalem.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">The built-up Jerusalem is like a city that was joined together within itself.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">There ascended the tribes, the tribes of God, testimony to Israel, to give thanks to the name of the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">For there were set thrones for judgment, thrones for the house of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Request the welfare of Jerusalem; may those who love you enjoy tranquility.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">May there be peace in your wall, tranquility in your palaces.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">For the sake of my brethren and my companions, I shall now speak of peace in you.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">For the sake of the house of the Lord our God, I shall beg for goodness for you.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="123"><pasuk id="1">A song of ascents. To You I lifted up my eyes, You Who dwell in heaven.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Behold, as the eyes of slaves to the hand of their masters, as the eyes of a handmaid to the hand of her mistress, so are our eyes to the Lord our God, until He favors us.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Favor us, O Lord, favor us, for we are fully sated with contempt.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Our soul is fully sated with the ridicule of the complacent, the contempt [shown] to the valley of doves.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="124"><pasuk id="1">A song of ascents. Of David. Had it not been for the Lord Who was with us, let Israel declare now.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Had it not been for the Lord Who was with us when men rose up against us,</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Then they would have swallowed us raw when their anger was kindled against us.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Then the waters would have washed us away; illness would have passed over our soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Then the wicked waters would have passed over our soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Blessed is the Lord, Who did not give us as prey for their teeth.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Our soul escaped like a bird from the hunters' snare; the snare broke, and we escaped.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Our help is in the name of the Lord, Who made heaven and earth.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="125"><pasuk id="1">A song of ascents. Those who trust in the Lord are like Mount Zion, which will not falter but will abide forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Jerusalem has mountains around it, and the Lord is around His people from now and to eternity.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">For the rod of wickedness will not rest on the lot of the righteous, because the righteous do not stretch out their hands into wrongdoing.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Be good, O Lord, to the good and to the upright in their hearts.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">And those who turn their crooked ways-may the Lord lead them away with the workers of iniquity, [and may there be] peace on Israel.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="126"><pasuk id="1">A song of ascents. When the Lord returns the returnees to Zion, we shall be like dreamers.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Then our mouths will be filled with laughter and our tongues with songs of praise; then they will say among the nations, "The Lord has done great things with these."</pasuk><pasuk id="3">"The Lord has done great things with us; we were happy."</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Return, O Lord, our captivity like rivulets in arid land.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Those who sow with tears will reap with song.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">He will go along weeping, carrying the valuable seeds; he will come back with song, carrying his sheaves.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="127"><pasuk id="1">A song of ascents about Solomon. If the Lord will not build a house, its builders have toiled at it in vain; if the Lord will not guard a city, [its] watcher keeps his vigil in vain.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">It is futile for you who arise early, who sit late, who eat the bread of toil, so will the Lord give to one who banishes sleep from himself.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Behold, the heritage of the Lord is sons, the reward is the fruit of the innards.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Like arrows in the hand of a mighty man, so are the sons of one's youth.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Praiseworthy is the man who has filled his quiver with them; they will not be ashamed when they talk to the enemies in the gate.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="128"><pasuk id="1">A song of ascents. Praiseworthy is every man who fears the Lord, who walks in His ways.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">If you eat the toil of your hands, you are praiseworthy, and it is good for you.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Your wife will be as a fruitful vine in the innermost parts of your house; your sons will be like olive shoots around your table.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Behold that so will a man who fears the Lord be blessed.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">May the Lord bless you from Zion, and see the good of Jerusalem all the days of your life.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">And may you see children [born] to your children, [and see] peace upon Israel.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="129"><pasuk id="1">A song of ascents. Much have they distressed me from my youth, Israel will say now.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Much have they distressed me from my youth, but also they have not prevailed against me.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">On my back, the plowmen plowed; they lengthened their furrow.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">The Lord is righteous; He will cut the ropes of the wicked.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">May all those who hate Zion be ashamed and retreat.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">May they be like the grass of the roofs, which, before it is plucked, withers.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Of which the reaper did not fill his hand, nor the gatherer his arm.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">And the passers-by did not say, "May the blessing of the Lord be to you; we have blessed you in the name of the Lord."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="130"><pasuk id="1">A song of ascents. From the depths I have called You, O Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">O Lord, hearken to my voice; may Your ears be attentive to the voice of my supplications.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">O God, if You keep [a record of] iniquities, O Lord, who will stand?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">For forgiveness is with You, in order that You be feared.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">I hoped, O Lord; yea, my soul hoped, and I wait for His word.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">My soul is to the Lord among those who await the morning, those who await the morning.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Israel, hope to the Lord, for kindness is with the Lord and much redemption is with Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">And He will redeem Israel from all their iniquities.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="131"><pasuk id="1">A song of ascent by David. O Lord, my heart was not haughty, nor were my eyes raised on high, and I did not pursue matters greater and more wondrous than I.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">I swear that I calmed and quieted my soul like a suckling on its mother; like a suckling was my soul with me.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Israel, hope to the Lord from now to eternity.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="132"><pasuk id="1">A song of ascents. Remember, O Lord, onto David all his affliction.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">That he swore to the Lord, he vowed to the Mighty One of Jacob;</pasuk><pasuk id="3">That I shall not come into the tent of my house, and I shall not go up on the bed that was spread for me.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">I shall not give sleep to my eyes nor slumber to my pupils,</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Until I find a place for the Lord, dwellings for the Mighty One of Jacob.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Behold we heard it in Ephrath; we found it in the fields of the forest.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Let us come to His Tabernacles; let us prostrate ourselves to His footstool.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Arise, O Lord, to Your resting place, You and the Ark of Your might.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Let Your priests be clothed with righteousness, and let Your devout ones sing praises.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">For the sake of David Your servant, turn not away the face of Your anointed.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">The Lord has sworn to David in truth, from which He will never turn back, "Of the fruit of your body I shall seat upon your throne.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">If your sons keep My covenant, and this, My testimony, which I shall teach them, also their sons will sit on your throne forever."</pasuk><pasuk id="13">For the Lord has chosen Zion; He desired it for His habitation.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">This is My resting place forever; here I shall dwell for I desired it.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">I shall bless its provision; I shall sate its needy with bread.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">And its priests I shall clothe with salvation, and its devout ones will sing praises.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">There I shall cause David's horn to sprout; I have set up a lamp for My anointed.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">His enemies I shall clothe with shame, and upon him his crown will shine.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="133"><pasuk id="1">A song of ascents of David. Behold how good and how pleasant it is for brothers also to dwell together!</pasuk><pasuk id="2">As the good oil on the head runs down upon the beard, the beard of Aaron, which runs down on the mouth of his garments.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">As the dew of Hermon which runs down on the mountains of Zion, for there the Lord commanded the blessing, life forever.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="134"><pasuk id="1">A song of ascents. Behold, bless the Lord, all servants of the Lord who stand in the house of the Lord at night.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Lift your hands in the holy place and bless the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">May the Lord bless you from Zion, He Who made heaven and earth.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="135"><pasuk id="1">Hallelujah, praise the name of the Lord, praise, you servants of the Lord,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Who stand in the house of the Lord, in the courts of the house of our God.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Praise God for the Lord is good; sing to His name because it is pleasant.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">For God chose Jacob for Himself, Israel for His treasure.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">For I know that God is great, and our Lord is more than all powers.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">All that the Lord wished, He did in the heavens and on the earth, in the seas and all the depths.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">He raises the clouds from the edge of the earth; He made lightning for the rain; He finds wind [to send] out of His treasuries.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">He struck down the firstborn of Egypt, from man to beast.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">He sent signs and wonders in the midst of Egypt, upon Pharaoh and upon all his servants.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">He struck down great nations and slew mighty kings.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Sihon the king of the Amorites and Og the king of the Bashan, and all the kingdoms of Canaan.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">And He gave their land as an inheritance, an inheritance to Israel His people.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">O Lord, Your name is eternal; O Lord, Your remembrance is throughout all generations.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">For the Lord will judge His people and relent for His servants.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">The idols of the nations are silver and gold, the handiwork of man.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">They have a mouth but do not speak; they have eyes but do not see.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">They have ears but do not listen; neither is there any breath in their mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Like them will be those who make them, all who trust in them.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">The house of Israel, bless the Lord; the house of Aaron, bless the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">The house of the Levites, bless the Lord; those who fear the Lord, bless the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Blessed is the Lord from Zion, He Who dwells in Jerusalem. Hallelujah!</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="136"><pasuk id="1">Give thanks to the Lord because He is good, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Give thanks to the God of the angels, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Give thanks to the Lord of lords, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">To Him Who performs great wonders alone, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">To Him Who made the heavens with understanding, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">To Him Who spread out the earth over the water, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">To Him Who made great luminaries, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">The sun to rule by day, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">The moon and stars to rule at night, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">To Him Who smote the Egyptians with their firstborn, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">And He took Israel from their midst, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">With a strong hand and with an outstretched arm, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">To Him Who cut the Sea of Reeds asunder, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">And caused Israel to cross in its midst, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">And He threw Pharaoh and his host into the Sea of Reeds, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">To Him Who led His people in the desert, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">To Him Who smote great kings, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">And slew mighty kings, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Sihon the king of the Amorites, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">And Og the king of Bashan, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">And He gave their land as an inheritance, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">An inheritance to Israel His servant, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Who remembered us in our humble state, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">And He rescued us from our adversaries, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">Who gives bread to all flesh, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">Give thanks to the God of heaven, for His kindness is eternal.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="137"><pasuk id="1">By the rivers of Babylon, there we sat, we also wept when we remembered Zion.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">On willows in its midst we hung our harps.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">For there our captors asked us for words of song and our tormentors [asked of us] mirth, "Sing for us of the song of Zion."</pasuk><pasuk id="4">"How shall we sing the song of the Lord on foreign soil?"</pasuk><pasuk id="5">If I forget you, O Jerusalem, may my right hand forget [its skill].</pasuk><pasuk id="6">May my tongue cling to my palate, if I do not remember you, if I do not bring up Jerusalem at the beginning of my joy.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Remember, O Lord, for the sons of Edom, the day of Jerusalem, those who say, "Raze it, raze it, down to its foundation!"</pasuk><pasuk id="8">O Daughter of Babylon, who is destined to be plundered, praiseworthy is he who repays you your recompense that you have done to us.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Praiseworthy is he who will take and dash your infants against the rock.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="138"><pasuk id="1">Of David. I shall thank You with all my heart; before the princes I shall sing Your praises.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">I shall prostrate myself toward Your holy Temple, and I shall give thanks to Your name for Your kindness and for Your truth, for You magnified Your word over all Your names.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">On the day that I called and You answered me; You made me great, [putting] strength into my soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">O Lord, all the kings of the earth will acknowledge You, for they heard the words of Your mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">And they will sing of the ways of the Lord, for great is the glory of the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">For the Lord is high but He sees the lowly, and He chastises the haughty from afar.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">If I walk in the midst of distress, You revive me; against the wrath of my enemies, You stretch forth Your hand and Your right hand saves me.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">May the Lord agree with me; O Lord, may Your kindness be eternal. Do not let go of the works of Your hands.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="139"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor. Of David, a song. O Lord, You have searched me out and You know.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">You know my sitting and my rising; You understand how to attach me from afar.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">My going about and my lying down You encompassed, and You are accustomed to all my ways.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">For there is no word on my tongue; behold, O Lord, You know it all.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">From the rear and the front You encompassed me, and You placed Your pressure upon me.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Knowledge is hidden from me; it is hard, I cannot attain it.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Where shall I go from Your spirit, and where shall I flee from Your presence?</pasuk><pasuk id="8">If I ascend to the heavens, there You are, and if I make my bed in the grave, behold, You are there.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">[If] I take up the wings of dawn, [if] I dwell at the end of the west,</pasuk><pasuk id="10">There too, Your hand will lead me, and Your right hand will grasp me.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">I said, "Darkness will darken me, and the night will be as light about me."</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Even darkness will not obscure [anything] from You, and the night will light up like day; as darkness so is the light.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">For You created my reins, You covered me in my mother's womb.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">I shall thank You for in an awesome, wondrous way I was fashioned; Your works are wondrous, and my soul knows it very well.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">My essence was not hidden from You, when I was made in secret, I was formed in the lowest parts of the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Your eyes saw my unformed body, and on Your book they were all written; days have been formed and one of them is His.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">And to me, how dear are Your friends, O Lord! How great is their sum!</pasuk><pasuk id="18">I shall count them; they are more numerous than sand; I have come to the end, and I am still with You.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">If only You would slay the wicked, O God, and men of blood, "Turn away from me."</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Who mention You with wicked thought; Your enemies took it up in vain.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Did I not hate Your enemies, O Lord? With those who rise up against You, I quarrel.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">I hate them with utmost hatred; they have become my enemies.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Search me out, O God, and know my heart; test me and know my thoughts.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">And see whether there is any vexatious way about me, and lead me in the way of the world.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="140"><pasuk id="1">For the conductor, a song of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Rescue me, O Lord, from an evil man from a man of robbery You shall guard me.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Who plotted evil things in their heart; every day they gather to wage war.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">They whetted their tongue like a serpent; the venom of a spider is under their lips forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Guard me, O Lord, from the hands of a wicked man; from a man of robbery You shall watch me, who plotted to cause my steps to slip.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Haughty men have concealed a snare for me, and [with] ropes they spread a net beside [my] path; they laid traps for me constantly.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">I said to the Lord, "You are my God." Hearken, O Lord, to the voice of my supplications.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">God, O Lord, the might of my salvation; You shall protect my head on the day of battle.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">O Lord, do not grant the desires of the wicked; do not let his thoughts succeed, for they are constantly haughty.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">The numbers of those who surround me, may the lies of their lips cover them.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Let fiery coals descend on them; He will cast them into fire, in wars, so that they will not rise.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">A slanderer will not be established on earth; a man of violence, the evil will trap him with thrust upon thrust.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">I know that the Lord will perform the judgment of a poor man, the cause of the needy.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">But the righteous will thank Your name; the upright will sit before You.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="141"><pasuk id="1">A song of David. O Lord, I called You; hasten to me, give ear to my voice when I call out to You.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">My prayer shall be established like incense before You, the lifting of my hands as the evening offering.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">O Lord, place a guard for my mouth; watch the portal of my lips.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Do not incline my heart to an evil thing, to perform deeds of wickedness with men who work iniquity, and may I not partake of their feasts.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">May a righteous man strike me with kindness and reprove me; may the oil of the anointment of my head not turn my head away, for as long as [I am] at my prayer, [it is] about their evils.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Their judges were led astray by [their hearts of] stone, although they heard my words, which are pleasant.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">As one who chops and splits [wood] on the ground, our bones are scattered at the mouth of the grave.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">For to You, O God the Lord, are my eyes; I took shelter in You; do not cast out my soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Guard me from the snare that they have laid for me, and the traps of the workers of iniquity.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">May the wicked fall together, [each] into his nets, until I pass by.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="142"><pasuk id="1">A maskil of David, when he was in the cave, a prayer.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">[With] my voice, I cry out to the Lord; [with] my voice, I supplicate the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">I pour out before Him my speech; my distress I recite before Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">When my spirit enwraps itself upon me, and You know my path. In whichever way I go, they have hidden a snare for me.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Looking to the right, I see that no one recognizes me; escape is lost from me; no one seeks my soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">I cried out to You, O Lord; I said, "You are my refuge, my lot in the land of the living."</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Hearken to my cry for I have become very low; save me from my pursuers for they have overpowered me.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Take my soul out of confinement to give thanks to Your name; because of me the righteous will crown You, because You will recompense me.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="143"><pasuk id="1">A song of David. O Lord, hearken to my prayer, lend ear to my supplications; with Your faith, answer me with Your righteousness.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">And do not come to judgment with Your servant, for no living being will be innocent before You.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">For an enemy pursued my soul; he crushed my soul to the earth; he has made me dwell in dark places like those who are long dead.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">And my spirit enwrapped itself upon me; within me my heart is appalled.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">I remember the days of yore; I meditate over all Your works; I speak of the work of Your hands.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">I spread out my hands to You; my heart is like a weary land to You forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Answer me quickly, O Lord, my spirit pines. Do not hide Your countenance from me, lest I be likened to those who descend into the pit.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Let me hear Your kindness in the morning, for I hope in You; let me know the way in which I am to go, for to You I have lifted up my soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Save me from my enemies, O Lord; to You I have hidden.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Teach me to do Your will for You are my God; may Your good spirit lead me in an even land.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">For the sake of Your name, O Lord, revive me; with Your righteousness, deliver my soul from distress.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">And with Your kindness, You shall cut off my enemies, and You shall destroy all the oppressors of my soul, for I am Your servant.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="144"><pasuk id="1">Of David. Blessed is the Lord, my Rock, Who trains my hands for battle, my fingers for war.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">My kindness and my fortress, my high tower and my deliverer, my shield in Whom I take refuge, Who flattens peoples beneath me.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">O Lord, what is man that You should know him, the son of man, that You should consider him?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Man is like a breath; his days are as a fleeting shadow.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">O Lord, bend Your heavens and descend; touch the mountains and they will smoke.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Flash lightning and scatter them; send forth Your arrows and confound them.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Stretch forth hands from above; deliver me and rescue me from great waters, from the hands of foreigners.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Whose mouth speaks vanity, and whose right hand is a right hand of falsehood.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">O God, I shall sing a new song for You; with a psaltery and a ten-stringed harp, I shall play music for You.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Who gives salvation to kings, Who delivers David His servant from an evil sword.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Deliver me and rescue me from the hands of foreigners, whose mouth speaks vanity and whose right hand is a right hand of falsehood.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">For our sons are like saplings, grown up in their youth; our daughters are like cornerstones, praised as the form of the Temple.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Our corners are full, supplying from harvest to harvest; our flocks produce thousands, yea, ten thousands in our streets.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Our princes are borne; there is no breach nor rumor going out, nor is there a cry in our squares.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Praiseworthy is the people that has this; praiseworthy is the people whose God is the Lord.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="145"><pasuk id="1">A praise of David. I shall exalt You, my God the King, and I shall bless Your name forever and ever.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Every day I shall bless You, and I shall praise Your name forever and ever.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">The Lord is great and very much praised, and His greatness cannot be searched.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Generation to generation will praise Your works, and they will recite Your mighty deeds.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Of the majesty of the glory of Your splendor and the words of Your wonders I shall speak.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">And the strength of Your awesome deeds they will tell, and Your greatness I shall sing.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Of the remembrance of Your abundant goodness they will speak, and of Your righteousness they will sing.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">The Lord is gracious and compassionate, slow to anger and of great kindness.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">The Lord is good to all, and His mercies are on all His works.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">All Your works will thank You, O Lord, and Your pious ones will bless You.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">They will tell the glory of Your kingdom, and they will speak of Your might.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">To make known to the children of men His mighty deeds and the glory of the majesty of His kingdom.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Your kingdom is a kingdom of all times, and Your ruling is in every generation.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">The Lord supports all those who fall and straightens all who are bent down.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Everyone's eyes look to You with hope, and You give them their food in its time.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">You open Your hand and satisfy every living thing [with] its desire.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">The Lord is righteous in all His ways and kind in all His deeds.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">The Lord is near to all who call Him, to all who call Him with sincerity.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">He does the will of those who fear Him, and He hears their cry and saves them.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">The Lord guards all who love Him, and He destroys all the wicked.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">My mouth will speak the praise of the Lord, and all flesh will bless His holy name forever and ever.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="146"><pasuk id="1">Hallelujah! My soul, praise the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">I shall praise the Lord in my life; I shall sing to the Lord as long as I exist.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Do not trust in princes, in the son of men, who has no salvation.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">His spirit leaves, he returns to his soil; on that day, his thoughts are lost.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Praiseworthy is he in whose help is the God of Jacob; his hope is in the Lord his God.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Who made heaven and earth, the sea and all that is in them, Who keeps truth forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Who performs justice for the oppressed, Who gives bread to the hungry; the Lord sets loose the bound.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">The Lord gives sight to the blind; the Lord straightens the bent; the Lord loves the righteous.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">The Lord guards the strangers; He strengthens the orphan and the widow, and He perverts the way of the wicked.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">The Lord will reign forever! Your God, O Zion, to all generations. Hallelujah!</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="147"><pasuk id="1">Hallelujah! For it is good to sing to our God; because He is pleasant, praise is fitting for Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">The Lord is the builder of Jerusalem; He will gather the outcasts of Israel.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Who heals the brokenhearted and binds up their wounds.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">He counts the number of the stars; He calls them all by name.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Our Lord is great and has much strength; His understanding cannot be calculated.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">The Lord strengthens the humble; He humbles the wicked to the ground.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Shout to the Lord with thanks; sing praises to our God with a lyre.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Who covers the heavens with clouds, Who prepares rain for the earth, Who causes the mountains to sprout grass.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">He gives the animal its food, to the young ravens which call out.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">He does not desire the might of the horse, nor does He take pleasure in the legs of man.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">The Lord desires those who fear Him, those who hope for His kindness.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">O Jerusalem, praise the Lord; extol Your God, O Zion.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">For He strengthened the bars of your gates; He blessed your children within you.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Within your borders He makes peace; with the best of the wheat He will sate you.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">He sends His commandment to the earth; His word runs swiftly.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">He gives snow like wool; He scatters hoarfrost like ashes.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">He hurls His ice like crumbs; before His cold, who can stand?</pasuk><pasuk id="18">He sends His word and melts them; He blows His wind; water runs.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">He tells His words to Jacob, His statutes and His judgments to Israel.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">He did not do so to any nation, and they did not know the judgments. Hallelujah!</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="148"><pasuk id="1">Hallelujah! Praise the Lord from the heavens, praise Him in the heights.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Praise Him, all His angels; praise Him, all His hosts.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Praise Him, sun and moon; praise Him, all stars of the night.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Praise Him, highest heavens and the water that is above the heavens.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">They shall praise the name of the Lord, for He commanded and they were created.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">And He set them up to eternity, yea forever, He issued a decree, which will not change.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Praise the Lord from the earth, sea monsters and all deeps.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Fire and hail, snow and vapor, a storm wind, performing His word.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">The mountains and all the hills, fruit trees and all cedars.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Beasts and all cattle, creeping things and winged fowl.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Kings of the earth and all kingdoms, princes and all judges of the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Youths and also maidens, old men with young boys,</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Will praise the name of the Lord, for His name alone is powerful; His splendor is on earth and heaven.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">He raised up a horn for His people, praise to all His pious ones, to the children of Israel, the people close to Him. Hallelujah!</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="149"><pasuk id="1">Hallelujah! Sing to the Lord a new song; His praise is in the congregation of the pious.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Israel will rejoice with its Maker; the children of Zion will exult with their King.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">They will praise His name in dance; with timbrel and harp they will play music to Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">For the Lord takes delight in His people; He lauds the humble with salvation.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">The pious will exult in glory; they will sing praises on their beds.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Lofty praises of God in their throats and a double-edged sword in their hands,</pasuk><pasuk id="7">To wreak vengeance upon the nations, contentions upon the kingdoms.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">To bind their kings with chains and their nobles with fetters of iron.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">To execute upon them a written judgment; that will be splendor to all His pious ones. Hallelujah!</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="150"><pasuk id="1">Hallelujah! Praise God in His holy place, praise Him in the firmament of His might.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Praise Him with His mighty deeds, praise Him as befits His superb greatness.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Praise Him with a shofar blast, praise Him with psaltery and lyre.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Praise Him with timbres and dance, praise Him with stringed instruments and flute.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Praise Him with resounding cymbals, praise Him with resonant cymbals.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Let every soul praise God. Hallelujah!</pasuk></chapter></book>