<book><chapter id="1"><pasuk id="1">Now it came to pass in the days when the judges judged, that there was a famine in the land, and a man went from Bethlehem of Judah to sojourn in the fields of Moab, he and his wife and his two sons.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">And the man's name was Elimelech, and his wife's name was Naomi, and his two sons' names were Mahlon and Chilion, Ephrathites, from Bethlehem of Judah, and they came to the fields of Moab and remained there.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Now Elimelech, Naomi's husband, died, and she was left with her two sons.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">And they married Moabite women, one named Orpah, and the other named Ruth, and they dwelt there for about ten years.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">And both Mahlon and Chilion also died, and the woman was left [bereft] of her two children and of her husband.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Now she arose with her daughters-in-law and returned from the fields of Moab, for she had heard in the field of Moab that the Lord had remembered His people to give them bread.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Then she went forth from the place where she had been, and her two daughters-in-law with her, and they went on the road to return to the land of Judah.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">And Naomi said to her two daughters-in-law, "Go, return each woman to her mother's house. May the Lord deal kindly with you as you have dealt with the deceased and with me.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">May the Lord grant you that you find rest, each woman in her husband's house," and she kissed them, and they raised their voices and wept.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">And they said to her, "[No,] but we will return with you to your people."</pasuk><pasuk id="11">And Naomi said, "Return, my daughters; why should you go with me? Have I yet sons in my womb, that they should be your husbands?</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Return, my daughters, go, for I have become too old to marry, that I should say that I have hope. Even if I had a husband tonight, and even if I had borne sons,</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Would you wait for them until they grew up? Would you shut yourselves off for them and not marry? No, my daughters, for it is much more bitter for me than for you, for the hand of the Lord has gone forth against me."</pasuk><pasuk id="14">And they raised their voices and wept again; and Orpah kissed her mother-in-law, but Ruth cleaved to her.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">And she said, "Lo, your sister-in-law has returned to her people and to her god; return after your sister- in-law."</pasuk><pasuk id="16">And Ruth said, "Do not entreat me to leave you, to return from following you, for wherever you go, I will go, and wherever you lodge, I will lodge; your people shall be my people and your God my God.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Where you die, I will die, and there I will be buried. So may the Lord do to me and so may He continue, if anything but death separate me and you."</pasuk><pasuk id="18">And she saw that she was determined to go with her; so she stopped speaking to her.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">And they both went on until they arrived to Bethlehem. And it came to pass when they arrived to Bethlehem, that the entire city was astir on their account, and they said, "Is this Naomi?"</pasuk><pasuk id="20">And she said to them, "Do not call me Naomi; call me Marah, for the Almighty has dealt very bitterly with me.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">I went away full, and the Lord has brought me back empty. Why [then] should you call me Naomi, seeing that the Lord has testified against me, and the Almighty has dealt harshly with me?"</pasuk><pasuk id="22">So Naomi returned, and Ruth the Moabitess, her daughter-in- law, with her, who returned from the fields of Moab-and they came to Bethlehem at the beginning of the barley harvest.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="2"><pasuk id="1">Now Naomi had a kinsman of her husband, a mighty man of valor, of the family of Elimelech, and his name was Boaz.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">And Ruth the Moabitess said to Naomi, "I will go now to the field, and I will glean among the ears of grain, after someone whom I will please." And she said, "Go, my daughter."</pasuk><pasuk id="3">And she went, and she came, and she gleaned in the field after the reapers, and her chance was [to come to] the field that [belonged] to Boaz, who was of the family of Elimelech.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">And behold, Boaz came from Bethlehem, and he said to the reapers, "May the Lord be with you!" And they said to him, "The Lord bless you."</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Then Boaz said to his servant, who stood over the reapers, "To whom does this maiden belong?"</pasuk><pasuk id="6">And the servant in charge of the reapers answered and said, "She is a Moabite maiden who returned with Naomi from the fields of Moab.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">And she said, 'I will now glean and gather from among the sheaves after the reapers.' And she came and stood even from the morning until now, except when she sat a little in the house."</pasuk><pasuk id="8">And Boaz said to Ruth, "Have you not heard, my daughter? Do not go to glean in another field, neither shall you go away from here, and here you shall stay with my maidens.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Your eyes shall be on the field that they reap, and you shall follow them; have I not ordered the youths not to touch you? And [if] you are thirsty, you may go to the vessels and drink from that which the youths draw."</pasuk><pasuk id="10">And she fell on her face and prostrated herself to the ground, and she said to him, "Why have I pleased you that you should take cognizance of me, seeing that I am a foreigner?"</pasuk><pasuk id="11">And Boaz replied and said to her, "It has been told to me all that you did for your mother-in-law after your husband's death, and you left your father and your mother and your native land, and you went to a people that you did not know before.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">May the Lord reward your deeds, and may your reward be full from the Lord God of Israel, under Whose wings you have come to take shelter."</pasuk><pasuk id="13">And she said, "Let me find favor in your sight, my lord, for you have comforted me, and you have spoken to the heart of your handmaid, but I am not [as worthy] as one of your handmaids."</pasuk><pasuk id="14">And Boaz said to her at mealtime, "Come here and partake of the bread, and dip your morsel in the vinegar." So she sat down beside the reapers, and he handed her parched grain, and she ate and was sated and left over.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">And she rose to glean, and Boaz ordered his servants, saying, "Let her glean also among the sheaves, and do not embarrass her.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">And also, pretend to forget some of the bundles for her, and leave it that she may glean, and do not scold her."</pasuk><pasuk id="17">And she gleaned in the field until evening, and she beat out what she had gleaned, and it was about an ephah of barley.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">And she carried [it] and came to the city, and her mother-in-law saw what she had gleaned. And she took [it] out and gave her what she had left over after being sated.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">And her mother-in-law said to her, "Where have you gleaned today and where have you worked? May he who took heed of you be blessed." So she told her mother-in-law with whom she had worked, and she said, "The name of the man with whom I worked today is Boaz."</pasuk><pasuk id="20">And Naomi said to her daughter-in-law, "Blessed be he of the Lord, who did not leave off his kindness with the living or with the deceased." And Naomi said to her, "The man is our kinsman; he is one of our near kinsmen."</pasuk><pasuk id="21">And Ruth the Moabitess said, "He also said to me; You shall stay with my youths until they finish my entire harvest."</pasuk><pasuk id="22">And Naomi said to Ruth her daughter-in-law, "It is good, my daughter, that you go out with his maidens, so that they do not molest you in another field."</pasuk><pasuk id="23">And she stayed with Boaz's maidens to glean until the completion of the barley harvest and the wheat harvest, and she dwelt with her mother-in-law.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="3"><pasuk id="1">And Naomi her mother-in-law said to her, "My daughter, shall I not seek rest for you, that it be good for you?</pasuk><pasuk id="2">And now, is not Boaz our kinsman, with whose maidens you were? Behold, he is winnowing the threshing-floor of the barley tonight.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">And you shall bathe and anoint yourself and put on your clothes and go down to the threshing-floor; do not make yourself known to the man until he has finished eating and drinking.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">And it shall be when he lies down, that you shall know where he will lie, and you shall come and uncover his feet and lie down, and he will tell you what you shall do. "</pasuk><pasuk id="5">And she said to her, "All that you say to me I will do."</pasuk><pasuk id="6">And she went down to the threshing-floor, and she did all that her mother-in-law had charged her.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">And Boaz ate and drank, and his heart was merry, and he went to lie at the edge of the stack, and she came softly and uncovered his feet and lay down.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">And it came to pass at midnight, and the man quaked and was taken around, and behold a woman was lying at his feet.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">And he said, "Who are you? " And she said, "I am Ruth, your handmaid, and you shall spread your skirt over your handmaid, for you are a near kinsman."</pasuk><pasuk id="10">And he said, "May you be blessed of the Lord, my daughter; your latest act of kindness is greater than the first, not to follow the young men, whether poor or rich.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">And now, my daughter, do not fear, all that you say I will do for you, for the entire gate of my people know that you are a valiant woman.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">And now, indeed, I am a near kinsman, but there is a kinsman closer than I.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Stay over tonight, and it will come to pass in the morning, that if he redeem you, well, let him redeem you, but if he does not wish to redeem you, I will redeem you, as the Lord lives; lie down until morning."</pasuk><pasuk id="14">And she lay at his feet until morning, and she rose before one could recognize his fellow, for he said, "Let it not be known that the woman came to the threshing-floor."</pasuk><pasuk id="15">And he said, "Ready the shawl you are wearing and hold it," and she held it, and he measured out six barleys and placed [them] upon her, and he came to the city.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">And she came to her mother-in-law, and she said, "Who are you, my daughter?" And she told her all that the man had done to her.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">And she said, "He gave me these six barleys, for he said to me: Do not come empty-handed to your mother-in-law."</pasuk><pasuk id="18">And she said, "Sit still, my daughter, until you know how the matter will fall, for the man will not rest until he has resolved the matter today."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="4"><pasuk id="1">And Boaz went up to the gate and sat down there, and behold, the kinsman of whom Boaz had spoken was passing, and he said, "Turn aside, sit down here, So-and-So," and he turned aside and sat down.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">And he took ten men of the elders of the city and said, "Sit down here," and they sat down.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">And he said to the near kinsman, "Naomi, who has returned from the field of Moab, is selling the portion of the field that belonged to our brother, to Elimelech.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">And I said, 'I will let you know, saying: Buy [it] in the presence of those who sit here and before the elders of my people; if you will redeem, redeem; and if he will not redeem, tell me, and I will know, for there is no one besides you to redeem, and I am after you.'" And he said, "I will redeem."</pasuk><pasuk id="5">And Boaz said, "On the day that you buy the field from the hand of Naomi and from Ruth the Moabitess, the wife of the deceased, you have bought [it], to preserve the name of the deceased on his heritage."</pasuk><pasuk id="6">And the near kinsman said, "I cannot redeem [it] for myself, lest I mar my heritage. You redeem my redemption for yourself for I cannot redeem [it]."</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Now this was the custom in former times in Israel concerning redemption and exchange, to confirm anything, one would remove his shoe and give [it] to his fellow, and this was the attestation in Israel.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">And the near kinsman said to Boaz, "Buy it for yourself," and he removed his shoe.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">And Boaz said to the elders and to the entire people, "You are witnesses today that I have bought all that was Elimelech's and all that was Chilion's and Mahlon's from Naomi.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">And also, Ruth the Moabitess, Mahlon's wife, have I acquired for myself for a wife, to preserve the name of the deceased on his heritage, so that the name of the deceased not be obliterated from his brethren and from the gate of his place, you are witnesses today."</pasuk><pasuk id="11">And all the people who were in the gate and the elders replied, "[We are] witnesses! May the Lord make the woman who is entering your house like Rachel and like Leah, both of whom built up the house of Israel, and prosper in Ephrathah and be famous in Bethlehem.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">And may your house be like the house of Perez, whom Tamar bore to Judah, with the seed that the Lord will give you from this maiden."</pasuk><pasuk id="13">And Boaz took Ruth, and she became his wife, and he was intimate with her, and the Lord gave her conception, and she bore a son.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">And the women said to Naomi, "Blessed is the Lord, Who did not deprive you of a redeemer today, and may his name be famous in Israel.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">And may he be to you a restorer of life and to sustain your old age, for your daughter-in-law, who loves you, bore him, and she is better to you than seven sons."</pasuk><pasuk id="16">And Naomi took the child and placed him in her bosom, and she became his nurse.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">And the women neighbors gave him a name, saying, "A son has been born to Naomi," and they called his name Obed-he is the father of Jesse, the father of David.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">And these are the generations of Perez: Perez begot Hezron.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">And Hezron begot Ram, and Ram begot Amminadab.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">And Amminadab begot Nahshon, and Nahshon begot Salmah.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">And Salmah begot Boaz, and Boaz begot Obed.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">And Obed begot Jesse, and Jesse begot David.</pasuk></chapter></book>