<book><chapter id="1"><pasuk id="1">In the second year of King Darius, in the sixth month, on the first day of the month, the word of the Lord came to Haggai, the prophet to Zerubbabel son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua son of Jehozadak the High Priest, saying:</pasuk><pasuk id="2">So said the Lord of Hosts, saying: This people has said, "The time has not come-the time for the house of the Lord to be built."</pasuk><pasuk id="3">And the word of the Lord came through Haggai the prophet, saying:</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Is it [an appropriate] time for you yourselves to sit in your ceiled houses, when this house is in ruins?</pasuk><pasuk id="5">And now, so said the Lord of Hosts: Consider your ways.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">You have sown much and you bring in little. You eat without being satiated. You drink without getting your fill. You dress, and it has no warmth. And he who profits, profits into a bundle with holes.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">So said the Lord of Hosts: Consider your ways.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Ascend the mountain, bring wood, and build the house-and I will accept it, and I will be honored, said the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">You looked for much, and behold, it became little. And you brought it home, and I will blow into it. Because of what? says the Lord of Hosts, Because of My house that is lying in ruins. Yet you run, each to his house.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Therefore because of you the heavens have kept back, so that there is no dew, and the earth has kept back its produce.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">And I called for a drought upon the land, and upon the mountains, and upon the grain, and upon the wine, and upon the oil, and upon everything that the ground will bring forth-and upon man, and upon beast, and upon all the labor of their hands.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">And Zerubbabel the son of Shaltiel, and Joshua the son of Jehozadak the High Priest, and all the remnant of the people heeded the command of the Lord their God and the words of Haggai the prophet, as the Lord their God had sent him, and the people feared the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">And Haggai, the messenger of the Lord, said in [fulfilling] the Lord's mission to the people, saying: I am with you, says the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">And the Lord inspired the spirit of Zerubbabel the son of Shaltiel, the governor of Judah, and the spirit of Joshua the son of Jehozadak the High Priest, and the spirit of all the remnant of the people, and they came and performed labor in the house of the Lord of Hosts, their God</pasuk><pasuk id="15">on the twenty-fourth day of the month, in the sixth [month], in the second year of King Darius.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="2"><pasuk id="1">In the seventh [month], on the twenty-first of the month, the word of the Lord came through Haggai the prophet, saying:</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Say now to Zerubbabel the son of Shaltiel, the governor of Judah, and to Joshua the son of Jehozadak the High Priest, and to the remnant of the people, saying:</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Who among you is left, who saw this house in its former glory? And as you see it now, is it not as nothing in your eyes?</pasuk><pasuk id="4">And now, be strong, Zerubbabel, says the Lord; and be strong, Joshua the son of Jehozadak the High Priest; and be strong, all the people of the land, says the Lord. And (for I am with you, says the Lord of Hosts) do</pasuk><pasuk id="5">the thing that I set up with you when you left Egypt. And My spirit stands in your midst; fear not.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">For so said the Lord of Hosts: [There will rise] another one, and I will shake up the heaven and the earth and the sea and the dry land [for] a little while.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">And I will shake up all the nations, and they shall come [with] the precious things of all the nations. And I will fill this House with glory, said the Lord of Hosts.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">The silver is Mine, and the gold is Mine, says the Lord of Hosts.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">The glory of this last House shall be greater than the first one, said the Lord of Hosts. And in this place I will grant peace, says the Lord of Hosts.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">On the twenty-fourth [day] of the ninth [month], in the second year of Darius, the word of the Lord came to Haggai the prophet, saying:</pasuk><pasuk id="11">So said the Lord of Hosts: Now ask the priests the Torah, saying:</pasuk><pasuk id="12">"Should a man carry contaminated flesh in the skirt of his garment, if it touches in his skirt the bread and the pottage and the wine and the oil, or any food, will it [the food] become contaminated?" And the priests replied and said, "No."</pasuk><pasuk id="13">And Haggai said, "If the contamination of a dead body touches all these, will it become contaminated?" And the priests replied and said, "It will become contaminated."</pasuk><pasuk id="14">And Haggai replied and said, "So is this people, and so is this nation before Me, says the Lord; and so is all the work of their hands, and whatever they sacrifice there is contaminated.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">And now, consider from this day and before-before placing a stone upon a stone in the Temple of the Lord</pasuk><pasuk id="16">so that they should not come to a heap of twenty measures, and there would be ten; [similarly,] when one would come to the winevat to draw off fifty press-measures, and there would be twenty.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">I smote you with blast and with yellowing and with hail in all the work of your hands, and you are not [returning] to Me, says the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Pay attention now, from this day and before-from the twenty-fourth [day] of the ninth [month]- from the day that the Temple of the Lord was founded, pay attention.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">The seed is still in the granary, and the grapevines, the fig trees, the pomegranate trees, and the olive trees have not yet borne [fruit]-from this day I will bless."</pasuk><pasuk id="20">And the word of the Lord came to Haggai a second time on the twenty-fourth of the month, saying:</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Say to Zerubbabel, the governor of Judah, saying: I am shaking up the heaven and the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">And I will overthrow the throne of the kingdoms, and I will destroy the power of the kingdoms of the nations. And I will overthrow the chariots and their riders; and the horses and their riders shall come down, each one by the sword of his brother.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">On that day, says the Lord of Hosts, I will take you, O Zerubbabel the son of Shealtiel, My servant; says the Lord, and I will make you as a signet; for I have chosen you, says the Lord of Hosts.</pasuk></chapter></book>