<book><chapter id="1"><pasuk id="1">The proverbs of Solomon the son of David, king of Israel, [are];</pasuk><pasuk id="2">To know wisdom and discipline, to comprehend words of understanding;</pasuk><pasuk id="3">To receive the discipline of wisdom, righteousness, justice, and equity;</pasuk><pasuk id="4">To give prudence to the simple, knowledge and discretion to the youth.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Let the wise man hear and increase learning. The understanding man shall acquire wise counsels</pasuk><pasuk id="6">to understand an allegory and a figure, the words of the wise and their riddles.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The fear of the Lord is the beginning of knowledge; fools despise wisdom and discipline.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Hearken, my son, to the discipline of your father, and do not forsake the instruction of your mother;</pasuk><pasuk id="9">for they are a wreath of grace for your head and a necklace for your neck.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">My son, if sinners entice you, do not consent;</pasuk><pasuk id="11">if they say, "Come with us; let us lie in wait for blood; let us hide for the innocent, without cause;</pasuk><pasuk id="12">let us swallow them up alive like the grave, and the whole ones like those who descend into the pit.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">We will find all precious possessions; we will fill our houses with plunder.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Cast your lot among us; we will all have one purse"</pasuk><pasuk id="15">my son, do not go on the way with them; restrain your foot from their path,</pasuk><pasuk id="16">for their feet run to evil, and they hasten to shed blood.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">For the net is scattered without cause in the eyes of all winged fowl,</pasuk><pasuk id="18">but they lie in wait for their blood; they hide for their lives.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">So are the ways of everyone who commits robbery; it will take away the life of its owner.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Wisdoms shout in the street; in the squares she gives forth her voice.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">She calls at the head of the noisy streets; she utters her words at the entrances of the gates in the city;</pasuk><pasuk id="22">"How long will you naive ones love naivete, and the scoffers covet scoffing, and the fools hate knowledge?</pasuk><pasuk id="23">You shall repent because of my reproof; behold! I will pour out my spirit to you; I will let you know my words.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">Since I called you and you refused, I stretched out my hand and no one listened,</pasuk><pasuk id="25">and you have made nothing of all my advice, and you did not desire my reproof</pasuk><pasuk id="26">I, too, will laugh at your calamity, I will scoff when what you fear comes;</pasuk><pasuk id="27">when your fear comes like a storm, and your calamity comes like a whirlwind; when trouble and straits come upon you.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">Then they will call me, and I will not answer; they shall seek me, and they shall not find me.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">Because they hated knowledge, and did not choose the fear of the Lord;</pasuk><pasuk id="30">they did not desire my advice, they despised all my reproof-</pasuk><pasuk id="31">they will eat of the fruit of their way, and from their counsels they will be sated,</pasuk><pasuk id="32">for the backsliding of the naive shall slay them, and the tranquility of the fools shall cause them to perish.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">But he who hearkens to me shall dwell confidently and shall be tranquil from the fear of harm."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="2"><pasuk id="1">My son, if you accept my words, and treasure my commandments,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">to make your ear attentive to wisdom, [if] you incline your heart to discernment;</pasuk><pasuk id="3">for, if you call for understanding [and] raise your voice for discernment,</pasuk><pasuk id="4">if you seek it like silver, and hunt for it like treasures,</pasuk><pasuk id="5">then you will understand the fear of the Lord, and you will find the knowledge of God.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">For the Lord gives wisdom; from His mouth [come] knowledge and discernment.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">He lays up sound wisdom for the upright, a shield for those who walk in integrity;</pasuk><pasuk id="8">to keep the paths of justice, and watch the way of His pious.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Then you shall understand righteousness, justice, and equity, every good path.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">When wisdom comes into your heart, and knowledge shall be pleasant to your soul,</pasuk><pasuk id="11">thought shall watch over you; discretion shall guard you,</pasuk><pasuk id="12">to save you from an evil way. From a man who speaks perversity;</pasuk><pasuk id="13">[from] those who forsake the ways of uprightness, to go on ways of darkness;</pasuk><pasuk id="14">[from] those who rejoice to do evil, and delight in the perversity of evil,</pasuk><pasuk id="15">who are crooked in their ways and perverse in their paths.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">To save you from a strange woman, from a foreign one who makes her words smooth,</pasuk><pasuk id="17">who deserts the lord of her youth and forgets the covenant of her God</pasuk><pasuk id="18">for her house sinks to death, and her paths [lead] to the dead;</pasuk><pasuk id="19">none who go to her return, neither do they achieve the ways of life</pasuk><pasuk id="20">in order that you go in the way of the good, and you keep the ways of the righteous.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">For the upright shall dwell in the land, and the perfect shall remain therein.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">But the wicked shall be cut off from the land, and the treacherous shall be uprooted therefrom.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="3"><pasuk id="1">My son, forget not My instruction, and may your heart keep My commandments;</pasuk><pasuk id="2">for they shall add length of days and years of life and peace to you.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Kindness and truth shall not leave you; bind them upon your neck, inscribe them upon the tablet of your heart;</pasuk><pasuk id="4">and find favor and good understanding in the sight of God and man.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Trust in the Lord with all your heart and do not rely upon your understanding.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Know Him in all your ways, and He will direct your paths.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Do not be wise in your own sight; fear the Lord and turn away from evil</pasuk><pasuk id="8">it shall be healing for your navel and marrow for your bones.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Honor the Lord from your substance and from the first of all your grain,</pasuk><pasuk id="10">and your barns shall be filled with plenty, and your vats will overflow with new wine.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">My son, despise not the discipline of the Lord, and do not abhor His chastening,</pasuk><pasuk id="12">for the Lord chastens the one He loves, as a father placates a son.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Fortunate is the man who has found wisdom and a man who gives forth discernment,</pasuk><pasuk id="14">for its commerce is better than the commerce of silver, and its gain [is better] than fine gold;</pasuk><pasuk id="15">it is more precious than pearls, and all your desirable things cannot be compared to it.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Length of days is in its right hand; in its left hand are riches and honor.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Its ways are ways of pleasantness, and all its paths are peace.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">It is a tree of life for those who grasp it, and those who draw near it are fortunate.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">The Lord founded the earth with wisdom, established the heavens with discernment.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">With His knowledge the depths were split, and the heavens drip dew.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">My son, let them not depart from your eyes; guard sound wisdom and thought,</pasuk><pasuk id="22">and they shall be life for your soul, and grace for your neck.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Then you shall go securely on your way, and your foot shall not stumble.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">If you lie down, you shall not fear, and when you lie down, your sleep shall be sweet.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">Be not afraid of sudden terror, or of the darkness of the wicked when it will come.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">For the Lord shall be your trust, and He shall keep your foot from being caught.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">Do not withhold good from the one who needs it when you have power in your hand to do it.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">Do not say to your fellow, "Go and return, and tomorrow I will give," though you have it with you.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">Devise no harm against your fellow, when he dwells securely with you.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">Do not quarrel with anyone without cause, if he did you no harm.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">Do not envy a man of violence and do not choose any of his ways;</pasuk><pasuk id="32">for the perverse is an abomination to the Lord, but His counsel is with the upright.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">The curse of the Lord is in the wicked man's house, but He shall bless the dwelling of the righteous.</pasuk><pasuk id="34">If [one goes] to the scoffers, he will scoff; but [if he goes] to the humble, he evokes grace.</pasuk><pasuk id="35">The wise shall inherit honor, but the fools take disgrace as their portion.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="4"><pasuk id="1">Children, hearken to the discipline of the Father, and listen to know understanding.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">For I gave you good teaching; forsake not My instruction.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">For I was a son to my father, a tender one and an only one before my mother.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">And he instructed me and said to me, "May your heart draw near to my words; keep my commandments and live.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Acquire wisdom, acquire understanding; do not forget, and do not turn away from the words of my mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Do not forsake her, and she will preserve you; love her and she will guard you.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The beginning of wisdom [is to] acquire wisdom, and with all your possession acquire understanding.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Search for her, and she will exalt you; she will honor you when you embrace her.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">She will give your head a wreath of grace; she will transmit to you a crown of glory.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Hearken, my son, and take my words, and years of life will increase for you.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">In the way of wisdom I instructed you; I led you in the paths of uprightness.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">When you walk, your step will not be straitened, and if you run, you will not stumble.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Take fast hold of discipline, do not let it loose; guard it, for it is your life.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">You shall not come in the way of the wicked, and do not walk in the way of the evil.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Avoid it, do not pass through it; turn away from it and pass.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">For they will not sleep if they do not commit evil, and their sleep will be robbed away if they do not cause stumbling.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">For they eat the bread of wickedness, and they drink the wine of violence.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">But the way of the righteous is like the light of dawn; it shines ever brighter until the day is perfect.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">The way of the wicked is like pitch darkness; they do not know on what they stumble.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">My son, hearken to my words; incline your ear to my sayings.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Let them not depart from your eyes; guard them within your heart,</pasuk><pasuk id="22">for they are life for those who find them, and for all his flesh a healing.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">From every interdict guard your heart, for the issues of life [come] out of it.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">Take crooked speech away from yourself, and put devious lips far away from you.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">Let your eyes look forward, and let your eyelids look straight ahead of you.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">Weigh the path of your feet, and all your ways will be established.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">Turn neither right nor left; keep your feet from evil.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="5"><pasuk id="1">My son, hearken to my wisdom; incline your ear to my understanding,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">to watch [your] thoughts, and your lips shall guard knowledge.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">For the lips of a strange woman drip honey, and her palate is smoother than oil.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">But her end is as bitter as wormwood, as sharp as a two-edged sword.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Her feet descend to death; her steps come near the grave.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Lest you weigh the path of life, her paths have wandered off and you shall not know.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">And now, children, hearken to me and do not turn away from the sayings of my mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Distance your way from her and do not draw near to the entrance of her house,</pasuk><pasuk id="9">lest you give others your glory, and your years to a cruel one;</pasuk><pasuk id="10">lest strangers be sated with your strength and your labors be in the house of an alien.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">And you shall moan when your end comes, when your flesh and your body are consumed,</pasuk><pasuk id="12">and you will say, "How [is it that] I hated discipline, and my heart despised reproof;</pasuk><pasuk id="13">and I did not hearken to my instructors, and to my teachers I did not incline my ear?</pasuk><pasuk id="14">I was almost in all evil, in the midst of the congregation and the assembly."</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Drink water from your own cistern and running water from your own spring.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">May your springs spread out rivulets of water in the squares.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">You alone shall have them, and strangers shall have nothing with you.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Your fountain shall be blessed, and you shall rejoice with the wife of your youth;</pasuk><pasuk id="19">a lovely hind and a graceful mountain goat, her breasts will satisfy you at all times; you shall always be intoxicated with her love.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Now why should you, my son, be intoxicated by a strange woman, and embrace the bosom of an alien one?</pasuk><pasuk id="21">For man's ways are opposite the Lord's eyes, and He weighs all his paths.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">His iniquities shall trap the wicked man, and he shall be hanged with the ropes of his sin.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">He shall die without discipline, and he shall err with his exceeding foolishness.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="6"><pasuk id="1">My son, if you have stood surety for your fellow, have given your hand for a stranger,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">you have been trapped by the sayings of your mouth; you have been caught by the sayings of your mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Do this then, my son, and be saved for you have come into your fellow's palm; go, humble yourself and give your fellow superiority.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Give no sleep to your eyes nor slumber to your eyelids.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Save yourself like a deer from the hand and like a bird from the hand of the snare.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Go to the ant, you sluggard; see her ways and become wise,</pasuk><pasuk id="7">for she has no chief, overseer, or ruler;</pasuk><pasuk id="8">yet she prepares her bread in the summer; she gathers her food in the harvest.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">O lazy one, how long will you lie [there]; when will you get up from your sleep?</pasuk><pasuk id="10">"A little sleep, a little slumber, a little folding of the hands to lie."</pasuk><pasuk id="11">And your poverty shall come like a fast walker and your want as an armed man.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">An unscrupulous man, a man of violence, walks with a crooked mouth;</pasuk><pasuk id="13">he winks with his eyes, shuffles with his feet, points with his fingers.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Contrariness is in his heart; he plots evil at all times; he incites quarrels.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Therefore, calamity shall come suddenly; he shall suddenly be broken beyond repair.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">There are six things that the Lord hates, and the seventh is an abomination of His soul;</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Haughty eyes, a lying tongue, and hands that shed innocent blood;</pasuk><pasuk id="18">a heart that thinks thoughts of violence; feet that hasten to run to evil;</pasuk><pasuk id="19">[one who] speaks lies with false testimony and incites quarrels among brothers.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">My son, keep the commands of your father, and do not forsake the instruction of your mother.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Bind them always upon your heart, tie them upon your neck.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">When you walk, it shall lead you; when you lie down, it shall guard you, and when you awaken, it shall speak for you.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">For a commandment is a candle, and the Torah is light, and disciplining rebukes are the way of life;</pasuk><pasuk id="24">to guard you from an evil woman, from the smoothness of the alien tongue.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">Do not covet her beauty in your heart, and do not let her captivate you with her eyelids.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">Because a man is brought to a loaf of bread for a harlot, and a married woman will hunt a precious soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">Can a man rake embers with his skirt without burning his clothes?</pasuk><pasuk id="28">Or can a man walk on live coals without scorching his feet?</pasuk><pasuk id="29">So is he who goes in to his neighbor's wife; no one who touches her will go unpunished.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">They will not despise a thief if he steals to sate his appetite, for he is hungry.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">And if he is found, he will pay sevenfold; he must give all he owns.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">One who commits adultery with a woman is devoid of sense; one who would destroy his soul-he will do it.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">He will find wounds and disgrace, and his reproach shall not be erased</pasuk><pasuk id="34">for jealousy [shall arouse] the husband's wrath, and he will not have pity on the day of vengeance.</pasuk><pasuk id="35">He will not have regard for any ransom, neither will he consent though you give him many bribes.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="7"><pasuk id="1">My son, keep my sayings, and hide my commandments with you.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Keep my commandments and live, and my instruction like the apple of your eyes.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Bind them on your fingers; inscribe them on the tablet of your heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Say to wisdom, "You are my sister," and you shall call understanding a kinsman;</pasuk><pasuk id="5">to guard you from a strange woman, from an alien woman who talks smoothly.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">For from the window of my house, through my lattice I gazed,</pasuk><pasuk id="7">and I saw among the simple-I discerned among the youths-a lad devoid of sense,</pasuk><pasuk id="8">crossing the street next to her corner, and he walks on the way to her house.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">In the twilight, in the evening of the day, in the pitch darkness of the night.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">And behold a woman [was coming] toward him, the nakedness of a harlot with her heart besieged.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">She is bustling and rebellious; her feet do not dwell in her house.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Sometimes [she is] in the street, sometimes in the squares, and she lurks at every corner.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">She takes hold of him and kisses him; brazenly she says to him,</pasuk><pasuk id="14">"I had to bring peace-offerings; today I paid my vows.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Therefore, I have come out toward you to look for you, and I have found you.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">I have bedecked my couch with covers, with superior braided work of Egypt.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">I fanned my couch with myrrh, aloes, and cinnamon.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Come, let us take our fill of lovemaking until morning; let us enjoy ourselves with amorous embraces.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">For the man is not at home; he has gone on a long journey.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">He has taken the bag of money with him; on the appointed day he will come home."</pasuk><pasuk id="21">She swayed him with all her talk; with the smooth talk of her lips she entices him.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">He follows her immediately-as an ox goes to the slaughter, and as a viper to the chastisement of a fool</pasuk><pasuk id="23">until an arrow splits his liver, as a bird hastens to a snare, and he does not know that it is at the cost of his life.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">And now, children, hearken to me, and listen to the sayings of my mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">Let your heart not veer off into her ways; stray not in her paths.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">For many are the dead that she has felled, and numerous are all her victims.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">The ways of the grave are to her house, descending to the chambers of death.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="8"><pasuk id="1">Will not wisdom call out, and understanding give forth its voice?</pasuk><pasuk id="2">At the top of the heights upon the road; at the crossroads she stands.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Beside the gates, at the entrance of the roof, at the entrance of the portals she cries,</pasuk><pasuk id="4">"To you, O men, I call, and my voice [is] to the children of man.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">O simpletons, understand cunning, and you fools, give understanding to your heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Hearken for I will speak noble things, and the opening of my lips shall be right things.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">For my palate shall utter truth, and wickedness is an abomination of my lips.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">All the sayings of my lips are with righteousness; there is nothing twisted or crooked in them.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">They are all true to the understanding one, and straight to those who find knowledge.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Take my discipline and not silver; knowledge is chosen above gold.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">For wisdom is better than pearls; all desirable things cannot be compared to it.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">I am wisdom; I dwelt [beside] cunning, and the knowledge of devices I will find.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Fear of the Lord is to hate evil, haughtiness, pride, the way of evil, and a perverse mouth; [these] I hate.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">I have counsel and sound wisdom; I am understanding; I have might.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Kings reign with me, and rulers legislate righteousness.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Through me princes govern, and nobles, yea, all judges of righteousness.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">I will love those who love me, and those who seek me eagerly will find me.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Riches and honor are with me, powerful wealth and charity.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">My fruit is better than gold-yea than fine gold- and my produce [is better] than choice silver.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">In the way of righteousness I will go, in the midst of the paths of justice.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">There is substance to give inheritance to those who love me, and I will fill their treasuries.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">The Lord acquired me at the beginning of His way, before His works of old.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">From the distant past I was enthroned, from the beginning, of those that preceded the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">I was created when there were yet no deeps, when there were no fountains replete with water.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">I was created before the mountains were sunk, before the hills;</pasuk><pasuk id="26">when He had not yet made the land and the outsides and the beginning of the dust of the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">When He established the heavens, there I was, when He drew a circle over the face of the deep;</pasuk><pasuk id="28">when He made the skies above firm, when He strengthened the fountains of the deep;</pasuk><pasuk id="29">when He gave the sea its boundary, and the water shall not transgress His command, when He established the foundations of the earth</pasuk><pasuk id="30">I was a nursling beside Him, and I was [His] delight every day, playing before Him at all times;</pasuk><pasuk id="31">playing in the habitable world of His earth, and [having] my delights with the children of man.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">And now, my children, hearken to me, and fortunate are those who observe my ways.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">Hearken to discipline and become wise, and do not put it to naught.</pasuk><pasuk id="34">Fortunate is the man who listens to me to watch by my doors day by day, to watch the doorposts of my entrances.</pasuk><pasuk id="35">For he who has found me has found life, and he has obtained favor from the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="36">But he who sins against me robs his soul; all who hate me, love death."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="9"><pasuk id="1">Wisdom has built her house; she has hewn her seven pillars.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">She has prepared her meat; she has mingled her wine; she has even set her table.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">She has sent her maidens, she calls on the wings of the heights of the city,</pasuk><pasuk id="4">"Whoever is simple, let him turn in here." To the one devoid of sense, she says to him,</pasuk><pasuk id="5">"Come, partake of my bread and drink of the wine I have mingled.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Leave, you simpletons, and live, and step in the way of understanding."</pasuk><pasuk id="7">He who chastens a scorner takes disgrace for himself, and he who reproves a wicked man, that is his blemish.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Reprove not a scorner lest he hate you; reprove a wise man and he will love you.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Give a wise man, and he will become yet wiser; teach a righteous man, and he will increase in learning.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">The beginning of wisdom is the fear of the Lord, and the knowledge of the holy ones is understanding.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">For with me shall your days increase, and they will add to you years of life.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">If you have become wise, you have become wise for yourself, and if you scorn, you will bear it alone.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">The woman of folly is turbulent; [she is] simple and knows nothing.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">She sits at the entrance of her house on a chair on the heights of the city,</pasuk><pasuk id="15">to call the passersby, who are going straight on their ways,</pasuk><pasuk id="16">"Whoever is simple, let him turn in here, and whoever is devoid of sense," and she says to him,</pasuk><pasuk id="17">"Stolen water is sweet, and bread eaten in secret is pleasant."</pasuk><pasuk id="18">But he does not know that shades are there; her guests are in the depths of the grave.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="10"><pasuk id="1">Proverbs of Solomon: A wise son makes his father happy, but a foolish son is the grief of his mother.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Treasures of wickedness will not avail, but charity will save from death.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">The Lord will not starve the soul of the righteous, but the destruction [wrought by] the wicked will cast [them] down.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">A poor man makes a deceitful scale, and the hand of those who make true decisions will make [them] rich.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">An intelligent son gathers in the summer, whereas an embarrassing son sleeps soundly during the harvest.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Blessings [shall come] upon the head of a righteous man, but violence shall cover the mouth of the wicked.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The mention of a righteous man is for a blessing, but the name of the wicked shall rot.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">The wise-hearted takes commandments, but he who talks foolishly will weary.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">He who walks in innocence walks securely, but he who perverts his ways will be broken.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">He who winks his eye causes grief, and he who talks foolishly will weary.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">The mouth of the righteous is a fountain of life, but the mouth of the wicked conceals violence.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Hatred arouses quarrels, but love covers all transgressions.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Wisdom is found in the lips of the understanding, but a rod is for the body of one devoid of sense.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Wise men store up knowledge, but the mouth of a fool [causes] destruction to come near.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">The wealth of the rich is the city of his strength; the destruction of the poor is their poverty.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">The act of the righteous is for life; what the wicked bring in is for sin.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">The way to life is if one keeps discipline, but he who forsakes reproof misleads.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">He who covers up hatred has false lips, and he who spreads slander is a fool.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">In a multitude of words, transgression will not be avoided, and he who holds back his lips is wise.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">The tongue of the righteous is choice silver; the heart of the wicked is worth little.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">The lips of the righteous will feed many, but the fools will die for lack of sense.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">The blessing of the Lord will bring riches, and toil will add nothing to it.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">As it is sport for a fool to carry out a sinful plot, [so is] wisdom for a man of understanding.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">The dread of a wicked man-that will befall him, but the desire of the righteous He will grant.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">When the whirlwind passes, the wicked man is no more, but the righteous is the foundation of the world.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">Like vinegar to the teeth and like smoke to the eyes, so is the sluggard to those who send him.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">Fear of the Lord will add days, but the years of the wicked will be shortened.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">The expectation of the righteous [will result in] joy, but the hope of the wicked shall be lost.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">The way of the Lord is a stronghold for the innocent, but ruin for those who work iniquity.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">The righteous will not collapse forever, but the wicked shall not dwell in the land.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">The mouth of a righteous man speaks wisdom, but a perverse tongue shall be cut off.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">The lips of a righteous man know how to please, but the mouth of the wicked [knows] how to distort.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="11"><pasuk id="1">Deceitful scales are an abomination of the Lord, but a perfect weight is His will.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">When willful wickedness comes, then comes disgrace, but with the modest is wisdom.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">The innocence of the upright leads them, but the distortion of the treacherous robs them.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Riches will not avail on the day of wrath, but charity will save from death.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">The righteousness of the innocent will straighten his way, but the wicked will fall in his wickedness.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">The righteousness of the upright will save them, but in the destruction, the treacherous will be caught.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">When a wicked man dies, hope is lost, and the expectation of his children is lost.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">A righteous man is extricated from trouble, and a wicked man comes in his stead.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">With his mouth, the flatterer destroys his neighbor; but with knowledge, righteous men are extricated.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">When it goes well with the righteous, the city rejoices, and when the wicked perish, there is song.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">With the blessing of the upright, the ceiling is raised, but with the mouth of the wicked it is demolished.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">He who despises his neighbor is devoid of sense, but a man of understanding is silent.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">He who reveals secrets is a talebearer, but one who is of faithful spirit conceals a matter.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Without strategy the people falls, but with many counselors there is victory.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">He who gives surety for a stranger will be broken by it, but he who hates hand-claspers [for surety] is secure.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">A charming woman draws near to honor, but strong men draw near to riches.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">A kind man does himself good, but a cruel one troubles his own flesh.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">A wicked man earns illusory wages, but he who sows charity [receives] a true reward.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">The truth of charity is for life, but one who pursues evil [leads] to his death.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Those who are perverse in heart are an abomination of the Lord, but He desires those who are sincere in their way.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">From hand to hand the evil will not be cleansed, but the seed of the righteous escapes.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">[As] a gold ring in a swine's snout, is a beautiful woman from whom sense has departed.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">The desire of the righteous is only good; the hope of the wicked is wrath.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">There is one who scatters and yet is given more, and one who withholds from [giving] what is proper, only for a loss.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">A generous person will become rich, and he who sates [others] shall himself become sated as well.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">He who keeps back grain-the nation will curse him, but a blessing will be bestowed on the head of him who sells grain.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">He who desires good seeks acceptance, but he who seeks evil, it will befall him.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">He who relies on his wealth will fall, but the righteous will flourish like a leaf.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">He who inherits the wind will trouble his household; the fool is a slave to the wisehearted.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">The fruit of a righteous man is the tree of life, and the wise man acquires souls.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">Behold! The righteous man will be requited on earth; surely a wicked man and a sinner.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="12"><pasuk id="1">He who loves discipline loves knowledge, but he who hates reproof is brutish.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">A good man will obtain favor of the Lord, but a man of evil devices will condemn.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">A man will not be established with wickedness; but the root of the righteous will not be shaken loose.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">A virtuous woman is the crown of her husband, but an embarrassing one is like rot in his bones.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">The thoughts of the righteous are justice; the devices of the wicked are deceit.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">The words of the wicked are to lurk for blood, but the mouth of the upright will save them.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The wicked will be overthrown and they are no more, but the house of the righteous will stand.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">According to his intelligence a man is praised, but he whose heart has turned away will be despised.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Better is he who is lightly esteemed but is a slave to himself than one who is honored but lacks bread.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">A righteous man has regard for the desire of his beast, but the mercy of the wicked is cruel.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">He who tills his soil will be sated with bread, but he who pursues empty things is devoid of sense.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">The wicked man yearns for the prey of evil men, but the root of the righteous yields [fruit].</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Because of the trangression of the lips there is an evil snare, but the righteous comes out of trouble.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">From the fruit of a man's mouth he will be sated with good, and He will return the reward of a man's hands to him.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">A fool's way is straight in his eyes, but he who listens to advice is a wise man.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">A fool's anger is known within the day, but a clever man conceals his shame.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">He who speaks the truth will testify justly, but a deceitful person will be a false witness.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">There is one who speaks like the jabs of a sword, but the tongue of the wise brings healing.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">A true tongue will be established forever, but a lying tongue, just for a moment.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">There is deceit in the heart of those who plot evil, but for the counselors of peace there is joy.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">No wrong shall be caused for the righteous, but the wicked are full of evil.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">False lips are an abomination of the Lord, but those who work faithfully are His delight.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">A cunning man conceals knowledge, but the heart of the fools calls out foolishness.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">The hand of the diligent will rule, but deceit will lead to payment of tribute.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">If there is concern in a man's heart, let him cast it down, and a good word will make it cheerful.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">The righteous is more generous than his neighbor, and the way of the wicked will lead them astray.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">He will not roast his prey of deceit, but the wealth of an honest man is precious.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">In the road of charity is life, and [on] the way of its path there is no death.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="13"><pasuk id="1">A wise son [seeks] his father's discipline, but a scorner does not listen to rebuke.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">From the fruit of a man's mouth he will eat good, but the desire of the treacherous is violence.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">He who watches his mouth guards his soul; for one who opens his lips wide there is ruin.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">The soul of the lazy man desires but has nothing, but the soul of the diligent shall be sated.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">The righteous man hates a false word, but the wicked disgraces and embarrasses.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Charity guards him who is steadfast in his way, but wickedness brings ruin upon the sinner.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">There is one who feigns riches but has nothing; one who feigns poverty but has great wealth.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">The ransom of a man's soul is his wealth, as long as the poor man has not heard a rebuke.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">The light of the righteous will rejoice, but the candle of the wicked will ebb away.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Only with wickedness does one cause quarrels, but there is wisdom with those who take counsel.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Wealth gotten by vanity shall be diminished, but he who gathers by hand will increase.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Hope deferred makes the heart sick, but a desire fulfilled is a tree of life.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">He who despises a thing will be pledged to it, but he who reveres a commandment will be rewarded.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">The instruction of a wise man is a spring of life, to turn away from the snares of death.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Good sense will grant favor, but the way of the treacherous is harsh.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Every cunning man acts with forethought, but a fool exposes [his] stupidity.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">A wicked messenger falls into evil, but a faithful emissary brings healing.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Poverty and disgrace befall him who spurns discipline, but he who keeps reproof will be honored.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">A desire fulfilled pleases the soul, but the abomination of the fools is to turn away from evil.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">He who goes with the wise will become wise, but he who befriends the fools will be broken.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Evil will pursue the sinners but the righteous He will pay a good [reward].</pasuk><pasuk id="22">A good man will leave an inheritance for his sons' sons, but the wealth of a sinner is laid away for the righteous.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">An abundance of food is the result of the plowing of the poor, and some perish because of lack of propriety.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">He who holds back his rod hates his son, but he who loves him disciplines him early.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">A righteous man eats to sate his appetite, but the stomach of the wicked shall feel want.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="14"><pasuk id="1">The wisest of women-each one built her house, but a foolish one tears it down with her hands.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">He who fears the Lord goes in his uprightness, but he whose ways are perverse despises Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">In a fool's mouth is a staff of haughtiness but the lips of the wise guard them.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Without oxen the manger is empty, but an abundance comes by the strength of an ox.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">A faithful witness does not lie, but he who speaks lies is a false witness.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">The scorner sought wisdom, but it is not there; but knowledge for the understanding one is easy.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Go far away from a foolish man or you will not know lips of knowledge.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">The wisdom of a cunning man is to understand his way, but the folly of the fools is deceit.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Amends for guilt plead for the fools, but there is good will among the upright.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">One's heart knows the bitterness of his soul, and in his joy no stranger shall mingle.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">The house of the wicked shall be destroyed, but the tent of the righteous shall flourish.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">There is a way that seems right to a man, but its end is ways of death.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Even with laughter, the heart aches, and its end is that joy turns to sorrow.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">The one with an impure heart shall have his fill from his ways, and above him is a good man.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">A fool believes everything, but a cunning man understands his steps.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">A wise man fears and turns away from evil, but a fool passes vigorously and slips.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">A quick-tempered man acts foolishly, and a man of sinful plots is hated.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Fools inherit folly, but the cunning make knowledge a crown.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">The evil bend down before the good, and the wicked on the gates of a righteous man.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">The poor man is hated even by his friend, but the friends of the rich are many.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">He who despises his friend is a sinner, but he who favors the humble-fortunate is he.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Will they who plan evil not go astray? But kindness and truth come to those who plan good.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">In every toil there will be gain, but a word of the lips is only for loss.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">The crown of the wise is their wealth; the folly of the foolish is folly.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">A true witness saves lives, but he who speaks lies is [a man of] deceit.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">In the fear of the Lord is a strong promise, and he will be a shelter for his sons.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">The fear of the Lord is a spring of life, to turn away from the snares of death.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">The King's glory is in a multitude of people, but the ruin of His Princedom is in lack of people.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">He who is slow to anger is of great understanding, but he who is quick-tempered selects folly.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">A healing heart is the life of the flesh, but anger is the rot of the bones.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">He who oppresses a poor man blasphemes his Maker, but he who favors a poor man honors Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">A wicked man is thrust down with his evil, but a righteous man is confident in his death.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">Wisdom rests in the heart of an understanding man, but in the midst of the fools it is known.</pasuk><pasuk id="34">Charity will elevate a nation, but the kindness of the kingdoms is sin.</pasuk><pasuk id="35">The king's good will is to an intelligent servant, but his wrath will be upon a shameful one.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="15"><pasuk id="1">A gentle reply turns away wrath, but a distressing word stirs up anger.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">The tongue of the wise enhances knowledge, but the mouth of the fools pours out folly.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">The eyes of the Lord are everywhere, viewing the evil and the good.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">A healing tongue is a tree of life, but if there is perverseness in it, it causes destruction by wind.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">A fool despises the discipline of his father, but he who keeps reproof will become cunning.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">The house of a righteous man possesses great strength, but it becomes ruined with the bringing of the wicked man.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The lips of the wise crown knowledge, but the heart of the fools is not so.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">The sacrifice of the wicked is an abomination of the Lord, but the prayer of the upright is His will.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">The way of a wicked man is an abomination of the Lord, but He loves him who pursues righteousness.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Harsh discipline will come to him who forsakes the way; he who hates reproof shall die.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">The grave and Destruction are opposite the Lord- surely people's hearts.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">A scorner does not like being reproved; he does not go to the wise.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">A merry heart makes a cheerful face, but by sadness of heart comes a breaking spirit.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">The heart of an understanding person seeks knowledge, but the mouth of fools befriends folly.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">All the days of a poor man are wretched, but he who has a cheerful heart always has a feast.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Better a little with the fear of the Lord, than a great treasury and turmoil with it.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Better a repast of herbs where there is love, than a fattened ox where there is hatred.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">A man of wrath stirs up quarrels, but he who is slow to anger abates strife.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">The way of a lazy man is like a hedge of thorns, but the path of the upright is even.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">A wise son makes his father happy, but a foolish person despises his mother.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Folly is joy to one devoid of sense, but a man of understanding walks straight.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Plans are foiled for lack of counsel, but they are established through many advisers.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">A man has joy with the response of his mouth; and how good is a word in time!</pasuk><pasuk id="24">The path of life is above the intelligent person, in order that he turn away from the grave below.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">The Lord will uproot the house of the haughty, but He will establish the boundary of the widow.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">The thoughts of an evil person are an abomination of the Lord, but pleasant words are pure.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">He who is greedy of gain troubles his own house, but he who hates gifts will live.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">The heart of a righteous man thinks to answer, but the mouth of the wicked pours out evils.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">The Lord is far from the wicked, but He listens to the prayer of the righteous.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">The light of the eyes makes the heart happy; good news fattens the bone.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">The ear that listens to reproof of life shall lodge among the wise.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">He who rejects discipline despises his life, but he who hearkens to reproof acquires sense.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">The fear of the Lord is the discipline of wisdom, and before honor there is humility.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="16"><pasuk id="1">The preparations of the heart are man's, but the answer of the tongue is from the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">All ways of man are pure in his eyes, but the Lord counts the spirits.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Commit your affairs to the Lord, and your plans will be established.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">The Lord made everything for His praise-even the wicked man for the day of evil.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Everyone of haughty heart is an abomination of the Lord; hand to hand he will not go unpunished.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">With loving-kindness and truth will iniquity be expiated, and through fear of the Lord turn away from evil.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">When the Lord accepts a person's ways, He will cause even his enemies to make peace with him.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Better a little with righteousness than great revenues with injustice.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">A man's heart plans his way, but the Lord prepares his step.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">There is magic on a king's lips; his mouth commits no treachery in judgment.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">The balance and scales of justice are the Lord's; all the weights in the bag are His work.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">It is an abomination to kings to commit wickedness, for with righteousness the throne is established.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Righteous lips are the delight of kings, and he loves the one who speaks honestly.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">The king's wrath is [like] messengers of death, but a wise man will pacify it.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">In the light of the King's countenance is life, and His delight is like a cloud of the late rain.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">How much better is it to acquire wisdom than gold! And to acquire understanding is preferable to silver.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">The highway of the upright is to turn away from evil; he who guards his soul watches his way.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Before destruction comes pride, and before stumbling [comes] a haughty spirit.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">It is better to be of humble spirit with the lowly than to divide the spoils with the haughty.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">He who considers a matter will find good, and he who trusts in the Lord is fortunate.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">The wise-hearted shall be called understanding; and the sweetness of speech increases learning.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Intelligence is a fountain of life to one who has it, but the chastisement of the fools is folly.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">The heart of a wise man give his mouth intelligence and adds learning to his lips.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">Pleasant words are as a honeycomb, sweet to the soul and healing to the bones.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">There is a way [that is] straight in a man's view, but its end is ways of death.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">The soul of a laborer labors for him, when his mouth forces him.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">An ungodly man digs up evil, and on his lips is a kind of searing fire.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">A perverse man incites quarrel, and a grumbler alienates the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">A man of violence entices his neighbor and leads him on a way that is not good.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">He winks his eyes to think perverse thoughts; he purses his lips, bringing evil to pass.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">A hoary head is a crown of glory; it will be found in the way of righteousness.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">One who is slow to anger is better than a mighty man, and one who rules over his spirit [is better] than one who conquers a city.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">The lot is cast in the lap, but all his judgment is from the Lord.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="17"><pasuk id="1">Better a piece of dry bread and tranquility with it, than a house full of sacrifices of strife.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">An intelligent slave will rule over a disgraceful son, and among the brothers he will divide the inheritance.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">A refining pot is for silver, and a furnace is for gold, but the Lord tests the hearts.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">An evildoer hearkens to a language of violence; a liar lends an ear to destructive language.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">He who mocks a poor man blasphemes his Maker; he who rejoices at a misfortune will not go unpunished.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Children's children are the crown of the aged, and the glory of the children is their fathers.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Proud words do not befit a vile person, surely not lying speech a generous one.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">A bribe is a precious stone in the eyes of the one who has it; wherever he turns, he prospers.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">He who conceals transgression seeks love, but he who harps on a matter alienates the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">The humility caused by the rebuke of an understanding person [is more effective] than a hundred blows to a fool.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">He who is only rebellious seeks evil, and a cruel angel shall be sent against him.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">May a bereaving bear encounter a person rather than a fool with his folly.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">He who repays evil for good-evil will not depart from his house.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">The beginning of strife is like letting out water, and before you are exposed, abandon the quarrel.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">He who vindicates the wicked and condemns the righteous-both are an abomination to the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Why is there a price in the fool's hand to buy wisdom, when the heart is not here?</pasuk><pasuk id="17">At all times, love a friend, for he is born a brother for adversity.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">A person without sense clasps hands; he becomes surety before his neighbor.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">He who delights in transgression delights in quarrels; he who speaks haughtily seeks disaster.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">He who is of a perverse heart will find no good, and he who has a hypocritical tongue will fall into evil.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">He who begets a fool, does so to his sorrow; neither will the father of a vile man rejoice.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">A happy heart enhances one's brilliance, and a broken spirit dries the bones.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">He will take a bribe from a wicked man's bosom, to pervert the roads of justice.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">Wisdom is directly in front of an understanding man, but the eyes of a fool are at the end of the earth.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">A foolish son causes anger to his father, and bitterness to her who bore him.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">To punish also the righteous man is not good-to strike the generous who possess uprightness.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">He who has knowledge keeps back his words; he whose breath is dear is a man of understanding.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">He who silences even a fool is considered a wise man; one who shuts his lips, a man of understanding.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="18"><pasuk id="1">He who is separated seeks lust; in all sound wisdom, he is exposed.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">A fool does not delight in understanding, but in revealing his heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">When a wicked man comes, there also comes contempt, and with disdain, provocation.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">The words of a man's mouth are like deep water; the wellspring of wisdom is a flowing stream.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">It is not good to be partial to the wicked, to subvert the righteous in judgment.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">The lips of a fool will enter a quarrel, and his mouth calls out for blows.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">A fool's mouth is his ruin, and his lips are a snare for himself.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">The words of a grumbler are like blows, and they descend into the inmost parts.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Even one who is slack in his work is akin to the destroyer.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">The name of the Lord is a tower of strength; the righteous runs into it and is strengthened.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">A rich man's wealth is his strong city, and like a strong wall in his chamber.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Before ruin, a man's heart becomes haughty, but before honor there is humility.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">He who answers a word before he understands-it is foolishness for him and an embarrassment.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">A man's spirit will sustain his illness, but a broken spirit-who will bear it?</pasuk><pasuk id="15">An understanding heart will acquire knowledge, and the ear of the wise will seek knowledge.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">A man's gift will make room for him, and it will lead him before the great.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">He who pleads his case first seems just, but his neighbor comes and searches him out.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">The lot causes quarrels to cease, and it separates contentious people.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">A rebellious brother [is deprived] of a strong city, and the quarrels are like the bolt of a castle.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">With the fruit of his mouth does a man's stomach become sated; with the produce of his lips he is sated.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Death and life are in the hand of the tongue, and those who love it will eat its produce.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">He who has found a wife has found good, and has obtained favor from the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">A poor man speaks with supplications, but a rich man replies with impudence.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">A man acquires friends with whom to associate, and there is a friend who sticks closer than a brother.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="19"><pasuk id="1">Better a poor man who walks innocently than one with perverse lips, who is a fool.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">It is also not good that a soul be without knowledge, and he who hastens with his feet sins.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">A man's folly perverts his way, but his heart is wroth with the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Wealth adds many friends, but a poor man is separated from his friend.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">A false witness will not go unpunished, and one who speaks lies will not escape.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">The great will beg the favor of a generous man, and everyone is a friend to a man who gives gifts.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">All the kinsmen of a poor man hate him; surely his friends distance themselves from him; he pursues statements that are fit for him.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">He who acquires sense loves his soul; he who guards understanding will eventually find good.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">A false witness will not go unpunished, and one who speaks lies will perish.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Pleasure does not befit a fool, much less a slave to rule over princes.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">It is good sense for a man to be slow to anger, and it is his glory to pass over a transgression.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">The King's fury is like a lion's roar, but His good will is like dew upon the grass.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">A foolish son is the calamity of his father, and the quarrels of a wife are [like] a constant dripping.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">A house and wealth are the heritage of the fathers, but an intelligent wife is from the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Laziness causes one to fall into a deep sleep, and a deceitful soul shall suffer hunger.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">He who keeps a commandment keeps his soul; he who despises his ways will die.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">He who is gracious to a poor man lends to the Lord, and He will repay him his reward.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Chastise your son for there is hope, but do not set your heart on his destruction.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">A hot-tempered man incurs punishment, but if you save you will yet increase.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Hearken to advice and accept discipline, in order that you may be wise in your later years.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">There are many thoughts in a man's heart, but God's plan-that shall stand.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">The attraction to a man is his kindness, and a poor man is better than a liar.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Fear of the Lord is for life, and he will rest satisfied, not to be visited by evil.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">A lazy man hid his hand in a kettle; he will not return it even to his mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">Beat a scorner, and a simple man will gain cunning; reprove a man of understanding, and he will understand knowledge.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">A son who causes shame and disgrace robs his father, puts his mother to flight.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">My son, cease to stray from words of knowledge to hear discipline.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">A godless witness testifies judgment, but violence will devour the mouth of the wicked.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">Punishments are prepared for the scorners and blows for the body of fools.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="20"><pasuk id="1">The [imbiber of] wine is a scorner; he roars, "Strong drink!" And whoever strays with it will not become wise.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Fear of a king is like a lion's roar; he who provokes him forfeits his life.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">It is honor for a man to refrain from quarreling, and every fool will be exposed.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Because of the winter, a lazy man does not plow; he will seek in harvest, and there will be nothing.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Counsel in man's heart is like deep water, but a man of understanding will draw it out.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Many people call upon the man who promises them kindness, but who can find a trustworthy man?</pasuk><pasuk id="7">He who walks innocently is righteous; fortunate are his sons after him.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">A king sits upon a throne of judgment; all evil is spread out before him.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Who will say, "I have cleansed my heart; I have become purified of my sin"?</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Diverse weights and diverse measures-even both are an abomination of the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Even a child can disguise himself with his deeds, if his deed is pure or upright.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">The hearing ear and the seeing eye, the Lord has made even both of them.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Do not love sleep lest you become poor, open your eyes and be sated with bread.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">"It is bad, it is bad, " says the buyer, but when he goes away, then he boasts.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">There is gold and many pearls, but lips of knowledge are like a precious vessel.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">Take his garment because he stood surety for a stranger, and hold him in pledge for an alien woman.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Bread of falsehood is sweet to a man, but afterwards his mouth will be filled with gravel.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Plans with counsel will be established, and with strategies wage war.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">You shall not mingle with one who divulges secrets, one who gossips, or with one who entices with his lips.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">If one curses his father and mother, his lamp will flicker in the blackest darkness.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">An inheritance may be acquired hastily in the beginning, but its end will not be blessed.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Do not say, "I will repay evil." Hope to the Lord, and He will save you.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Diverse weights are an abomination of the Lord, and deceptive scales are not good.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">A man's steps are from the Lord, for man understands nothing of his way.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">When a man is trapped he impairs his sanctity, and he must seek vows.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">The Wise King scatters the wicked, and turns the wheel over them.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">Man's soul is the Lord's lamp, which searches out all the innermost parts.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">Kindness and truth preserve the king, and he supports his throne with kindness.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">The glory of young men is their strength, and the beauty of elders is a hoary head.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">Contusions and wounds come for outpouring in evil, and plagues in the innermost parts.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="21"><pasuk id="1">A king's heart is like rivulets of water in the Lord's hand; wherever He wishes, He turns it.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Man's every way is straight in his own eyes, but the Lord counts the hearts.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Performing charity and justice is preferred by God to a sacrifice.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Haughty eyes and unlimited lust-the tillage of the wicked is sin.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">The plans of a diligent man lead only to advantage, whereas every hasty one hurries only to want.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Gathering treasures with a lying tongue is like a driven vapor; they seek death.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The plunder of the wicked frightens them, for they have refused to perform justice.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">A man's way is changeable and he is strange, but as for a pure one-his deed is right.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">It is better to sit on the corner of a roof than with a quarrelsome wife and the house of a friend.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">The soul of a wicked man desires evil; his neighbor finds no favor in his eyes.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">When a scorner is punished, a fool gains wisdom, but when a wise man is instructed, he gains knowledge.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">The Righteous One considers the house of the wicked, overthrowing the wicked to their ruin.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">He who stops up his ear from the cry of a poor man-he, too, will cry out and not be answered.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">A gift in secret will appease wrath, and a bribe in the pocket [will even appease] strong wrath.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">It is a joy for a righteous man to do judgment, and a ruin for those who commit violence.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">A man who strays from the way of understanding will rest in the congregation of the shades.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">He who loves joy shall be a poor man; he who loves wine and oil shall not become rich.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">A wicked man shall be ransom for a righteous man, and a treacherous one instead of the upright.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">It is better to dwell in a desert land than [with] a quarrelsome and vexatious wife.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Precious treasure and oil are in the dwelling of the wise man, but man's foolishness will swallow it up.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">He who pursues charity and kindness will find life, charity, and honor.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">A wise man ascended to a city of mighty men and brought down the stronghold in which it trusts.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">He who watches his mouth and his tongue guards his soul from troubles.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">A malevolent, haughty man-scorner is his name; he acts with malevolent anger.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">The desire of a lazy man will bring about his death, for his hands refuse to labor.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">All day he covets greedily, but the righteous man gives and does not spare.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">The sacrifice of the wicked is an abomination, how much more if he brings it with plans of wickedness!</pasuk><pasuk id="28">A false witness will perish, but an obedient man may speak forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">A wicked man shows his brazenness in his anger, but an upright man-he will understand his way.</pasuk><pasuk id="30">There is neither wisdom nor understanding nor counsel against the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">A steed is prepared for a day of battle, but the victory is the Lord's.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="22"><pasuk id="1">A name is chosen above great wealth; good favor over silver and gold.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">A rich man and a poor man were visited upon; the Lord is the Maker of them all.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">A cunning man saw harm and hid, but fools transgressed and were punished.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">In the wake of humility comes fear of the Lord, riches, honor, and life.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Troops [and] snares are in the way of the perverse; he who preserves his soul will distance himself from them.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Train a child according to his way; even when he grows old, he will not turn away from it.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">A rich man will rule over the poor, and a borrower is a slave to a lender.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">He who sows injustice will reap violence, and the rod of his wrath will fail.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">He who has a generous eye will be blessed, for he gave of his bread to the poor.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Banish a scorner, and quarrel will depart, and litigation and disgrace will cease.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">He who loves one pure of heart with charm on his lips-the King is his friend.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">The eyes of the Lord preserve knowledge and He will frustrate the words of a treacherous man.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">The lazy man says, "There is a lion outside; I will be murdered in the middle of the streets."</pasuk><pasuk id="14">The mouth of strange women is [like] a deep pit; the one abhorred by the Lord will fall therein.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Foolishness is bound in a child's heart; the rod of discipline will drive it far from him.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">He who exploits a poor man to increase for himself will give to a rich man only to want.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Incline your ear and hearken to the words of the wise, and put your heart to my knowledge,</pasuk><pasuk id="18">for it is pleasant that you guard them in your innards; they will be established together on your lips.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">That your trust shall be in the Lord, I have made known to you this day, even you.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Have I not written to you thirds with counsels and knowledge,</pasuk><pasuk id="21">to make known to you the certainty of the true words, to respond with words of truth to those who send you?</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Do not rob a poor man because he is poor, and do not crush the poor man in the gate.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">For the Lord will plead their cause and rob those who rob them, of life.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">Do not befriend a quick-tempered person, neither shall you go with a wrathful man;</pasuk><pasuk id="25">lest you learn his ways and take a snare for your soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">Do not be one of those who give their hands, who stand surety for debts.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">If you do not have what to pay, why should he take your bed from under you?</pasuk><pasuk id="28">Do not remove an ancient boundary that your forefathers set.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">Have you seen a man quick in his work? He will stand before kings; he will not stand before poor men.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="23"><pasuk id="1">If you sit down to dine with a ruler, you should understand well who is in front of you,</pasuk><pasuk id="2">and you shall put a knife into your jaw if you are a man with a hearty appetite.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Do not desire his delicacies, for it is bread of lies.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Do not weary yourself to grow rich; cease from your own understanding.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Should you blink your eyes at it, it is not here; for it will make wings for itself, like the eagle, and it will fly toward the heavens.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Do not dine upon the bread of a stingy person and do not desire his delicacies;</pasuk><pasuk id="7">for it is as though it poured gall into his friend, so is he. He will tell you to eat and drink, but his heart is not with you.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">You will vomit out your morsel that you ate, and you will lose your sweet words.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Do not speak into the ears of a fool, for he will despise the sense of your words.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Do not remove an ancient boundary, and do not enter the fields of the orphans-</pasuk><pasuk id="11">for their Redeemer is mighty; He will plead their cause with you.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Bring your heart to discipline and your ears to words of knowledge.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Do not withhold discipline from a child; when you strike him with a rod, he will not die.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">You shall strike him with a rod, and you will save his soul from the grave.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">My son, if your heart has grown wise, my heart too will rejoice.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">And my reins shall rejoice when your lips speak right things.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Let your heart not envy the sinners, but fear of the Lord all day-</pasuk><pasuk id="18">for because of this, there is a future, and your hope will not be cut off.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Hear you, my son, and grow wise, and walk in the way of your heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Do not be among wine-guzzlers, among gluttonous eaters of meat for themselves,</pasuk><pasuk id="21">for the guzzler and the glutton will become impoverished, and slumber will clothe [you] with tatters.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Hearken to your father; this one begot you, and do not despise your mother when she has grown old.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Buy truth and do not sell; [also] wisdom, discipline, and understanding.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">The father of a righteous son will rejoice greatly, and he who begets a wise son will have joy with him.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">May your father and mother rejoice, and may she who bore you have joy.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">My son, give me your heart, and let your eyes keep my ways.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">For a harlot is like a deep ditch and a foreign woman like a narrow well.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">She, too, will suddenly lurk, and she will increase the faithless among men.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">Who cries, "Woe!" Who, "Alas!" He who has quarrels. He who talks too much. Who has wounds without cause? Who has bloodshot eyes?</pasuk><pasuk id="30">Those who sit late over wine, those who come to search for mixed wine.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">Do not look at wine when it is red; when he puts his eye on the cup, it goes smoothly.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">Ultimately, it will bite like a serpent, and sting like a viper.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">Your eyes will see strange women, and your heart will speak confusedly.</pasuk><pasuk id="34">And you shall be like one lying in the midst of the sea and like one lying at the top of a mast.</pasuk><pasuk id="35">"They struck me but I did not become ill; they beat me but I did not know it. When will I awaken? I will continue; I will seek it again."</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="24"><pasuk id="1">Do not envy men of evil; do not desire to be with them;</pasuk><pasuk id="2">for their heart thinks of plunder, and their lips speak of wrongdoing.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">A house is built with wisdom, and it is established with understanding.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">With knowledge, the rooms are filled with all riches, precious and pleasant.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">A wise man is with strength, and a man of knowledge maintains strength.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">For you shall wage war for yourself with strategies, and the victory results from the superiority of the counselor.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Wisdom is as pearls to the fool; in the gate he will not open his mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">He who plots to do evil is called a man of wicked designs.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">The counsel of folly is sin, and what makes man an abomination is scorn.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">If you have become lax, on a day of trouble your strength will be weak indeed.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">If you refrain from rescuing those taken to death and those on the verge of being slain</pasuk><pasuk id="12">will you say, "Behold, we did not know this"? Is it not so that He Who counts hearts understands, and He Who guards your soul knows, and He will requite a man according to his deed?</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Eat honey, my son, for it is good, and the honeycomb is sweet to your palate.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">So too, know wisdom for your soul; if you have found it, you will have a future and your hope will not be cut off.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">Wicked man, do not lurk by the dwelling of a righteous man; do not plunder his resting place.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">For a righteous man can fall seven times and rise, but the wicked shall stumble upon evil.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">When your enemy falls, do not rejoice, and when he stumbles, let your heart not exult,</pasuk><pasuk id="18">lest the Lord see and be displeased, and turn His wrath away from him.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Do not compete with evildoers; do not envy the wicked</pasuk><pasuk id="20">for there will be no future for an evil one; the lamp of the wicked will flicker.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">My son, fear the Lord and the king; do not mingle with dualists.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">For suddenly their misfortune will rise, and the ruin of both of them who knows?</pasuk><pasuk id="23">These too are for the wise; To have respect [for persons] in judgment is not good.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">He who says to a wicked man, "You are righteous"-peoples will curse him; nations will be wroth with him.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">But for those who reprove it will be pleasant, and a good blessing shall come upon them.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">Lips should kiss him who gives a right answer.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">Prepare your work outside and make it fit in the field for yourself; afterwards you shall build your house.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">Do not be a witness without cause for your friend, that you should be enticed with your lips.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">Do not say, "As he did to me, so will I do to him; I will repay the man according to his deed."</pasuk><pasuk id="30">By the fields of a lazy man, I passed and by the vineyard of a man without sense.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">And behold, thistles had grown all over it; nettles had covered its surface, and its stone fence had been torn down.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">And I, myself, saw; I applied my heart; I saw and learned a lesson.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">Little sleep, little slumber, little clasping of the hands to lie down.</pasuk><pasuk id="34">Then your poverty will come strolling and your wants like an armed man.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="25"><pasuk id="1">These too are Solomon's proverbs, which the men of Hezekiah, king of Judah, maintained.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">The honor of God is to conceal a matter, whereas the honor of kings is to search out a matter.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">The heaven for height, the earth for depth, and the honor of kings are unsearchable.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Remove dross from silver, and a vessel emerges for the refiner.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Remove the wicked man before the king, and his throne will be established with righteousness.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Do not glorify yourself before a king, and do not stand in the place of great men;</pasuk><pasuk id="7">for it is better that he say to you, "Come up here," than to humble you before a prince, as your eyes have seen.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Do not go out quickly to quarrel lest [you will not know] what you will do at its end, when your friend puts you to shame.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Have your quarrel with your friend, but do not divulge another's secret</pasuk><pasuk id="10">lest one who hears embarrass you, and your slander cannot be taken back.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Like golden apples on silverplated vessels, is a word spoken with proper basis.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Like a golden earring and jewelry of finest gold, is a wise man giving reproof to an ear that listens.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Like the cold of snow on the day of harvest, is an emissary faithful to his sender, who refreshes his master's soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Clouds and wind, but no rain-so is a man who boasts with a false gift.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">The Ruler is won over with slowness to anger, and a gentle tongue will break a bone.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">If you have found honey, eat enough for you, lest you become sated with it and vomit it.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Visit your neighbor sparingly, lest he become sated with you and hate you.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">A man who testifies falsely against his friend is like a club, a sword, and a sharpened arrow.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">Like a broken tooth and an unsteady leg is trust in a traitor on a day of trouble.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">A worn-out garment on a cold day is like vinegar on chalk, and so is one who sings songs to a broken heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">If your enemy is hungry, feed him bread, and if he is thirsty, give him water to drink;</pasuk><pasuk id="22">for you will be scooping coals on his head, and the Lord will reward you.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">As the north wind begets rain, so a backbiting tongue [begets] an angry countenance.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">It is better to sit on the corner of a roof than a quarrelsome wife and a house of companionship.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">As cold water to a faint soul, so is good news from a distant country.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">A righteous man slipping before a wicked man is like a muddied spring and a ruined fountain.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">Eating honey to excess is not good, but fathoming their honor is honor.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">Like a broken city without a wall, so is a man whose spirit is unrestrained.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="26"><pasuk id="1">Like snow in the summer and like rain at harvest, so is honor unbefitting for a fool.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Like a wandering sparrow and like a flying swallow, so will a vain curse come home.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">A whip is for the horse, a bridle is for the donkey, and a rod is for the body of fools.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Do not answer a fool according to his folly lest even you become like him.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Answer a fool according to his folly lest he be wise in his sight.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">He who sends a message by the hand of a fool wears out legs and "drinks violence."</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The thighs seem raised to a lame man, and [that is] a parable in the mouth of fools.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">He who gives honor to a fool is as binding a stone in a slingshot.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">A thorn came up in a drunkard's hand and a parable in the mouth of fools.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">The Master created all, and He hires a fool, and He hires transients.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">As a dog returns to his vomit, so does a fool repeat his folly.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">If you see a man who is wise in his own eyes, there is more hope for a fool than for him.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">The lazy man says, "There is a middle-sized lion on the road, a mature lion is between the streets."</pasuk><pasuk id="14">As a door turns on its hinge so does a lazy man on his bed.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">The lazy man buries his hand in the cauldron; it wearies him to bring it back to his mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">A lazy man in his own eyes is wiser than seven men who give advice.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">A passerby who becomes embroiled in a quarrel that is not his is like one who grabs a dog by its ears.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Like one who wearies himself shooting firebrands, arrows, and death,</pasuk><pasuk id="19">so is a man who deceives his friend and says, "Am I not joking?"</pasuk><pasuk id="20">Just as without wood, the fire goes out, so without a grumbler the quarrel quiets down.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">As charcoal is for coals and wood is for fire, so is a quarrelsome man for kindling strife.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Words of a grumbler are as though waging battle, and they penetrate the innermost parts of the body.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Burning lips and a wicked heart are like silver dross overlaid on earthenware.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">An enemy dissembles with his lips and within him he places deceit.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">When he entreats with his voice, do not believe him, for there are seven abominations in his heart.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">When the hatred is covered with darkness, his evil will be revealed in public.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">He who digs a pit will fall into it, and he who rolls a stone-it will return to him.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">[He who has] a false tongue hates those crushed under him, and a smooth mouth effects rejection.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="27"><pasuk id="1">Do not boast for tomorrow, for you do not know what the day will bear.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">May a stranger praise you and not your mouth, an alien and not your lips.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">The weight of a stone and the burden of sand-the anger of a fool is heavier than both.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Cruelty of wrath, and destruction of anger, but who can stand up before jealousy?</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Open rebuke is better than concealed love.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Wounds of a lover are faithful, whereas kisses of an enemy are burdensome.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">A sated soul tramples honeycomb, but to a hungry soul all bitter is sweet.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">As a bird wandering from its nest, so is a man wandering from his place.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Oil and incense make the heart rejoice, and the sweet words of his friend more than one's own counsel.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Do not forsake your friend and your father's friend, and do not enter your brother's house on the day of your misfortune; a close neighbor is better than a distant brother.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Be wise, my son, and cause my heart to rejoice, that I may answer him who taunts me.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">A cunning man saw harm and hid, but fools passed and were punished.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Take his garment because he stood surety for a stranger, and hold him in pledge for an alien woman.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">He who blesses his friend in a loud voice early every morning, it shall be considered a curse for him.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">A constant dripping on a rainstormy day, and a quarrelsome woman, are alike.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">He who guards her guards the wind, and he calls "the oil of his right hand."</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Iron sharpens iron, and a man sharpens the countenance of his friend.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">He who guards a fig-tree shall eat its fruit, and he who guards his master shall be honored.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">As in water, face answers to face, so is the heart of a man to a man.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">The grave and Gehinnom will not be sated, and the eyes of man will not be sated.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">The refining pot is for silver and the furnace for gold, and a man according to his praise.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">If you crush the fool in a mortar among grain with a pestle, his folly will not leave him.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Know well the condition of your flocks; give your attention to the herds.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">For riches are not forever, neither is a crown for generations.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">When the hay is carried away and the grass is visible, and the grasses of the mountains have been gathered,</pasuk><pasuk id="26">there will be lambs for your clothing, and he-goats are the worth of the field;</pasuk><pasuk id="27">and enough goat milk for your food, for the food of your household, and sustenance for your maidens.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="28"><pasuk id="1">The wicked flee without a pursuer, but the righteous are as trusting as a young lion.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">Because of the sin of a land, its princes are many, but because of an understanding, knowledgeable man, so will [its retribution] be delayed.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">A poor man who oppresses the poor is like a flooding rain that leaves no food.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Those who forsake the Torah praise the wicked, but those who keep the Torah contend with them.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Men of evil do not understand judgment, but those who seek the Lord understand everything.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">A poor man who walks innocently is better than one of perverse ways who is rich.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">He who keeps the Torah is the son of an understanding man, but he who befriends gluttons puts his father to shame.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">He who increases his riches with usury and interest gathers it for him who is gracious to the poor.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">He who turns his ear away from hearing the Torah-even his prayer is an abomination.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">He who misleads the upright in an evil way will fall into his own pit, but the innocent will inherit goodness.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">A rich man is wise in his own eyes, but a discerning poor man will search him out.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">When the righteous rejoice, there is much glory, but when the wicked rise up, a person will be searched out.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">He who conceals his sins will not succeed, but he who confesses and abandons [them] will obtain mercy.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Fortunate is the man who is always afraid, but he who hardens his heart will fall into evil.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">A wicked man ruling over a poor people is like a roaring lion and a growling bear.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">A ruler who lacks understanding is a great oppressor, for he who hates unlawful gain will live long.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">A man who is guilty of robbing one's lifeblood will flee to the pit, but no one will support him.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">He who walks innocently will be saved, but he who is perverse in his way will fall in one.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">He who tills his soil will be sated with bread, but he who pursues vain things will be sated with poverty.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">A trustworthy man will have many blessings, but he who hastens to become rich will not go unpunished.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">To be partial is not good, but for a piece of bread a man will sin.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">He who hastens to [acquire] wealth is a man with an evil eye, and he does not know that want will come upon him.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">He who admonishes man after Me, will find more favor than he who speaks with flattery.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">He who robs his father or his mother and says, "This is not a sin," is the companion of a destroyer.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">A greedy man stirs up quarrels, but he who puts his trust in the Lord will be greatly gratified.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">He who trusts his heart is a fool, but he who goes with wisdom will escape.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">He who gives to a poor man will suffer no want, but he who hides his eyes will have many curses.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">When the wicked rise up, people hide; but when they perish, the righteous increase.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="29"><pasuk id="1">A man who requires reproof but stiffens his nape, will suddenly be broken without cure.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">When the righteous become great, the people rejoice, but when a wicked man rules, the people sigh.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">A man who loves wisdom makes his father happy, but one who keeps company with harlots wastes his wealth.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">A king establishes the country with justice, but a haughty man tears it down.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">A man who flatters his friend spreads out a net for his feet.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">When a wicked man sins, there is a snare, and a righteous man sings and rejoices.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">A righteous man knows the judgment of the poor; a wicked man does not put his mind to knowing it.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Scornful men inflame a city, but the wise turn away wrath.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">When a wise man contends with a foolish man, whether he is angry or he laughs, he will have no contentment.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Murderous men hate the innocent, but the upright seek his soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">A fool lets out all his wind, but afterwards a wise man will quiet it.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">A ruler who hearkens to false words-all his servants are wicked.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">A poor man and a man of deep thoughts were visited upon; the Lord enlightens the eyes of both of them.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">A king who judges the poor justly-his throne will be established forever.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">A rod and reproof give wisdom, but a child left free brings shame to his mother.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">When the wicked attain greatness, transgression increases, and the righteous will see their downfall.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Chastise your son and he will give you rest, and he will grant pleasures to your soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Without vision the people become unrestrained, but he who keeps the Torah is fortunate.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">A slave cannot be chastised with words, because he will understand, but without response.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">If you see a man hasty with his words, there is more hope for a fool than for him.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">If one pampers his slave from childhood, he will ultimately be a ruler.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">A quick-tempered man stirs up strife, and a wrathful man abounds in transgression.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">A man's haughtiness will humble him, but one of humble spirit will grasp honor.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">He who shares with a thief hates his soul; he hears an oath but does not testify.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">A snare brings terror to a person, but he who trusts in the Lord will be safeguarded.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">Many seek the countenance of a ruler, but the judgment of a person is from the Lord.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">An unjust man is an abomination to the righteous, and a person whose way is straight is an abomination to a wicked man.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="30"><pasuk id="1">The words of Agur, the son of Jakeh, the prophecy; the words of the man concerning, "God is with me; yea, God is with me, and I will be able."</pasuk><pasuk id="2">For I am more boorish than any man, neither do I have man's understanding.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Neither have I learned wisdom, nor do I know the knowledge of the holy ones.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Who ascended to heaven and descended? Who gathered wind in his fists? Who wrapped the waters in a garment? Who established all the ends of the earth? What is his name and what is the name of his son, if you know?</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Every word of God is refined; He is a shield for all who take refuge in Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Do not add to His words, lest He prove to you, and you be found a liar.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">I ask two [things] of You; do not withhold them from me before I die.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Distance falsehood and the lying word from me; give me neither poverty nor wealth; provide me my allotted bread,</pasuk><pasuk id="9">lest I become sated and deny, and I say, "Who is the Lord?" And lest I become impoverished and steal, and take hold of the name of my God.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Do not inform on a slave to his master, lest he curse you, and you be found guilty.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">A generation that curses its father and does not bless its mother.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">A generation that is pure in its eyes, but is not cleansed of its filth.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">A generation-how lofty are its eyes! And its eyelids are raised.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">A generation whose teeth are [like] swords, and its molars are [like] knives, to devour the poor of the land and the needy of men.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">The leech has two daughters, "Give" and "Give." There are three that are not sated, and four that do not say, "Enough!"</pasuk><pasuk id="16">The grave, the confined womb, and the earth, which is not sated with water, and fire, which does not say, "Enough!"</pasuk><pasuk id="17">The eye that mocks the father and despises the mother's wrinkles-may the ravens of the valley pick it out, and the young eagles devour it.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">There are three things that are concealed from me, and four that I do not know;</pasuk><pasuk id="19">The way of the eagle in the heavens, the way of a serpent on a rock, the way of a ship in the heart of the sea, and the way of a man with a young woman.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">So is the way of an adulterous woman; she eats and wipes her mouth, and she says, "I have committed no sin."</pasuk><pasuk id="21">Under three things the earth quakes, and under four it cannot endure;</pasuk><pasuk id="22">Under a slave who rules and a wretch who is sated with food;</pasuk><pasuk id="23">under a hated woman who is married, and a maidservant who inherits her mistress.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">There are four small creatures on the earth, yet they are exceedingly wise;</pasuk><pasuk id="25">The ants are a people not strong, yet they prepare their food in summer.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">The hyraxes are a people not strong, yet they make their home in the rock.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">The locusts have no king, yet they all go out in a troop.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">The spider grasps with [her] hands, and she is in a king's palaces.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">Three are outstanding in their step, and four are outstanding in their walk;</pasuk><pasuk id="30">The lion is the mightiest of the beasts, who is undaunted by anyone.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">The greyhound and the he-goat, and the king against whom no one dares to rise up.</pasuk><pasuk id="32">If you have been put to shame, you will be in your ascendency; and if you thought evil, put your hand to your mouth.</pasuk><pasuk id="33">For pressing milk will give out butter, and pressing the nose will give out blood, and pressing anger will give out strife.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="31"><pasuk id="1">The words of Lemuel the king; a prophecy that his mother chastised him;</pasuk><pasuk id="2">What, my son, and what, the son of my womb, and what, the son of my vows?</pasuk><pasuk id="3">Do not give your strength to women, nor your ways to the pleasures of kings.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">It is not for kings, Lemoel, it is not for kings to drink wine, neither is strong drink for rulers.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Lest he drink and forget what was made law, and change the judgment of all the impoverished.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Give strong drink to the one who is perishing and wine to those of bitter soul.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">Let him drink and forget his poverty, and let him remember his misery no more.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Open your mouth for the dumb, to the cause of all whose help has passed.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Open your mouth, judge justly and plead the cause of the poor and the needy.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">A woman of valor who can find, for her price is beyond pearls.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Her husband relies on her, and he will lack no gain.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">She requites him with good and not with evil all the days of her life.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">She seeks wool and flax, and she works it with the will of her hands.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">She is like the merchant ships, she brings her food from afar.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">She rises when it is still night; she gives food to her household and an allotted share to her maidens.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">She contemplates a field and purchases it; from the fruit of her hands she plants a vineyard.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">She girds her loins with vigor and strengthens her arms.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">[When] she advises that her merchandise is good her lamp does not go out at night.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">She stretches forth her hands onto the distaff, and her hands support the spindle.</pasuk><pasuk id="20">She spreads out her hand to the poor man, and she stretches her hands out to the needy.</pasuk><pasuk id="21">She fears not for her household for snow, for all her household are dressed in crimson.</pasuk><pasuk id="22">She makes beautiful bedspreads for herself; fine linen and purple wool are her raiment.</pasuk><pasuk id="23">Her husband is known in the gates, when he sits with the elders of the land.</pasuk><pasuk id="24">She makes a cloak and sells it, and she gives a belt to the trafficker.</pasuk><pasuk id="25">Strength and beauty are her raiment, and she laughs at the last day.</pasuk><pasuk id="26">She opens her mouth with wisdom, and instruction of kindness is on her tongue.</pasuk><pasuk id="27">She supervises the ways of her household and does not eat bread of idleness.</pasuk><pasuk id="28">Her children rise and call her fortunate; [also] her husband, and praises her.</pasuk><pasuk id="29">"Many women have acquired wealth, but you surpass them all."</pasuk><pasuk id="30">Charm is false and beauty is futile; a God-fearing woman is to be praised.</pasuk><pasuk id="31">Give her of the fruit of her hands, and her deeds will praise her in the gates.</pasuk></chapter></book>