<book><chapter id="1"><pasuk id="1">The harsh prophecy concerning Nineveh. The book of the vision of Nahum the Elkoshite.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">The Lord is a jealous and vengeful God and is full of wrath; the Lord avenges Himself upon His adversaries, and He bears a grudge against His enemies.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">The Lord is slow to anger and great in power, but He will surely not acquit; the Lord-His way is with a tempest and with a storm? and cloud is the dust of His feet.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">He rebukes the sea and dries it up, and He has dried up all the rivers; Bashan and Carmel are cut off, and the blossoms of the Lebanon are cut off.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Mountains quaked because of him and the hills melted, and the land raised up from before Him-and the inhabited earth and all who dwell thereon.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">Who can stand before His fury and who can rise amidst His wrath? His wrath has reached [the earth] like fire, and the rocks have been broken up by Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The Lord is good-yea, a stronghold on a day of trouble- and is cognizant of those who trust in Him.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">But, with an overrunning flood He shall make a full end of its place, and darkness shall pursue His enemies.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">What do you think of the Lord? He will make a full end; the trouble will not rise twice.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">For, while the thorns are entangled and the drunkards are drinking, they are consumed like dry stubble, fully ripe.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">From you has emanated one who plots evil against the Lord, one who counsels wickedness.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">So said the Lord: Though they be at peace-and likewise many-and likewise they have crossed and passed over, I will no longer afflict you.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">And now I will break off his yoke from you, and I will rend your bonds asunder.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">And the Lord shall command concerning you; No more [offspring] of your name shall be sown; from the house of your god I will cut off a graven image and a molten image; I will make your grave, for you have become worthless.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="2"><pasuk id="1">Behold on the mountains the feet of a herald announcing peace. O Judah, keep your feasts, pay your vows-for the wicked one shall no longer continue to pass through you; he has been completely cut off.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">The scatterer who came up before you is besieged by a siege. Watch the way! Strengthen your loins! Fortify your power mightily.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">For the Lord has restored the pride of Jacob as the pride of Israel, for the emptiers have emptied them out and destroyed their branches.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">The shields of his mighty men are dyed red; the men of the army are in crimson; the chariots are in the fire of torches on the day of his preparation, and the cypresses are enwrapped.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">The chariots shall dash about madly in the streets; they shall clatter in the city squares; their appearance is like torches; like lightning, they shatter.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">He shall remember his mighty men; they shall stumble in their walk; they shall hasten to its wall, and the protector is armed.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">The gates of the rivers have opened, and the palace has dissolved.</pasuk><pasuk id="8">And the queen has been exposed and taken away, and her maidens moan, like the voice of doves beating their breasts.</pasuk><pasuk id="9">And Nineveh is like a pool of water-it is since days of yore-and they flee. Halt! Halt! But no one pays attention.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">Plunder silver! Plunder gold! And there is no end to the treasures-to sweep out [Nineveh] of all precious vessels.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">Empty, yea, emptied out and breached; and the heart melts, the knees stumble, and there is trembling in all loins; and the faces of all of them have gathered blackness.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">Where is the lions' den? And it is pasture for young lions, where the grown lion and the old lion went, and the lion's whelp-and none made them afraid.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">The grown lion tore enough for his whelps and strangled for his lionesses, and he filled his caves with prey and his dens with prey.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Behold! I am against you, says the Lord of Hosts, and I will ignite her chariots with smoke; and the sword shall consume your young lions, and I will cut off your prey from the land; and the voice of your ambassadors shall no longer be heard.</pasuk></chapter><chapter id="3"><pasuk id="1">Woe to the city of blood; it is all lies, full of robbery; the prey departs not.</pasuk><pasuk id="2">The sound of the scourge..and the sound of the noise of the wheels and the galloping horses and the bounding chariots.</pasuk><pasuk id="3">The horseman raises himself and the blade of the sword and the burnished spear and the many slain-yea, the heaps of corpses. There is no end to the bodies, and they shall stumble over their bodies.</pasuk><pasuk id="4">Because of the many harlotries of the harlot, charming and enchanting, who delivers nations with her harlotries, and families with her enchantments.</pasuk><pasuk id="5">Behold! I am against you, says the Lord of Hosts, and I will uncover your skirts upon your face-and I will show the nations your nakedness, and the kingdoms your shame.</pasuk><pasuk id="6">And I will cast detestable things upon you and make you vile, and I will make you like dung.</pasuk><pasuk id="7">And it shall come to pass that whoever sees you shall wander away from you, and he shall say, "Nineveh has been plundered." Who will console her? Whence shall I seek comforters for you?</pasuk><pasuk id="8">Are you better than No-Amon, which was situated among the rivers, with water around it-whose wall was the sea and of the sea, its wall?</pasuk><pasuk id="9">Cush was [its] strength, and Egypt, which had no end; Put and the Lubim were your helpers.</pasuk><pasuk id="10">She, too, went into exile in captivity. Her young children, too, were dashed at the head of all the streets. And they cast lots on her dignitaries, and all her great men were bound in chains.</pasuk><pasuk id="11">You, too, shall become drunk; you shall disappear; you, too, shall seek refuge from the enemy.</pasuk><pasuk id="12">All your fortresses are like fig trees with first-ripe fruits; if they be shaken, they fall into the mouth of the eater.</pasuk><pasuk id="13">Behold! Your people are [like] women in your midst. For your enemies, the gates of your land shall be opened; a fire shall consume your bars.</pasuk><pasuk id="14">Draw siege water for yourself; strengthen your fortifications; come into the clay and tread the mortar; grasp the brickmold.</pasuk><pasuk id="15">There a fire shall consume you; a sword shall cut you off, it shall consume you as the nibbling locust [does]. You shall be swept away by the nibbling locust; you shall be swept away like the increasing locust.</pasuk><pasuk id="16">You have increased your traffickers more than the stars of the heavens; the nibbling locust spreads out and flies away.</pasuk><pasuk id="17">Your princes are like the increasing locust, and your marshals like armies of locusts which alight on the walls on a cold day; the sun shines, and it flies away, and its place is not known-where they are.</pasuk><pasuk id="18">Your leaders slumber, O King of Assyria; your mighty men are at rest; your people are scattered on the mountains, and no one gathers them in.</pasuk><pasuk id="19">No one is pained over your destruction; your wound is grievous; all who hear your report clap hands over you, for upon whom did your harm not pass constantly?</pasuk></chapter></book>