<book>
  <chapter id="1">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And there was one man: ">It all follows the order, i.e., Moses gave over the Torah to Joshua, and Joshua to the Elders, and each judge to his successor, until it reached Eli, by whom it was given over to Samuel, as we learned in the Mishnah (Avoth 1:1): and the Elders gave it over to the Prophets.</text>
      <text title="from Ramathaim Zophim: ">There were two hills, each visible to the other. (Meg. 14a) Jonathan, however, renders ‘Zophim’ of the disciples of the Prophets.</text>
      <text title="Elkanah: ">Elkanah was a Levite of the sons of Ebiasaf the son of Korah. Thus his ancestry is recorded in Chron. (I, 6:7 12).</text>
      <text title="an Ephraimite: ">Jonathan renders: on the mountain of the House of Ephraim. Midrash Aggadah (M.S. 1:16): Ephrathi, a palace dweller, a nobleman, an important person, like (the Talmudic word ‘aperion’, used in B.M. 119a): Let us extend ‘aperion’ to Rabbi Simon. An expression of favor.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And that man was wont to go up: ">This is the present tense. He would go up from one appointed season to another appointed season, to Shiloh. Midrash Aggadah (M.S. 1: 1,5, 7): The route he followed this year he did not follow the next year, in order to publicize (his pilgrimage) to the Israelites that they should do likewise.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="And when it was the day: ">And it was the festive day.[after Jonathan].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="מנה אחת אפים: ">one choice portion: a portion which is fit to be accepted with a friendly countenance.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="And her rival: ">Her husband’s other wife, Peninnah.</text>
      <text title="frequently anger her:: ">Anger after anger, always. Therefore, it is written: ‘also anger.’ She would say to her, “Did you buy your older son a cloak today, or your younger son a shirt?”</text>
      <text title="in order to make her complain:: ">(Literally, to make her storm.) Our rabbis explain, “in order to make her storm” that she pray. And Peninnah had good intentions.</text>
      <text title="her womb:: ">Lit., opposite her womb, and so is every expression of the word בעד.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And so he would do:: ">I. e., Elkanah.</text>
      <text title="year by year:: ">He would give her a choice portion to demonstrate to her that he loved her and her rival would anger her more and more according to the affection which her husband demonstrated to her.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="better to you:: ">Don’t I love you more dearly…</text>
      <text title="..than (I love) ten sons:: ">that Peninnah has borne to me?</text>
      <text title="after eating: ">(אכלה). The הא is not dotted and the אלף is voweled with a short קמץ, and it is like אחרי אכול, meaning after eating in Shiloh and after drinking, and this expression is properly used both for masculine and feminine.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="after eating: ">‘After eating’ is a gerund. It is constructed like לאכלה (Lev. 25:6) to eat, an expression equivalent to לאכול an infinitive.</text>
      <text title="and Eli the priest was sitting on the chair:: ">The defective spelling denotes that on that day, he was seated on a huge chair, for he was appointed judge over Israel.</text>
      <text title="beside the doorpost:: ">lit. on the doorpost.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="O Lord of Hosts:: ">Why was this Name designated here? (The answer is as follows:) She said before Him: O Lord of the universe, You created two hosts in Your world. The heavenly beings do not multiply, neither do they die, while the earthly beings both multiply and die. If I am of the earthly beings let me multiply, and if I am of the heavenly beings let me not die. I found this explanation in the Aggadah of Rabbi Jose the Galilean. Our sages in tractate Ber. (31b), however, expounded what they expounded: Until then there was no person who called the Holy One, blessed be He, “Hosts.” (Why then, did Hannah call Him by this Name?) But, so said she before Him: “O Lord of the universe, from all the hosts which You created in Your world, do You find it difficult to grant me one son?”</text>
      <text title="if You will look:: ">(Lit., if seeing You will see.) In tractate Ber., our sages expounded what they expounded.</text>
      <text title="Your bondswoman:: ">which is stated three times in this verse, corresponds to the three precepts which a woman is commanded to observe.</text>
      <text title="A man child:: ">(Lit., seed of men, meaning) righteous men, as it is written (Kings I:2:32): “Upon two righteous men.” אנשים also means important men, as it is written (Deut. 1:13): wise and known men.</text>
      <text title="and I shall give him to the Lord:: ">that he be fit to be given to the Lord.</text>
      <text title="and no razor shall come upon his head:: ">(translation follows K, however,) Jonathan renders: and the fear of man will not be upon him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="watched her mouth:: ">He waited for her to stop. Jonathan renders thus: and Eli waited for her until she stopped.</text>
      <text title="watched:: ">an expression of waiting, as in (Gen. 37:11) “and his father awaited the thing,” and (Job 14:16) “You do not wait for my sin.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="and Eli thought her to be a drunken woman:: ">for they were not accustomed to praying silently.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="Not my lord:: ">You are not a lord in this instance. You yourself have revealed that the holy spirit is not resting upon you, otherwise you would know that I am not intoxicated from wine.</text>
      <text title="I am a woman of sorrowful spirit:: ">like Sarah (who was childless) [old editions of Rashi].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="Deliver not your bondswoman:: ">Considering the fact that she spoke harshly to him, she returned to appease him so that he deliver her not, unprotected and disgraced, at the mercy of her rival, the unscrupulous woman.</text>
      <text title="for out of the abundance of my complaint:: ">have I spoken harshly before you.</text>
      <text title="my complaint: ">(lit., my speech.) In some instances, it is an expression of grief of heart. Another explanation is, according to the Targum, as follows: for out of the abundance of my provocation and my vexation, have I prolonged my prayer until now.</text>
      <text title="and my vexation:: ">which my rival vexes me.</text>
      <text title="Deliver not:: ">(Lit. do not give.) An expression of delivery, like, “deliver me not unto the will of my adversaries” (Ps. 27:12).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="your request: ">(שלתך, instead of שאלתך). The ‘alef’ is missing to expound in this word an expression of ‘children,’ as in Deut. 28:57: ובשליתה “and against her young, which came out, etc.”</text>
      <text title="will grant your request:: ">He announced to her that her prayer had been accepted.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="May your bondswoman find favor:: ">to beg mercy for her.</text>
      <text title="and her face was not (sad) anymore:: ">(Lit., and she no longer had her face, meaning) the face of anger.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="and came to their house, and Elkanah knew:: ">From here is deduced that a traveler is forbidden to have marital relations.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="when the time came about:: ">(After the seasons and the days.) The minimum of seasons is two and the minimum of days is also two. Hence, she gave birth after six months and two days. From here it is deduced that a woman who gives birth after seven months, can give birth after a fraction of the seventh month of pregnancy.</text>
      <text title="Samuel:: ">El after the name of God, and in reference to the incident, he was so called, for I asked him of the Lord.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="the sacrifice of the days:: ">of the appointed seasons.</text>
      <text title="his vow:: ">The vows which he made between pilgrimage festivals, he would sacrifice on the following festival.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="Until the child is weaned:: ">after twenty two months (other versions, twenty four), for that is the time of nursing a child.</text>
      <text title="and abide there forever:: ">“Forever” in the Levitic sense means fifty years, as it says, (Num. 8:25), “and from the age of fifty years he shall return from the host of the work.” Figuring as follows, we determine that Samuel’s lifetime was fifty-two years. Eli judged Israel for forty years (see 4:18), and on the day of Hannah’s prayer, he was appointed judge (See above v. 9). By subtracting the year in which Hannah conceived Samuel, there remain thirty nine years. Samuel governed Israel from the time of Eli’s death for thirteen years, figuring thus: On the day of Eli’s death, the Ark was abducted, and it remained in the field of the Philistines for seven months (below 6:1). From there, it was brought to Kiriath-jearim, where it remained until David took it out of there after he had reigned seven years in Hebron over Judah, and all Israel had accepted him as their king. And it is written: And is was, from the day that the Ark abode in Kiriath-jearim that the time was long, for it was twenty years, etc. (below 7:2). Subtract from them seven years which David reigned in Hebron. We find that from the time that the Ark was abducted until Saul’s death, were thirteen years and seven months, and Samuel died four months before Saul.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="only, may the Lord fulfill His word:: ">Since you asked of Him seed of righteous men (above v. 11), and Eli announced to you through divine inspiration: (above v. 17) “The God of Israel will grant your request,” may the Lord fulfill His word. This is according to the simple interpretation. The Midrash Agadah, however, explains thus: Rabbi Nehemiah said in the name of Rabbi Samuel, the son of Rabbi Isaac: Every day, a divine voice would resound throughout the world, and say: A righteous man is destined to arise, and his name will be Samuel. Thereupon, every woman who bore a son, would name him Samuel. As soon as they saw his deeds, they would say, “This is not Samuel.” When our Samuel was born, however, and people saw his deeds, they said, “It seems that this one is the expected righteous man.” This is what Elkanah meant when he said, ‘May the Lord fulfill His word,’ that this be the righteous Samuel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="and one ephah of meal: ">I heard from Rabbi Isaac Halevi, that she brought one ephah of meal, which is equivalent to three seahs, from which to extract three tenths of an ephah of fine flour, which are required for one bull (Num. 15:8), as we learned in the Mishnah (Men. 76b): The showbread was made of twenty-four tenths of an ephah from twenty-four seahs; i.e., 1 tenth part of an ephah of fine flour from a seah of wheat.</text>
      <text title="and an earthenware jug of wine:: ">for a drink offering. והנער נער and the child was young (after Jonathan).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="and they brought the child to Eli: ">to see that his prophecy was fulfilled. And our sages, however, expounded what they expounded, that he decided a point of law, that a priest is unnecessary for sacrificial slaughter, as it is stated in Tractate Ber. (31b).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="Please, my lord:: ">Take care of him that he become your disciple. And according to the Midrash of our sages, not to punish him with death.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="For this child did I pray:: ">Do not say, “This one shall die and another one shall be given to you.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="And I also have lent him to the Lord: ">like a person who lends a utensil to his master, or lends him his son to serve him.</text>
      <text title="he is borrowed: ">empunte in French, i.e., you have no right to punish him, for the Lord has become a borrower over him, since I have lent him to Him, and He must return him to me.</text>
      <text title="And he prostrated himself: ">Samuel, and some say Elkanah.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="2">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="My mouth is opened wide against my enemies: ">against Peninnah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="And there is no rock like our God.: ">There is no artist like our God, Who makes a form within a form (Ber. 10a).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="Do not increasingly speak haughtily: ">All those who are haughty when good fortune shines upon them. And according to the peshat, she is speaking for the benefit of Peninnah, who behaved haughtily toward her. According to the derash, however, we follow J’s translation.</text>
      <text title="arrogance: ">(Lit.) strong speech. Others explain it as an expression of falsehood, something which is removed from the truth, like ויעתק“and he moved from there to the mountain” (Gen. 12: 8). We, therefore, render: Let not falsehood come out of your mouth.</text>
      <text title="For the Lord is a God of thoughts: ">He knows what is in your heart.</text>
      <text title="And to Him are deeds counted: ">All men’s deeds are counted before Him. Heb. ‘nithk’nu,’ an expression of number, like: and the number (tochen) of bricks shall you give (Ex. 5:18).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="The bows of the mighty are broken, etc.: ">So is the custom of the Most Holy, blessed be He. He weakens the mighty, and strengthens the weak. He sates the hungry and starves those who are satiated.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="Those who were satiated: ">and do not need to hire themselves out for any work, He starves them, and they must hire themselves out for their daily bread, while the hungry who would toil and weary themselves for food…</text>
      <text title="… have ceased: ">from their toil. While the barren woman has born seven, she that had many children has been bereaved and buries her children. Hannah bore seven, as it is stated: For the Lord remembered Hannah, and she conceived and bore three sons and two daughters (2:21). When Hannah bore four, Peninnah buried eight, and when she conceived and bore a fifth child, Peninnah prostrated herself at her feet, and begged for mercy. Consequently, they lived, and were therefore called on her name. This is Rabbi Nehemiah’s opinion. Rabbi Judah says: Grandchildren are considered like children, (and she saw Samuel’s two sons). Some say: the numerical value of שבעה (seven) is equivalent to that of שמואל, (thus: ש =300, ב =2, ע =70, ה =5, totaling 377. Likewise, ש =300, מ =40, ו =6, א =1, ל =30, totaling 377).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="His pious ones: ">It is spelled חסידו, His pious one. It is read חסידיו, His pious ones, i.e., either a single one or many. Likewise, “Those who strive with the Lord will be broken.” This reading is מריביו, those who strive with Him. The spelling is מריבו, he who strives with Him, i.e., either one or many.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="Upon him will he thunder in Heaven: ">The spelling is עלו, they have ascended, even if they have ascended to the heavens, He thunders upon and casts them down.</text>
      <text title="will judge the ends of the earth: ">will judge them; in old French, jostizier.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="was serving the Lord before Eli the priest:: ">(The Talmud asks, “Did Samuel actually serve the Lord?” Didn’t he serve before Eli? [He was too young to serve the Lord!] We therefore deduce) from here that whoever serves before a Torah scholar, is considered as though he had served before the Divine Presence.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="the due of the priests: ">They themselves established this law, since they rightfully inherited only the breast and the thigh of the peace offering.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="or into the pot: ">דוד is a [small] pot.</text>
      <text title="or into the cauldron: ">קלחת is a large pot.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="for the men despised: ">כי נאצו, an expression of being despised.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="robe: ">(Hebrew ephod.) kardut of linen (Jonathan). This is an expression meaning a robe (מעיל) , for Jonathan renders ‘m’ilim’ in the passage, "for so were the virgins wont to wear robes (m’ilim) kardutin.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="And a small robe his mother would make for him: ">from year to year.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="And Eli would bless Elkanah: ">this is the present tense (i.e., he would bless him every year).</text>
      <text title="because of the request which he had requested: ">for himself a son. And Eli would say to him, “May the Lord grant seed, etc.” May it be the Divine Will that all the children which you will have, will be from this righteous woman. This is (therefore) an inverted sentence.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="that they would lie: ">This is explained according to the ordinary sense of the passage. Our rabbis, however, said: Since they delayed the sacrifice of their birds, (i.e., of the women who had given birth, or had had an issue. v. Lev. 22:6 8,15:29), and they (the women) would wait until they would see their birds being offered, the Scripture charges them as though they had lain with them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="which I hear the Lord’s people spreading: ">The rumor which the Lord’s people are spreading about you. This is an expression similar to: “And they caused to be proclaimed in the camp” (Ex. 36: 6). Hence, they let out a rumor about you, which is not good.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="will judge him: ">(Heb. ‘ufil’lo,’) an expression of judgment, like (Ex. 21:22): and he shall pay as the judges determine (bi-flilim).</text>
      <text title="the judge: ">Heb. elohim.</text>
      <text title="for the Lord desired to kill them: ">For their verdict had already been sealed. Before the verdict is sealed, however, the Scripture states: For I desire not the death of one who dies (Ezek. 17: 32).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="And a man of God came:: ">(The Sifrei informs us that the man of God mentioned here) was Elkanah.</text>
      <text title="Did I appear to the house of your father: ">From here (we deduce) that Aaron prophesied in Egypt. What was the prophecy? It is that which is stated (Ezek. 20:7), And I said to them: Each man, cast away the detestable things upon which his eyes gaze, and with the idols of Egypt, defile not yourselves.</text>
      <text title="Did I appear: ">Did you know that I gave to Aaron this favor and greatness?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="אשר צויתי מעון: ">which I commanded in My dwelling place.</text>
      <text title="to feed yourselves from the first part, etc.: ">(lit., and you honor your sons above Me to feed yourselves from the first part of every offering of Israel to My people.) This is an inverted sentence, (to be explained thus): and you honor your sons above Me before My people, i.e., in the eyes of My people, you honored your son above me. And what is the honor? To feed yourselves from the first part of every offering of Israel. Your meal preceded My meal, as it is stated: Also before they caused the fat to smoke, etc. (above, verse 15).</text>
      <text title="to feed yourselves: ">(Heb. ‘l’havriachem’) An expression of a meal, similar to: Please let my sister feed me bread (Heb. ‘v’thavreni’).</text>
      <text title="before My people: ">This reverts to: And you honor your sons above Me. You showed to My people that you are more honored than I. And with what have you shown this? To feed yourselves from the first part of My offering.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="I said: ">(Heb. ‘amor amarti’) Twice I assigned greatness to the sons of Ithamar. Concerning the sons of Gershon and the sons of Merari, it is stated: Under the hand of Ithamar, the son of Aaron the Priest. (Num. 4:23, 33). And Eli was one of the descendants of Ithamar. This I found in M.S.(8:3). I have, however, heard a more fitting version, as follows: I said: Your house and your father’s house, etc. Originally, I gave the high priesthood to Eleazar the Priest, as it is stated: And remove from Aaron his garments, and put them on Eleazar, his son (Num. 20:26). At the time of the concubine (in Gibeah, v. Judges 19, 21), when the Israelites freed themselves of most of the Commandments. And who caused them (to do so)? Phinehas and his colleagues, who should have gone around from city to city to reprove them. I, (therefore) took the High Priesthood away from them, and gave it to you, for you are of the descendants of Ithamar, and I said: They shall walk before Me forever, for when greatness is assigned to someone, it is assigned to him and to his generations forever.</text>
      <text title="for those who honor Me shall I honor: ">The descendants of Phinehas who honored Me at Shittim (Num. 21:7,8). And so it came about in the days of Solomon, that when he built the Temple, Solomon dismissed Ebiathar from being a priest to the Lord, to fulfill the word of the Lord which He had spoken to the house of Eli (I Kings 2:27), and Zadok became High Priest, since he was of the descendants of Phinehas, for so he is listed in the genealogical records in the Book of Chronicles (I Chron. 6: 35 38).</text>
      <text title="and those who despise Me will be disgraced: ">By themselves, when I shall withdraw Myself from them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="I shall cut off your arm: ">I.e., the power which you exert in My House, for you say: And if not, I shall take by force.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="And you will look upon a rival in My dwelling place: ">And you will see your rival at your side in My dwelling place like a woman who sees her rival with her in the house.</text>
      <text title="in all (the days) which (God) will do good to Israel: ">(Lit., in all that which He will do good to Israel.) "When the Temple will be built in the day of Solomon, and the goodness promised to Israel will be complete, as it is said there: There has not failed one word of all His good promise, etc. (I Kings 8:56). Judah and Israel were many, like the sand which is by the sea (ibid. 4:20). And Judah and Israel dwelt in safety, every man under his vine and under his fig tree, etc. all the days of Solomon (ibid. 5:5).</text>
      <text title="and there will not be an elder in your household: ">This is an appropriate punishment. You ate sacrifices before their time, before they made the fat smoke, similarly, you will die before your time.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="and to sadden: ">(Heb. ‘v’la’div,’) same as ‘v’lad’iv.’</text>
      <text title="will die (as young) men: ">(Lit., will die men.) There is no comparison between mourning for a young man and mourning for a child.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="And this is the sign to you: ">That the prophecy will be fulfilled: In one day your two sons will die, and this will be to you a sign that all the retribution which was said to you, will be fulfilled. I.e., “And you will look upon a rival in My dwelling place, etc., and all those raised in your house will die as young men” (above 32, 33).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="a faithful priest: ">i.e., Zadok.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="for a silver piece: ">In order to earn a coin called ‘ma’ah.’</text>
      <text title="A silver piece: ">(Heb. Agorath Kesef,) a silver piece of the weights of twenty gerah (Exod. 30:13). ספחני Take me… into.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="3">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="was withheld: ">(Heb. ‘yakar,’ dear.) And similarly, (Prov. 17:27) ‘y’kar ruach’ one whose breath is dear is an understanding man, meaning, one whose speech is withheld is an understanding man.</text>
      <text title="vision had not broken through: ">Prophecy was not revealed (Jonathan). ‘Nifratz,’ an expression similar to ‘ufaratzta,’ and you shall spread westward and eastward (Gen. 28:14).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="and Samuel was lying down: ">In his place, in the court of the Levites who watch in the Temple. Jonathan paraphrases thus: And Samuel was lying in the court of the Levites…</text>
      <text title="..in the Temple of the Lord: ">where the Ark of God was,…</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="The Lord called: ">And a voice emanated from the Temple of God, from the Holy of Holies, which called, ‘Samuel!’ The end of the above verse is connected to the beginning of the following verse. This is what is inferred by the Scriptural verse (Job 37:5): The Lord thunders wondrously with His voice….Now, Eli was a priest, and was watching from within, while Samuel was lying without. Yet, the voice jumped over Eli to Samuel. Tractate Tamid.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="had not yet known the Lord: ">(Heb. ‘terem,’) i.e., he had not yet recognized the nature of the prophetic voice. Every ‘terem’ in the Scriptures is an expression of ‘not yet,’ and is not an expression of ‘before.’ This instance proves this supposition. Furthermore, the passage: “That you do not yet fear” (Exod. 9:30), is more explicit than this. Also, “No shrub of the field was yet on the earth” (Gen. 2:5).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="and Samuel said, “Speak,…”: ">He did not mention the Name of the Deity as Eli had commanded him, for he said (to himself), “Perhaps it is another voice.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="I am about to do something: ">This is the capture of the Ark by the Philistines.</text>
      <text title="will tingle: ">(Heb. ‘t’zillenah,’) an expression similar to ‘zelz’lim,’ cymbals, retentir, in French, to resound, ring.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="beginning and ending: ">On that day, My decree upon Eli’s house will commence (to be fulfilled), for Hophni and Phinehas shall die and from then on, I shall finish My decree and complete it upon them from generation to generation, to cause them to die (as young) men of eighteen years.</text>
      <text title="beginning and ending: ">Commencant et accomplissant, in French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="that his sons are bringing disgrace upon themselves: ">(Lit. disgrace or despise themselves.) It should properly state “despise Me,” but the Scripture euphemized.</text>
      <text title="disgrace or despise (Heb. ‘m’kall’lim’: ">usually rendered ‘curse’) and likewise, every curse is an expression of irreverence and disgrace.</text>
      <text title="and he did not rebuke them: ">And he did not darken them; i.e., he did not darken their faces by removing them from their high office.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="So shall God do to you: ">like that very curse, that you shall not have worthy children. And that (curse actually) befell him (Infra 7:3), even though he told him (Eli).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="and did not conceal: ">(Deducing) from here, (our Sages) stated: A curse of a wise man, even though pronounced on condition, will be realized.</text>
      <text title="He is the Lord: ">he is Master, and everything belongs to Him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="for the Lord revealed Himself to Samuel: ">Since the Scripture stated above (2:1) “and the word of the Lord was withheld in those days,” he states here that from now on, for Samuel’s sake, He revealed Himself repeatedly.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="4">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And the word of Samuel was to all Israel, and Israel went out to war: ">I.e., the word which was said to Samuel, was fulfilled, and came to all Israel. Now, how did this misfortune (befall them)? And Israel went out to war against the Philistines.</text>
      <text title="Ebenezer (The rock of help): ">This was not yet its name, for it was first called this (name) in Samuel’s time, but here the Scripture calls it by its future name.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="and the battle spread: ">(Heb. ‘vatitosh’) similar to “and behold they were spread over the face of the earth” (Heb. ‘n’tushim’) (infra 30:16), “and they were scattered by the jaw bone,” (Heb. ‘vayinat’shu’) (Judges 15: 9).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="with every (sort of) plague in the wilderness:: ">By the Reed Sea. Jonathan, however, renders: (These are the mighty deeds of God, Who smote Egypt with every sort of plague,) and for His people He performed wonders in the wilderness. In Sifrei (Behaaloth’cha), we learned that this passage is a combination of statements. The worthy among them said, “Who will save us from the hand of this mighty God?” while the wicked among them retorted, “This is the God Who smote the Egyptians with every plague.” All the plagues which He had, He brought upon the Egyptians. Thenceforth, He has no plagues.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And a man of Benjamin: ">This was Saul, who grabbed the tablets from the hands of Goliath and fled.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="beside the road: ">By the place of the road, he was anxiously waiting.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="and his neck: ">(Heb. ‘mafrakto’) ‘targum mafrakuthei’ the bone of the neck.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="was with child, ready to give birth: ">(Heb. ‘lolath.’) We are compelled (to agree) that the meaning of this word, is ‘to give birth,’ like ‘laledeth,’ although (the daleth is missing), and there is no similar form (in the Scriptures). Menahem, (however,) joined this (with other verb forms) in the section dealing with the word, ‘yelalah,’ wailing, because her birth pangs came upon her with wailing. The root of the word ‘yelalah,’ is the ‘lamed’ alone.</text>
      <text title="had suddenly come upon her: ">They were unnatural, and that is why she died.</text>
      <text title="her pains: ">(translation follows Metzudas Zion. Rashi, however, explains it as ‘hinges’;) i.e., the hinges of the doors of her womb, in French, charniere.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="Ichabod: ">There is no glory, like ‘ein kabod.’ Similarly (Job 22:30), He will save ‘i naki’ one who is not innocent, like ‘ein naki.’</text>
      <text title="because the Ark of God has been taken: ">(Lit., to the being taken of the Ark of God.) Like “because of the being taken of the Ark of God,” but it is unnecessary to remove it from the expression of ‘to’ for the one who understands its meaning.</text>
      <text title="because the Ark of God was taken: ">In French, “envers l’etre pris,” (concerning the being taken).</text>
      <text title="and because of her father-in-law: ">and because of this misfortune that her father- in-law and husband had perished.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="5">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="the house of Dagon: ">An idol made in the likeness of a fish.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="the threshold: ">(Heb. ‘ha miftan,’) equivalent to the Mishnaic ‘askupah.’</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="and He ravaged them: ">(Heb. ‘va’y’shimmem,’) an expression of desolation (‘sh’mamah’).</text>
      <text title="with hemorrhoids: ">(‘t’chorim’ refers to) the mesentery of the large intestine; (i.e., He smote them with) a plague of the rectum. Mice would enter their recta, disembowel them, and crawl out.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="hidden: ">(Heb. ‘vayisath’ru,’ spelled with a ‘sien,’) identical with ‘vayisath’ru’ (spelled with a ‘samech,’) for it is listed in the Masora, among those words written with a ‘sien,’ and explained as though written with a ‘samech.’ I.e., there was a plague in the hidden parts of the body.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="a panic of death: ">All panics (mentioned in the Scriptures) are caused by thunder; the following is the origin thereof: “And the Lord thundered with a mighty voice on that day upon the Philistines, and He threw them into confusion” (infra 7:10). This is explained in the Aggadah of Thirty two Rules of Rabbi Eliezer, the son of Rabbi Jose the Galilean (not found in our edition).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="6">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="in what: ">In what manner shall we send it away, so that He will not be angry, and so that His wrath will be removed from us.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="a guilt offering: ">An indication that you confess that you have betrayed Him.</text>
      <text title="Then you will be cured, and it will be known to you: ">that He did this, for why wouldn’t His hand turn away from you then?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="lords of the Philistines: ">They were five, as it is stated (Jos. 13:3): “The Gazite and the Ashdodite, the Ashkelonite, the Gittite, and the Ekronite.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="עלות: ">milch cows.</text>
      <text title="upon which no yoke has (ever) come: ">This is for the test. Since these cows are not capable of pulling a load, and furthermore, they will low after their young, if the Ark will have the power to enable them to pull it by themselves, we shall know that He wrought this upon us.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="in the box: ">escrin in French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="they shut up in the house: ">(Heb. ‘kalu,’) an expression of imprisonment, ‘kele.’</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="went straight: ">(Heb. ‘vayisharnah,’ aggadically interpreted as ‘sang’ from the root ‘shir.’) This word is a grammatical hermaphrodite (possessing the preformative ‘yod’ of the masculine and the afformative ‘nun’ ‘heh’ of the feminine). This teaches us that even the young (hence masculine) recited a song, viz., “Sing aloud, sing aloud, O Ark of acacia wood! Exalt yourself with the greatness of your splendor, you who are girded with golden embroidery, you who are praised with the scroll of the palace (Moses’ scroll of the Pentateuch), and lauded with choice ornaments,” (Tractate Abodah Zarah 24b). According to its simple meaning, it is an expression meaning ‘straight,’ i.e., they followed a straight path.</text>
      <text title="and lowing as they went: ">(Heb. ‘haloch v’gao.’) This is an expression of the cry of the cattle.</text>
      <text title="Beth-shemesh: ">[The people of] Israel were there.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="and they rejoiced to see (it): ">They were gazing to see how it came alone, and out of their joy, they behaved with levity, for they did not gaze at it with awe and respect.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="open village: ">A village without a wall.</text>
      <text title="and even to the great stone: ">(Heb. ‘abel,’ mourning.) This is the aforementioned great stone, for the ‘lamed’ comes in place of the ‘nun’ (in ‘eben’), similar to ‘nishkah’ instead of ‘lishkah’ (chamber), in the book of Nehemiah (13:7), since they experienced mourning at that spot, (v. infra 6:19), they called it Abel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="seventy men, fifty thousand men: ">Jonathan renders: And He killed of the elders of the people seventy men, and of the community, fifty thousand men. Our Rabbis, however, said: Seventy men, each of whom was equal to fifty thousand, or fifty thousand men, each of whom was equal to the seventy of the Sanhedrin.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="7">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="קדשו: ">they designated (after Jonathan).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="from the day the Ark was stationed in Kiriath-jearim: ">And they saw the retribution which befell them because of the sin of the house of Eli and the mighty deed which the Holy One, Blessed be He, had performed against the Philistines.</text>
      <text title="and all the house of Israel were drawn after the Lord: ">
through Samuel who would travel from city to city, judging and reproving them. Heb. ‘va’yinahu,’ an expression of drawing, in Aramaic, similar to Jonathan, who paraphrases: And they were drawn after the worship of God. And similarly (Ez. 7:11) ‘v’lo noah bahem’ and there is no use to attract them to good. Menahem classifies this thus: ‘Va’yinahu’ is an expression of lamentation, like (Micah 2:4): ‘nehi nihyah’ “a lamentation shall be wailed.” And likewise, ‘v’lo noah bahem’ (will be explained “and they have no remorse”). And the meaning of our verse is: They lamented their evil deeds, and returned after the Lord. Another explanation is that ‘va’yinahu’ means “and they gathered.” “And all nations will be gathered into it (Jerusalem)” (Jer. 3:17). Jonathan renders: And all nations will gather (‘v’yithnahon’) to worship therein. The quotation from Ezekiel may also be rendered in this manner: neither from them, nor from their multitude… nor from their gathering.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="and drew water, and poured: ">Jonathan renders: and they poured out their hearts in repentance, like water, before the Lord. And according to its simple meaning, it is merely a symbol of humility, i.e., they implied, we are like spilled water.</text>
      <text title="and Samuel judged: ">between two litigants on monetary matters which came up between them, or concerning sins which they had committed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="and offered it up as a burnt offering: ">The kethiv is ‘vayaaleha’ fem. gender, because it was a female. Hence, our Rabbis deduced that a female animal is acceptable for a burnt offering in a private high place, in Tractate Abodah Zarah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="below Bethcar: ">below Beth-sharon (from Jonathan).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="the peak: ">(Heb. ‘shen,’ a tooth or peak) i.e., the peak of the rock.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="8">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="and they turned: ">They themselves; (i.e., ‘va’yittu’ is an intransitive verb, of the ‘kal’ or simple conjugation).</text>
      <text title="and they perverted: ">Something else; viz. justice. (I. e., ‘va’yattu’ is a transitive verb of the ‘hiph’il’ or causative conjugation.) And our Rabbis said: Samuel’s sons did not sin. They merely did not follow their father’s footsteps. While their father would travel to all places of Israel and judge them in their cities they did not do so, in order to increase the income of their sheriffs and scribes, (who were employed to summon the litigants to trial).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="And the thing was displeasing: ">because they said, ‘to judge us like all the nations.’</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="you shall warn them: ">that the fear of their king be upon them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="and to make his weapons: ">to make them craftsmen, blacksmiths and carpenters.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="for perfumers: ">who prepare perfumes and spices for women’s cosmetics.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="9">
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="into the land of Zuph: ">(Jonathan renders:) into the land wherein there was a prophet.</text>
      <text title="Zuph: ">like ‘Zopheh,’ a prophet, or seer).</text>
      <text title="lest my father cease to worry about the she-asses: ">because his worry for us will increase until he forgets the she-asses.</text>
      <text title="and worry: ">doutera in French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="our way: ">The story of the she-asses, i.e., what has become of them, for whom we have gone all this way.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="and what shall we bring to the man: ">Jonathan paraphrases: If he accepts money, what shall we bring to the man? Saul was not familiar with Samuel’s practice and thought that he would ask for a reward.</text>
      <text title="and there is no present: ">(Heb ‘t’shurah’) Jonathan renders: and there is nothing proper. This is an expression of ‘yosher,’ propriety. (The root is ‘yashor.’ The yud is missing, and the ‘tav’ is a prefix.) Menahem, however, explains ‘t’shurah’ as an expression of an offering for the privilege of seeing a king or an important person. An expression related to ‘ashurenu,’ “I behold them” (Num. 24: 17). And his opinion is acceptable to me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="a fourth of a shekel: ">one zuz of silver (from Jonathan).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Formerly in Israel: ">The author wrote this. This is not part of the statement of Saul’s servant.</text>
      <text title="for he who is called prophet today: ">(lit., to the prophet today.) The one who is called a prophet today, was formerly called a seer.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="When you come to the city, straightway: ">They prolonged their conversation in order to gaze upon Saul’s handsomeness.</text>
      <text title="to the high place: ">Jonathan renders: to the banquet hall. When Shiloh was destroyed, the high places were permitted, and they would sacrifice peace- offerings in the high place and eat together.</text>
      <text title="for he will bless the sacrifice: ">Jonathan renders: for he will break bread. For the peace-offering they recited the following benediction: Blessed are You, O Lord our God, King of the universe, Who has sanctified us with His commandments, and commanded us to eat the sacrifice.</text>
      <text title="at this time: ">just as the day exists.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="will rule over My people: ">(Heb. ‘yazor,’ will restrain,) meaning ‘will rule,’ similar to “restrained (azur) and let free” (Deut. 32:36). So is the function of the ruler, viz., to restrain the people during a war, that they do not scatter, and that they do not spread out from one another, and to restrain everyone from doing evil. In our language, we call ‘maazor’ (restraint) contenir, in French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="approached Samuel: ">(The Heb. is ‘vayigash,’ accompanied by ‘eth’ instead of the usual ‘el’, to. Therefore,) Jonathan interprets this as: And Saul met Samuel (similar to ‘vayifgash’).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="and to whom does all that is desirable in Israel belong?: ">He came here to hint to him the matter of the kingdom.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="at the head of the invited guests: ">in the place where the most important people are seated, for from the manner of the seating, it was apparent in which place the most important person sat.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="which I said to you: ">Since Samuel knew that Saul would come, he ordered to give him a handsome portion for his benefit.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="the thigh and that which was upon it: ">I.e., the thigh and the hip which is above it.</text>
      <text title="Behold that which has been reserved: ">from the portions of the invited guests, and has been set aside for you.</text>
      <text title="Place (it) before you (and) eat: ">In the final chapter of Tractate Zeb. 119b, it is established that (the waving of) the breast and thigh is (practiced) in a large (public) high place, but the waving of the breast and thigh is not (practiced) in a small (private) high place. It was, therefore, permissible for Saul to eat.</text>
      <text title="because for the appointed time it is reserved: ">because for the appointed time of the banquet, this thigh was reserved for you.</text>
      <text title="by saying, “I have invited the people.”: ">My statement was to the cook, (as follows): ‘I invited the people to the feast, and I know their number. Be careful with their portions.’ And I gave (assigned) him the portions according to their number, and this was reserved for you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="and he spoke with Saul on the roof: ">reproving him and teaching him to fear the Holy One, Blessed be He.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="to go ahead of us: ">to go far from us so that he will not overhear our conversation.</text>
      <text title="and he went ahead: ">The servant went ahead of them, and to Saul he said, “And you stand still with me.”</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="10">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="by Rachel’s tomb, in the border of Benjamin: ">Now, isn’t Rachel’s tomb in the border of Judah, in Bethlehem? Rather, (this is the meaning:) Now, they are by Rachel’s tomb, and when you will meet them, you will find them in the border of Benjamin, in Zelzah. Thus taught the Rabbis in the Tosefta of Tractate Sotah. Zelzah is a combination of the words: ‘zel l’zah,’ the shadow of the Fair One, of the Holy One, Blessed be He, Who is fair and ruddy (So described in Song of Songs 5:10). And this is Jerusalem.</text>
      <text title="is worried: ">fears concerning you, and likewise, every expression of worry (d’agah) is an expression of fear. Douter in French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="אילון תבור: ">the plain of Tabor.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="the hill of God: ">the hill of Kiriath-jearim, where the Ark of God was now (stationed).</text>
      <text title="Philistine officers: ">officers whom they had appointed over Israel for they were ruling over them and stationing officers in the cities of Israel.</text>
      <text title="a band of prophets: ">(Heb. ‘hevel n’viim’) Jonathan renders: a band of scribes. ‘Hevel’ is a band. Likewise, “The bands of sheol surrounded me” (II Sam. 22:6) is rendered: The camps of the wicked surrounded me.</text>
      <text title="from the high place: ">Jonathan renders from the banquet hall.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And it will be that when these signs will come to you: ">And you will know that my words are true, for just as these signs will have come to you, so will the matter of the kingdom be fulfilled.</text>
      <text title="do for yourself what your hand will find: ">Prepare for yourself regal garments (Jonathan), and prepare for yourself the court ceremonial.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="And you shall come down before me to Gilgal: ">And after you reign, you shall come down to Gilgal before me, i.e., before I come down.</text>
      <text title="and behold, I shall go down to you: ">at the termination of seven days after you will have gone down. תוחל shall you wait.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="another heart: ">a spirit of regal power.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And who is their father?: ">Why do you wonder about the matter “Who is the father of the prophets? Is prophecy hereditary?”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="and the matter of the kingdom he did not tell him.: ">He possessed the trait of discretion.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="and Saul… was taken: ">Even though he was not there, the lot fell upon him, for their names were written on pieces of parchment and placed in a box. Now the Prophet would insert his hand and take one piece of parchment.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="is hidden among the baggage: ">(Heb. ‘el hakelim,’ lit., to the vessels,) to the house where the comers had placed their baggage. (He did this) because he was fleeing the high position. And the Midrash Agadah of Rabbi Tanhuma (Levit. 1) explains: ‘to the vessels’ as referring to the Urim and Tummim. He said, ‘Perhaps I am not worthy of this high position. (I shall not assume it) until they ask of the Urim and Tummim.’ Thereupon they asked, and he achieved it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="whose heart God had touched: ">(Jonathan renders:) sin fearing men, in whose heart God had given fear.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="11">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="the right eye: ">(We explain this) literally, but the Midrash Agadah (MS. 14:7) (explains it figuratively): He said, “Bring me your Torah which was given by the right hand (of the Almighty),” (Deut. 33:2), and I shall burn it, because He wrote therein: “An Ammonite and a Moabite shall not enter the congregation of the Lord” (Deut. 23:3).</text>
      <text title="a reproach: ">an insult.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="after the cattle: ">after the appointed time that the cattle come in from the field.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="to his oxen: ">to his animals.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="And he counted them in Bezek: ">Our Rabbis said: (He counted them) with fragments of earthenware. (I. e., ‘bezek’ is a common noun, not the name of a place.) (Yoma 22b) (The following does not appear in certain editions of Rashi.) Another explanation is that ‘b’vezek’ means ‘with pebbles,’ i.e., he took a pebble from each one, and counted them, similar to “And he counted them with lambs” (infra 15:4), which means that he took a lamb from each one, and counted them therewith, just as they would count them with half shekels. In (Prov. 26: 8) “like a pebble for throwing in a slingshot,” the Targum uses the word ‘bizka.’ And in Midrash Yelam’denu (T. Ki Thissa 9, Buber 8) “And he counted them with lambs.” When they were poor, they were counted with pebbles; when they became rich, they were counted with lambs. Another explanation is that ‘bezek’ is the name of a place, mentioned (in Judges 1:5): “And they found Adoni-bezek in Bezek.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="Whosoever says: ">derisively, “Saul will reign over us?” give them over, and let us put them to death.</text>
      <text title="will reign: ">as a question.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="And Samuel said, etc.,… and let us renew there the kingdom: ">Since previously, there was opposition in the matter, and now they were all agreeable.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="12">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="and I have become old and hoary: ">Our Rabbis said that he aged prematurely, as it is stated in Tractate Taanith (5b).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="whose ox did I take: ">for my work.</text>
      <text title="or whose ass did I take: ">When I used to go from city to city to judge them concerning their needs, I used to go on my own ass, although I should have taken (one) of theirs.</text>
      <text title="or whom did I oppress: ">Every expression of ‘meruzah’ which follows ‘oshek’ (robbery), is an expression of “robbed and oppressed” (Deut. 28:33), one who robs the poor and oppresses them.</text>
      <text title="that I hide my eyes therewith: ">in order to hide my eyes from the judgment because of the money.</text>
      <text title="and I shall restore to you: ">all that you will say.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="and they said, “(He is) witness.”: ">(lit., ‘and he said.’ The Rabbis, taking the word literally, explain that) a bath kol (a heavenly voice) came forth and said, ‘I am witness.’ This was one of three places in which the holy spirit entered the earthly court, as it is stated in Tractate Makkoth (23b).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="Who made Moses and Aaron: ">to be prepared for His mission to take your forefathers out of Egypt.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="and I shall reason: ">or debate.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="Jerubaal: ">This is Gideon (Jud. 6:32).</text>
      <text title="Bedan: ">This is Samson who came from the tribe of Dan.</text>
      <text title="and Jephthah: ">Here are three insignificant leaders with three eminent leaders: Moses, Aaron, and Samuel, to tell you that the insignificant leader in his generation is equal to the eminent leader in his generation. Every court which is appointed over the generation must be followed as though its members were the noblest of nobility.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="both you and the king who reigns over you will be: ">Both you and the king who reigns over you will live to a ripe old age.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="the Lord’s hand will be against you and against your fathers: ">Meaning, after it was against your fathers. Our Rabbis, however, said: (Jeb. 63b) “against you and against your fathers” refers to the digging up of the dead, which is a visitation of disgrace upon the dead.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="stand and see, etc.: ">and just as through my prayer, I am able to change the seasons, similarly, if a war befell you, there would be power in my prayer to protect you against the adversary, and you had no need to ask for a king during my lifetime despite the fact that I am old.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="Is it not wheat harvest today?: ">Rain is an evil omen (Taanith 12b), and the Holy One Blessed be He is reluctant to visit retribution for nothing. Nevertheless, I have power; I shall call to the Lord, and He will send thunder and rain.</text>
      <text title="and you shall know and see: ">that it was unnecessary to ask for a king and to treat me with disrespect.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="for His great Name’s sake: ">for His Name has spread concerning you, that He is your Savior and lest the Name of His greatness be diminished.</text>
      <text title="the Lord swore: ">(Heb. ‘ho il,’) like (infra 14:24) “And Saul made the people swear (Heb. ‘vayoel’).”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="also far be it from me: ">Since you will do your part by returning to the Lord, I also, far be it from me to stop praying for you.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="13">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Saul was a year in his reign: ">(lit., a year old.) Our Rabbis of sainted memory said: Like a one year old, who did not experience the taste of sin (Yoma 22b). It may also be interpreted thus: Saul was a year in his reign, i.e., in the first year in which he was made king (and he reigned two years over Israel), and in the first year, immediately, Saul chose for himself three thousand.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="the officer of the Philistines: ">They had an officer over Israel whom they had stationed in Gibeah of Benjamin.</text>
      <text title="Let the Hebrews hear: ">that we have rebelled against the Philistines, and let them beware of them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="and also Israel has become hateful: ">Lit., they have come in bad odor with the Philistines. An expression of hatred.</text>
      <text title="after Saul to Gilgal: ">This is what Samuel had said to him (supra 10: 8), “And you shall come down before me to Gilgal.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="to the east of Beth-aven: ">(Heb. ‘kidmath’) same as ‘mizrach’ Beth- aven.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="and in the thickets: ">a place where thorns are concentrated. Epine in French (thorn).</text>
      <text title="and in the towers: ">(as a forest in which the trees and branches are bent over all around the forest,) Plisse in French (folded).</text>
      <text title="and in the pits: ">Holes [in the ground].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And some Hebrews crossed the Jordan to the land of Gad: ">to flee from before the Philistines since the Philistines were in the land of Canaan on the west side of the Jordan.</text>
      <text title="hurried after him: ">(lit. trembled after him;) i.e., they hurried to go after him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="ויוחל: ">And he waited.</text>
      <text title="to the appointed time which Samuel: ">this is a short verse, with one word missing. (We must explain:) to the appointed time which Samuel had set, or to the appointed time of Samuel. And an example of this, we find (II Samuel 4:2) “And two men, officers of troops were the son of Saul.” He should have written: were to the son of Saul (or the son of Saul had). Here too, ‘which was to Samuel’ (or ‘of Samuel’), who said to him, “Seven days shall you wait until I come to you” (supra 10:8).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Bring near to me the burnt offering: ">A stranger (non-priest) is permitted to sacrifice on a high place.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="“What have you done?”: ">Did I not say to you, ‘Behold I shall come down to you to offer up the burnt offering?’ I should offer it up, and not you.</text>
      <text title="at the appointed time of the days: ">at the beginning of the day.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="and I forced myself: ">I overcame my will, for my heart told me to wait for you, and against my will I suppressed my heart, and offered up the burnt offering.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="for now: ">Before you did this.</text>
      <text title="the Lord would have established your kingdom over Israel forever: ">for when a high position is assigned to a person, it is assigned to him and to his posterity.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="But now, your kingdom shall not continue: ">for so said Moses in the Torah, “and that he turn not aside from the commandment right or left, in order that he prolong his days, etc.” (Deut. 17:20). Hence, if he turns aside, he will not prolong his days. And if you will argue that this was not said in reference to a commandment of a Prophet, but only in reference to a commandment of the Torah, (I shall answer you that) it was already stated: “and to observe all the words of the Law,” and afterwards, “that his heart be not lifted up above his brothers, and that he turn not aside from the commandment,” (meaning) even from a commandment of a Prophet.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="who were present with him: ">(lit., who were found with him) for the people had scattered from him, and these remained.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="the valley of the ‘zeboim’: ">where the ‘zeboim’ were found. This is the creature referred to by Rabbi Meir when he said: also the zabua (The owner is considered forewarned to pay the full damage the first time it damages B.K. 16a). Jonathan renders: ‘af’aya,’ and so did our Rabbis of sainted memory, explain: ‘zabua’ is ‘eph’eh,’ a species of fierce and destructive reptiles.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="Now, not a smith was to be found: ">Not one was found at the beginning of Saul’s reign, because the Philistines who ruled over Israel, dismissed all the ironsmiths from Israel, lest they make weapons to wage war.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="And all Israel went down (to the land of) the Philistines: ">And when the Israelites needed ironsmiths to sharpen colters and axes and mattocks, they were forced to go down to the land of the Philistines.</text>
      <text title="his plowshare: ">(Heb. ‘maharashto’) ‘soc’ in French (a plowshare).</text>
      <text title="his colter: ">(Heb. ‘eitho’) ‘coutre’ in French (a colter).</text>
      <text title="his axe: ">(Heb. ‘kardumo’) ‘baisague’ in French (a twibil or axe).</text>
      <text title="his mattock: ">(Heb. ‘mahareishatho’) ‘pioche’ in French (a mattock or pickaxe).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="And there was the file for the mattocks: ">And those who found it overly troublesome to go down to the Philistines to sharpen had an implement called ‘pezirah pim,’ ‘lime’ in French (a file), which has many mouths, i.e., many sharp surfaces. They had this to sharpen the mattocks and the colters.</text>
      <text title="and the three pronged pitchforks: ">a fork made like a sort of pitchfork, which is called ‘fourche’ (a pitchfork), having three prongs.</text>
      <text title="and to set the goad: ">to sharpen it at the tip, to insert it, and set it into the handle.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="but Saul… had them.: ">(lit., and there was found to Saul) through a miracle.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="the garrison of the Philistines: ">It is the custom of soldiers to form a garrison and a raiding party. The raiding party is composed of those who spread out into a city in quest of plunder. This is called ‘gens pille’ (plunderers).</text>
      <text title="garrison: ">They are the officers who stand guard that no raiders come out of the city against them.</text>
      <text title="the other side of Michmash: ">The Philistines were encamped in Michmash and Michmash was on a mountain. And the Israelites were in a city named Geba and Geba was also at the top of a mountain, and those two mountains were opposite one another, and the valley was between them, as is stated in this episode, “and the garrison of the Philistines approached the other side of Michmash,” which is on the side toward Geba, (i.e., they approached) the valley between them.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="14">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="on the other side yonder: ">(Heb. ‘ha-laz.’) Every ‘ha’laz’ and ‘lazeh’ in the Scriptures is not an expression of ‘ha-zeh’ (this), but it is something which is opposite the speaker, and he points it out with his finger. It is not an expression of ‘cet,’ (this), but of ‘celle’ (that) in French.</text>
      <text title="on the other side yonder: ">of the valley between the two mountains.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="in the outskirts of Gibeah: ">(Heb. ‘bik’zeh’) at the edge of Gibeah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="wearing an ephod: ">(This includes the ‘hoshen’ with the) urim and tummim.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="And between the sides which Jonathan sought to cross: ">(Thus was the layout of the terrain, lit.) Thus it was made. There was a rocky crag from this side of ‘between the sides,’ and there was a rocky crag from the other side of ‘between the sides.’ The valley is called ‘between the sides,’ and it had a stone from here and a stone from here, one on this side and one on the other side, and the valley was between the two sides. It was that valley that Jonathan sought to cross.</text>
      <text title="the name of one: ">The name of one crag was Bozez and the name of the second was Seneh.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="was situated from the north: ">slanting from the north side toward Michmash.</text>
      <text title="opposite Geba: ">whence Jonathan emerged.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Wait!: ">(Heb. ‘domu’) Wait, like: “Sun, wait in Gibeon” (Jos. 10: 12), and so, “Wait for the Lord” (Ps. 37:7). If they say thus, “Wait, and we shall go up to you,” they are prosperous at this time, and they are proud.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="And if they say thus, ‘Come up to us,’ then shall we go up.: ">A fear inspired by the Holy One Blessed be He is in their heart, and they are afraid to move from their place.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And they called: ">(Heb. ‘va’ya’anu,) an expression of raising the voice.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="on his hands and on his feet: ">i.e., with all his might and running.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="in about half a furrow, (which) a yoke (of oxen plow in) a field: ">(He killed them) within the limit of a land measure, viz., the amount of half a furrow of the plowing of a yoke of oxen plowing a field.</text>
      <text title="furrow: ">(Heb. ‘ma’anah’) That is the ridge which is called ‘rainure’ (ridge or furrow) in French. It was a very mighty deed, because they were close to one another and ready to aid one another.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="Saul’s lookouts: ">the lookouts whom Saul had in Gibeah of Benjamin. Lookouts (Heb. ‘zophim’) ‘esculca’ in Old French.</text>
      <text title="and behold the multitude: ">of the Philistines wandered from its place and continuously came nearer to there, to the side of the Israelites.</text>
      <text title="wandering: ">Like ‘wandering and moving.’</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="Inspect: ">An expression of supervision, like “And should inspect him every morning” (Job 7:18).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="Bring near the Ark of God: ">Urim and Tummim.</text>
      <text title="for the Ark of God was on that day: ">This verse is missing one word: for the Ark of God was there on that day.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="And the Hebrews (who) were with the Philistines: ">at their aid out of fear, in earlier times, today they too turned with their fellows to be at the assistance of their brethren.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="And the men of Israel were hard pressed: ">They were being rushed and pressed to wage war against the Philistines.</text>
      <text title="adjured: ">(Heb. ‘va’yo’el.’) an expression of an oath.</text>
      <text title="who will eat food: ">(Heb. ‘lehem,’ lit. bread) All food is included in the meaning of this word, like “Let us destroy the tree with its fruit.” (Heb. ‘b’lahmo’) (Jer. 11:19).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="and there was honey: ">Cane sugar grows in Eretz Israel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="a flow of honey: ">which was flowing from the canes.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="into the honeycomb.: ">(Heb. ‘ya’rath D’vash,’ lit. the forest of honey.) into the sugar cane, like “and she placed it in the reeds” (Exod. 2:3) which Onkelos renders: and she placed it in the ‘yaar,’ and reeds are grasses which grow in the swamp. (Hence, we find that a group or clump of grasses or canes, may be referred to as ‘yaar.’) And so, “I ate my sugar cane with my sugar,” (S. of S. 5:1), and in Arabic, that honey is called ‘sukra’ in their language. (sic) From Rabbi Nathan the Ishmaelite.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="My father has perturbed the land: ">(Heb. ‘achar’) He confused their thoughts, and (hindered) their salvation, like unclear water (‘maim 'achurim’).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="would there not now have been a greater slaughter among the Philistines?: ">This is a question.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="And the people flew: ">(Heb. ‘va’ya’at,’) similar to ‘va’yo’at bahem’ (infra 25:14) “and he drove them away (He made them fly),” an expression of ‘ayit’ (birds of prey) who swoop down on their victims (Gen. 15:11).</text>
      <text title="sheep, and oxen, and calves: ">(lit., oxen and young of oxen) I say that this was a violation of the precept: You must not slaughter it and its young on the same day (Lev. 23:28). He, therefore, called them sinners (infra v. 33). But our Rabbis said in Tractate Zebahim (120a) that they sanctified them for peace- offerings, and they were eating before the sprinkling of the blood. This is what the Scripture means when it states: “And the people ate with the blood,” they ate when the blood was yet in the basin.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="Roll to me: ">(Heb. ‘golu’) like ‘gil’lu.’</text>
      <text title="this day: ">while it is yet daytime, and below (v. 34) it is stated: and all the people brought near, each man his ox in his hand that night. 0ur Rabbis at the end of Tractate Zebahim (120a) hold diverse views. Some of them explain: Here (v. 34) (the Scripture is referring to) ordinary animals, while here (v. 33) (the Scripture is referring to) sacrificial animals. Others explained: Here (v. 33) (the Scripture is referring to) sacrificial animals which were sanctified to be offered at the large high place in Nob, while here (v. 34) (the Scripture is referring to) sacrificial animals which were sanctified to be offered at a small high place. The Scripture thereby teaches us that a private burnt offering may be slaughtered at night (in a small, or private high place).</text>
      <text title="a huge stone: ">He made it a high place to sprinkle the blood thereon and for burning the fatty parts.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="Disperse among the people: ">Announce in many places, and let the announcers disperse among the people.</text>
      <text title="and you shall slaughter here.: ">(Heb. ‘bazeh,’ lit. ‘in this’ or ‘with this’) Here is the place of slaughtering. Another explanation is: He examined a slaughtering knife for them.</text>
      <text title="that night: ">The ordinary animals were slaughtered at night. Thus it is explained in Zeb.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="with that one he started: ">That altar was the first of the altars which Saul built.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="38">
      <text title="you chiefs of the people: ">(lit., the corners of the people) i.e., the chiefs of the people. The cornerstone is the most esteemed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="40">
      <text title="to one side: ">to cast lots between all of you, and us.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="41">
      <text title="Give a perfect lot: ">Give a true lot.</text>
      <text title="and the people escaped: ">innocent, from the lot.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="45">
      <text title="and the people redeemed Jonathan: ">They nullified Saul’s oath for him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="48">
      <text title="ויעש חיל: ">And he gathered an army.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="50">
      <text title="Abner the son of Ner: ">And Ner was Saul’s uncle, the brother of Kish, and they were both the sons of Abiel. Abiel was also known as Ner, in (I) Chron. (8:33), because he would light candles for the public in the dark streets.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="52">
      <text title="And when Saul would see: ">This is a present tense, meaning: And when Saul would see a valiant soldier, he would bring him in to himself.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="15">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="and now, hearken to the voice of the words of the Lord: ">Once you acted foolishly. Now, take heed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="ox and sheep: ">for they were sorcerers, and they would change themselves to resemble animals.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="And Saul called… together: ">An expression of announcing, as though it would say, שאול ויזעק.</text>
      <text title="and he counted them in Telaim: ">(According to ‘peshat,’ this is the name of a place, as in Jos. 15:24. Our Rabbis, however, take it as a common noun, meaning ‘with lambs,’ explaining thus:) He told everyone to take a lamb from the King’s flocks, since it is forbidden to count Jews, for it is stated concerning them: “which will not be counted for multitude” (Gen. 32:12).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="and he fought in the valley: ">(וירב) and he fought in the valley (from ריב, a quarrel). Our Rabbis said: Concerning the valley, he argued and concluded, thus: if for the sake of one soul, the Torah said, “decapitate a calf in the valley” (Deut. 21), how much more for the sake of all these souls. If man has sinned, what have the animals sinned?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="to the Kenites: ">the descendants of Jethro, who were residing in the wilderness of Judea, in the south of Arad, who went to Jabez to learn Torah, Arad being Amalek. The Canaanite king of Arad was Amalek, for it is stated: “the dweller of the South” (Num. 21:1), and “Amalek dwells in the Southland” (ibid. 12:29).</text>
      <text title="with all the children of Israel: ">for Moses, Aaron, and all the elders of Israel partook of his (Jethro’s) repast (Ex. 18:12). (The Scripture, therefore) considers it as though he had done kindness with all the children of Israel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="and the fatlings: ">(Heb. ‘vehamishnim.’) It has no likeness (to any other word in the Scriptures). These are the fatlings, and I say that the expression of ‘mishnim’ is like ‘kesef mishneh’ (double money Gen. 43:15) because they are doubled over with flesh and fat. Similarly, (we explain:) “And the ox which was fattened (sheni) seven years.” (Jud. 6:25).</text>
      <text title="vile and feeble: ">(נמבזה) like נבזה (despised), and the ‘mem’ is superfluous.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="I regret: ">A thought has arisen in my heart concerning the kingdom of Saul, whom I have appointed king.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="he is setting up a place for himself: ">He is building an altar for himself. That is the altar referred to concerning Elijah, “And he repaired the altar of the Lord, which had been torn down.” Jonathan however, renders: and behold, he is setting up there a place for himself, to divide the spoils.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="Desist: ">Like the Targum, ‘orich,’ meaning ‘wait’.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="are you not the head of the tribes of Israel: ">Jonathan renders: The tribe of Benjamin crossed the Reed Sea at the head of the people, as it is said: “Benjamin, the youngest, rules over them” (Ps. 68: 28).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="until they destroy them: ">The people who are with you will destroy them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="but you flew: ">(ותעט,) like ותעף (and you flew), an expression relating to עיט, bird of prey (Gen. 15:11).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="the best of the ban: ">(ראשית, lit., the beginning), and similarly, “the best of your corn” (Deut. 18: 4), as it is said: “When you separate the best part of it therefrom” (Num. 18:30). Jonathan however, renders: before they banned it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="Behold, to obey: ">His command is better than a peace-offering.</text>
      <text title="to hearken, than the fat of rams.: ">This refers to: Behold, to obey is better than a peace- offering, and to hearken (is better) than the fat of rams.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="For rebellion is as the sin of divination, and stubbornness is as idolatry and teraphim: ">And like the penalty for idolatry and teraphim, so is the penalty for stubbornness. Jonathan renders: for, as the sin of a people who divine, so is the sin of any man who disobeys the word of the Lord; and as the sins of a nation who has strayed after idols, so is the sin of any person who adds to the words of a prophet.</text>
      <text title="stubbornness: ">An expression of adding, and similarly, (Gen. 36:11) He prevailed upon him (ויפצר). He spoke many words to convince him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="I feared the people: ">Doeg the Edomite, who was as esteemed as all of them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="and he seized the skirt of his robe: ">According to the simple interpretation, the implication is that when Samuel turned to go away from following Saul, Saul seized the skirt of Samuel’s robe, since Saul was entreating him to return until he would prostrate himself in Gilgal, where the tent of meeting had been. In Midrash Aggadah, however, Amoraim differ on this point. Some say that Saul tore Samuel’s robe, and some say that Samuel tore Saul’s robe, thereby giving over to him this sign, that whoever would sever the skirt of his robe would reign in his place. And that is what Saul said to David on the day that he severed the robe, “I know that you will reign” (infra 24:21).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="And also, the Strength of Israel will neither lie: ">And if you say, “I shall repent of my sin before Him, it will no longer avail to take the kingdom from the one to whom it was given, for the Holy One, Blessed be He, Who is the Strength of Israel, will not lie by not giving the good to whom He promised to give it.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="And Agag went to him delicately: ">(Heb. ‘ma’adanoth.’) Jonathan renders: delicately.</text>
      <text title="Surely, the bitterness of death has turned.: ">Indeed, I know that the bitterness of death has turned toward me, and is approaching.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="As your sword bereaved women: ">to render them veritable widows from their husbands, for you would cut off the membrum virile of the youths of Israel.</text>
      <text title="And he hewed: ">(וישסף) He cut him into four pieces. There is no similarity to this word. The Targum renders: ‘ufashah.’ And in our Gemara (i.e., T.B., Bets. 33b) we find: He broke a branch off (‘m’fashah’), and gave us each several sticks, meaning that he split.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="16">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="the Bethlehemite: ">(בית-הלחמי,) from Bethlehem, and so is the rule of every noun which is composed of two words, e. g., Beth-lehem, Beth-shemesh, Beth-el, Kiriath-arba, if one wishes to add a ‘heh’ (definite article) thereto, he adds it between the two words, e.g., Kiriath-ha’arba (Gen. 35:27), בית-האלי (I Kings 16:34), בית-הלחמי.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="hurried: ">(lit., trembled) hurried out toward him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="that he said, “Surely, before the Lord is His anointed.”: ">and he said to himself, “Surely, it is true that this one is fitting for the kingdom.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="Look not upon his appearance: ">upon the beauty of his form.</text>
      <text title="for I have rejected him: ">because he is an irascible person, as it is stated: “And Eliab’s wrath was kindled against David” (infra 17:29).</text>
      <text title="for it is not as man sees: ">Even though you called yourself ‘seer,’ for you said to Saul, “I am the seer,” (supra 9:19), here I inform you that you do not see.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Shammah: ">That is Shimeah (mentioned in II Sam. 12:3; II Chron. 2:13).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="The youngest still remains: ">(Heb. שאר, kal conj. active) This is like נשאר (remains, niph’al conj. passive).</text>
      <text title="we will not sit down: ">(לא נסב) We will not sit down to eat. Every instance of sitting down to a meal is called הסבה (leaning).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="And a spirit of the Lord passed: ">a spirit of valiance.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="your servants are before you: ">Behold, your servants are before you, who will do your bidding.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="one of the young men: ">The special one of the young men, Doeg the Edomite.</text>
      <text title="who knows how to play: ">With his entire essence, he intended to introduce Saul’s evil eye into David, i.e., that he envy him.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="17">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="in Ephes-dammim: ">This is the name of the place.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="the champion: ">A hero who would emerge from his battle array, to stand between the two arrays.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="and a coat of mail: ">scales like those of fish, made of iron, spread over the coat (another version, the holes of the coat), a scale for each hole.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="greaves of copper: ">a sort of copper handle, extending from the helmet, opposite the nose, called ‘nasal’ in French, and it reached the feet.</text>
      <text title="and a copper javelin: ">Jonathan renders: ומסחפא דנחשא נפיק מן קולסא ומטל בין כתפוהי A sort of copper javelin, protruding from the helmet, and extending between his shoulders, to protect his neck from the sword.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="כמנור אורגים: ">like a weaver’s beam - (Jonathan) ‘ensouple’ in French (cylinder in a loom).</text>
      <text title="six hundred shekels: ">All shekels mentioned in the Prophetic books, are ‘maneh’s’.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="Why should you come out: ">i.e., Why should all of you come out to wage war? Let one fight against me for all of you, and on the condition which is specified: if he is able to fight with me, etc.</text>
      <text title="Am I not the Philistine, and you the servants of Saul?: ">I am neither a captain over a hundred, nor a captain over a thousand. I am but a Philistine like one of the others, even though I have fought many wars for them. I killed Hophni and Phinehas, and I captured the Ark. You, on the other hand, have become servants to Saul, although he never saved you with his heroism.</text>
      <text title="Choose for yourselves: ">(ברו לכם. The root is ברר). Hence, it is like בררו לכם, (with two ‘resh’es’).</text>
      <text title="a man: ">Saul, and let him come down to me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And David was the son of this Ephrathite man: ">Bethlehem is situated in the land of Ephrath.</text>
      <text title="and he had eight sons: ">And that which is stated (in I Chron. 2:15), “Ozem the sixth, David the seventh,” and he states no more, may be reconciled by supposing that one died without children. He was, therefore, not counted there.</text>
      <text title="among men: ">counted in the assemblies of the esteemed men.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="And David was the youngest: ">who had heretofore been in Saul’s palace to play music before him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="Now David went: ">would always go to and fro from Saul to his father’s house.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="morning and evening: ">Our Rabbis said: (He did this) in order to prevent them from reciting ‘Shema.’</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="חריצי החלב: ">cheeses (Jonathan).</text>
      <text title="to the captain of the thousand: ">I say (that Jesse meant) “to the captain of that thousand to which I belong,” for all the tribes had captains of thousands “according to their thousands” (This last phrase is vague). I have heard, however, that ‘to the captain of the thousand’ refers to Jonathan, concerning whom the Scripture states: “And a thousand were with Jonathan in Gibeah of Benjamin.” (supra 13:3).</text>
      <text title="and the tidings of their welfare you shall take: ">And the assurance of their salvation and their welfare you shall take into your ears and your heart, and you shall relate it to me. And so did Jonathan render: ‘and their welfare.’</text>
      <text title="their welfare: ">(Heb. ‘arubatham,’) an expression of salvation, like (Ps. 119:112).“Assure your servant for good,” ‘garantir’ in French. Our Rabbis said: He should take a bill of divorcement from them, and deliver it to their wives, to break the connection between man and wife (lit., between him and her).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="to the barricade: ">They would form a circle around the camp, and whoever would go out of the circle, either ahead of or behind the camp, would be liable (to death); ahead, lest the men of the enemy armies attack him, and behind, since he seeks to desert.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="And the Israelites… put: ">(The feminine form is used, referring to) the army of Israel, (which is grammatically feminine).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="the keeper of the baggage: ">of the soldiers.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="from the ranks of the Philistines: ">The ‘kethib’ is ממערות פלשתים. Our Rabbis expounded the word מערות : as ממאה ערלות (from 100 foreskins) meaning that one hundred men were intimate (הערו) with his mother Orpah, when she parted with Ruth and her mother-in-law Naomi.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="and he will make his father’s house free: ">from the things mentioned in the laws of the kingdom.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="ובא הארי ואת הדוב: ">and also a bear (Jonathan).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="Both the lion and the bear: ">These three words (גם את גם) are of inclusive nature, meaning a lion and its two whelps, and a bear and its two cubs.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="The Lord Who saved me from the paw of the lion: ">I know that this incident did not occur to me for naught, but as an indication that in the future, I would come through similar circumstances, to a salvation for Israel. And I shall rely upon this, and go out. And he was one of the two righteous men, to whom the Almighty gave a hint, and they took heed, to understand the matter, viz., David and Mordecai, as it is stated: “And everyday, Mordecai would walk before the courtyard, etc.” (Es. 2:11) He said, “It is not for nothing that this righteous woman (Esther) has been taken into the bed of this uncircumcised one (Ahasuerus). It can only mean that she is destined to stand up for the Jews in a day of distress.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="38">
      <text title="David with his garments: ">They changed to David’s size, (explaining מדיו from מדה, a measure, cf., Lev. 6:3) since he had been anointed with the anointing oil, although they belonged to Saul who was taller than any of the people, from his shoulder and upward (supra 9:2), and when Saul noticed this, he cast an envious glance toward him, and David realized it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="39">
      <text title="ויאל ללכת: ">and he did not want to go (in them - Jonathan.) (Despite the fact that ויאל usually means, he wanted, [cf., Ex. 2:21],) there are words which have two opposite definitions, e.g., “will cut off a branch (Is. 10:32),” (using מסעף, will cut off, derived from סעיף, a branch). And he will uproot you from the land of the living (Ps 52:7), (using ושרשך, will uproot you, derived from שרש, a root). כי לא נסה for he was not accustomed (after Jonathan).</text>
      <text title="for I am not accustomed: ">(Heb. לא נסיתי (Jonathan explains this as derived from נס, a miracle, and, therefore, renders:) for there is no miracle in them, i.e., there will be no praise for the miracle in this manner. Another explanation is ויאל ללכת - he wanted to go, and to try, when he saw that they were too heavy for him, he took them off.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="40">
      <text title="five smooth pebbles: ">five thin, smooth stones.</text>
      <text title="and in the sack: ">(Jonathan renders:) ובתרמיליה.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="44">
      <text title="and to the cattle of the field: ">It is not customary for cattle to eat human (sic) flesh. Said David “This one’s mind is already deranged (like one who is close to death). He is mine.” David then came and said “… and I shall give the carcasses of the camp of the Philistines… and to the beasts of the earth (not to the cattle).”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="49">
      <text title="and he fell on his face to the ground: ">He should have fallen backwards since he had been struck in the forehead. But, (he fell forward) in order that David should not be troubled to walk and sever his head, for David saved twelve cubits and two spans. Since his height was six cubits and a span, David saved (a walk of) his entire height back and his entire height forth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="53">
      <text title="from pursuing: ">(מדלק) Same as מרדף, similar to “you have pursued me” (דלקת) (Gen. 31: 36).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="55">
      <text title="Whose son is this youth,: ">Our Rabbis said: Did he not recognize him? Is it not stated: “And he became his weapon bearer” (supra 16:21)? But, (rather this is the explanation): he saw him behaving in a kingly manner. (Vid. supra v. 38) Said Saul, “If he comes from the family of Perez, he will be a king, for the king may break fences (פורץ, related to פרץ) to make a way for himself, and no one may stop him. If, however, he comes from the family of Zerah, he will merely become an esteemed person. Said Doeg to him, ” Before you ask whether or not he is descended from a family which qualifies him for the throne, ask whether or not he is qualified to enter the congregation, (i.e., whether or not he may marry among Jews) since he is descended from Ruth the Moabitess.“ Said Abner to him, ” We have learned: An Ammonite (is forbidden, Deut. 23:3) but not an Ammonitess. (Similarly, a Moabite is forbidden, but not a Moabitess.) “ Said Doeg to him, ” If so (let us say), a ‘mamzer’ (the male issue of a union forbidden under penalty of extinction is forbidden,) and not a ‘mamzereth’ (the female issue of such a union).“ He replied, ” It is stated here: Because they did not meet you with bread and water (v. 5 ibid.), and it is not customary for a woman to do so.“ He said to him,” Men should have met men, and women should have met women." Abner became silent. Saul said to him:</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="56">
      <text title="You ask whose son this youth is: ">Above (v. 55) it is written: הנער, and here it is written העלם. He said to him, “This law has escaped your memory (נתעלמה). Go out and ask in the academy.” This is as it is stated in Jeb. 77a.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="18">
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="and with cymbals: ">(ובשלשים) - Jonathan renders: and with cymbals, a type of musical instrument.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="“… And what more can he have…”: ">(lit., and he has yet; i.e.,) What more is he lacking, that he needs to acquire…</text>
      <text title="but the kingdom?: ">He needs nothing else but the kingdom.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="eyed: ">with an envious glance.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="and he raved: ">(lit., he prophesied. Jonathan renders:) and he raved. A prophet and a mad man speak with unintelligible hints.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="“I shall pin David to the wall,”: ">(lit., I shall strike David and the wall) I shall strike one blow that the spear will pierce David and the wall.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="and Saul said: ">to himself (lit., in his heart).</text>
      <text title="Let not my hand be upon him: ">lest I be punished.</text>
      <text title="but let the hand of the Philistines be upon him.: ">Therefore, he said to him, ‘… and wage the wars of the Lord.’</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="at the time that Merab, Saul’s daughter, should have been given: ">When the time which they had set to give her to him arrived, and while they were occupied with giving her to him, the matter turned out that she was given to Adriel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="With two, shall you become my son-in-law: ">I have two daughters. Through one of them, will you become my son-in-law. And so did Jonathan render: with one of two. Similar to this, (we find:) Three things I cast upon you (II Sam. 24:12), meaning, one of three things. As it is explained there, “Choose for yourself one of them.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="and the days had not expired: ">He did not wait until the expiration of the days which he had set for him to bring the hundred foreskins.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="and they delivered them in full: ">Presenter in French (to present).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="afraid: ">(לרא), equivalent to ליראה (to fear).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="And the princes of the Philistines came out: ">to come in troops to plunder the Israelites.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="19">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="beside my father: ">(lit., at the hand of my father.) Near my father, ‘en son aise’ (‘on his side,’ from Latin ‘adiacentia,’ adjacent) in Old French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="she put… at its head: ">since the teraphim has no hair, and this resembles human hair.</text>
      <text title="And Michal took: ">so that they should not understand that he fled, and pursue him.</text>
      <text title="the teraphim: ">made in the likeness of a human body.</text>
      <text title="a goatskin: ">A hide skinned in one piece, like a skin bottle. Flocete in French (a hairy stuff).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="He said to me, ‘Let me go, etc.’: ">You delivered me into the hands of a bandit. He drew his sword over me until I allowed him to leave.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="and stayed in Naioth: ">(lit., dwellings; Jonathan renders:) in the house of study.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="the company: ">להקת, reversed from קהלת a company (Jonathan).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="And he too stripped off his clothes: ">his royal garments, to don the garments of the disciples.</text>
      <text title="And he fell naked: ">(Rashi’s commentary, as it appears in available editions, is very difficult, and probably erroneous. I should like to take the liberty to emend the text to read:) And he fell naked. Jonathan renders: ונפל ברשן, and in the name of Rabbi Menahem, who heard from an Arab, ברשן in Arabic means insane.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="20">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="there is but a step between me and death: ">With (or about) one step I drew away from before him, and he drove the spear into the wall. With that step, I was saved from death.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="Behold tomorrow is the new moon: ">(Heb. ‘hodesh,’ from ‘hadash,’ new.) The renewal of the moon. And of all those who eat at the King’s table, no one refrains from coming to the repast on the festive day.</text>
      <text title="and I am accustomed to eat with the king: ">(ואנכי ישב אשב) This is the present tense meaning ‘and I am accustomed to sit with the king regularly to eat beside him.’</text>
      <text title="And you shall let me go: ">from now, and I shall hide until the evening of the third day, and I shall not be with the eaters and my seat will be vacant, and the king will wonder about me either tomorrow or the day after tomorrow.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="took leave: ">(lit., asked) He asked me for permission.</text>
      <text title="the yearly sacrifice: ">from year to year at this time.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="If he says thus, ‘Good’: ">i.e., he is not angry.</text>
      <text title="then it is well with your bondsman: ">He does not have in mind to kill me.</text>
      <text title="but if he becomes angry: ">This is proof that he wants me to be accessible to him to kill me.</text>
      <text title="the evil has been decided upon by him: ">(lit., the evil has been ended from him) - The end of the matter is, that he has an evil thought concerning me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="And you shall do kindness: ">to let me go.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Far be it from you: ">to suspect me thus, that I should know that evil has been decided upon by him, and not reveal it to you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="Who will tell me: ">in the place where I shall be hidden?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="(By) the Lord God of Israel: ">This is an expression of an oath.</text>
      <text title="the third morrow: ">of the following day. That means the third day at this time, for tomorrow is the new moon, and perhaps my father will not wonder (about your absence) tomorrow, but will wonder on the third day.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="So shall do to me: ">the Holy One, Blessed be He. (This is an obvious error, and should read:)</text>
      <text title="So shall the Lord do to Jonathan.: ">When I sound out my father and find that he is favorable toward you if I do not send by way of messenger and reveal to you, for good I am able to reveal. And if it pleases my father to do evil to you, that I shall not reveal (by messenger), lest your whereabouts become known to my father, but I myself, shall reveal it to you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="And please, if I am still alive.: ">(ולא אם עודני חי) An expression of request, like ולא and if only it will be given to your bondsman (II Kings 5:17). It is, however, not removed from its usual sense, i.e., “and will you not do with me the kindness of the Lord before I die?” And what is the kindness? That you will not discontinue your kindness with my household. Regarding this, you shall make a covenant with me in my lifetime.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="and not even when the Lord cuts off: ">And also, you shall not remove your kindness from them (מהם) even when retribution befalls my father’s house, for I know that the Lord will cut off your enemies.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="and the Lord demanded it: ">this covenant.</text>
      <text title="from the hand of David’s enemies: ">The Scripture euphemized. Its real meaning is: The Holy One, Blessed be He, demanded the punishment of the transgression from David’s hand. When he transgressed the covenant, and said to Mephibosheth, “You and Ziba shall divide the field” (II Sam. 19:30), a bath-kol came forth, and said, “Rehoboam and Jeroboam shall divide the kingdom.” And so did Jonathan render: and the Lord took retribution from David’s enemies.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="Tomorrow is the new moon: ">and it is the custom of all those who eat at the king’s table to come on the festive day to the table.</text>
      <text title="and you will be remembered: ">My father will remember you, and ask where you are.</text>
      <text title="for your seat will be vacant: ">for your seat in which you sit, will be vacant, and so did Jonathan render: and you will be sought, for your seat will be vacant.</text>
      <text title="and you will be remembered: ">[ונפקדת is] an expression of remembering.</text>
      <text title="will be vacant: ">[יפקד is] an expression of lacking.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="And for three days you shall hide very well: ">And you shall triple the days, and then you shall descend very much, i.e., when the third day arrives, you shall descend into a secret place, and hide very well, for then they will seek you. And you shall come to this secret place, wherein you are hiding today, which is a workday. And so did Jonathan render: on the weekday, for he hid on that day, as it is stated: (infra v. 24) “And David hid in the field;” immediately, “and it was the new moon” on the morrow.</text>
      <text title="the travelers’ stone: ">(Heb. ‘even-ha azel,’ lit., the going stone, i.e.) a stone which was a sign (a landmark) for travelers.</text>
      <text title="Ha-azel: ">those who go on the road. And so did Jonathan render: even atha, the stone which was a sign.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="to the side, I shall shoot: ">This is not a ‘mappiq-heh’ (aspirate ‘heh’). צדה is to be interpreted like לצד, to a side, for every word which requires a ‘lamed’ as a prefix, the Scripture gives a ‘he’ as a suffix. (Jeb. 13b) At the side of that stone, I shall shoot arrows to a mark, so that the youth will not understand, and this sign shall be for you to divine whether you must flee.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="And behold, I shall send, etc.: ">And it is customary for one who seeks an arrow which has been shot, to go to the place where he sees the arrow flying, but he cannot ascertain exactly. Sometimes he searches for it, and the arrow is beyond him, and sometimes he goes beyond the arrow and searches for it, and you shall have this sign.</text>
      <text title="If I say to the youth… take it and come: ">you yourself emerge from your hiding place, and take it, and come to me, for you have not to fear, for it is well with you. The Holy One Blessed be He, desires that you be here, and even if I have heard evil from Father.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="But, if I say thus… Go! For the Lord has sent you away: ">The Holy One Blessed be He tells you to flee and escape.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="And concerning the matter which we have spoken: ">the covenant which we made together.</text>
      <text title="behold, the Lord is between me and you: ">as Witness concerning that matter.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="the seat by the wall: ">at the head of the couch beside the wall.</text>
      <text title="and Jonathan arose: ">He got up from his place, since it is not proper for a son to recline beside his father. Since their custom was to eat reclining on couches and David would recline between Jonathan and Saul, now that David did not come, Jonathan did not recline until Abner sat down beside Saul, and afterwards, Jonathan sat beside Abner. And if you say that he did not sit at all, the Scripture states: (infra v. 34) “And Jonathan arose from the table,” implying that he had been sitting.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="It is an incident: ">He has experienced a seminal emission.</text>
      <text title="he is not clean: ">and he has not yet immersed himself, for had he immersed himself for the uncleanness of his emission, he would not have to wait until sunset in order to eat ordinary food.</text>
      <text title="for he is not clean: ">This clause gives the reason for the matter; i.e., since he is not clean, he, therefore, did not come, lest he contaminate the feast.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="on the morrow of the new moon: ">on the morrow of the renewal of the moon.</text>
      <text title="the second: ">on the second day of the month.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="and he, my brother, commanded me: ">The eldest of the house, commanded me that I be there. And he is my brother Eliab.</text>
      <text title="let me slip away: ">‘Escamoter’ in French. I shall go away for one day and come back.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="a straying woman, deserving of punishment: ">(בן נעות המרדות) An expression of straying and wandering, נע ונד, a gadding woman. Just as you say זעוה from זע, and the ‘tav’ is for the construct state, for it is connected to the word המרדות.</text>
      <text title="deserving of punishment: ">(Heb. המרדות), who deserves to be chastised and disciplined. Another explanation is as follows: When the men of Benjamin grabbed the girls of Shiloh, who came out to dance in the vineyards (Jud. 21:21), Saul was bashful, and did not want to grab [a girl], until she came herself, behaving insolently, and pursued him. נעות because of the vineyards. And that is a winepress, like (the Talmudical passage): Purge the winepress (which was used for forbidden wine) (Ab. Zarah 74b); His winepresses will drip with wine (Targum Onkelos, Gen. 40:12)….(The last three words of Rashi are incomprehensible, and are probably erroneous. The correct version is unknown to us.)</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="he was grieved (lit.) to David: ">concerning David.</text>
      <text title="for his father had put him to shame: ">concerning David.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="at David’s appointed time: ">at the time which David had set for him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="to cause it to go beyond him.: ">The arrow went beyond the boy.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="41">
      <text title="from a place toward the south: ">(lit., from by the south. Jonathan renders:) from the side of the travelers’ (or sign) stone which was toward the south.</text>
      <text title="until David exceeded: ">He cried more.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="42">
      <text title="Go in peace!: ">And the oath which we have sworn, may the Lord be witness thereon forever.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="21">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And I troubled the young men: ">(Heb. ‘va’yada’) An expression of troubling. The young men who came out with me, I have troubled them to run before me to a hidden, secret place.</text>
      <text title="I troubled: ">similar to, “And with them he broke (va’yoda) the men of Succoth” (Jud. 8:16).</text>
      <text title="hidden, secret: ">(Heb. ‘ploni almoni.’) ‘Almoni’ is derived from ‘almon’ (a widower), bereft of a name, (as a widower is bereft of his spouse), for I do not wish to mention it, since it is a secret matter.</text>
      <text title="hidden: ">(Heb. ‘ploni,’) like: ‘ki yipalei’ (Deut. 17:8), which means ‘will be concealed.’</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="or whatever is found.: ">If there are not five, give me whatever is found in your possession.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="but… from women: ">With difficulty, I give them to strangers (non-priests) to eat, but it is impossible to give it to unclean people.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="withheld from us.: ">lit., withheld to us.</text>
      <text title="and the young men’s garments are hallowed: ">i.e., ritually clean.</text>
      <text title="and that is in a manner common: ">and the bread, since it has been removed from the table, and they have burned the spoonfuls (of frankincense), it is almost common, since it has been excluded from the prohibition of ‘me’ilah’ (betrayal) from the time it is permitted for the priests.</text>
      <text title="and even if today it would be hallowed in the vessel: ">and even if today were the commencement of its sanctity on the table, I should (or perhaps it should read, ‘you would’) be obliged to take it from there and feed us, for a ravenous hunger has seized me, and my life is in danger. Thus it is explained in Men. (95b).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="to place warm bread: ">i. e., other warm bread on the day this was taken away. And our Rabbis said: Warm on the day it was taken - It was as warm on the day it was taken as it was on the day it was arranged.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="detained before the Lord: ">he tarried before the tent of meeting to engage in Torah.</text>
      <text title="the chief of Saul’s shepherds: ">the head of the tribunal.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="ואין יש פה: ">And if there is here.</text>
      <text title="urgent: ">hurried.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="wrapped: ">(Heb (לוטה wrapped, and so: “and be wrapped (וילט) his face in his mantle” (I Kings 19:13).</text>
      <text title="behind the ephod: ">(after the ephod) after he had consulted the Urim and Tummim for him. And so did Jonathan render: after he asked the ephod for him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="Is this not David the king of the land?: ">They said to Achish, There was a stipulation between us, (supra 17:9) “If he is able to fight with me and kill me, we shall be slaves to you.” You have nothing to do but get off your throne and let him become king of this land.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="אתטעמו: ">his speech. ויתהולל and he feigned insanity.</text>
      <text title="and he scribbled: ">he wrote.</text>
      <text title="his saliva: ">(Heb. ‘riro’) his saliva. Anything which drips is called ‘rir,’ and so: “in saliva (b’rir) of health” (Job 6:7), and so: “whether his flesh run (rar)” (Lev. 15:3).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="Will this one: ">(הזה)</text>
      <text title="come into my house?: ">This is a question form. It is therefore punctuated by a “hataf patah” (under the ‘heh’), and (the ‘zain’) is not punctuated by a ‘dagesh.’</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="22">
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="and they stayed with him all the time that David was in the stronghold: ">near Moab, and when David went away from there to the forest of Heresh, the king of Moab slew his father, mother, and brothers, with the exception of one of them, whom Nahash the Ammonite preserved alive. And that is the kindness which David (meant when he) said, (II Sam. 10:2) “As his father did kindness with me,” as it is stated in the Mid. of Rabbi T. (T. Buber, Vayera 25).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="that David… had become known: ">for he investigated, to beware of him.</text>
      <text title="under the tamarisk tree on a hill: ">(Heb. ‘b’ramah,’) on one hill, which was in the border of Benjamin. Our Rabbis, however, said: This was Samuel’s Ramah, and since these are two distinct places, it is expounded thus: Saul was sitting in Gibeah through the merit of the great tamarisk tree (Samuel) who was in Ramah, and was praying for him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="and by inquiring of the Lord on his behalf: ">You made him a king (by inquiring of the Urim and Tummim for him), since we may not inquire of the Urim and Tummim for a commoner.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="and goes to do your service: ">(וסר) like “And they turned to him (ויסורו)” (Gen. 19:6), meaning that he comes near to do your service and to do your commands. (The root סור, which usually means ‘to turn away,’ is used here to mean ‘to come near.’) Was I able to understand that he was not going on your mission?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="Have I begun today to inquire: ">This is a question, inferring as follows: It is already a long time that the community has need for him for he (i.e., the king) appointed him as the one who leads Israel to and from battle, and since then, I inquire of God on his behalf.</text>
      <text title="Far be it from me: ">to have done this thing with the intent of rebellion or treason.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="who were standing beside him: ">They were Abner and Amassa.</text>
      <text title="And… would not: ">They expounded ‘buts’ and ‘onlys.’ The Scripture states: “Every man who rebels against your command shall be put to death” (Jos. 1:18). One may think that this means even to commit a sin. The Scripture, therefore, states: Only (be strong and of good courage).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="to Doeg: ">(the ‘kethib’ is דויג, upon which our Rabbis comment:) His name was changed (from דואג to דויג). He said to him, “You are caught like a fish. You informed on them. You slay them.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="I brought about: ">I brought about the matter until it came to this.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="for he who seeks my soul: ">One man is pursuing both of us. Wherever I shall escape, you shall escape, for you will always be in my safeguard. Jonathan renders: for he who seeks to kill me, seeks to kill you. It may also be interpreted: for he who will love me, will love you, and he who will guard my soul, will guard your soul. There is another instance of this in the Scriptures: “Men of blood hate him that is sincere, but the upright seek his soul” (Prov. 29:10). Here is (an instance of) seeking a soul for good.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="23">
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="God has delivered him into my hand: ">(נכר) delivered, and so, “And do not look on, on the day of your brother, on the day of his being delivered” (Ob. 1:12). This is the conjugation of the strong verbs (piel, being punctuated by a dagesh in the middle letter of the root), like בריחיה אבד ושבר“He destroyed and broke her bars” (Lam. 21:9). (These words are punctuated in like manner.) If he desired to speak in the conjugation of the weak verbs, (Kal), it would have been punctuated thus: נכר.</text>
      <text title="for he has been shut in by coming into a city with doors and bars: ">and he will rely on that, and will not take care to flee from me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="מחריש הרעה: ">plotting the evil (from Jonathan).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="Will the citizens of Keilah deliver me: ">We derive from here that one who inquires concerning two matters, receives a reply concerning one only, and he is only answered concerning the first one. And here, David asked in an inverted order, since he should have first asked, Will Saul come down? Will the citizens of Keilah deliver me? He was answered according to the order (in which he should have asked).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="wherever they would go: ">(Jonathan renders:) in a place where it is proper to go, in a place where they would be saved.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="and he strengthened his hand: ">He renewed the covenant which was between them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="ולא הסגירו: ">and it is incumbent upon us to deliver him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="for one told me: ">(lit., for he told me.) The one who told.</text>
      <text title="that he deals cunningly: ">He acts with cunning; today he is here and tomorrow in another place, so that no one should know where he is.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="with the certainty: ">with an exact and true statement.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="before Saul: ">for Saul was destined to go after them, and they went before him, to search (and find out) exactly (where David was).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="were encircling: ">(עטרים, from עטרה, a crown;) i.e., encircling and surrounding from side to side, like a crown which encircles the head.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="And a messenger came: ">(Heb. ‘malach’) a real angel, in order to save David.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="the Rock of the Divisions: ">that Saul’s heart was divided by two thoughts, whether to return to save his country from the Philistines, or to pursue David. Thus Jonathan renders.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="24">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="צורי היעלים: ">the Rocks of the Wild Goats.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="to cover his feet: ">To stool.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <title>And it was afterwards, etc.: </title>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And he said to his men,: ">“The Lord forbid…” These two verses are written in reversed order, but since he began to speak of the severing of the coat, he finished all the matter concerning it, and stated that he even regretted the severing of the coat. Afterwards, he returns to his first subject, and states that upon his men’s statement, “Behold, concerning this day, etc.” He retorted to them, “May the Lord forbid it for me, etc.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="And David stayed: ">He separated and held them off with these words.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="Why should you listen: ">Why should you accept Doeg’s slander concerning me?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="and (one) said to kill you, but (my soul) had pity on you: ">(lit., and said to kill you, and she had pity on you) Two words are missing here, (to be explained thus): and the sayer said that I should kill you, but my soul had pity on you, similar to “and David longed to go forth to Absalom” (II Sam. 14:2. In our editions, it is 13:39), (meaning): and the soul of David longed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And Father, see!: ">i.e., pay attention to the matter, and also see the testimony, for the skirt of your coat is in my hand, and I was able to kill you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="As says the proverb of the ancient one: ">the proverb of the Ancient One of the world; i.e., the Torah, which is the proverb of the Holy One Blessed be He.</text>
      <text title="“From the wicked one comes forth wickedness”: ">The Holy One Blessed be He, destines the wicked to fall into the hand of another wicked man like himself. And where did the Torah say (this)?“And the Lord destined it into his hand” (Ex. 21:13), as it is stated in Tractate Makkoth (10b).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="I know that you will reign: ">for I see that the Holy One blessed be He saves you from my hand. The Midrash Agadah states: Samuel transmitted this sign to him that the one who tears his coat will reign after him.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="25">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="in Maon: ">the name of the city.</text>
      <text title="and his possessions: ">(lit., his work, or deed.) His cattle and his possessions.</text>
      <text title="great: ">wealthy.</text>
      <text title="and he was, while shearing his sheep, in Carmel: ">And he was one day, when the time of his sheepshearing came around, in Carmel. And his custom was to make a banquet and a festival for the sheepshearers.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="a Calebite: ">of the house of Caleb.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="So: ">will he be shearing in the coming year. (</text>
      <text title="So to the living: ">So shall be next year living and existing luck.) (Another version is:</text>
      <text title="So to the living: ">Say this concerning his meal and his wine, “So is befitting a live man, and active and esteemed man,” like: [II Sam. 23:20] “the son of a live man (kethib) of many heroic deeds.” I.e., alive and active in all his deeds.)</text>
      <text title="to the living: ">good and existing.</text>
      <text title="and peace to you: ">So shall it be to the length of days.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="We did not disgrace them: ">If they needed us for anything, we did not send them back empty handed.</text>
      <text title="neither was anything missing to them.: ">of your flocks, for we were watching for them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="and may the youths: ">i.e., my youths, find favor in your eyes, for the kindness which your servants will tell concerning them.</text>
      <text title="for we have come on a festive day.: ">Depending upon the banquet and festive day which you have, we have now come to ask. Another explanation is: This was the eve of Rosh Hashanah, (and they said,) “We are in need of a holiday feast.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="and spoke to Nabal according to all these words, in David’s name, and they rested: ">They were weary from the way, yet they were quick to execute David’s command, and did not rest until they spoke to him, and afterwards they rested. Jonathan, however, renders: and they ceased, i.e., they stopped speaking further, until they would hear his reply.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="Who is David: ">Of what importance is he that I should give him mine? Is he not descended from Ruth the Moabitess?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="and David too, girded his sword: ">Hence, we derive that in cases involving capital punishment, we commence from the most insignificant in law first.</text>
      <text title="by the luggage: ">to watch their tents and utensils.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="one youth of the youths: ">hers.</text>
      <text title="and he drove them away: ">(ויעט בהם) With words, he made them fly away. An expression of עיט (a bird) (Gen. 15:11).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="and we were not disgraced: ">(Heb. הכלמנו ולא. This is synonymous with the usual passive form,) ולא נכלמנו.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="for the evil has been decided upon: ">by David against him.</text>
      <text title="and he is such a base person that I cannot speak to him: ">And our master is such a base person that I cannot speak to him that which I am saying to you, lest he become angry with us.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="prepared: ">Jonathan renders: תכברא, filled with finely cut meat and eggs. Pates (meat pies) in French, as we learned in Pesahim (74a): And he places the feet and its intestines inside. Rabbi Tarfon calls it תכברא, (a combination of two words, תוך, inside, and ברא, outside). That which is inside is placed outside, according to Rabbi Akiva, who says that the intestines hang outside of it (the paschal lamb). Thus it is stated in the Tosefta(?), and Rabbi Klonimos of sainted memory, from Rome, explained it to us thusly.</text>
      <text title="raisins: ">dried grapes.</text>
      <text title="cakes of figs: ">round cakes of dried figs, trodden and pressed in a vessel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="going down toward her: ">There was a valley between the two mountains. She was going down one mountain, and they were going down the opposite mountain.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="And David said: ">to himself when his youths related to him Nabal’s insults, “Surely in vain have I watched, etc.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="even one dog: ">(משתין בקיר.) Jonathan renders: one possessing intelligence, (explaining משתין from משית, placing, i.e.,) one who places the walls of his heart (i.e., capable of intelligent thought, an adult). Another explanation is: even a dog whose manner is to urinate against the wall, (explaining משתין in the usual manner).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="In me alone, my lord, is the iniquity: ">First she said this so that he would heed her words. At the end, however, she told him the truth: “I, your handmaid, did not see my lord’s youths” (supra v. 25).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="that… withheld: ">for He sent me toward you to withhold you from bloodshed.</text>
      <text title="and from saving yourself with your hand: ">lest you personally avenge yourself and be punished.</text>
      <text title="as Nabal: ">She prophesied with the divine spirit that Nabal would not live long.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="shall be given: ">(Heb. ונתנה)And it shall be given to the youths, etc. נתנה, (It was given) is past tense, ונתנה (with a ‘vav’) is future tense.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="for the Lord shall make for my lord a sure house: ">to be King over Israel. Therefore,</text>
      <text title="let no evil be found in you: ">Therefore, it is not fitting for you to do anything contrary to the Law, to spread evil talk concerning your kingdom.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="the soul of your enemies, the Lord will sling it with the hollow of the sling: ">A wide piece of leather, made like a sort of hollow, in the middle of the sling, in which one places the stone.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="And it will be, when the Lord will do, etc.: ">and you will reign.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="And let this not be to you as a stumbling block: ">(לפוקה) as a stumbling block, like: “and the stumbling (ופיק) of the knees” (Nahum 2:11), for, had you done this, you would not be able to open your mouth to reprove anyone of the future generations, concerning bloodshed.</text>
      <text title="or that my lord has avenged himself: ">that you avenge yourself.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="restrained me: ">(Heb. כליתני) you withheld me, like: You shall not withhold (תכלא) your mercy (Ps. 40:12); will not withhold (כלה) from you (Gen. 12:7).</text>
      <text title="and from avenging myself with my own hand: ">(lit., and avenging etc.) This is connected with the phrase, “from coming into bloodshed.” The ‘mem’ of מבוא, (from coming) is connected to ‘and avenging,’ to be explained as, ‘from coming into bloodshed and from avenging myself with my own hand.’</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="when the wine had left Nabal: ">when the effect of the wine had left Nabal (from Jonathan).</text>
      <text title="and his heart died: ">(He became paralyzed and lifeless, because) he was shocked concerning the gift which had been brought to David.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="38">
      <text title="just ten days after: ">The Holy One Blessed be He suspended his sentence until after Samuel’s mourning period, lest the mourning period of this wicked man coincide with his mourning period. Afterward, He reprieved him for three days and he died, as it is stated: And the Lord inflicted a stroke upon Nabal, and the Rabbi said: If one was ill three days and died, this is a death of a stroke (or a plague). Our Rabbis stated: These are the Ten Days of Repentance (between Rosh Hashanah and Yom Kippur, cf. supra v. 8) which the Holy One Blessed be He waited for him to repent. Some say that they correspond to the meals which Nabal gave David’s servants for David had sent him ten youths (supra v. 5), and he fed them (v. 9“and they rested” meaning that he gave them refreshments).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="39">
      <text title="the cause of my reproach: ">my insult which he insulted me today, (by saying, Who is David and who is the son of Jesse?). Nowadays there are many slaves who break away (supra v. 10).</text>
      <text title="and restrained His bondsman from evil: ">that I did not kill him.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="26">
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="מעוכה: ">thrust (lit., crushed).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="As the Lord lives: ">Some say: He swore to his temptation. While others say: He swore to Abishai: If you kill this righteous man, I shall mingle your blood with his blood.</text>
      <text title="but the Lord will smite him: ">will bring his death prematurely.</text>
      <text title="or his day will come: ">the day in which his death is destined.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="צפחת: ">jug.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="incited you against me.: ">(Heb. הסיתך בי) to hate me. Every expression of הסתה means setting, (setting one against another), ameutement in French, (inciting, stirring up).</text>
      <text title="will accept an offering: ">(lit., will smell an offering,) will accept with mercy my prayer to turn your anger away from me.</text>
      <text title="for they have driven me: ">from Eretz Israel.</text>
      <text title="Go, worship other gods.: ">One who goes out of Eretz Israel to other lands (during the existence of the Temple [probably inserted by the censors]) is accounted as though he worshipped idols. Jonathan, however, paraphrases: Go, David, among nations who worship idols.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="as the partridge: ">(Heb. ‘hakoray’) a bird named ‘koray’ and in French ‘perdrix’ (partridge), and so: (Jer. 17:11) “As the partridge which hatches the eggs which she has not laid. And it hunts after the nests of other birds and sits on them.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="every man: ">(lit., to the man) to every righteous man.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="27">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Now, I shall perish one day: ">Perhaps he will ambush me and come upon me suddenly.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="for why should your servant dwell, etc.: ">and be a burden to you?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="(some) days and four months: ">The minimum of days, being two. It is impossible to explain this word, ‘yomim,’ as ‘a year,’ since David did not go to Achish until Samuel had died, and Saul reigned only four months after Samuel’s demise, as we learned in S.O. (ch. 13). (This can) also (be determined) from the number of Eli’s years (i.e., the forty years which he judged Israel, supra 4:18), and the twenty years that the Ark was in Kiriath-jearim (supra 7:2), totaling sixty years. Subtract therefrom Samuel’s fifty-two years, plus one year for his conception with these four months, plus the seven years which David reigned in Hebron (II Sam. 5:5) before he brought the Ark from Kiriath-jearim. It is found that Saul reigned after Samuel’s demise but four months.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="And David… would go up: ">This is a present tense. He was always accustomed to this.</text>
      <text title="as you come to Shur: ">from the entrance of Shur (according to Rashi’s version of Jonathan).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="Where did you raid?: ">(Heb. אל פשטתם) The ‘lamed’ is substituted for a ‘nun’ (making the word אן, where) like: And he made for himself a chamber (נשכה) in the book of Ezra (Neh. 13:7) like לשכה.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="28">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And Samuel had died: ">It was already stated: And Samuel died (supra 25:1), but since he came to speak of Saul, that he had to ask of a necromanceress, he commenced by saying: And Samuel had died, for had he been alive, Saul would have inquired of him. And since Saul had abolished the necromancers, he had to seek a necromanceress.</text>
      <text title="and all Israel lamented him and buried him in Ramah, and… in his own city.: ">(The difficulty of the word ‘and’ is explained by Jonathan with the following paraphrase:) And all Israel lamented him and buried him in Ramah, and each one lamented him in his own city. ‘And in his city’ is connected with ‘And they lamented him.’ They lamented him and buried him in Ramah, and each one lamented him in his own city.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="nor by the Urim: ">Since he had slain Nob, the priestly city, he was not answered.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="And Saul disguised himself: ">(ויתחפש) , he changed his clothes and similarly, “Disguise yourself and come into the battle” (I Kings 22:30). And similarly, “By the great force (of my disease), is my garment changed” (Job 30:18). And so did Jonathan render: And Saul changed.</text>
      <text title="and they came to the woman by night: ">It was (really) daytime but because of their distress it seemed to them (dark) as night. So did Rabbi Tanhuma expound (this passage).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="lay a snare: ">seek a stumbling block.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="and she cried aloud: ">for she saw him ascending not in the usual manner of those who ascend through necromancy, for when one conjures up (the dead) through necromancy, they ascend with their feet upward, while this one was ascending with his head upward, in honor of Saul.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="I have seen angels ascending from the earth.: ">Two angels (righteous men as holy as angels), viz., Moses and Samuel, for Samuel feared, “Perhaps I am being summoned for judgment,” and brought Moses up with him, as it is stated in Hag. 4b (and in Taan.).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="What is his form?: ">Three things were said concerning necromancy, viz., (1) The one who conjures him (the dead) up sees him, but does not hear his voice. (2) The one who inquires of him hears him, but does not see him. Therefore, he asked, ‘What is his form?’ (3) Others neither see nor hear him.</text>
      <text title="and he is wrapped in a cloak: ">for he was accustomed to wear a cloak, as it is stated: And his mother would make him a small cloak (supra 2:19). He was buried with it, and so he arose. And so in the future, will the dead rise with their garments.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="… have you roused me: ">You have caused me to shudder.</text>
      <text title="neither through the prophets nor through dreams: ">But he did not tell him of the Urim and Tummim, even though he had inquired of them, as it is stated above (v. 6), for he was ashamed of it, since he had slain Nob the priestly city.</text>
      <text title="And I have called you: ">(ואקראה) An expression meaning: And I have been summoned after you, similar to: I was summoned (נקרא נקראתי) on Mt. Gilboa (II Sam. 1:6), and similar to: “And there chanced an unscrupulous man” (II Sam. 20:1). (The reference is ambiguous.) It was necessary for me to be summoned after you, that you let me know what I am to do.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="And why do you ask me: ">Since you have asked of the live prophets.</text>
      <text title="and has become your adversary: ">(Jonathan paraphrases) and has become the supporter of the man whose adversary you are.</text>
      <text title="your adversary: ">(Heb. ‘orecha,’) an expression meaning an enemy. There are many (examples) in the Scriptures, e. g.: “And they will fill the face of the earth with adversaries” (Is. 14:21); “And I shall destroy your adversaries” (Mic. 5:13); “The dream be to your enemies and its interpretation to your adversaries” (Dan. 3:49. In our editions 4:16, Christian editions 4:19).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="to your fellow to David: ">But during his lifetime, he did not mention his name to him, only “and gave it to your fellow who is better than you” (supra 15:28) because he feared him lest he kill him, since he (Samuel) had anointed him (David) as king.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="you and your sons will be with me: ">in my abode.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="עגל מרבק: ">a fatted calf (from Jonathan).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="29">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="from the day he fell: ">from the day of his camping with me.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="30">
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="and they came to the Brook Besor: ">six hundred men.</text>
      <text title="and those who were left behind stayed: ">When they reached the Brook Besor, there were among them some who were faint, and some of them remained there.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="who refrained: ">(Heb. (פגרו, who refrained. And I say that this is Aramaic, the translation of ונהרסו (Ez. 30:4) and they will be destroyed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="The south of the Cherethites: ">To the south of the Philistines, for we find elsewhere that the Philistines are called a nation of Cherethites [as it says,] “the inhabitants of the seacoast, the nation of the Cherethites! [The word of the Lord is against you, Canaan land of the Philistines]…” (Zeph. 2:5).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="their morrow: ">The Amalekites are accustomed to being defeated on the morrow (On the second day of battle), as it is stated (Ex. 17:9): “Tomorrow I shall stand etc.” Therefore, it is stated: on their morrow.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="all the sheep and the cattle: ">which the troop had captured from the south of Judah and from the south of Caleb.</text>
      <text title="They led: ">men who were leading and marching before those cattle, to honor and praise themselves, (by saying,) “This is David’s spoil.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="from that day on: ">(lit., from that day and above) It is not stated: from that day on, but ‘from that day and above (i.e., before).’ Abraham had already instituted this statute when he said, “Aside from that which the youths have eaten,” those are the ones who stayed with the luggage, “and the share of the men” who went to war.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="to his friends: ">(לרעהו), to his friends.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="had frequented: ">for they would hide him from Saul.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="31">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And the Philistines fought with Israel: ">This is like a person saying, “Let us return to the earlier topic.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="about him: ">(אליו, lit., to him) like עליו, about him, i.e., about Saul.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="and they buried them there: ">(Jonathan renders:) And they burned for them as they burn for the kings there. As we learned: (A.Z. 11a, Tos. Sab. ch. 8:9, Tos. San. ch. 4:2) We perform burning at the burial of kings, and it is not considered a custom of the Amorites.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
</book>