<book>
  <chapter id="1">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="In the third year of the reign of Jehoiakim: ">Now is it possible to say so? Did he [Nebuchadnezzar] not reign in the fourth year of Jehoiakim, as is stated (Jer. 25:1) “in the fourth year of Jehoiakim son of Josiah, king of Judah that is the first year of Nebuchadnezzar?” So what is the meaning of “In the third year?” In the third year of his rebellion, as is stated (II Kings 24:1): “and Jehoiakim was his vassal for three years; then he turned and rebelled against him” ; and in the third year, he overcame him, and that was the eighth year of Nebuchadnezzar, for the master said (Seder Olam ch. 24): In his first year he conquered Nineveh, and in his second year he advanced and vanquished Jehoiakim, who served him for three years and rebelled against him for three years. That was the eleventh year of the reign of Jehoiakim: five years before he vanquished him, three years that he served him, and three years that he rebelled against him. And then Jehoiakim died under his hand, and in his stead, Nebuchadnezzar enthroned Jehoiachin, his son.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="and some of the vessels of the House of God: ">he took, and some of them remained, as is stated (in Jeremiah 27:19): “so has the Lord of Hosts said concerning the pillars, concerning the sea, concerning the bases, and concerning the rest of the vessels, which Nebuchadnezzar did not take into exile (sic).”</text>
      <text title="and he brought them to the land of Shinar, to the house of his god: ">to praise his idols; he brought the entire captivity there, even the people, and the vessels he brought afterwards to the treasury.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="the nobles: ">Heb. הַפַּרְתְּמִים, dukes.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="and who have strength: ">Our Sages explained (Sanh. 93b) that they should restrain themselves from laughing, speaking and sleeping, out of fear of the throne, and resist the urge when they feel the need to relieve themselves.</text>
      <text title="and to teach them the script: ">This refers back to “who have strength.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="allotted: ">Heb. וַיְמַן, an expression of preparation.</text>
      <text title="of… food: ">Heb. מִפַּתבַּג. That is the name of the king’s fare in the language of the Chaldeans. Some interpret פַּתבַּג, [as] bread, but it does not appear correct, for it is written (below verse 16): “The steward would take away פַּתבָּגָם … and give them pulse.” Now pulse is not a substitute for bread, but a substitute for cooked food.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="Belteshazzar: ">He named him after the god of Babylon, which was called Bel, as it is said (4:5): “whose name is Belteshazzar, like the name of my god.” Teshazzar is the Aramaic expression denoting wisdom.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="not to be defiled: ">Heb. לֹא יָתְגָּאַל, an expression of sullying.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="the chief officer: ">who was the chief over the king’s servants.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="who allotted: ">who prepared and provided.</text>
      <text title="like you: ">כְּגִילְכֶם, of your likeness. It is the language of the Mishnah; one of his likeness.</text>
      <text title="and you will forfeit my head to the king: ">You shall bring about that I will be condemned to be beheaded.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="the steward: ">Heb. הַמֶּלְצַר, the one who arranges the portions and the plates, called maestre sala, seneschal, steward.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="test: ">Heb. נַס an expression of (נִסָיוֹן) testing.</text>
      <text title="some pulse: ">a type of beans instead of the food.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="and as you will see: ">According to what you see, do.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="carry away their food: ">He would take it for himself.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="that the king ordered to bring them: ">that they come before him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="the necromancers: ">These are the ones who inquire of טִימֵי מֵתִים, the bones of the dead, as you say, “May his bones be crushed,” שְּׁחִיק טַמַיָא.</text>
      <text title="the astrologers: ">These are the ones who “press” the constellation. So it is explained in Tanhuma (Miketz 2, Buber, Miketz 4).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="And Daniel was there: ">in greatness in Babylon until the first year of King Cyrus. According to the one who says that Hathach (Esther; 4:5, 6, 9, 10) is Daniel; and why was he called Hathach? Because he was cut off (חֲתָכוּהוּ) from his greatness; [according to his explanation] we must say that this is Cyrus I, who preceded Ahasuerus. But according to the one who says that all royal affairs were decided (נֶחְתָּכִים) by his orders, we must say that this Cyrus was Darius II, [who came] after Ahasuerus, and in the days of Darius the Mede, when they cast [Daniel] into the lions’ den, he was not demoted from his greatness, as it is said (6: 29): “And this Daniel prospered during the reign of Darius and during the reign of Cyrus the Persian.” We learn that during the days of Cyrus I he was [still] in his greatness.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="2">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Now in the second year of Nebuchadnezzar’s reign: ">It is impossible to say this, except that [it happened] in the second year after the destruction of the Temple. So it is taught in Seder Olam (ch. 28), and Scripture called it “of Nebuchadnezzar’s reign,” because he demonstrated his insolence by entering the Inner Sanctum of the Sovereign of the Universe.</text>
      <text title="and his spirit was troubled: ">Heb. וַתִּתְפָּעֶם רוּחוֹ. Concerning Pharaoh it says (Gen. 41: 8): וַתִּפָּעֶם רוּחוֹ, for only the interpretation of the dream was hidden from him, but here, since the dream too was hidden from him, the expression is doubled: וַתִּתְפָּעֶם, an expression of pulsating and beating.</text>
      <text title="was interrupted: ">Heb. נִהְיְתָה, an expression of breaking like (Ezek. 7:25): “Breach upon breach (הוָה עַל הוָה).”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="May the king live forever: ">Aram. מַלְכָּא לְעָלְמִין חֱיִי.</text>
      <text title="Tell your servants the dream: ">[as translated,] Tell your servants the dream.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="The matter has escaped me: ">The thing has left me.</text>
      <text title="If you do not let me know the dream and its meaning: ">[as translated,] if you do not let me know the dream and its meaning.</text>
      <text title="you shall be torn limb from limb: ">Aram. הַדָמִין תִּתְעַבְּדוּן. You shall be cut to pieces, and there are many such in the Gemara (Gittin 67b): “Arrange the cuts” הַדְמּוּה) (ָהַדוּמֵי.</text>
      <text title="a dungheap: ">Aram. נְוָלִי, a dungheap.</text>
      <text title="shall be made: ">Aram. יִתְּשָּׂמוּן an expression of וְיָשֵּׂם, and he will make. They shall be made into dungheaps.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="But if: ">[as translated,] But if.</text>
      <text title="and lavish presents: ">[as translated,] presents.</text>
      <text title="but: ">[as translated,] but.</text>
      <text title="tell me: ">[as translated,] tell me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="a second time: ">[as translated,] a second time.</text>
      <text title="we shall tell: ">[as translated,] we shall tell.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="in truth, I know: ">[as translated,] in truth, I know.</text>
      <text title="truth: ">Aram. יַצִיב, a true and permanent thing.</text>
      <text title="that this time you are doomed: ">Aram. אַנְתוּן זַבְנִין דִּי עִדָּנָא, that this time you are delivered to death.</text>
      <text title="because you see: ">because you see that the matter escaped me, but you repeatedly ask me to tell you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="or if you have prepared yourselves… a false and corrupt word: ">Or if you have prepared yourselves to say before me a false and corrupt word.</text>
      <text title="until the time changes: ">until the time changes, i.e., before the shadows of evening slant, when the time of morning changes. “Until the time changes” is an expression of rebuke and an exaggeration: so will he be punished, and the punishment was already delineated above. A similar instance is (Gen. 4:15): “Therefore, whoever kills Cain.”</text>
      <text title="but: ">the dream; tell me what I dreamed, and I shall know that you will surely tell me the interpretation.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="who… the king’s word: ">who will be able to tell the king’s word.</text>
      <text title="because: ">Aram. כָּל קַבֵל, lit. all opposite; i.e., our reply is true, in view of the fact that there was never a king who asked anything like this.</text>
      <text title="such a thing: ">Aram. מִלָה כִדְּנָה, a thing like this.</text>
      <text title="astrologer: ">who presses the constellation.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="difficult: ">Aram. יַקִירָה, heavy, and its burden is heavy.</text>
      <text title="and there is no other who can tell it: ">and there is no other who will tell it.</text>
      <text title="but the angels: ">but the angels whose dwelling is not with flesh and blood.</text>
      <text title="whose dwelling: ">Aram. מְדָרְהוֹן, their dwelling. The Midrash of Rabbi Tanhuma (ad loc.) [says]: וְאַחֲרָן לָא אִיתַי, and Aaron is not here. A priest who wears the Urim and Tummim is not here to tell you. He said to them, “That Temple was so powerful, and you advised me to destroy it?” Immediately, he became angry and commanded to slay them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="In view of this: ">in view of this reply.</text>
      <text title="in great wrath and anger: ">Aram. מַלְכָּא בְּנַס וּקְצַף שַּׂגִיא. The king was in great wrath and anger. (בְּנַס) means in wrath. (Gen. 40:6): "And behold they were angry (זֹעַפִים), and Onkelos renders: נסִיסִין.</text>
      <text title="and ordered to destroy: ">Aram. וַאֲמַר לְהוֹבָדָה. About this “vav” of וַאֲמַר, Menahem and Dunash disputed. Menahem (p. 46) forced himself to make the “beth” of בְּנַס, a radical and did not interpret בְּנַס וּקְצַף as nouns, but as an expression of a verb: was greatly wroth and angry and ordered to destroy. The “vav” in וַאֲמַר forced him to interpret it this way. Dunash (p. 9) says that it is impossible for the “beth” to be a radical, but it is a noun, and he interpreted it in this manner: with great wrath and anger he ordered to destroy, and the “vav” there is superfluous, like the “vav” of (Ps. 76:7): “chariot (וְרֶכֶב) and horse.” But I say that the “vav” is not forced to be superfluous, but so is its interpretation: מַלְכָּא בְּנַס וּקְצַף שַּׂגִּיא, the king was in great wrath and anger, and he ordered in his wrath to destroy them. Accordingly, this is an elliptical verse.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="And a decree was issued: ">The law of the king and his decree were issued in the province.</text>
      <text title="and Daniel and his colleagues were sought to be slain: ">[as translated,] and Daniel and his colleagues were sought to be slain.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="Then: ">Aram. בֵּאדַיִן, the Targum for אָז.</text>
      <text title="answered with counsel and good sense: ">He answered [with] counsel and good sense to Arioch, the name of the man.</text>
      <text title="the… chief executioner: ">the officer over those who executed the ones condemned to death.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="Why was the decree issued so hastily: ">Why is the decree of the king [issued] in such a haste to kill?</text>
      <text title="Then Arioch made the matter known to Daniel: ">that the king was angry because no one told him his dream.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="entered and requested: ">[as translated,] entered and requested.</text>
      <text title="be given him: ">[as translated,] be given him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="the secret was revealed: ">[as translated,] the secret was revealed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="changes: ">[as translated,] changes.</text>
      <text title="removes: ">He removes kings, for he understood from the dream that Nebuchadnezzar’s kingdom would terminate, and another kingdom would rise.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="He reveals the profound: ">[as translated,] He reveals the profound.</text>
      <text title="and secret things: ">for He revealed this profound thing to me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="You have let me know: ">[as translated,] You have let me know.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="In view of this: ">in view of this, that the secret was revealed to him.</text>
      <text title="Daniel came in to Arioch: ">He entered Arioch’s premises.</text>
      <text title="had appointed: ">[as translated,] had appointed.</text>
      <text title="Do not destroy: ">[as translated,] Do not destroy.</text>
      <text title="bring me in: ">[as translated,] bring me in.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="Then: ">Aram. אֶדַיִן, [the equivalent of] אָז.</text>
      <text title="in haste: ">Aram. בְּהִתְבְּהָלָה, in haste, i. e., quickly.</text>
      <text title="brought… in: ">brought Daniel in.</text>
      <text title="that “I have found a man: ">[as translated,] that” I have found a man.</text>
      <text title="the exiles of Judea: ">[as translated,] the exiles of Judea.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="Do you have the ability: ">Are you able?</text>
      <text title="that I have seen: ">[as translated,] that I have seen.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="demonologists: ">Aram. גָזְרִין, the name of a type of ruler over demons.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="But there is… and He lets Nebuchadnezzar know: ">He revealed this secret to me, and through me let the king know that his dream refers to future events.</text>
      <text title="your dream and the visions of your head on your bed: ">which are on your bed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="your thoughts: ">Aram. רַעְיוֹנָי.</text>
      <text title="came while on your bed: ">What you were thinking of during the day, what would be after you, came [to you] on your bed.</text>
      <text title="and the Revealer of secrets: ">and the Holy One, blessed be He, Who reveals secrets, let you know what will come about.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="And I, not with wisdom: ">And I, not with superior wisdom that I have, more than other creatures, was this secret revealed to me.</text>
      <text title="but in order that they should let the king know the interpretation: ">They should let you know from heaven.</text>
      <text title="and you should know the thoughts of your heart: ">and the thoughts of your heart about which you are constantly thinking, [which are] to know who will rise after you.</text>
      <text title="you should know: ">[as translated,] you should know.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="you were watching: ">[as translated,] you were watching.</text>
      <text title="and behold: ">Aram. וַאֲלוּ, an expression of “behold.”</text>
      <text title="an image which had a large base: ">[as translated,] an image which had a large base.</text>
      <text title="with unusual splendor, was standing opposite you: ">[as translated,] standing opposite you.</text>
      <text title="and its form was frightening: ">[as translated,] and its form was frightening.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="of fine gold: ">[as translated,] of fine gold.</text>
      <text title="its breast: ">[as translated,] its breast.</text>
      <text title="and its arms: ">[as translated,] and its arms.</text>
      <text title="its belly and thighs: ">[as translated,] its belly and thighs.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="Its legs were of iron: ">[as translated,] Its legs were of iron.</text>
      <text title="were partly of iron and partly of clay: ">[as translated,] were partly of iron and partly of clay [i.e., part of each foot was of iron and part of clay].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="until one stone was hewn: ">that one stone was cut and separated.</text>
      <text title="without hands: ">not with hands, but by itself.</text>
      <text title="and it struck the image: ">[as translated,] and it struck the image.</text>
      <text title="and crumbled them: ">[as translated,] and crumbled them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="Then… crumbled together: ">Then all the types of metals and the clay that were in it crumbled together.</text>
      <text title="and they were like chaff from the threshing floors of the summer: ">[as translated,] and they were like chaff from the threshing floors of the summer.</text>
      <text title="and the wind carried them off: ">[as translated,] and the wind carried them off.</text>
      <text title="and no place was found for them: ">i.e., their original place was unknown, and it was unrecognizable that they were ever there.</text>
      <text title="became a huge mountain: ">[as translated,] became a huge mountain.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="This is the dream: ">Behold this is the dream that you dreamed.</text>
      <text title="and its interpretation we shall recite, etc.: ">and its interpretation we shall tell you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="The King of kings: ">Our Sages, of blessed memory, explained (Shev. 35b): Every mention of “king” in Daniel refers to an earthly king, except this one, which he said in reference to the Holy One, blessed be He, and this is what it means: The King of kings, Who is the God of heaven.</text>
      <text title="a strong… kingdom: ">gave you a strong and prominent kingdom.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="38">
      <text title="and has given you dominion over them all: ">And He gave you dominion over them all, so that even if you decree upon a horse, it will not whinny, or upon a bird, it will not fly, as it is said (Jer. 27:6): “and even the beasts of the field I have given to him to serve him.”</text>
      <text title="You are the head of gold: ">You are the golden head of the image that you saw, for your kingdom is strong, and now it is in existence and is very prominent.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="39">
      <text title="And after you will arise another kingdom lower than you: ">And after you, after the reign of your son, Belshazzar, will arise a kingdom that will take the ruling power from your seed, lower and humbler than your kingdom.</text>
      <text title="lower: ">Aram. אֶרַע, lower, as silver is lower and humbler than gold, and you saw that the breast, which is after the head, was of silver; so will the kingdom of Media and Persia, which will follow the kingdom of Babylon, be humbler than the kingdom of Nebuchadnezzar.</text>
      <text title="and another, a third kingdom: ">[as translated,] another.</text>
      <text title="of copper: ">as strong as copper, and that is the kingdom of Alexander of Macedon.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="40">
      <text title="And a fourth kingdom: ">will be as hard as iron, as you saw the thighs, which are the fourth from the head, the breast, and the belly, and they are of iron.</text>
      <text title="crumbles and flattens everything: ">flattens and crumbles all kinds of metal, which are flattened with a hammer.</text>
      <text title="and flattens: ">Aram. וְחָשֵּׁל, and flattens. There are many such [words] in the Talmud. Keth. 77a, “who thins copper for kettles (חַשְּׁלָא דוּדֵי) ” ; Hul. 93a: “crushed testicles (בֵּיעֵי חֳשִּׁלָתָא).”</text>
      <text title="all these: ">all these kinds of metals that you saw in the image.</text>
      <text title="it will crumble and shatter: ">It will crumble and shatter all the nations.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="41">
      <text title="potter’s clay: ">Aram. חֲסַף דִּי פֶחָר, a potter’s clay, and there are many instances of this in the Talmud (Taanith 7a): “vessels of a potter (מָאנֵי דְפַחְרָא).”</text>
      <text title="it will be a divided kingdom: ">It will be a divided kingdom; two kings will rise from it at once, strong and weak, as explained below (verse 42): “part of the kingdom will be strong.”</text>
      <text title="and in it will be some of the strength of iron: ">Even the weak one will be stronger than the other nations through the strength of his fellow, for they will fear him. And this is the meaning of וּמִן נִצְבְּתָא דִּי פַרְזְלָא לֶהֶוֵא בָהּ; some of the strength of the stability of iron will be in the weak king.</text>
      <text title="in view of what you saw: ">in view of what you saw-iron mixed with clay.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="43">
      <text title="that they will mingle with the seed of men: ">They will intermarry with the other nations but they will not be at peace and truly cleave to them wholeheartedly, and their laws will differ from the laws of the other nations.</text>
      <text title="as iron does not mix with clay: ">Is it not just as iron does not stick well to clay?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="44">
      <text title="And in the days of these kings: ">in the days of these kings, when the kingdom of Rome is still in existence.</text>
      <text title="the God Of heaven will set up a kingdom: ">The kingdom of the Holy One, blessed be He, which will never be destroyed, is the kingdom of the Messiah.</text>
      <text title="it will crumble and destroy: ">It will crumble and destroy all these kingdoms.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="45">
      <text title="Just as you saw: ">just as you saw that a stone was broken off the mountain, which crumbled the entire image. This is the interpretation that the fifth kingdom will destroy and shatter them all.</text>
      <text title="what will be after this: ">what will be after this, after this kingdom of yours.</text>
      <text title="and its interpretation is reliable: ">for the Eternal of Israel neither lies nor repents.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="46">
      <text title="ordered to offer up… libations: ">He wished to deify him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="47">
      <text title="truly: ">[as translated,] in truth.</text>
      <text title="and the Master of the kings: ">The Lord of lords.</text>
      <text title="this secret: ">[as translated,] this secret.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="48">
      <text title="elevated Daniel: ">He elevated Daniel over all the princes.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="49">
      <text title="and he appointed, over the affairs of the capital cities of Babylon: ">He appointed, over all the necessities of the kingdom, Hananiah Mishael, and Azariah.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="3">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="made an image: ">He had an urge to make an image of gold.</text>
      <text title="its width six cubits; he set it up etc.: ">If its thickness was only six [cubits], how could it stand at a height of sixty cubits? Said Rav Bibi: They would set it up and it would fall, until they brought all the gold of Jerusalem and poured a base around its feet, to fulfill what was said (Ezek. 7:19): “and their gold will be for a repugnant thing.”</text>
      <text title="in the plain of Dura: ">the name of a place.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="the satraps: ">Aram. לַאֲחַשְּׁדַרְפְּנַיָּא dukes.</text>
      <text title="governors: ">rulers.</text>
      <text title="the judges, the treasurers, etc.: ">They are all names of nations.</text>
      <text title="the dedication of the image: ">the beginning of its worship.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="And the announcement was issued aloud: ">[as translated,] and the announcement was issued aloud.</text>
      <text title="To you we are saying, O peoples: ">[as translated,] To you, all peoples and nations, we are announcing the command of the king as a message from the king.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="At the time you hear the sound of the whistling horn: ">Aram. קָל קַרְנָא מַשְּׁרוֹקֵיתָא, the sound of the whistling horn, like (Zech. 10:8) “I will whistle (אֶשְּׁרְקָא) to them, and I will gather them.”</text>
      <text title="the clavichord, the harp, etc.: ">They are all musical instruments.</text>
      <text title="kinds of music: ">Aram. זְנֵי זְמָרָא kinds of music. (Gen. 1:11) “After its kind,” Onkelos renders: לִזְנוֹהִי.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="a fiery furnace: ">a pit that is made to burn rocks into lime, and that is כִּבְשָּׁן in all the Scriptures.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="In view of this: ">in view of this, that they took heed to observe the king’s command concerning this. bagpipes would be played.</text>
      <text title="at that time: ">At the time that they hear the sound of the music, which is a sign that those who prostrate themselves should come to prostrate, all peoples would fall etc.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="In view of this: ">in view of this, that their enemies saw that there is a time to denounce them.</text>
      <text title="some Chaldean men approached and denounced: ">Aram. וַאֲכַלוּ קַרְצֵיהוֹן informed about them. (Lev. 19: 16) “Do not go as a talebearer among your people,” is translated by Targum as קוּרצִין לָא תֵיכוּ I say that it was the custom of talebearers to eat a meal in the place where they informed, and that was a sign of the verification of their words; for at that time it was incumbent upon them to clarify their words and to verify the slander that they spoke, and that meal was called eating קוּרצִין, an expression of (Prov. 6:13) “he winks (קוֹרֵץ) with his eyes,” which is a sign of slander.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="They spoke up and said: ">Aram. עֲנוֹ, they shouted. Every [expression of] עֲנִיָה in Scriptures is an expression of raising the voice.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="gave an order: ">issued a decree.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="There are: ">Aram. אִיתַי</text>
      <text title="Judahite men: ">of the tribe of Judah.</text>
      <text title="these: ">Aram. אִלֵּ</text>
      <text title="did not take counsel to follow your decree: ">Aram. עֲלָיִ מַלְכָּא טְעֵם לָא שָּׂמוּ. They did not care to give themselves counsel to care for your decrees.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="ordered to bring: ">[as translated,] ordered to bring.</text>
      <text title="were brought: ">[as translated,] were brought.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="Is it meaningless: ">Aram. הַצְדָא. Are my decrees void and desolate and an empty thing in your eyes, Shadrach, Meshach, and Abednego, that you do not worship my god? The “hey” of הַצְדָא is used as an interrogative expression.</text>
      <text title="that I have set up: ">[as translated,] that I have set up.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="Now, behold you are destined: ">Now, behold you are destined against your will to accept this upon yourselves.</text>
      <text title="and if you do not prostrate yourselves: ">and if you do not prostrate yourselves, you shall be cast.</text>
      <text title="into: ">into the midst of.</text>
      <text title="and who is a god: ">and who is a god who will save you from my hands?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="to the king, ‘Nebuchadnezzar: ">Why is his name mentioned? But this is what they said to him: “If [it concerns] taking upon ourselves to pay taxes, either the tax from the crops or the head taxes, you are king over us, [but] if [it concerns] denying the Holy One, blessed be He, [you are merely] Nebuchadnezzar. In our eyes, you are a lowly person and the most despised of the people. You and a dog are equal.”</text>
      <text title="we do not care: ">We do not care to take counsel on what to answer you, for the answer is ready and fluent in our mouths.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="He can save us: ">He can save us from all our troubles.</text>
      <text title="From the burning fiery furnace and from your hands, O king, He will save us: ">from the furnace and from your hands He will save.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="And if not: ">And if He will not wish to save our bodies, let it be known to you, etc.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="was filled with wrath: ">[as translated,] was filled with wrath.</text>
      <text title="and the features of his face changed: ">[as translated,] and the features of his face changed.</text>
      <text title="to heat the furnace: ">to light the fiery furnace and to heat it.</text>
      <text title="seven times as much as it should be heated: ">instead of once, seven times as much as they calculated to heat it up; and it was as though they would kindle it seven times as much as it required.</text>
      <text title="to be heated: ">lit. to heat it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="certain mighty men in his army: ">[as translated,] certain mighty men in his army.</text>
      <text title="And he commanded… to bind: ">He commanded to bind them because he saw that they were strengthening themselves to answer him harshly, and he said, “These are mighty”; so he commanded the mighty men in his army to bind them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="these men: ">[as translated,] these men.</text>
      <text title="were bound in their cloaks: ">They were bound in the garments in which they enwrapped themselves.</text>
      <text title="their trousers, their robes: ">types of royal raiment that they had; and although they were going forth to be judged before Nebuchadnezzar regarding their death sentence, they did not change their clothes to humble their greatness. From here the Sages learned that even in times of danger, a person should not change from the ruling position to which he has become accustomed.</text>
      <text title="their robes: ">Aram. וְכַרְבְּלָתְהוֹן. There is a word similar to this (in I Chron. 15:27): "And David was clothed (מְכֻרְבָּל).</text>
      <text title="and they were cast into the burning, fiery furnce: ">[as translated,] and they were cast into the burning, fiery furnace.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="In view of this: ">in view of this, that the king’s command was strong.</text>
      <text title="and the furnace was heated excessively: ">and the furnace was heated to a great degree.</text>
      <text title="these men: ">these mighty men who had bound Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah and had cast them into the furnace.</text>
      <text title="were killed by a spark of fire: ">The power of a spark of fire burned them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="bound: ">[as translated,] bound.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="was bewildered: ">Aram. תְּוַהּ, wondered.</text>
      <text title="and stood up in haste: ">Aram. וְקָם בְּהִתְבְּהָלָה.</text>
      <text title="answered and said: ">Aram. עָנַיִן וְאָמְרִין They answered and said to the king.</text>
      <text title="The king is true: ">Aram. יַצִיבָא מַלְכָּא The king has spoken the truth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="free men walking in the midst of the fire: ">freed from their bonds and walking in the midst of the fire.</text>
      <text title="and there is no wound upon them: ">[as translated,] and there is no wound upon them.</text>
      <text title="and the form of the fourth: ">[as translated,] and the form of the fourth.</text>
      <text title="is like [that of] an angel: ">It is like the angel I saw when I was with Sannecherib, when his armies were burned, as it is said (II Kings 19:35): “[And an angel of the Lord went forth] and slew… of the camp of Assyria.” And Nebuchadnezzar was there and fled among the ten who fled from them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="approached the gate of the… fiery furnace: ">He approached the gate of the court, in which the furnace was situated, to speak with them, and at first, he saw them from afar.</text>
      <text title="Step out and come: ">“step out and come,” but he did not say to them, “step out and ascend.” From here we learn that the floor of the furnace floated up and became even with the ground, so that they should not be troubled to go up.</text>
      <text title="Then… came out: ">Although they were confident of the miracle that had been performed for them, they did not dare to treat the king lightly, to go out without permission.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="And the satraps… gathered: ">Four nations were counted above in the first gathering who were not counted here: Adargazeria, Dethaveria, Gedaveria, Tiftaei. They are the mighty men whom the spark of fire had killed when they cast Hananiah and his colleagues into the fire.</text>
      <text title="saw these men: ">saw these men: Hananiah and his colleagues.</text>
      <text title="that the fire had taken no effect on their bodies: ">[as translated,] that the fire had taken no effect on their bodies.</text>
      <text title="on their bodies: ">בְּגֶשְּׁמְהוֹן, their bodies, in Aramaic, and there are many [instances of it] in this Book.</text>
      <text title="the hair of their heads was not singed: ">[as translated,] the hair of their heads was not singed.</text>
      <text title="their robes were not changed: ">They did not change from their appearance.</text>
      <text title="and the smell of fire had not been absorbed by them: ">Aram. לָא עֲדַת בְּהוֹן, did not pass into their midst.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="Nebuchadnezzar cried out: ">[as translated,] Nebuchadnezzar cried out.</text>
      <text title="who trusted him: ">[as translated,] who trusted him.</text>
      <text title="deviated from the command of the king: ">They deviated from the king’s command by not fulfilling it.</text>
      <text title="and risked their lives: ">lit. delivered their bodies.</text>
      <text title="except to their God: ">[as translated,] except to their God.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="Now an order is issued by me: ">[as translated,] Now an order is issued by me.</text>
      <text title="that will speak amiss: ">that will speak in error, i.e., any disrespectful word.</text>
      <text title="limb from limb: ">Aram הַּדָּמִין limbs; i.e., they will cut him into limbs.</text>
      <text title="shall be made a dungheap: ">[as translated,] shall be made a dungheap.</text>
      <text title="that can save in this manner: ">[as translated,] that can save in this manner.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="made… prosper: ">made them prosper and aggrandized them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="King Nebuchadnezzar [says] to all peoples: ">This is the text of the missive: King Nebuchadnezzar greets all peoples.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="it behooves me to recite: ">It is good for me to tell.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="4">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="was tranquil in my house: ">[as translated,] was tranquil in my house.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="and it frightened me: ">It brought upon me fear and fright.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="Until, at last,: ">until, at last, Daniel was brought in before me.</text>
      <text title="like the name of my god: ">The deity of Babylon was named Bel. Teshazzar is the name of an expression of wisdom in Aramaic.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="and no secret is hidden from you: ">No mystery is robbed [from you] or denied you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="The tree grew and became strong: ">The tree grew and became stronger and stronger.</text>
      <text title="reached the sky: ">[as translated,] reached the sky.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="its branches were beautiful: ">[as translated,] its branches were beautiful.</text>
      <text title="and its fruit was plentiful: ">[as translated,] and its fruit was plentiful.</text>
      <text title="and on it was sustenance for all: ">On it was enough sustenance for all</text>
      <text title="took shade: ">Aram. תַּטְלֵל, an expression of shade.</text>
      <text title="dwelt: ">Aram. יְדֻרָן, an expression of dwelling and lodging.</text>
      <text title="was nourished: ">Aram. יִתְּזִין, an expression of food.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="I saw: ">lit. I was seeing.</text>
      <text title="and behold a wakeful holy one: ">i.e., an angel who is forever awake and holy.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="Crying out loudly: ">crying with might.</text>
      <text title="Cut down the tree… shake off its branches: ">shake off and cause its branches to fall.</text>
      <text title="shake off its branches: ">shake off and cause its branches to fall.</text>
      <text title="and scatter its fruit: ">[as translated,] and scatter its fruit.</text>
      <text title="the beasts shall wander away from beneath it: ">[as translated,] the beasts shall wander away from beneath it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="But leave its main roots in the ground: ">but its main roots leave over.</text>
      <text title="and in fetters of iron and copper: ">i.e., place his feet in iron fetters as is done to a horse that is left in the meadow; so shall you chain him with fetters.</text>
      <text title="in the grass: ">Aram. בְדִתְאָא in the grass of the field, i.e., in the meadow, so that he should not move from there.</text>
      <text title="it shall be drenched: ">Aram.</text>
      <text title="its lot: ">[as translated,] its lot. יִצְטַבַּע, it shall always be drenched, an expression of immersion.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="and seven periods: ">seven years.</text>
      <text title="will pass over him: ">will pass over him with this decree.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="the edict: ">a decree, but since they take counsel from the Holy One, blessed be He, before they issue the decree, he calls it a question.</text>
      <text title="in order that: ">Aram. עַד דִּבְרַת, like לְמַעַן.</text>
      <text title="that the living should know: ">in order that all the living should know.</text>
      <text title="and to whom He wishes: ">[as translated,] and to whom He wishes.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="its interpretation: ">[as translated,] its interpretation.</text>
      <text title="but you can: ">[as translated,] but you can.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="Then Daniel, whose name is Belteshazzar, was bewildered: ">He was silent.</text>
      <text title="and his thoughts: ">[as translated,] and his thoughts.</text>
      <text title="alarmed him: ">for he was afraid to interpret the dream for him.</text>
      <text title="My lord: ">Aram. מָרִאי. Our Rabbis said (Shevu. 35b): “My Lord, may the dream be for Your enemies,” refers to God. He raised his eyes to the Holy One, blessed be He, and said, “May this dream be fulfilled upon this enemy of Yours.” But if you say that he said it to Nebuchadnezzar, was not Israel his enemy? Is it possible that he would curse them?</text>
      <text title="for your foes: ">Aram. לְעָרָ, like (Sam. 28:16): “and has become [the supporter of] your foes (עָרֶ).”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="which befalls my lord, the king: ">[as translated,] which befalls my lord, the king.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="And they will banish you from mankind: ">[as translated,] and they will banish you from mankind.</text>
      <text title="and with the dew of the heavens you shall be drenched: ">They will immerse you.</text>
      <text title="and seven periods shall pass over you: ">We may say that this is the recompense for the Temple, which he destroyed, which was built in seven years.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="And what they said, etc.: ">What they said-to leave the roots of the tree-this is the interpretation: מַלְכוּתָ, your kingdom-will remain yours. Your kingdom will ultimately be restored to you.</text>
      <text title="as soon as you know that Heaven rules: ">as soon as you know that the heavenly beings rule over the world.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="Indeed, O king: ">Indeed, O king, hearken to my counsel.</text>
      <text title="my counsel: ">Aram. מִלְכִּי, my counsel, like (Num. 24:14): “I shall advise you (אִיעָצְ),” which is translated: אֲמַלְּכִינָ.</text>
      <text title="please you: ">May my counsel please you that you hearken to my words.</text>
      <text title="and with charity you will remove your sin: ">With charity, break your sin off your neck.</text>
      <text title="and your iniquity by showing mercy to poor: ">and remove your iniquities by showing mercy to the poor.</text>
      <text title="perhaps your tranquility will last: ">Perhaps there will be time for your tranquility, that the evil should not come swiftly. Now what did Daniel see to give Nebuchadnezzar good advice? He saw the Jews poor and humbled by the exile, going from door to door begging for alms, and he gave him advice to deal mercifully with them. He said to him, “These poor people whom you exiled are hungry; nourish them.” And so he did. He opened his storehouses and fed them for a full twelve months.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="All this befell: ">The entire interpretation befell Nebuchadnezzar.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="he was walking: ">[as translated,] he was walking.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="Is this not: ">He heard poor people coming to the door and crying out. He said, “What is the sound of this multitude in my ears?” His servants said to him, “These are the poor for whom you arranged a time to feed.” He said, “Is this not the great Babylon, etc. If I had squandered my storehouses, from where would I have built all these palaces? From now on, I shall not feed them.” Rabbi Tanhuma (Mishpatim 4) explained it in this manner.</text>
      <text title="and for the honor of my glory: ">[as translated,] and for the honor of my glory.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="has turned away from you: ">[as translated,] has turned away from you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="they will banish: ">Aram. טָרְדִין. an expression of driving away.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="was fulfilled: ">The decree was executed upon him.</text>
      <text title="his hair grew like [the feathers of] eagles: ">His hair grew over his entire body like eagles’ feathers.</text>
      <text title="and his nails like birds: ">and his nails were like a bird’s [talons].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="And at the end of the days: ">at the end of the days that were set for him; at the end of the seven years.</text>
      <text title="raised: ">[as translated,] raised.</text>
      <text title="and my understanding was restored to me: ">[as translated,] and my understanding was restored to me.</text>
      <text title="and I blessed the Most High: ">[as translated,] and I blessed the Most High.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="are reckoned as nothing: ">Aram. כְּלָה. Our Rabbis said (Yoma 20b): The dust of the sun is called לָא i.e., the dust that appears in the sun.</text>
      <text title="and according to His will, He does with the host of heaven: ">[as translated,] and according to His will, He does with the host of heaven.</text>
      <text title="and no one can stop His hand: ">Aram. בִידֵהּ וְלָא אִיתַי דִּי יְמַחֵא. And there is none who will stop His hand.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="At that time: ">[as translated,] at that time.</text>
      <text title="and I returned to the glory of my kingdom: ">[as translated,] and I returned to the glory of my kingdom.</text>
      <text title="and my splendor: ">the features of my face.</text>
      <text title="my leaders and my dignitaries were seeking me: ">and My advisers and my princes were seeking me and hoping for my return.</text>
      <text title="and I was established: ">[as translated,] and I was established.</text>
      <text title="and excessive greatness was added to me: ">and more greatness than the earlier [kings] was added to me. Our Rabbis said (Shab. 150a) that he rode astride a lion and tied a serpent to its head.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="and Whose ways are just: ">His ways are just.</text>
      <text title="who walk with arrogance: ">Those who walk with arrogance He can humble.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="5">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="King Belshazzar: ">He was his son, and he reigned after Evil- merodach, who reigned instead of Nebuchadnezzar, and (he) too was the son of Nebuchadnezzar.</text>
      <text title="made a great feast: ">We find in Josephon (Book 1, ch. 3) that he waged war by day with Darius the Mede and Cyrus and was victorious in the battle. So in the evening he made a feast, as Isaiah had prophesied about him: (21: 5) “Setting the table, setting up the lamp, eating, drinking. ‘Arise, princes, etc.’ ” For in the midst of the feast the enemies returned, waged war on the city and captured it.</text>
      <text title="as much wine as the thousand: ">The equivalent of one thousand men [was the amount] he was drinking [in] wine.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="said, with the counsel of the wine: ">He said with the counsel of the wine that he had imbibed.</text>
      <text title="to bring: ">[as translated,] to bring.</text>
      <text title="that… had taken out: ">[as translated,] had taken out.</text>
      <text title="his queen: ">Aram. שֵּׁגְלָתֵה, an expression of a queen in Aramaic, like: (Neh. 2:6): “and the queen (וְהַשֵׁגָל) was sitting beside him.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="were brought: ">[as translated,] were brought.</text>
      <text title="that they had taken out: ">[as translated,] that they had taken out.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="the fingers… emerged: ">The fingers of a human hand emerged from heaven.</text>
      <text title="opposite the candelabrum: ">opposite the menorah that was before the table, and a similar word appears (in Tractate Yoma 37a): “made a candelabrum (נִבְרֶשֶׁת) of gold.”</text>
      <text title="on the plaster: ">on the lime that is plastered on the wall, like (Isa. 27:9): “like crushed chalkstones (אַבְנֵי גֵר),” which resemble lime.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="his color changed: ">His features changed upon him.</text>
      <text title="and his thoughts: ">[as translated,] and his thoughts.</text>
      <text title="and the belts of his loins became untied: ">The belts of his loins opened because his loins were emptying out of fear, and his belt opened.</text>
      <text title="and the belts of his loins became untied: ">were untied.</text>
      <text title="and his knees: ">[as translated,] and his knees.</text>
      <text title="knocked one against the other: ">bumped and knocked.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="aloud: ">Aram. בְּחַיִל, lit. with strength.</text>
      <text title="to bring in: ">[as translated,] to bring in.</text>
      <text title="this writing: ">[as translated,] this writing.</text>
      <text title="shall wear purple: ">following the custom of the nobles.</text>
      <text title="chain: ">Aram. וְהַמְנִיכָא, medallion, necklace.</text>
      <text title="and rule over over a third of the kingdom: ">[as translated,] and rule over a third of the kingdom.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="entered: ">[as translated,] entered.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="became very frightened: ">Aram. מִתְבָּהַל שַּׂגִּיא, extremely frightened.</text>
      <text title="were perplexed: ">They were confused.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="The queen, in response to the words of the king: ">The queen, because she heard the words of the king and his princes, came to the banquet hall.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="There is a man: ">There is a man in your kingdom in whom is the spirit of the holy ones.</text>
      <text title="like the wisdom of the angels: ">[as translated,] angels.</text>
      <text title="appointed him: ">He appointed him prince over them all.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="All because, etc.: ">because a superior spirit, knowledge and understanding are within him, and the talent to tell riddles.</text>
      <text title="and untie knots: ">The revelation of all secrets is found in Daniel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="Now if you can: ">[as translated,] Now if you can.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="and give your lavish gifts: ">[as translated,] and give your lavish gifts.</text>
      <text title="give to someone else: ">give to another person.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="and when his heart became haughty: ">[as translated,] and when his heart became haughty.</text>
      <text title="so that he dealt wickedly: ">[as translated,] so that he dealt wickedly.</text>
      <text title="he was deposed: ">Aram. הָנְחַת, lit. he took him down.</text>
      <text title="was removed from him.: ">Aram. הֶעְדִּיו, He removed from him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="was banished: ">Aram. טְרִיד was driven away.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="in view of the fact that you know all this: ">in view of the fact that you know all this that befell your father, and you should have feared the Holy One, blessed be He.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="the palm of a hand was sent forth: ">[as translated,] the palm of a hand was sent forth.</text>
      <text title="and it inscribed this writing: ">and this is the writing that it inscribed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="MENE God has counted: ">i.e., MENE means that God has counted your kingdom.</text>
      <text title="and has brought it to an end: ">He calculated the end of the allotted time for the kingdom of your father and his seed, and found that it has already been completed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="TEKEIL You were weighed on the scales: ">TEKEIL means that you were weighed on the scales and found wanting of all righteousness.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="Your kingdom has been broken up, etc.: ">i.e., UFARSIN means two definitions of PEREIS; one is that your kingdom פְּרִיסַת, your kingdom has been broken up, and the second one is that it has been given to Media and Persia (וּפָּרַס).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="6">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And Darius the Mede received the kingdom at the age of sixty-two: ">Why does he count his years? To tell you that on the day that Nebuchadnezzar entered the Heichal in the days of Jehoiachin, his adversary, Darius, was born (Seder Olam ch. 28). From the exile of Jeconiah until now were sixty-two years, and the master said: They were exiled in the days of Jehoiachin in the seventh year counting from the conquest of Jehoiakim, which is eight years after the beginning of Nebuchadnezzar’s reign. There remained to Nebuchadnezzar’s reign thirty-seven years, for he reigned forty-five years, and twenty-three of Evil-merodach’s, as our Sages stated in Tractate Megillah (11b), and the two years of Belshazzar that passed, totaling sixty-two.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And over them: ">[as translated,] and over them.</text>
      <text title="that these satraps should give them counsel: ">that these satraps should give counsel to the three viziers.</text>
      <text title="and the king should not suffer any injury: ">And the king should not suffer any loss in any royal matter that is incumbent upon them to perform.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="this Daniel: ">[as translated,] this Daniel.</text>
      <text title="surpassed: ">[as translated,] surpassed.</text>
      <text title="and the king contemplated: ">The king was thinking in his heart to set him up over all of them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="sought to find a pretext: ">They were seeking a pretext to find about Daniel in matters of the kingdom so that they could inform on him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="No pretext can be found: ">They said among themselves, “No pretext can be found about this Daniel.”</text>
      <text title="but we shall find [a pretext] against him: ">but we shall find a pretext against him through the law of his God if we ask the king to issue some decree to cause him to transgress His law, and he will not fulfill the king’s command; and this is the pretext.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="assembled: ">Aram. הַרְגִּישׁוּ, they approached the king.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="have taken counsel: ">[as translated,] have taken counsel.</text>
      <text title="to preserve the king’s law: ">to preserve the king’s law with power because you have recently ascended the throne. [Moreover], you are from another country and are in need of support.</text>
      <text title="make any request: ">[as translated,] make any request.</text>
      <text title="except from you, O King: ">[as translated,] except from you, O King.</text>
      <text title="into a pit of lions: ">into the pit where the king’s lions were [kept].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="you shall issue a decree: ">lit. you shall put up this decree.</text>
      <text title="that will not be amended: ">that will not be amended, like the law of Media and Persia.</text>
      <text title="which will not be repealed: ">which will not pass.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="when he knew: ">and when he found out.</text>
      <text title="where there were open windows in his upper chamber: ">Aram. בְּעִלִּיתֵהּ, in his upper story.</text>
      <text title="opposite Jerusalem: ">toward the side of the Temple, and although it was in ruins, he did as Solomon said (I Kings 8:48): “and pray to You toward their land.”</text>
      <text title="and three times: ">the evening prayer, the morning prayer and the afternoon prayer.</text>
      <text title="kneeled on his knees: ">[as translated,] kneeled on his knees.</text>
      <text title="and three times: ">[as translated,] and three times.</text>
      <text title="as he had done prior to this: ">just as all that he had done before this.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="searched: ">Aram. הַרְגִישּׁוּ, tapped and searched.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="concerning the king’s decree: ">concerning the infraction of the king’s decree, about which they had come to inform.</text>
      <text title="the thing is true: ">[as translated,] the thing is true.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="did not pay heed to you, O king: ">He did not pay heed or counsel to care about your decrees.</text>
      <text title="he offers up his prayer: ">Aram. בָּעֵא בָּעוּתֵה, he prays his prayer.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="when… heard the thing: ">[as translated,] when he heard the thing.</text>
      <text title="he became very displeased: ">It was very bad in his eyes because he loved Daniel, and his death would be painful to him.</text>
      <text title="and he gave Daniel a reprieve to save him: ">He gave Daniel a reprieve to push off the matter to save him, and he said to them, “I don’t believe you.”</text>
      <text title="a reprieve: ">Aram. בָּל. I do not know of any word like it, but its context shows its meaning.</text>
      <text title="and until sunset: ">and until sunset he tried to save him, but when the time of his prayer arrived, he prayed his prayer, and the king had no longer had a pretext to save him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="that the king establishes: ">What the king decrees and ratifies, no man can alter.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="And a stone was brought: ">lit. and one stone was brought. Throughout the entire land of Babylon there are no stones but bricks, as it is written: (Gen 11:3): “Let us make bricks.” We learn that there are no stones in Babylon, but for the occasion, angels brought it [a stone] from the land of Israel. If God stipulated with the Creation on the sea that it should split for the Children of Israel, and on the fire that it cool off for Hananiah and his colleagues, and on the lions that they should not hurt Daniel, He did not stipulate about casting stones or weapons that they should not hurt any man. So the king said, “From the lions I cannot take him away. I shall be careful with him that no man hurt him, and if the miracle comes, let it come.” This does not appear in some editions.</text>
      <text title="and placed on the mouth of the pit: ">[as translated,] and placed on the mouth of the pit.</text>
      <text title="with his signet ring: ">with his signet ring so that no one could move it from its place and cast stones upon him to kill him.</text>
      <text title="that his will about Daniel not be altered: ">so that his will should not be changed; i.e., so that they should not harm him against his [the king’s] will.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="and retired while fasting: ">[as translated,] and retired while fasting.</text>
      <text title="table: ">Aram. וְּדַּחֲוָן, and a table, in the Mishnah (Tosefta Kelim, B.M. 5:1). So did Dunash explain (p. 58). They did not bring before him a table upon which to eat.</text>
      <text title="and his sleep wandered from him: ">[as translated,] his sleep wandered.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="at dawn: ">Aram. בִּשְׁפַרְפָרָה, at the rise of dawn, and there are many [examples of this] in Targum Jonathan.</text>
      <text title="arose to the light of morning: ">He arose at the light of morning, not after three hours, like other kings.</text>
      <text title="and in haste went to the pit of the lions: ">[as translated,] and in haste went to the pit of the lions.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="I have done no harm: ">No unseemly or false act have I committed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="it pleased… exceedingly: ">It was very good in his eyes.</text>
      <text title="and… Daniel: ">and he ordered that Daniel be lifted up out of the pit.</text>
      <text title="because he believed in his God: ">[as translated,] because he believed in his God.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="who had informed on Daniel: ">[as translated,] who had informed on Daniel.</text>
      <text title="and they did not reach the bottom of the pit: ">They did not reach the bottom of the pit before the lions overwhelmed them and crushed their bones to powder.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="Then King Darius… that lived in all the land, May your peace increase!: ">[as translated,] that lived in all the land, May your peace increase!</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="and in the kingdom of Cyrus: ">who reigned after Darius, for Darius reigned only one year, and he was slain in battle, as it is written in the book of Joseph ben Gurion, and they crowned Cyrus his son-in-law in the midst of the battle.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="7">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="then he wrote the dream: ">Then [he wrote the dream] and told the beginnings of the matters.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="and behold: ">[as translated,] and behold.</text>
      <text title="the four winds of the heavens were stirring up, etc.: ">four blowing winds coming from the four directions of the world and waging war with the Great Sea and stirring it up.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And four beasts: ">[as translated,] and four beasts.</text>
      <text title="each one different from the other: ">[as translated,] each one different from the other.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="The first one was like a lion, and it had the wings of an eagle: ">It was like a lion, and it had the wings of an eagle; that is the kingdom of Babylon, which was ruling at that time, and so did Jeremiah see it (4:7): “A lion has come up from its thicket,” and he says also (48:40): “like an eagle he shall soar.”</text>
      <text title="until its wings were plucked: ">Its wings were plucked, which is an allusion to its downfall</text>
      <text title="and it was taken from the earth: ">an expression of being removed from the earth, an allusion to the curtailment of the kingdom from the world.</text>
      <text title="and the heart of a mortal: ">Aram. וּלְבַב אֶנָשׁ, an expression of weakness, like (Psalms 9:21): “Let the nations know that they are forever mortal men (אֶנוֹשׁ)”.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="another: ">[as translated,] another.</text>
      <text title="second: ">that emerged second from the sea.</text>
      <text title="resembling a bear: ">This represents the kingdom of Persia, which will reign after Babylon, who eats and drinks like a bear and is enwrapped in flesh like a bear.</text>
      <text title="resembling a bear: ">It is spelled לְדֹב [without a “vav,”] like דִיבָא, the Aramaic for זְאֵב, a wolf, for the kingdom of Persia was also called a wolf, as it is said: (Jer. 5:6): “Therefore a lion smote them, a wolf of the deserts spoils them.”</text>
      <text title="and it stood to one side: ">and it stood to one side, indicating that when the kingdom of Babylon terminates, Persia will wait one year, when Media will reign.</text>
      <text title="and there were three ribs in its mouth: ">Aram. וּתְלָת עִלָעִין בְּפֻמַּהּ, three ribs. Our Sages explained that three provinces were constantly rebelling against it [i.e., Persia] and making peace with it; sometimes it would swallow them and sometimes spit them out. That is the meaning of “in its mouth between its teeth,” sometimes outside its teeth, sometimes inside (Kid. 72a), but I say that the three עִלָעִין are three kings who will rise from Persia: Cyrus, Ahasuerus, and Darius who built the Temple.</text>
      <text title="much meat: ">[as translated,] much meat.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="four wings… four heads: ">They are the four rulers to whom Alexander of Macedon allotted his kingdom at his death, as is written in the book of Joseph ben Gurion (Book 3, ch. 14), for this third beast is the kingdom of Antiochus, and it is called נָמֵר because it issued decrees upon Israel [which were] spotted (מְנֻמָּרוֹת) and varied one from the other.</text>
      <text title="and dominion was given it: ">[as translated,] and dominion was given it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="in the visions of the night: ">on another night. The first three he saw on one night, and this one on another night, because it is equal to them all. In Leviticus Rabbah (13:5).</text>
      <text title="and it had… iron teeth: ">[as translated,] iron teeth.</text>
      <text title="and crushed: ">It crushed and ground finely.</text>
      <text title="and… the rest: ">what it left over from its eating.</text>
      <text title="and… ten horns: ">Aram. וְקַרְנַיִן עֲשַׂר. The angel explained to him that these are the ten kings who would ascend [the throne] of Rome before Vespasian, who would destroy the Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="and behold: ">Aram. וַאֲלוּ, like וַאֲרוּ, an expression of “behold.”</text>
      <text title="speaking arrogantly: ">words of arrogance. That is Titus, about whom the Rabbis, of blessed memory, said (Gittin 56b) that he blasphemed and berated and entered the Heichal with brazenness.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="until thrones were set up: ">Thrones were set up and established to sit in judgment, one for judgment for the nations of the world and one for charity for Israel.</text>
      <text title="and the Ancient of Days sat: ">The Holy One, blessed be He, was sitting in judgment on this kingdom and on those before it, who provoked Him and oppressed His children.</text>
      <text title="as white as snow: ">to whiten the iniquities of His people.</text>
      <text title="and the hair of His head was like clean wool: ">He cleanses Himself of the merits that the nations have before Him, and He pays them all their reward in this world. In Lev. Rabbah.</text>
      <text title="of fire: ">[as translated,] of fire.</text>
      <text title="a burning fire: ">[as translated,] a burning fire.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="was flowing and emerging: ">[as translated,] was flowing and emerging.</text>
      <text title="serve Him: ">i.e., the Ancient of Days.</text>
      <text title="justice was established: ">The judgment is established before Him.</text>
      <text title="and the books were opened: ">The books were opened; the book of the transgressions and the evils that they committed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="from the sound of the arrogant words: ">From the sound of the haughty words that the horn was speaking, the wrath of the Ancient of Days was aroused.</text>
      <text title="until the beast was slain and its body was destroyed and given: ">[as translated,] and its body was destroyed.</text>
      <text title="to a flame of fire: ">to a flame of fire; this refers to Jacob’s fire etc.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="But as for the other beasts, their dominion was removed: ">And from the other kingdoms, their dominion was removed by Heaven.</text>
      <text title="and they were given an extension of life: ">And He gave them time to live until a set day in the future, the wars of Gog and Magog.</text>
      <text title="an extension: ">Aram. אַרְכָה, waiting.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="one like a man was coming: ">That is the King Messiah.</text>
      <text title="and… up to the Ancient of Days: ">Who was sitting in judgment and judging the nations.</text>
      <text title="came: ">arrived, reached.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="And He gave him dominion: ">And to that man He gave dominion over the nations, for the heathens he likens to beasts, and Israel he likens to a man because they are humble and innocent.</text>
      <text title="which will not be removed: ">[as translated,] will not be removed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="My spirit… became troubled: ">Aram. אֶתְכְּרִיַת an expression of (Exod. 21:33): “or if… digs (יִכְרֶה),” and Hebrew and Aramaic are alike in this case; i.e., it was humbled because of the depth of its digging.</text>
      <text title="within its sheath: ">Aram. בְּגו ֹנִדְנֶה; i.e., my spirit became terrified in my body from this dream.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="I drew near to one of those standing: ">I drew near to one of those standing there beside the Ancient of Days. The angels are called standing ones, as it is said: (Zech. 3:7): “among these who stand by (הָעמְדִים),” because they have no joints.</text>
      <text title="and I asked him the truth: ">[as translated,] and I asked him the truth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="four kingdoms: ">Aram. אַרְבְּעָא מַלְכִין, lit. four kings.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="And the high holy ones will receive the kingdom: ">These are Israel, who will take the kingdom from the fourth one.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="Then I wished to determine the truth: ">Then I wished to determine the truth concerning the fourth beast.</text>
      <text title="which was different from all of them-excessively dreadful: ">which was different from all of them with excessive dreadfulness.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="and [the] three [that] fell before it: ">and three of the first ones fell before it.</text>
      <text title="and the horn that was like this and that had eyes: ">and the horn that was like this, and had eyes, as is written above.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="I looked: ">in my first dream, which I told above.</text>
      <text title="with the holy ones: ">with Israel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="and gave revenge to the high holy ones: ">and He gave them revenge from it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="So he said: ">So did the angel who interpreted the dream for me reply to me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="And the ten horns: ">And its ten horns that you saw-this is its interpretation.</text>
      <text title="from that kingdom: ">[as translated,] from that kingdom.</text>
      <text title="and the last one will rise after them: ">and the last one will rise after them-that is Titus.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="against the Most High: ">[as translated,] against the Most High.</text>
      <text title="and he will oppress the high holy ones: ">He will burden and oppress Israel.</text>
      <text title="and he will think to change the times and the law: ">He will plan in his heart to cause them to transgress all their appointed times and their laws.</text>
      <text title="until a time, two times, and half a time: ">This is an obscure end, as was said to Daniel (12:4): “And you, Daniel, close up the words and seal,” and the early commentators expounded on it, each one according to his view, and the ends have passed. We can still interpret it as I saw written in the name of Rav Saadia Gaon, that they are the 1,335 years stated at the end of the Book (12:12): “Fortunate is he who waits [and reaches the days one thousand three hundred and thirty-five],” and he explains the appointed time as until the time of two times and a half time, and he [Rav Saadia Gaon] said that the times are 480 [years], which is the time from the Exodus from Egypt until the Temple was built, and 410 [years], [which are] the days of the First Temple, totaling 890, and another half of this time, 445, totaling 1,335. Figure these from the time the daily sacrifice was discontinued until the daily sacrifice will be restored to its place; it was discontinued six years prior to the destruction, and there is somewhat of a proof in this Book. [See Rashi to 8:14.] Others bring further proof to this computation, namely that (Deut. 31: 18): “And I, will hide My face” [the words] הַסְתֵּר אַסְתִּיר add up in gematria to 1,335.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="And the judgment was established: ">And the judgment was established before Him.</text>
      <text title="and they will remove his dominion: ">from heaven. They will remove the dominion and the rule of that kingdom.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="and obey: ">They will obey his command to execute it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="until here: ">[as translated,] until here.</text>
      <text title="my thoughts terrified me greatly: ">My thoughts were terrifying me greatly.</text>
      <text title="and my colors changed: ">The appearance of my good looks and my features changed.</text>
      <text title="I kept… in my heart: ">I hid in my heart.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="8">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="In the third year: ">after the first vision that appeared to me in the beginning, i.e., the dream stated above (7:1), which appeared to him in the first year of Belshazzar.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="beside the river Ulai: ">beside the river named Ulai.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="and it had horns: ">symbolizing the kingdom of Persia and Media.</text>
      <text title="and one was higher than the other: ">symbolizing the kingdom of Persia, which was greater than the kingdom of Media, for the kingdom of Media existed for only one year, as it says (9:1): “In the first year of Darius the son of Ahasuerus of the seed of Media,” and we learned in Seder Olam (ch. 28): “We do not find any year ascribed to Media in the Holy Writ but this one only.”</text>
      <text title="and the higher one sprouted last: ">This symbolizes that the kingdom of Media will precede the kingdom of Persia.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="I was pondering: ">I was contemplating it.</text>
      <text title="a he goat: ">Heb. צְפִיר.</text>
      <text title="and it did not touch the ground: ">He resembled one skipping in the air.</text>
      <text title="a conspicuous horn: ">Heb. קֶרֶן חָזוּת, a large horn visible to the eye.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="and it fought with it: ">Heb. וַיִתְמַרְמַר אֵלָיו, and it fought with it. That is an expression of bitter (מַר) anger.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="an appearance of four: ">an appearance of four horns.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="And from one of them: ">and from one of these kingdoms.</text>
      <text title="emerged a… horn: ">The kingdom of Titus emerged from it.</text>
      <text title="small: ">A small and despised kingdom, as he calls it above one small horn, and that is in the manner of (Obad. 1:2): “… you are very despised.”</text>
      <text title="and it became very great: ">Heb. וַתִּגְדַּל מְאֹד.</text>
      <text title="to the south: ">That is Egypt, which is to the south of the land of Israel.</text>
      <text title="and to the coveted land: ">Heb. הַצְבִי The land of Israel, called אֶרֶץ הַצְבִי, the coveted land [or the land of beauty] after the manner of (Jer. 3:19): “an inheritance of the beauty of hosts of nations.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="until the host of heaven: ">They are Israel, who were compared to the stars.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="And until the Prince of the host: ">That is the Temple, which is the House of the Holy One, blessed be He, the Prince of the host. He blasphemed the Holy One, blessed be He.</text>
      <text title="and through him the daily sacrifice was removed: ">And through his troops and his armies, which he sent to Jerusalem, the daily sacrifice was abolished, for he sent there Nero Caesar, his general, as our Rabbis relate in Gittin (56a) and in Gorion.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And a time will be given for the daily sacrifice: ">A set time will be given for the daily sacrifice to be discontinued because of transgression.</text>
      <text title="And a time: ">Heb. וְצָבָא, time, like (Job 7:1): “Is not man on earth for a limited time (צָבָא)” ?</text>
      <text title="and it will cast truth to the earth: ">It humbled the Torah of truth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="one holy one: ">one of the angels.</text>
      <text title="and… said: ">that angel.</text>
      <text title="to the anonymous: ">Heb. לַפַּלְמוֹנִי. This word is like two: פְּלוֹנִי אַלְמוֹנִי, and Jonathan ben Uziel translated it in the Book of Samuel (I 21:3): “covered and hidden,” like (Deut. 17:8): “If a matter be hidden (יִפָּלֵא) from you.” אַלְמוֹנִי means a widower (אַלְמָן) without a name, [i.e., bereft of a name] for he [the angel] did not explain to him what he was and what his name was.</text>
      <text title="to the anonymous one who was speaking: ">to the angel who was speaking and issuing decrees, viz. “And a set time will be given for the daily sacrifice because of transgression.”</text>
      <text title="How long will be the vision: ">this [vision] which concerns the daily sacrifice, that it should be discontinued, and the silent abomination will be placed in its stead. The silent abomination is an idol worshipped by the pagans, which was like a mute stone, and so it is called in this Book in many places, as it says (12:11): “And from the time the daily sacrifice was removed and the silent abomination placed.”</text>
      <text title="mute: ">Heb. שֹּׁמֵם, an expression of being mute and silenced, like (4:16): “was bewildered (אֶשְּׁתּוֹמַם) for awhile;” (Ezek. 3:15): “and I sat there seven days bewildered (מַשְּׁמִים) among them,” like one who is dumb.</text>
      <text title="permitting the Sanctuary and the host to be trampled: ">to make the base of the Sanctuary and the host of heaven, which he cast down to the earth, to be a trampling for his feet, as is stated above (verse 10): “and it cast down to the ground some of the host and some of the stars.”</text>
      <text title="the Sanctuary and the host: ">Heb. וְצָבָא וְקֹדֶשּׁ. The “vav” [of וְקֹדֶשּׁ] is superfluous, and there are many such instances in Scripture, e.g. (Ps. 76:7): “chariot (וָרֶכֶב) and horse were stunned,” and also, in the language of people, some speak that way.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="Until evening and morning, two thousand and three hundred: ">I saw an interpretation in the name of Rav Saadia Gaon for this matter, but it has already passed, and he interpreted further “until evening and morning,” that evening about which it says (Zech. 14:7): “and it shall come to pass that at eventide it shall be light,” and we are confident that our God’s word will stand forever; it will not be nullified. I say, however, that the עֶרֶב and בֹּקֶר stated here are a gematria, and there is support for this matter from two reasons: 1) that this computation should coincide with the other computation at the end of the Book, and 2) that Gabriel said to Daniel later on in this chapter (verse 26): “And the vision of the evening and the morning is true.” Now, if he had not hinted that the computation was doubtful, why did he repeat it to say that it was true? And the seer was commanded to close up and to seal the matter, and to him, too, the matter was revealed in a closed and sealed expression, but we will hope for the promise of our king for end after end, and when the end passes, it will be known that the expounder has erred in his interpretation, and the one who comes after him will search and expound in another manner. This can be interpreted [as follows]: namely, that עֶרֶב בֹּקֶר has the numerical value of 574, ע = 70; ר = 200; ב = 2; ב = 2; ק = 100; ר = 200. Added together, this equals 574; plus 2,300, we have 2,874.</text>
      <text title="and the holy ones shall be exonerated: ">The iniquity of Israel shall be expiated to bring an end to the decrees of their being trodden upon and crumbled since they were exiled in their first exile to Egypt, until they will be redeemed and saved with a perpetual salvation by our king Messiah, and this computation terminates at the end of 1, 290 years from the day the daily sacrifice was removed, and that is what is stated at the end of the Book (12:11): “And from the time the daily sacrifice is removed, and the silent abomination placed, will be 1,290 years,” and no more, for our king Messiah will come and remove the silent abomination. The daily sacrifice was removed six years before the destruction of the Second Temple, and an image was set up in the Heichal. Now that was the seventeenth day of Tammuz, when Apostomos burned the Torah, put an end to the daily sacrifice, and set up an image in the Heichal, as we learned in Tractate Ta’anith (26b), but for the six years that I mentioned, I have no explicit proof, but there is proof that the daily sacrifice was abolished less than a complete shemittah cycle before the destruction, for so did Daniel prophesy about Titus (9:27): “… and half the week of years [shemittah cycle] he will curtail sacrifice and meal-offering,” meaning that a part of the week of years before the destruction, sacrifices will be abolished. So it is explained below in this section. Let us return to the earlier matters, how the computation of “evening and morning, two thousand and three hundred,” fits exactly with the time commencing from the descent to Egypt to terminate at the end of 1,290 years until the day that the daily sacrifice was abolished: 210 years they were in Egypt. 480 years transpired from the Exodus until the building of the Temple. 410 years the Temple existed. 70 years was the Babylonian exile. 420 years the Second Temple stood. 1,290 should be added until the end of days, totaling: 2,880. Subtract six years that the daily sacrifice was removed before the destruction, for Scripture counted 1,290 years only from the time that the daily sacrifice was removed. Here you have the computation of “evening and morning, and 2,300” added to the computation. Fortunate is he who waits and reaches the end of days 45 years over 1,290 [years]. We may say that the king Messiah will come according to the first computation, and he will subsequently be concealed from them for forty-five years. Rabbi Elazar HaKalir established (in the concluding poem of the portion dealing with the month of Nissan): in the foundation of his song: six weeks of years, totaling 42. We may say that the three years that did not total a week of years he did not count. And I found it so in Midrash Ruth that the king Messiah is destined to be concealed for forty-five years after he reveals himself, and proof is brought from these verses.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="that I sought understanding: ">I was longing that they should enable me to understand [the vision] from heaven.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="in the midst of the Ulai: ">in the midst of the river.</text>
      <text title="and he called: ">i.e., the man.</text>
      <text title="and said: ">to the angel, “You, Gabriel.”</text>
      <text title="enable this one to understand the vision: ">explain the vision to this one.</text>
      <text title="this one: ">Heb. לְהַלָּז, an expression of esteem, as he called him חֲמוּדוֹת, one of desirable qualities. Wherever it says הַלָז it refers to a person of form, and from here they learned in the Aggadah: Isaac resembled his father in form and in likeness, for he is called הָאִישּׁ הַלָז in the section commencing, “Now it came to pass when Isaac was old.” (Gen. 39: 6): “… and Joseph was fair in form and fair in appearance.” This is the beauty enumerated among the five things that a father merits for his son.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="to the time of the end.: ">For many days this vision will come about.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="I fell into a sound sleep: ">An expression of slumber and bewilderment.</text>
      <text title="and stood me up where I had been standing: ">Where my feet were standing.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="for it is the end of the time: ">for it is at the time of the end of many days.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="The kings of Media and Persia: ">The two horns represent two ruling nations, as I explained above.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="the first king: ">He is Alexander of Macedon who slew Darius, the son of Esther, as we find in the book of Josiphon (ch. 9).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="And the broken one: ">that you saw being broken.</text>
      <text title="in whose stead stood four: ">as is written in the narration of the dream above (verse 8), [there] are four kingdoms which will arise from that nation, for Alexander of Macedon divided his kingdom upon his death [into parts for] four youths, and Joseph called them four heads of a leopard in his book, and they were not the sons of the king.</text>
      <text title="but not with its strength: ">The last ones will not be as strong as the first king, but they will be weaker than him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="And at the end of their kingdom, when the transgressors have been destroyed: ">When the end arrives, and the wicked of Israel in the Second Temple will be finished, a brazen-faced person will rise; he is Titus.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="And his power will become strong: ">and not with might but with smooth talk, as is explained at the end of the Book (11: 21).</text>
      <text title="and he will destroy wondrously: ">and with wonder upon wonder, he will destroy.</text>
      <text title="and he will prosper and accomplish: ">his desire.</text>
      <text title="and he will destroy the mighty: ">many nations.</text>
      <text title="and the people of the holy ones: ">Israel, who believe in the Torah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="And through his intellect, he will cause the deceit in his hand to prosper: ">And because he is clever wherever he turns and [because] he will prosper, he will hold onto deceit with his hand.</text>
      <text title="and in his heart he will become proud: ">Heb. יַגְדִּיל, lit, he will grow larger.</text>
      <text title="and in tranquility he will destroy many: ">With guile and with smooth talk he will destroy many who dwell with him with a covenant and in peace.</text>
      <text title="and over the Prince of princes he will stand: ">He will speak blasphemously about Heaven. This is the meaning of the dream written above (verse 11): [“And until the Prince of the host it grew.”]</text>
      <text title="and without strength he will be broken: ">And without strength he will be broken, through a mosquito, the weakest of creatures, which entered his nose, as we learned in Tractate Gittin (56b).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="And the vision of the evening and the morning: ">which was said to you in the preceding dream, is true.</text>
      <text title="and you close up the vision: ">Do not explain it, but close it up in your heart, for it will come about in many days.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="became broken: ">Heb. נִהְיֵיתִי, an expression of calamity (הוָה) and breach; i. e., I was pained because of this trouble and I was depressed.</text>
      <text title="the king’s work: ">for I was appointed over the assignment of the work of the government of Belshazzar’s kingdom, for Nebuchadnezzar his father had appointed him, as is written in the beginning of the Book (2:48): “… and gave him dominion over all the capital cities of Babylon.”</text>
      <text title="and I was terrified about the vision: ">Heb. עַל הַמַרְאֶה וָאֶשְׁתּוֹמֵם.</text>
      <text title="but no one realized: ">that I was terrified because I restrained myself before the princes.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="9">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="In the first year of Darius, the son of Ahasuerus: ">This is not the Ahasuerus of the days of Haman, for he was the king of Persia, whereas this one was Darius the Mede who was crowned over the kingdom of the Chaldeans when Belshazzar was slain, as is written above (6:1): “And Darius the Mede took (sic) the kingdom.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="Contemplated the calculations: ">Heb. בִּינֹתִי בַּסְפָרִים.</text>
      <text title="the number of the years, etc.: ">I contemplated the calculation of the years, for I thought about what Jeremiah (29:10) prophesied: “For at the completion of seventy years of Babylon I will remember you,” and I thought that this remembrance is the building of the Temple, and that the seventy years end in the first year of Darius the Mede, since the kingdom of Babylon stretched forth a hand upon Israel, when Nebuchadnezzar vanquished Jehoiakim to be his slave. Now that was in the second year of Nebuchadnezzar’s reign, as the master said (Meg. 11b): “In the first year he conquered Nineveh; in the second year he went up and vanquished Jehoiakim.” Figure from that year until now, and you will find them [the 70 years]. This calculation is found also in the Mishnah of Seder Olam (ch. 28), and we learned there that in the year of Belshazzar’s death were 70 years from the day that Nebuchadnezzar ascended the throne: seventy minus one since the day that he conquered Jehoiakim, and yet one more year for Babylon, which Darius completed. And when I [Daniel] saw that the redemption was not hastening to come, I contemplated and put my heart to the calculation, and I knew that I should not have counted according to the conquest of Jehoiakim but [according] to the destruction of Jerusalem, when 70 years will be complete from the exile of Zedekiah, when Jerusalem was destroyed. And there are yet 18 years to come, for this exile was in the eighteenth year counting from the conquest of Jehoiakim, as we learned in Seder Olam: “They were exiled in the seventh year; they were exiled in the eighth year; they were exiled in the eighteenth year; they were exiled in the nineteenth year.” Our Sages in Tractate Megillah (11b) explained that they were exiled in the exile of Jeconiah in the seventh year, counting from the conquest of Jehoiakim, which is the eighth year of Nebuchadnezzar’s reign. They were exiled a second time in the eighteenth year, counting from the conquest of Jehoiakim, which is the nineteenth year of Nebuchadnezzar’s reign.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="and I confessed: ">the sins of my people.</text>
      <text title="O great and awesome God: ">but he did not say, “mighty.” He said [to himself], “Heathens are enslaving His children, so where are His mighty deeds?”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="turning away: ">We were constantly turning away from Your commandments, tolant in Old French, turning away.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="To you, O Lord, is the righteousness: ">i.e., Your judgments and retributions that You have brought upon us-justice and righteousness are with You.</text>
      <text title="and to us is the shamefacedness: ">We should be ashamed for what has happened to us, for we caused it for ourselves.</text>
      <text title="as of this day: ">as we see today.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="To the Lord our God are the mercies: ">that we did not perish for our iniquities, for we rebelled against Him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="have befallen us: ">Heb. וַתִּתַּ, and You caused to reach us, like (Exod. 9:33): לֹא נִתַּ אָרְצָה, and Onkelos rendered: did not reach the earth.</text>
      <text title="the curse and the oath: ">the curses of the Covenant with which You adjured us at Horeb (Lev 26: 14): “And if you do not listen etc.”; all the curses written there.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="as was done in Jerusalem: ">the sword, slaying, the burning of the city; and they humbled women and put captives into neck irons.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="As is written in the Law of Moses: ">a hint that He warned us that if we transgress the oath, all this evil will befall us.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="hastened: ">Heb. וַיִשְׁקֹד, and hastened.</text>
      <text title="for… is righteous: ">for justice is with Him. Our Rabbis, however, explained that the Holy One, blessed be He, is charitable, and it is charity for us that He hastened and brought [the evil] two years before the numerical value of וַנוֹשַּׁנְתֶּם (Deut. 4:25): “and you will have grown old,” in order that [the curse of] “that you shall perish” should not be fulfilled with you. The numerical value of וַנוֹשַּׁנְתֶּם is 852, but they were exiled at the end of 850 [years] after their entry into the land.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="And now, O Lord, our God: ">We confess that we have sinned and have dealt wickedly.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="a mockery: ">[as translated,] a mockery.</text>
      <text title="to all those surrounding us: ">to all our neighbors; they all mock us.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="for the sake of the Lord: ">For the sake of the holy Name that is called upon the Temple, as it says (Exod. 15:17): “the Sanctuary, O Lord, (אֲדֹנָי) which Your hands have established.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="and see our desolations: ">and the desolations of the city upon which Your name is called, because not upon the support of our righteousness do we cast our supplications to benefit us, but we have come upon Your mercies.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="O Lord, hear: ">our supplications.</text>
      <text title="O Lord, forgive: ">our sins.</text>
      <text title="O Lord, hearken: ">Your ear to our cry.</text>
      <text title="and do: ">our request and do not delay.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="about the mount of the Sanctuary of my God: ">for the mount of the House of God, that it be built.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="at first: ">in the days of Belshazzar, as is written above (8:15 26).</text>
      <text title="in swift flight: ">[He was] caused to fly to me with flying and with gliding.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="And he enabled me to understand: ">Heb. וַיָבֶן.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="In the beginning of your supplications, a word came forth: ">a true [word came] from the Holy One, blessed be He, to me to tell you.</text>
      <text title="for you have desirable qualities: ">You have qualities that are desirable to the Holy One, blessed be He.</text>
      <text title="now contemplate the word: ">Put your heart to understand the word.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="Seventy weeks [of years] have been decreed: ">on Jerusalem from the day of the first destruction in the days of Zedekiah until it will be [destroyed] the second time.</text>
      <text title="to terminate the transgression and to end sin: ">so that Israel should receive their complete retribution in the exile of Titus and his subjugation, in order that their transgressions should terminate, their sins should end, and their iniquities should be expiated, in order to bring upon them eternal righteousness and to anoint upon them (sic) the Holy of Holies: the Ark, the altars, and the holy vessels, which they will bring to them through the king Messiah. The number of seven weeks is four hundred and ninety years. The Babylonian exile was seventy [years] and the Second Temple stood four hundred and twenty [years].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="And you shall know and understand from the emergence of the word: ">From the emergence of this word, which emerged at the beginning of your supplications to tell you, you shall know to understand [how] to restore and build Jerusalem.</text>
      <text title="until the anointed king: ">Time will be given from the day of the destruction until the coming of Cyrus, king of Persia, about whom the Holy One, blessed be He, said that he would return and build His city, and He called him His anointed and His king, as it says (Isa. 45:1): “So said the Lord to His anointed one, to Cyrus etc.” (verse 13): “He shall build My city and free My exiles, etc.”</text>
      <text title="seven weeks: ">Seven complete shemittah cycles they will be in exile before Cyrus comes, and there were yet three more years, but since they did not constitute a complete shemittah cycle, they were not counted. In the one year of Darius, in which Daniel was standing when this vision was said to him, seventy years from the conquest of Jehoiakim terminated. Deduct eighteen years from them, in which the conquest of Jehoiakim preceded the destruction of Jerusalem, leaving fifty-two years. This is what our Rabbis learned (Yoma 54a): “For fifty-two years no one passed through Judea.” They are the fifty-two years from the day of the destruction until they returned in the days of Cyrus. Hence, we have seven shemittah cycles and three years.</text>
      <text title="and in sixty-two weeks it will return and be built: ">i.e., the city with its streets.</text>
      <text title="and moat: ">Heb. וְחָרוּץ. They are the moats that they make around the wall to strengthen the city, which are called fosse in French, ditch or moat.</text>
      <text title="but in troubled times: ">But in those times they will be troubled and distressed, for in the subjugation of the kings of Persia and the heathens, they will burden them with harsh bondage. Now although there are sixty-two weeks and four years more that remain from the eighth week, whose beginning, viz. the three years, was included in the fifty-two years of the duration of the exile, those four years were not counted here because here he counted only weeks, and you find that from the beginning he started to count seventy weeks, and at the end, when he delineated their times and their judgments, he counted only sixty-nine, proving that one week was divided, part of it here and part of it there; and he mentioned only whole weeks.</text>
      <text title="but in troubled times: ">They will be troubled in those times.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="And after: ">those weeks.</text>
      <text title="the anointed one will be cut off: ">Agrippa, the king of Judea, who was ruling at the time of the destruction, will be slain.</text>
      <text title="and he will be no more: ">Heb. וְאֵין לוֹ, and he will not have. The meaning is that he will not be.</text>
      <text title="the anointed one: ">Heb. מָשִׁיחַ. This is purely an expression of a prince and a dignitary.</text>
      <text title="and the city and the Sanctuary: ">lit. and the city and the Holy.</text>
      <text title="and the people of the coming monarch will destroy: ">[The monarch who will come] upon them. That is Titus and his armies.</text>
      <text title="and his end will come about by inundation: ">And his end will be damnation and destruction, for He will inundate the power of his kingdom through the Messiah, and until the end of the wars of Gog the city will exist.</text>
      <text title="cut off into desolation: ">a destruction of desolation.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="And he will strengthen a covenant for the princes for one week: ">לָרַבִּים, for the princes, like “and all the officers of (רַבֵּי) the king,” in the Book of Jeremiah (39:13).</text>
      <text title="will strengthen: ">Titus [will strengthen] a covenant with the princes of Israel.</text>
      <text title="for one week: ">He will promise them the strengthening of a covenant and peace for seven years, but within the seven years, he will abrogate his covenant.</text>
      <text title="he will abolish sacrifice and meal-offering: ">This is what he says in the first vision (8:26): “and in tranquility he will destroy many.” Through a covenant of tranquility, he will destroy them.</text>
      <text title="and on high, among abominations will be the dumb one: ">This is a pejorative for pagan deities. i.e., on a high place, among abominations and disgusting things, he will place the dumb one, the pagan deity, which is dumb like a silent stone.</text>
      <text title="high: ">Heb. כְּנַף, lit. wing, an expression of height, like the wing of a flying bird.</text>
      <text title="and until destruction and extermination befall the dumb one: ">and the ruling of the abomination will endure until the day that the destruction and extermination decreed upon it [will] befall it, in the days of the king Messiah.</text>
      <text title="befall the dumb one: ">Heb. תִּתַּ, reach; and total destruction will descend upon the image of the pagan deity and upon its worshippers.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="10">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="and for a long time: ">and it will come in a long time.</text>
      <text title="and he understood the word: ">and to understand the word, the vision was revealed to me.</text>
      <text title="and he understood it in the vision: ">Heb. וּבִינָה and to make him understand it in the vision. Now this word is not a noun, like (Job. 38:4): “if you know understanding (בִּינָה) Instead, the ” hey “ is superfluous, and it is like (Ps 5:2)” understand (בִּינָה) my thoughts “ Therefore, the accent is above on the” beth," and its meaning is like הָבֵן, understand.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="had been mourning: ">when he saw that Cyrus had curtailed the construction of the Temple, for he had ordered to commence it, and he reneged because of the missive of the adversaries of Judah and Benjamin: Rehum the adviser and Shimshai the scribe, as is written in the Book of Ezra (4:5).</text>
      <text title="three weeks of days: ">twenty-one years. They are eighteen years from the one year of Darius the Mede, when he [Daniel] put to his heart to calculate the seventy years of the exile, as it is written: until the second year of Darius the Persian, the son of Esther, who built the Temple. As for the three extra years, I do not know whether he started to fast before them or whether the duration of the acceptance of the vow of his fasts terminated three years after the building.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="white bread: ">Heb. לֶחֶם חֲמֻדֹת, white (lit. clean) bread, as Onkelos rendered (Gen. 27:15): “Esau’s clean clothes (הַחֲמֻדֹת),” דַּכְיָתָא, clean.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="clad in linen: ">a linen garment.</text>
      <text title="with a girdle of gold studded with jewels: ">Heb. בְּכֶתֶם אוּפָז, with a girdle of a cluster of pearls. Every [instance of] כֶּתֶם is an expression of a cluster of gold and precious stones.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="And his body was like tarshish: ">Our Sages of blessed memory explained in Tractate Hullin (9lb): “His body was two thousand parasangs large, like the measurement of the sea named Tarshish, and that is the sea of Africa (the Mediterranean).”</text>
      <text title="brandished: ">Heb. קָלָל, smelted, refined, and shiny.</text>
      <text title="like the voice of a multitude: ">like the voice of a gathering of a large multitude, whose voice is heard from afar.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="but the men who were with me: ">Our Sages of blessed memory said that they were Haggai, Zechariah, and Malachi.</text>
      <text title="but a great quaking fell upon them: ">Our Sages of blessed memory said that although a person does not see something of which he is terrified, his guardian angel, who is in heaven, does see it; therefore, he becomes terrified.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="was turned in me into corruption: ">Heb. לְמַשְׁחִית, lit. to a destroyer. To corruption, and it is customary for Biblical verses to speak in this manner, like (Jer. 5:8): “They were like armed stallions early in the morning.” מַשְׁכִּים is the equivalent of בְּהַשְׁכָּמַת הַבּקֶר, in the early morning.</text>
      <text title="I could not summon up strength: ">i.e., I did not gather. All my strength left my innards.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="I fell into a sound sleep: ">out of great fright.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="and moved me: ">as one who moves a sleeping person to awaken him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="man of desirable qualities: ">אִישׁ חֲמֻדוֹת, pure man.</text>
      <text title="upright: ">Heb. עַל עָמְדֶ, on the stand of your feet.</text>
      <text title="I have been sent to you: ">I have been sent to you from the Omnipresent.</text>
      <text title="quaking: ">[as translated,] quaking.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="and I have come because of your words: ">I have come on this mission because of your words. Our Rabbis, however, explained in Tractate Yoma (77a): “and I came within the curtain because of you, for I was banned from its midst.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="has been standing against me: ">to battle with me in heaven by requesting an extension for the kingdom for Persia to enable them to subjugate you (Israel). Behold twenty-one days that he has been standing against me.</text>
      <text title="the first princes: ">those counted first among those who enter.</text>
      <text title="and I remained there: ">to silence the princes of Persia in heaven.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="for there is yet a vision: ">to tell you what has not yet been told, and it will come in many days at an appointed time.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="my joints turned upon me: ">Heb. צִירַי. These are the ends of the bones, all the limbs that are thrust into their sockets and turn within them like a door on its hinge in the socket of the threshold. My joints turned to become dislocated from their place out of much trembling and quaking.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="this servant of my lord: ">He refers to himself as a servant, and to the angel as “my lord,” i.e., to say, How will your servant be able to speak with you?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="And now I shall return to battle with the prince of Persia: ">and I know that I will be victorious, but when the time of the kingdom of the heathens [Greece Malbim ed., Antiochus Vilna ed.] arrives, I know that I will leave, and he will enter after thirty-four years of the existence of the Temple. Alexander of Macedon will rise, for although Israel was subjugated by the kings of Persia in those days, they exacted a light tribute from them, and they did not burden them heavily because the Holy One, blessed be He, caused them to have mercy on them. But the kings of the heathens [Greece, Antiochus] laid a heavy yoke upon them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="what is inscribed in a true script: ">the document of the decree is true, but not one of the heavenly princes is exerting himself to assist me with all these, except etc.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="11">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="As for me, in the first year of Darius the Mede: ">when the kingdom of Babylon fell, and the rule of Media and Persia commenced, and the princes of Media and Persia entreated the Omnipresent to make the yoke of their frightful rule heavy upon you, I, Gabriel, stood as a supporter and as a stronghold for Michael, your prince.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="Behold three more kings: ">Our Sages of blessed memory in Seder Olam (ch. 28) said: “This refers to Cyrus, Ahasuerus, and Darius who rebuilt the Temple. Now what is the meaning of fourth’? The fourth, counting from Media.” In the book of Joseph Ben Gorion, however, it is written that Cyrus had a son who succeeded him before the reign of Ahasuerus, named Cambyses.</text>
      <text title="and when he becomes strong: ">i.e., Darius.</text>
      <text title="with his wealth, he will arouse: ">his entire kingdom to wage war against the kingdom of the heathens.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And a mighty king will arise: ">in Greece, viz. Alexander of Macedon.</text>
      <text title="and do according to his will: ">with Darius the king of Persia, and he will slay him and receive his kingdom, and the Persians will be enslaved by the heathens [the Greeks.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="And when he arises, his kingdom will be broken: ">When he becomes very strong and reaches the height of his strength, his kingdom will be broken, meaning that he will die.</text>
      <text title="and it will be divided to the four directions of the heavens: ">It is written in the book of Ben Gorion (ch. 14) that he divided his kingdom between the four heads of his family; they are the four heads of the leopard that Daniel saw (above 7:6): “And behold another one, like a leopard, and it had four wings of a bird on its back, and the beast had four heads.” He gave this one dominion in the east, this one in the west, this one in the north and this one in the south, and so in the first vision (8:8): “an appearance of four sprouted in its stead,” concerning the horns of the he-goat.</text>
      <text title="but not to his posterity: ">The dominion will not come to his sons but to his family members. [The word] אַחֲרִיתוֹ coincides only with the expression of sons, and so Scripture states (Amos 4:2): “and you shall be borne on shields and your posterity (אַחֲרִיתְכֶן) in fishing boats,” which Jonathan renders: and your sons (sic) and daughters in fishermen’s boats.</text>
      <text title="and not like the dominion that he ruled: ">but the kingdom of these will not be as strong as that of Alexander.</text>
      <text title="for his kingdom will be uprooted: ">to divide to these four heads and to others besides these.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="And the king of the south will overwhelm: ">The head who will reign in the south will be stronger than the head opposite him who reigns in the north, and [stronger] than his officers.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="to make a compromise: ">a compromise of peace between him and her father.</text>
      <text title="will not retain, etc.: ">The king of the north will capture her, those who brought her, and her father who begot her and supported her in her time of trouble.</text>
      <text title="will not retain: ">The arm of those who brought her [will not retain] strength to stand, [and her father will not prevail] before him, neither he nor his arm, meaning his mighty men.</text>
      <text title="will be surrendered: ">into the hands of the king of the north, she and those who brought her, and he who begot her, i.e., her father.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="A scion of her roots will arise: ">a son sitting on his position, on the throne of the kingdom.</text>
      <text title="and he will come to the army: ">to the king of the north.</text>
      <text title="into the stronghold of the king of the north: ">i.e., in the cities of his strength, in his fortresses.</text>
      <text title="and he will succeed in them: ">Heb. וְעָשָׂה בָהֶם, lit. and he will succeed against them.</text>
      <text title="and take hold: ">and he will conquer them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="their princes: ">[as translated,] their princes.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="And he will come into the kingdom of the king of the south: ">Through the kingdom of the king of the south, who was her father’s father, he will return to his land, which is Egypt, as is stated above: “will bring in captivity to Egypt.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="And his sons: ">[i.e., the sons] of the king of the north will agitate.</text>
      <text title="and he will come: ">Heb. וּבָא בוֹא, like וְהוֹלֵ הָלוֹ. The son of the king of the north will come and pass to the land of the south.</text>
      <text title="and he will return and agitate: ">against the king of the south.</text>
      <text title="until his stronghold: ">his fortified city.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="will wage war: ">will fight against the people.</text>
      <text title="and the multitude will be given into his hand: ">[i.e., the multitude] of the king of the north [will be given] into his hand.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And the multitude will be raised up: ">that of the king of the north, to become very haughty, for they planned in their hearts to be victorious in the war.</text>
      <text title="and he will fell myriads: ">many of the army of the king of the south.</text>
      <text title="but he will not prevail: ">Nevertheless, the victory of the war will not be his.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="and the sons of the renegades of your people will exalt themselves to bring about the vision: ">I saw in the name of Rav Saadia Gaon that they were the renegades of Israel and their company.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="and the people of his chosen ones: ">will be in the war.</text>
      <text title="will have no strength to stand: ">before the king of the north, and although there is a superfluous “vav” here, it is customary for Scripture to speak in this manner as in, for example: “As for its nobles, there are none (וְאֵין) who proclaim the kingdom,” Isaiah (34:12).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="will do: ">The king of the north, who comes to the king of the south, [will do] as he wishes.</text>
      <text title="in the land of beauty: ">in the land of Israel.</text>
      <text title="and he will destroy it: ">He will destroy the land with his army.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="And he will set his face: ">i.e., the king of the north, to come into the strength of the entire kingdom of the king of the south.</text>
      <text title="and the upright will be with him: ">and Israel will be with the king of the south. Also with them will the king of the north battle in those days.</text>
      <text title="and he will succeed: ">Heb. וְעָשָׂה, lit. and he will do.</text>
      <text title="Now the daughter of the women he will give him to destroy her: ">This is the nation of Israel, [referred to in Song of Songs 1:8 as] “the fairest of women.” The king of the north will command the general of his army to destroy her. I say that he is Antiochus, the king of Greece, who issued decrees against Israel, and he commanded his general, Phillip, to kill whoever identified himself as a Jew, as is written in the book of Josiphon (ch. 18).</text>
      <text title="but it will not stand: ">this counsel of his.</text>
      <text title="and she will not be for him: ">the daughter of the women, for Mattathias the son of Johanan will rise and break off his [Antiochus’s] yoke from Israel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="and the Prince will terminate his blasphemy to Him: ">His reproach and his blasphemy, with which he blasphemed the Holy One, blessed be He, and Israel, as is written in the book of Josiphon (ch. 20), and He punished him, for He smote him with evil boils while he was in transit, for he went to besiege Jerusalem, and his flesh became putrid, his limbs fell off and he ordered his slaves to bring him back to Antioch, but he did not manage to get there before he died of evil illnesses.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="to the strongholds of his land: ">to return to his fortified city.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="And one who removes the oppressor will stand on his base: ">and Mattathias the son of Johanan, who removed the oppressor from Israel, and who is the glory of the kingdom of Israel, will strengthen himself on his base on Mt. Modin, for he will be a prince and a mighty man, he and all his descendants after him, viz. the Hasmoneans.</text>
      <text title="in a few days it will be broken: ">In a few days, their kingdom will be broken.</text>
      <text title="but not with anger: ">of another nation.</text>
      <text title="and not with war: ">but from themselves and with themselves, that Hyrcanus and Aristobulus will be jealous over the throne.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="And a contemptible person will stand on his base: ">Then the kingdom of Rome will strengthen itself on its stand, as it says (Obad. 1:2): “you are very despised,” and the Romans will rise and take the kingdom from the Greeks.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="And the arms of inundation: ">And the mighty of the kingdom, who previously were inundating and powerful, will be inundated before the Romans and be broken.</text>
      <text title="and also the king with whom they made a covenant: ">Also the king of Israel, who will form a treaty with them, will ultimately be inundated from before him, for [the Romans] will violate the treaty and betray them, as our Sages of blessed memory said: “Twenty-six years they kept their trust with Israel, but later they subjugated them.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="And from the alliance with him he will work deceitfully: ">And from the alliance that Rome will make with Israel, he will work deceitfully, for he will not reveal his evil plan.</text>
      <text title="and he will go up: ">from his place.</text>
      <text title="and overpower: ">in all places around the land of Judea: in Edom, in Ammon, and in Moab.</text>
      <text title="with few people: ">He will not require a massive army, for the king of Judea will aid him, and so it is written in the book of Josiphon (ch. 23).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="plunder and spoils and belongings he will distribute to them: ">He will distribute to those who accept their yoke upon themselves until they conquer all with flattery and smooth speech.</text>
      <text title="will distribute: ">Heb. יִבְזוֹר, like יִפְזוֹר. and so (Ps. 68:31): “he scatters (בִּזַר) peoples.”</text>
      <text title="and about the fortresses: ">of the nations he will devise in his plans-to station [in them] the heads of his troops until the time that all will be conquered under them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="and he will not stand: ">the king of the south.</text>
      <text title="because they will devise plans against him: ">They will plot against him to fell him through the bribery that they will bribe his officers to betray him, as he concludes: “and those who eat his food will break him.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="his food: ">Heb. פַּתבָּגוֹ, his food; one who takes a portion from his table.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="As for the two kings: ">the officer of the Romans and the king with whom they made to covenant, which is mentioned above. That is Hyrcanus, who will form an alliance to aid him so that he, too, will aid him against Aristobulus his brother, ruling in Jerusalem.</text>
      <text title="their hearts are to do evil: ">to the people of your nation, to harm Judea.</text>
      <text title="and on one table: ">They will murmur lies about the kingdom of Aristobulus.</text>
      <text title="but it will not succeed: ">for Israel will not be surrendered to destruction in those days.</text>
      <text title="for there is still an end to the appointed time: ">of the destruction, at the end of sixty two weeks [of years], stated in this Book (9:25), and that appointed time is in the days of Agrippa, the son of Agrippa of the seed of Herod.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="And he will return: ">The Roman king [will return] to his land from [fighting] with the king of the south with many possessions.</text>
      <text title="and his heart is on the covenant with the holy ones: ">to abrogate his treaty with Israel.</text>
      <text title="and he will succeed: ">Heb. וְעָשָׂה, lit. and he will do, i.e., and he will succeed and return to his land.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="After a time: ">Heb. לַמּוֹעֵד, after a time, but this coming will not be as successful as the first one mentioned above (verse 7): “A scion of her roots will arise etc.,” in which the king of the north succe eded over the king of the south, or like the last, meaning this second time, about which we said: “and he will return to his land” with many possessions.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="will come upon him: ">to battle with him.</text>
      <text title="companies: ">Heb. צִיִים.</text>
      <text title="Kittites: ">Romans, troops from the kingdom of Rome who will rebel against him.</text>
      <text title="and he will be crushed: ">He will be slightly broken.</text>
      <text title="and he will return and be wroth with the holy covenant: ">And he will return to his land and abrogate the treaty he had made with Israel.</text>
      <text title="and he will return and contemplate those who abandoned the holy covenant: ">He will put his mind to it and contemplate that Israel has abandoned the holy covenant (and law), and unwarranted hatred and controversy will increase in the Second Temple [era], as is written in the book of Josiphon (ch. 45), and they will shed innocent blood, and he will rely on this and know that he will succeed, and he will abrogate his treaty with them and provoke them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="And arms from him will stand: ">He will send his officers and his mighty men to Jerusalem.</text>
      <text title="and they will profane: ">the stronghold of the Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="And those who deal wickedly against the covenant: ">The renegades of Israel, who will join him and deal wickedly against their covenant with their fellows, he will flatter with smooth speech.</text>
      <text title="but the people that knows its God: ">but the devout of Israel, who will adhere to the fear of their God will grasp it and not abandon it.</text>
      <text title="and perform: ">their Torah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="And the wise of the people: ">the wise among them, such as the household of Rabbi [Judah Hanasi] and the sages of the generations.</text>
      <text title="will allow the public to understand: ">They will preach the Torah to the common people and encourage them to adhere to it.</text>
      <text title="will stumble: ">in their exile by the sword and by flames, etc.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="they will be helped with a little help: ">Through bribes and the money that they will pay tribute to their enemies, they will be helped.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="will stumble to clarify some of them: ">They will stumble in the calculations of the end, for they will put their mind to refine them and to resolve them to know them, but they will err concerning them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="And the king will do as he wishes: ">the kingdom of Rome.</text>
      <text title="and he will succeed until the fury is spent: ">until the wrath of the Holy One, blessed be He, returns from Israel.</text>
      <text title="when it will be finished and executed: ">when His decree will be finished. כִּי is like כַּאֲשֶׁר, when.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="And he will not contemplate the God of his fathers: ">he will not put his mind to the Holy One, blessed be He, Who is the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, his [i. e., Israel’s] forefathers.</text>
      <text title="the most desirable of women: ">the nation of Israel, [called] fairest of women.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="38">
      <text title="But the god of the strongholds: ">the god of the cherubim who will make a treaty with him.</text>
      <text title="on its base he will honor: ">for he will flatter the nations to be subservient to him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="39">
      <text title="And he will construct: ">buildings.</text>
      <text title="for the fortresses of the strongholds with a foreign god: ">i.e., in honor of a foreign god.</text>
      <text title="whomever he will recognize, he will honor increasingly: ">He will increase the honor [and greatness] of those princes whom he will see fit to recognize their faces and to flatter.</text>
      <text title="and he will apportion: ">to them.</text>
      <text title="for a price: ">for little money.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="40">
      <text title="And at the time of the end: ">when our redemption draws near.</text>
      <text title="and the king of the north will storm over him: ">over the king of the south.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="12">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Now at that time, Michael… will be silent: ">He will be silent like a mute person, for he will see the Holy One, blessed be He, judging by Himself and saying, “How will I destroy a great nation like this for the sake of Israel?”</text>
      <text title="and it will be a time of distress: ">in heaven there will be accusations against Torah scholars, [and there will be] plunderers and plunderers of plunderers, as our Rabbis said in the Aggadah in the last chapter of Kethuboth (112b).</text>
      <text title="your people will escape: ">The kingdom of Gog will be destroyed and Israel will escape.</text>
      <text title="everyone who is found inscribed in the book: ">This is a short verse, [meaning] whoever is found inscribed in this Book, through the dreams inscribed in it (7:11): “until the beast is slain” ; (verse 18): “and the high holy ones will receive the kingdom.” All will be fulfilled.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="And many who sleep in the dust of the earth will awaken: ">The dead will come to life.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And the wise: ">who engaged in the Torah and in the commandments, will shine like the brightness of the sky.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="and when they have ended shattering the strength of the holy people: ">Heb. נַפֵּץ יַד, lit. shattering the hand. When Israel’s strength terminates, [similar to] (Deut. 32:36): “that power has vanished (אָזְלַת יַד) and nothing left to keep or abandon.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="but I did not understand: ">I did not know what “the time of two times and a half” means.</text>
      <text title="what is the end of these: ">the end of these calculations.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="until the time of the end: ">until our redemption draws near.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="They will be clarified and whitened: ">[i. e.,] these calculations.</text>
      <text title="and… will be purified: ">[i.e.,] many [will be purified] by them to understand them.</text>
      <text title="and the wicked will pervert: ">the calculations by computing them incorrectly, and when they terminate, they will say that there is no more redemption.</text>
      <text title="will not understand: ">All the wicked [will not understand] them.</text>
      <text title="but the wise will understand: ">them when the time of the end arrives.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="And from the time the daily sacrifice was removed: ">in order to place a silent abomination in its stead, are days of one thousand two hundred and ninety years since the daily sacrifice was removed until it will be restored in the days of our King Messiah, and this calculation coincides with the calculation of (8:14): “evening and morning, two thousand and three hundred” from the day of their exile to Egypt until the final redemption: Egyptian exile 210; From their Exodus until the First Temple 480; First Temple 410; Babylonian exile 70; Second Temple 420; Totaling 1590. The daily sacrifice was removed six years before the destruction, which equals 1584. Add 1290, and the total sum is 2874; like the numerical value of בֹּקֶר עֶרֶב [574] plus 2300 [2874].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="Fortunate is he who waits etc.: ">Forty five years are added to the above number, for our King Messiah is destined to be hidden after he is revealed and to be revealed again. So we find in Midrash Ruth, and so did Rabbi Eleazar HaKalir establish (in the concluding poem of the morning service of the portion dealing with the month of Nissan): “and he will be concealed from them six weeks of years.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="go to the end: ">You will depart to your everlasting home.</text>
      <text title="to your lot: ">to receive your portion with the righteous.</text>
      <text title="at the end of the days: ">Heb. לְקֵץ הַיָמִין, like הַיָמִים בְּאַחֲרִית. We cannot interpret הַיָמִין as an expression of the right hand, because it is mentioned in the Large Masorah among the six words that are unusual because they have a final “nun” at the end of the word, which serves instead of a “mem,” and there is none like them, e.g. (Job 31:10): “and may others (אֲחֵרִין) kneel upon her;” (ibid. 24:22): “and he is not sure of life (בַּחַיִין) ” (Ezek. 4: 9): “take yourself wheat (חִטִין) ” ; (ibid. 26:18): “Now the isles (הָאִיִן) will tremble;” (Prov. 31:3): “to the pleasures of kings;” (here): “to the end of the days (הַיָמִין).”</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
</book>