<book>
  <chapter id="1">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="The words of Jeremiah son of Hilkiah: ">Let the son of the corrupt woman, whose deeds are properJeremiah was descended from Rahab the harlotand let him reprove the son of the righteous woman whose deeds are corrupt these are Israel who corrupted their deeds who are descended from legitimate seed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="To whom the word of the Lord came: ">Upon whom the Shechinah commenced to rest at that time.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And he was in the days of Jehoiakim: ">And he was a prophet all the remaining days of Josiah, the days of his son Jehoiakim, and the days of his son Zedekiah, until the end of the eleventh yearthat is the yearuntil the exile of Jerusalem in the fifth month.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="When I had not yet formed you in the womb, etc.: ">Since the days of the first man. The Holy One, blessed be He, showed Adam each generation and its prophets.</text>
      <text title="I… formed you: ">Heb. אצרך, an expression of צורה, a form.</text>
      <text title="I knew you: ">connois toi in O.F. Comp. (Exodus 6:3), “I was not known (נודעתּי) to them.”</text>
      <text title="I appointed you: ">I appointed you for this.</text>
      <text title="a prophet to the nations: ">To Israel, who behave like the nations. In this manner it is expounded in Sifrei on the verse: “A prophet from your midst, etc.” (Deut. 18:15), will set up for you and not for those who deny the Torah. How then do I fulfill “A prophet to the nations I made you” ? To the children of Israel who deport themselves with the customs of the nations. It can further be interpreted: “A prophet for the nations,” like “About the nations,” to give them to drink the cup of poison, to prophesy retribution upon them, as it is said: “Take this cup of the wine of wrath from My hand, you shall give all the nations to drink of it” (infra 25:15). Another explanation of “When you had not yet emerged from the womb I appointed you” is: Concerning you I said to Moses: “I will set up a prophet… like you” (Deut. 18:18). This one reproved them, and this one reproved them. This one prophesied for forty years and this one prophesied for forty years.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="Alas: ">This is an expression of wailing (konpljjnt in 0.F.).</text>
      <text title="for I am a youth: ">I am not worthy to reprove them. Moses reproved them shortly before his death, when he was already esteemed in their eyes through the many miracles that he had performed for them. He had taken them out of Egypt, split the Reed Sea for them, brought down the manna, caused the quails to fly, given them the Torah, brought up the well. I come to reprove them at the beginning of my mission.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="wherever I send you: ">to the heathens.</text>
      <text title="and whatever I command you: ">to Israel, you shall speak.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="And the Lord stretched forth His hand: ">Every sending mentioned concerning a hand is an expression of stretching forth. Another explanation is like the Targum: And the Lord sent the words of His prophecy.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="I have appointed you: ">I have appointed you over the heathens.</text>
      <text title="to uproot and to crush: ">(depayser in French, to uproot) and over Israel to build and to plant if they heed. So did Jonathan paraphrase it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="a rod of an almond tree: ">(amendleer in O.F.) Jonathan, however, renders: A King who hastens to do evil.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="You have seen well: ">This almond tree hastens to blossom before all other trees. I, too, hasten to perform My word. And the Midrash Aggadah (Ecc. Rabbah 12:8) explains: An almond tree takes twenty-one days from its blossoming until it is completely ripe, as the number of days between the seventeenth of Tammuz, when the city was broken into, until the ninth of Ab, when the Temple was burnt.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="a bubbling pot: ">[lit. blown up,] seething (boillant in French).</text>
      <text title="whose foam: ">[lit. and its face,] its seething (et ses ondes in O.F.) [and its waves].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="From the north the misfortune will break forth: ">Babylon is on the north of Eretz Israel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="And I will utter My judgments against them: ">I will debate with them, with Judah and Jerusalem.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="And you shall gird your loins: ">This is an expression of quickening like a man of valor.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="against the Kings of Judah: ">lit. to the Kings of Judah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="And they shall fight against you: ">They shall quarrel and fight against you to refute the words of your prophecy.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="2">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="I remember to you: ">Were you to return to Me, I would desire to have mercy on you for I remember the loving kindness of your youth and the love of the nuptials of your wedding canopy, when I brought you into the wedding canopy, and this (כלולתיך) is an expression of bringing in. Your nuptials (Noces in O.F.). Now what was the loving kindness of your youth? Your following My messengers, Moses and Aaron, from an inhabited land to the desert without provisions for the way since you believed in Me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="Israel is holy: ">like terumah.</text>
      <text title="the first of His grain: ">Like the first of the harvest before the Omer, which it is forbidden to eat, and whoever eats it is liable, so will all those who eat him be guilty. So did Jonathan render it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="And they did not say, Where is the Lord: ">that we should follow other gods?</text>
      <text title="plains: ">Heb. ערבה (planure in O.F.), related to pianoro in Old Italian, meaning ‘a plateau.’</text>
      <text title="and pits: ">Heb. ושוחה (enfosses in O.F.), pitted.</text>
      <text title="waste: ">Heb. ציה (degat in French).</text>
      <text title="and darkness: ">Heb. וצלמות. An expression of darkness.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="to a forest land: ">To the land of Israel which is planted like כרמל, meaning: planted like a forest.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="and those who hold onto the Torah: ">The Sanhedrin.</text>
      <text title="and the rulers: ">the kings.</text>
      <text title="prophesied by Baal: ">In the name of Baal.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Therefore, I will still contend: ">Before I bring misfortune upon you, I will still contend with you through My prophets, although I have already contended with you many days.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="the isles of the Kittites: ">To the isles of the Kittites. איי is (isles in French).</text>
      <text title="and send to Kedar: ">And send to Kedar to see their custom.</text>
      <text title="and consider diligently: ">And put your heart to it to consider the matter diligently.</text>
      <text title="whether: ">Heb. הן, like אם, if. Whether either of those nations exchanged its god although they are no gods, yet My nation exchanged their glory, with which they were honored. The Kittites and the Kedarites were tent dwellers and cattle herders, who would travel, go, and wander from pasture to pasture and from desert to desert, and they carry their gods with them to the place where they encamp. But I carried you until I established you, yet you forsook Me. This is how Jonathan paraphrased it. Our Sages said however: The Kittites worshipped water and the Kedarites worshipped fire. And although they know that water quenches fire, they did not forsake their god.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="for what does not avail: ">For an idol that does not avail.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="O heavens, be astonished: ">Heb. שמו, an expression of astonishment, like השתוממוּ. It is the imperative form, with the same vowel points as (I Sam. 14:9): “If they say thus to us,” Wait (דּמּוּ)."</text>
      <text title="and storm: ">Heb. ושערו, an expression of סער, a storm.</text>
      <text title="become very desolate: ">As though you are becoming desolate because of the Temple that is destined to be destroyed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="two evils: ">Had they exchanged their Deity [lit. their fear] for one His equal, it would be one evil, and now that they have forsaken Me, that I am a spring of living waters, to follow idols, which are like cisterns of stored up water, and they are broken and cracked, and their water is absorbed in their cracks, these are two evils.</text>
      <text title="to dig: ">Heb. לחצב, lit. to hew.</text>
      <text title="that do not hold: ">(Tendront in O.F.) their water, for the water will make their edge and their walls muddy, and they cave in.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="Is he a home born slave?: ">The son of a maidservant.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="roar: ">roar, a present tense.</text>
      <text title="young lions: ">Symbolic of kings.</text>
      <text title="were burnt: ">were burnt with fire.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="Also the children of Noph and Tahpanhes: ">They are the Egyptians upon whom you trust for aid.</text>
      <text title="will break your crown: ">They will break your skull. ירעוּך is an expression of breaking (רציצה), as we translate ורצוץ, “and crushed” (Deut. 28:33), וּרעיע.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="Is not this caused to you: ">Is not this misfortune and this retribution caused to you by the guilt and the iniquity that you have forsaken the Lord your God?</text>
      <text title="at the time He leads you by the way: ">For He would teach you the good and the straight way.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="what have you to do in the way of Egypt: ">Why do you leave Me and trust in Egypt?</text>
      <text title="to drink the water of the Shihor: ">For they drowned your male children in the Nile. Shihor is the Nile, as it is said: “From the Shihor which is before Egypt,” in the Book of Joshua (13:3).</text>
      <text title="and what have you to do: ">to rebel against Me so that you should be exiled to the way of Assyria, to the other side of the Euphrates River?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="Your evil will chastise you: ">Eventually, your evil will bring suffering upon you.</text>
      <text title="and your backslidings: ">, Heb. ומשבותיך, an expression related to “backsliding children (שובבים)” (infra 3:22).</text>
      <text title="will reprove you: ">Heb. תוכחך, an expression of reproof.</text>
      <text title="and the fear of Me was not: ">My fear was not in your heart that you should fear Me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="I broke your yoke: ">To the wooden yoke an expression of breaking applies, and to the yoke-bands which are of leather an expression of tearing open applies.</text>
      <text title="yoke-bands: ">[מוסרותיך are the] ropes used to shackle the yoke [to the animal].</text>
      <text title="and you said, “I will not transgress.”: ">your words.</text>
      <text title="but on every lofty hill: ">Put you did not keep your promise, for on every lofty hill you recline (צעה). This is an expression of a bed and a sheet (מצע). [The word] כי serves as an expression of ‘but.’</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="I planted you a noble vine stock: ">Heb. שורק is the branches of a good vine, that is to say the children of pious and righteous fathers. Its midrashic interpretation is: I planted you שורק. I added for you to the seven commandments of the children of Noah, six hundred and six, as is the numerical value of שורק.</text>
      <text title="degenerate: ">Heb. סוּרי (Destoultours in O.F).</text>
      <text title="wild vine: ">that grows in the forests.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="with natron: ">A type of earth with which garments are cleansed and rubbed.</text>
      <text title="soap: ">Heb. בֹּרִית, cleanliness. Comp.“And pure (וּבַר) of heart” (Ps. 24:4). Some explain בֹּרִית as savon in French, soap.</text>
      <text title="your iniquity is stained: ">Jon. renders: Like the mark of a stain that is unclean, so have your sins increased before Me. כתם is tka in O.F.</text>
      <text title="your iniquity: ">This is said concerning the iniquity of the ‘Golden Calf,’ which remains in existence forever, as it is stated: “And on the day of My visitation, I will visit upon them their sin” (Exodus 32:34). All visitations that come upon Israel have part of the iniquity of the Golden Calf in them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="See your way in the valley: ">See what you have done opposite Beth-Peor, and until now you adhere to that way like a swift she camel clinging to her ways.</text>
      <text title="young she-camel: ">Heb. בכרה, a young female camel, that loves to wander.“The young camels (בכרי) of Midian” (Isa. 60:6) is translated “and they are young camels,” as we find in Sanhedrin 52a: There are many old camels laden with the skins of young camels (הוגני).</text>
      <text title="clinging: ">Adhering to the ways of her youth, an expression similar to: “it would have clung (מסריך סריך)” (Chullin 51a). This may be associated with “a shoe thong נעל) (שרוך ” (Gen. 14:23). She binds the ways of her youth in her heart.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="A wild donkey: ">(salvatico in O.F.) wild, and some interpret it as poulain in O.F., a foal.</text>
      <text title="accustomed to the desert: ">Accustomed to be in the deserts, so she loves to wander.</text>
      <text title="that snuffs up the wind: ">She opens her mouth and snuffs up the wind, and he always returns to his place.</text>
      <text title="her tendency like the sea creatures, who can hinder her?: ">That trait of the sea creatures that she has, for also the sea creature snuffs up the wind, as it is said: “They snuff up the wind like sea creatures” (infra 14:6). Who can hinder her from that trait? So it is with you who can return you from your evil way?</text>
      <text title="her tendency like a sea creature: ">Son dagronemant in O.F., dragon nature. Jonathan rendered it in this manner, כערודה. Another explanation: It is an expression of wailing, comp.“moaning and wailing”</text>
      <text title="all who seek her will not weary: ">For they will weary needlessly, for they will be unable to overtake her. What will her end be? In her month, they will find her. There is one month in the year that she sleeps for the whole month, and then she is captured. You, too, - one month (viz. Ab) was already prepared for you from the days of the spies, when your forefathers established it as a time of vain weeping, therein, you will be captured. (תּאניה ואניה) (Lam. 2:5). Another explanation: (sa contree in French,) her country, comp. Taanath Shiloh (Josh. 16:6).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="Withhold your foot from going barefoot: ">This your habit, like the wild donkey that loves to wander. My prophets say to you, “Withhold your foot from idolatry lest you go barefoot into exile and withhold your throat from dying of thirst.”</text>
      <text title="but you said: ">concerning the words of the prophets.</text>
      <text title="I despair: ">It is of no concern. I despair of your words. נואש is (nonkalajjr in O.F.) nonchalair in modern French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="when he is found out: ">At the beginning, when he is found to be a thief, and he was presumed to be faithful. In this manner, Jonathan rendered it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="and at the time of their misfortune they say: ">i.e., they say to Me, “Arise and save us.” Jonathan, too, translates in this manner: And at the time that misfortune befalls them, they deny their idols and confess before Me, and say. “Have mercy upon us and save us.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="as many as your cities were your gods: ">In every city was another god.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="Why do you contend: ">How do you come to contend with the quarrel and say, “We do not sin” ?</text>
      <text title="All of you have rebelled against Me: ">Even the righteous are meant. This is what people say, “With the thorn the cabbage suffers.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="In vain have I smitten: ">For no purpose, for it did not avail that they should receive correction.</text>
      <text title="Your sword devoured: ">your prophets, Zechariah and Isaiah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="See the word of the Lord: ">He took out to them the jar of manna. He said to them, “See here how helpful the word of the Lord is.”</text>
      <text title="was I a desert to Israel: ">Heb. המדבר. This is the interrogative form. Therefore, the ‘mem’ is punctuated ‘weak,’ i.e., without a ‘dagesh’ and the ‘heh’ with a ‘hataph-pattah.’ Did it seem to your forefathers that it was a desert when they traversed it? For I brought down for them this bread, the necessity of each day in its day.</text>
      <text title="thick darkness: ">מאפליה, an expression of darkness.</text>
      <text title="Why have My people said, “We have been separated…” ?: ">Heb. רדנו, we have been separated from You. Like one who separates (רודֶה) bread from the oven. So is the midrash of Rabbi Tanhuma (Bamidbar 2). Menahem, however, explains רדנוּ as an expression of descending (ירידה) and also in other manners (Machbereth Menahem, p. 162).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="How you adorn: ">Heb. תיטבי. You adorn yourself to greet your adulterers. Comp.“And she adorned her head” (I Kings 9:30) concerning Jezebel in the section dealing with Jehu.</text>
      <text title="even to the most evil you accustomed: ">You searched throughout all the evil ways to learn the most corrupt of them all. גם is an expression of ‘even.’</text>
      <text title="verily: ">Heb. לכן, an expression of a true oath. Verily, to the most evil way of all the ways you accustomed yourself.</text>
      <text title="you accustomed: ">Heb. למדת, lit. you taught.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="you did not find them breaking in: ">You did not find them breaking in when you slew them.</text>
      <text title="you did not find them: ">So does Scripture say for a feminine second person singular, and there are many such examples in the Book of Ezekiel (16:58), “You bore them (נשאתים).”</text>
      <text title="but for all these: ">i.e., because they were reproving you for all these things.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="And you said: ">i.e., you said in your heart.</text>
      <text title="But I am innocent: ">That I have purified my soul.</text>
      <text title="I contend with you: ">I will come with you in judgment.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="degrade yourself: ">Heb. תזלי, an expression of degradation.</text>
      <text title="to change your way: ">To leave Me and to rely on Egypt for aid in the days of Jehoiakim and Zedekiah (infra 37).</text>
      <text title="to change: ">Heb. לשנות, an expression of change.</text>
      <text title="as you were ashamed through Assyria: ">Upon whom Ahaz relied and “he oppressed him and did not strengthen him” (II Chron. 28:20).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="3">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="to say: ">I have to say that you are no longer fit for me, for so is the way of one who sends away his wife and she goes away, etc.</text>
      <text title="But you have played the harlot [with] many lovers: ">With many lovers. Nevertheless, return to Me.</text>
      <text title="yet return to me: ">Heb. ושוב, lit. and to return to me, like עשות, to do, and to return to Me, I long for you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="rivulets: ">rivulets of water.</text>
      <text title="you were not lain with: ">Heb. שלגת, an expression of a פילגש a concubine.</text>
      <text title="you sat for them: ">to be prepared to greet them.</text>
      <text title="like an Arab: ">A tent dweller, who is always found outside in the deserts, and because of this, he is called ערבי since he dwells in the ערבה, the plain.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="and the latter rain: ">The rain that falls in Nissan on the ears (מלילות) and the straws (קשים). מלקוש is (tardif in O.F.).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="Will you not from now: ">If only you repent of your evil and call me “My Father.” If you do so, will your Lord bear a grudge forever for what you have sinned? Will He keep it to eternity? He will not keep it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="Behold, you have spoken: ">with your mouth, “We will no longer come to You,” and that evil you will do, and you will not give any thought of returning.</text>
      <text title="and you were able: ">And you prevailed in rebelling with a victorious and irrefutable reply.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="In the days of King Josiah: ">when He commanded me to bring back the Ten Tribes,"Have you seen what the backsliding Israel has done? משבה is the same as שובבה, (envejjsede in O.F).</text>
      <text title="Israel: ">The Ten Tribes.</text>
      <text title="she goes: ">i.e., when she was still on her land before she was exiled in the days of Hezekiah with Hoshea son of Elah. הלכה means, she would go on every lofty mountain.</text>
      <text title="and she played the harlot there: ">i.e., she played the harlot by worshipping idols. וַתִּזְנִי is the equivalent of וַתִּזֶן, the ‘yod’ being superfluous.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And I said: ">through My prophets, Amos and Hosea son of Beeri and the other prophets, “You shall return to Me.”</text>
      <text title="And her treacherous sister Judah saw it: ">i.e., saw all this. The appellation “treacherous” is harsher than “backsliding.” Israel, since they were the first to sin, and they did not see any retribution from which to learn and to repent, are called “backsliding.” Judah, who saw that these went in exile and did not receive correction, are called “treacherous.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="And I saw, because of all that backsliding Israel had committed adultery: ">The signs of the intonation of this verse teach us its explanation. ישראל is punctuated with a ‘zakef-katan,’ separated from שלחתיה, I sent her away. שלחתיה, I sent her away, is punctuated with a ‘zakef-gadol’ by itself. And this is its explanation: I saw; i.e., I contemplated her to exact punishment upon her. And why? Because of all that backsliding Israel had committed adultery. And what was My vengeance? I sent her away from before Me. And treacherous Judah did not fear when she saw the retribution of Samaria, to set her heart to repent.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="and she committed adultery with the stones: ">Jonathan paraphrases: And she strayed with the worshippers of stones and wood. And Jonathan renders מִקֹל as an expression of lightness, since her idols were light in her eyes.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="And yet for all this: ">that they saw the misfortune of the retribution of their companions.</text>
      <text title="but falsely: ">Josiah’s generation would show themselves as righteous although they were wicked. They would make forms of pagan deities on the inside of their doors, half on this door and half on this one, and when the destroyers of idols would inspect, the door would be open, and they would not notice it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="has proved herself more righteous: ">She has been cleared and she has freed herself from an unfavorable verdict, for she had no one to learn from.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="Go and proclaim, etc.: ">Go, as the Targum renders, אזיל, the imperative form. Here he commanded him to go and bring back the Ten Tribes during the days of Josiah, as he states above that during the days of Josiah this prophecy was said to him and some of them returned in the eighteenth year of Josiah.</text>
      <text title="to the north: ">To the places where they were exiled there to Assyria.</text>
      <text title="My anger: ">My anger, so did Jonathan render it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="you have rebelled: ">Heb. פשעת.</text>
      <text title="and you have scattered your ways: ">This is an expression of harlotry, spreading the legs to the woman’s private parts.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="backsliding children: ">(Envasec in O.F.) That you perverted your way because of much good, that you enjoyed tranquility and pleasure, as Scripture states: They hum snatches of song to the tune of the lute (Amos 6:5), those who drink from bowls of wine (v. 6).</text>
      <text title="for I possessed you: ">and you are called by My name, that I am your Master, and it is not honorable for Me to leave you in the hands of My enemies.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="they will no longer say, “The ark of the Lord’s covenant”: ">For your entire assembly will be holy, and I will dwell therein as though it were an ark.</text>
      <text title="nor shall they remember it: ">Heb. יפקדו, like יזכרוּ, remember or mention.</text>
      <text title="nor shall it be done anymore: ">i.e., it shall not be done what was done with it already in Shiloh, that they brought it into the battle with the Philistines in the days of Eli.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="shall gather: ">Heb. ונקוו, an expression of: מקוה מים, a gathering of water.</text>
      <text title="the idea of: ">an expression of seeing. Comp. אשורנו “I see him” (Num. 24:17).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="the house of Judah will go with the house of Israel: ">They will join them and they will be added to them to be one kingdom.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="And I said: ">to Myself, etc. and therefore, I caused your forefathers to inherit them.</text>
      <text title="How shall I place you among the sons?: ">i.e., how shall I place you, my congregation and My nation, among the other sons, mingled with the heathens. I, therefore, selected a handsome portion, and I gave you a desirable land.</text>
      <text title="the beauty of hosts of nations: ">The beauty of all the hosts of nations.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="Truly: ">But you did not live up to My expectations [lit., do My thought], but like a woman who betrays her beloved because he cannot provide her sustenance, so did you betray Me, Who provides you with all good. So is the Midrash Aggadah (Tanhuma Mishpatim 17).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="A voice on the rivulets is heard: ">It is likely to be heard.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="Here we are, we have come to You: ">The prophet teaches them to confess and to say as follows, “Here we are, we have come to You… Truly, in vain… But the shameful thing has consumed, etc., Let us lie in our shame.” All this is the language of the prayer that the prophet teaches them to say. We have come אתנו.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="Truly, in vain: ">we awaited from the hills and the multitude of mountains where we worshipped idols.</text>
      <text title="Truly: ">in truth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="But the shameful thing: ">The idolatry with which we occupied ourselves, as Scripture states.“And they turned aside to the shameful thing” (Hosea 9:10).</text>
      <text title="consumed the toil of our fathers: ">Because of the iniquity of its worship, our toil was pillaged.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="4">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="If you return, O Israel: ">with this repentance, to Me, you will return to your original glory and greatness.</text>
      <text title="and if you remove your detestable things from My Presence: ">Then you shall not wander to go out in exile.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="And you will swear, “As the Lord lives,” in truth: ">When you swear by My name, you will swear in truth, not as now, that it is written concerning you, “And if they say, ‘As the Lord lives,’ surely they swear falsely” (5:2).</text>
      <text title="nations will bless themselves with him: ">If you do so, then nations will bless themselves with Israel. Every non-Jew will say to his son, “You shall be like So-and-so the Jew.”</text>
      <text title="boast: ">Heb. יתהללו, they will recite your praise. Another explanation of is יתהללו : Whoever is able to cleave to Israel will boast about the matter (porvanter in French).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="For so said the Lord, etc. Plow for yourself a furrow: ">Learn from the tillers of the soil, who plow it in the summer to kill the roots of the grasses, that it should not grow thorns at the time of sowing in the winter. You, too, improve your deeds before the evil befalls you, so that your prayer should not be rejected when you cry out.</text>
      <text title="and do not sow upon thorns: ">And let not your cry before Me be from amidst wickedness, but from amidst repentance, that you shall not resemble one sowing without plowing, and that turns into thorns (kardons in O.F., chardons in modern French).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="Circumcise yourselves to the Lord: ">Before My anger comes forth like fire. This is like plowing before the sowing.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="and say, “Sound a shophar…”: ">Warn the inhabitants of the land that they sound the shophar to flee.</text>
      <text title="assemble: ">Heb. מלאו. An expression of gathering, and there are many in the Scriptures: (Isaiah 31: 4) “Although a band of (מְלֹא) shepherds gather against him,” Also (infra 12:6) “They called after you a band (מָלֵא).” Also (Job 16: 10) “Together they gather (יתמלאוּן) against me.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="Raise a standard: ">to flee to Zion.</text>
      <text title="assemble: ">Heb. העיזו. Comp.“Send, gather (העז)” (Exodus 9:19).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="A lion has come up: ">That is Nebuchadnezzar.</text>
      <text title="from his thicket: ">It is customary for a lion to lie in wait in the thickets of the forest (espaises in O.F.).</text>
      <text title="will be desolate: ">Heb. תצינה, an expression of desolation.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="Because of this: ">What is “this?” “For the fierce anger etc.” Although he spoke above concerning Nebuchadnezzar in regards to the destruction, here he returns to speak of the death of Josiah.</text>
      <text title="for the fierce anger of the Lord etc.: ">Although Josiah repented wholeheartedly, it is stated concerning him. (II Kings 23:26)…“the Lord did not turn back from his great wrath… because of all the provocations that Manasseh had provoked Him.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="And it shall be on that day: ">On the day of Josiah they will wonder why so much befell him, for they do not know that his generation did not repent properly. When he came to abolish idolatry, what did the scorners of the generation do? They would engrave an image of a pagan deity on their doors, half of it on this door and half of it on this door. When he would open it, it was not discernible, and when he went away from there, he would close it, and it would join together.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="Surely You have misled: ">Heb. השא השאת (fa)tenter in O.F.), tempting, an expression like (Gen. 3:13) “The serpent misled me (השיאני),” for the false prophets prophesy for them, You will have peace.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="of this people: ">Concerning this people when they are all exiled.</text>
      <text title="has swept the rivulets: ">It sweeps even the fields with rivulets of water to make them into a desert. Another explanation: צח is an expression of thirst, which is translated צחותא.</text>
      <text title="[on] the way of the daughter of My people: ">That wind will come, and also, not to winnow the chaff from the threshing floor ([a] vanner in O.F.). Comp. (infra 15:7) “And I winnowed them with a sieve במזרה) (ואזרם.”</text>
      <text title="and not to cleanse: ">And not to cleanse grain does it come. That is to say, not for good but for evil, to exile men [women], and children, and livestock.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="A full spirit: ">of these retributions shall come to me.</text>
      <text title="A full spirit: ">A full spirit, that I will not retract and not repent.</text>
      <text title="spirit: ">(talant in O.F.)</text>
      <text title="debate: ">Heb. משפטים, an expression of debating.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="and like the whirlwind: ">(comme tourbillon in O.F.)</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="your iniquitous thoughts: ">Your injustice.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="For a voice proclaims from Dan: ">Jonathan paraphrases: “Behold the voice of the prophets prophesy about them that they will be exiled because they worshipped the calf that was in Dan, and people bringing bad tidings will come upon them because they subordinated themselves to the image that Micah erected on the mountain of the house of Ephraim.” Although the calves had already been exiled since the days of Sennacherib, their iniquity was still existing. Sin is harsh, for it destroys [lit. breaks] before it and after it; before it, since the days of Abraham, as it is stated (Gen. 14:14): “And he pursued until Dan.” As soon as he reached Dan, he grew faint [lit. his strength was weakened], for his children would, in the future, worship idols there, and after it, in the destruction of the Temple, as it is stated: “A voice proclaims from Dan.”</text>
      <text title="and announces calamity: ">Heb. און, a breach.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="besiegers: ">Heb. נצרים. Those who will make a siege upon them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="a field: ">like שדה, a field.</text>
      <text title="for she has rebelled against me: ">She has provoked Me. Comp. (Deut. 9:24) “You have been rebellious (ממרים),” provoking.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="have done these to you: ">To do these to you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="I writhe in pain: ">Heb. אוחילה. An expression of writhing in pain (חיל) and shuddering.</text>
      <text title="the walls of my heart!: ">(ettancon in O. F.), blocking wall, perhaps from late Latin, intimus, innermost.</text>
      <text title="you, my soul, have heard: ">From behind the curtain of heaven the ridings of the sound of the alarm of war reached me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="Destruction upon destruction: ">The destruction of Jerusalem upon the exile of Jeconiah.</text>
      <text title="in a moment my curtains: ">In a moment my curtains were plundered.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="How long will I see: ">these groups carrying the standard to come to wage war.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="moved to and fro: ">Heb. התקלקלו, they were uprooted and cast out of their place. Menahem associates it with: “He shakes the arrows to and fro (קלקל) ” (Ezek. 21:26).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="and behold, the fruitful field: ">The land, planted with all good like a forest, has become like a desert. The Midrash Aggadah states: “I saw the mountains” These are the Patriarchs. “And all the hills” These are the Matriarchs. That is to say that their merit was depleted. “There were no people” This refers to Moses, about whom it is said: “humbler than all the people” (Num. 12:3).“And behold the Karmel” This is Elijah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="but I will not make an end: ">of its inhabitants, for I will leave over refugees who will go into exile.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="shall mourn: ">Shall be destroyed.</text>
      <text title="I planned: ">Heb. זמתי, an expression of thought.</text>
      <text title="for that which I spoke: ">i.e., this retribution, and I will fulfill it.</text>
      <text title="and I will not turn back: ">And I will not repent to think good thoughts about them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="archers: ">Heb. רמה קשת, lit. bow shooters. Comp.“Cast (רמה) into the sea” (Exodus 15:1).</text>
      <text title="they came into the thickets: ">Into the thick forests, a place intertwined with thorns, to hide.</text>
      <text title="and they ascended among the boulders: ">Heb. ובכפים. סלע, a rock, is translated into Aramaic as בכפיא.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="that you wear crimson: ">to beautify yourself and to gain clemency before the plunderer.</text>
      <text title="that you enlarge… with paint: ">Heb. תקרעי. An expression of tearing, for the paint appears as widening the opening of the eye. So have I heard, and Menahem did not differentiate in the group of קרע.</text>
      <text title="paint: ">Heb. בפוך, an expression of a blue paint.</text>
      <text title="lovers: ">Heb. עגבים, those who jest with the women with various types of adultery. Comp. (Ezekiel 23:20) “She lusted (ותעגבה) for concubinage with them.”</text>
      <text title="they seek your life: ">They seek to kill you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="like a woman bearing her first child: ">Heb. כמבכירה, like a woman bearing her first child, the beginning of her birth.</text>
      <text title="who will wail: ">Heb. תתיפח, she will wail and cry out with sighs (konpljjnt in O.F:). Comp.“who speak (ויפח) violence” (Psalms 27:12), an expression of speech.</text>
      <text title="“Woe is to me…”: ">This is what she says.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="5">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="O Lord, Your eyes: ">are they not on people with faith, to do good to them? Now why have these betrayed You, and they do not seek faith?</text>
      <text title="You smote them: ">and they did not become ill because of the blow to lay it to their heart to repent of their evil.</text>
      <text title="to receive: ">Heb. קחת, equivalent to (לקחת) , to receive.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="And I said: ">The prophet says so, “They are but impoverished of wisdom,” these with whom I speak.</text>
      <text title="they have become foolish: ">Heb. נואלו, an expression of אויל, a fool, as the Targum renders: אטפשו.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="I will go to the great ones: ">They will hearken. But I did not avail, and they too together broke the yoke of the Holy One, blessed be He, off them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="a lion: ">The kingdom of Babylon.</text>
      <text title="a wolf: ">The kingdom of Media.</text>
      <text title="a leopard: ">The kingdom of Greece.</text>
      <text title="shall be torn to pieces: ">by Edom.</text>
      <text title="a wolf of the deserts: ">Heb. ערבות, an expression of (supra 2:6) ערבה ושוחה“plains and pits,” a wolf of the desert.</text>
      <text title="hastens: ">Heb. שקד. Menahem (p. 180) associates it with an expression of watching. Comp. (Prov. 8:34) “To watch (לשקוד) My doors daily.” And Jonathan rendered it as an expression of lying in wait.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="Shall I forgive you for this?: ">This is the rhetorical question, Shall I forgive you for this? And Menahem (p. 22) explains אי like אין, not. For this I will not forgive you, because your children have forsaken Me, when I sated them with all good.</text>
      <text title="they banded together: ">They gather in troops.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="Like armed stallions they would arise early: ">Like these stallions who are armed with erect membra, every morning they would arise at daybreak.</text>
      <text title="they would neigh: ">Heb. יצהלו. This too is an expression appropriate for horses. Comp. (8:16) “From the sound of the neighing (מצהלות) of his steeds,” an expression of shouting (esjodement in O.F.).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="Ascend upon its rows: ">Heb. בשרותיה, an expression of a plain. Menahem (p. 181) associates it as an expression of a wall with (II Sam. 22: 30) “I scale a wall (שור),” but נטישותיה (cep in Prov.) do not fitfor they are the roots of the vineyard to be associated either with the walls or with the plain. I say, therefore, that בשרותיה is an expression of the rows of the vineyard. Jonathan, however, rendered בשרותיה, in her cities, and נטישותיה, her palaces.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And [they] said, “It is not He”: ">[The Targum renders:] Our good fortune does not come before Him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="And the prophets shall become wind: ">As the Targum renders: And the false prophets shall become naught. That is to say, the prophecy that the false prophets prophesy for us in the name of the Holy One, blessed be Hetheir words shall turn to futility, and the speech of holiness that they say to us in the name of the Holy One, blessed be He, is not in them.</text>
      <text title="So shall be done to them: ">The prophet says to those who say this, “So shall be done to them as the Lord said to me, and what did the Lord say to me?” Because you have spoken this word, etc."</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="and it shall consume them: ">Heb. ואכלתם.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="mighty: ">Heb. איתן, strong.</text>
      <text title="It is an ancient nation: ">From days of yore it began to rebel against Me, in the generation of separation in the land of Shinar.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="His quiver: ">Heb. אשפתו. The place of the arrow case.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="He will impoverish your fortified cities [upon which you rely, with the sword]: ">This verse is in the wrong order [and should be arranged as follows:] He will impoverish with the sword your fortified cities upon which you rely.</text>
      <text title="impoverish: ">Heb. ירשש, he will impoverish.</text>
      <text title="with the sword: ">With troops. Comp.“And a sword will not pass in your land” (Lev. 26:6).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="Will you not fear Me?: ">Does not the sea, which is not concerned about retribution and does not look forward to receiving reward, fear Me and not cross the boundary that I set around it?</text>
      <text title="do you not quake: ">Heb. תחילו, an expression of fear.</text>
      <text title="and toss themselves: ">i.e., its waves, and they lift themselves to cross the border but cannot cross.</text>
      <text title="and its waves roar: ">A loud sound of roaring.</text>
      <text title="but they do not pass it: ">The waves do not pass the border.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="the early rain and the latter rain: ">Heb. יורה ומלקוש, as the Targum renders: בכיר ולקיש, the early rain and the latter rain.</text>
      <text title="the weeks of the laws of harvest: ">Seven weeks in which He ordained two ordinances of harvest, the ordinance of the omer, and the ordinance of the two breads.</text>
      <text title="He keeps for us: ">that the harvest should be in its time.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="have brought about these: ">Have brought about these laws. Have cast aside these laws from you, so they don’t guard you and you will be consumed from hunger.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="they lie in wait: ">Heb. ישור. Comp. למען שוררי because of those who lie in wait for me (Psalms 27: 11), an expression of “I see him (אשורנו) but not near” (Num. 24:17).</text>
      <text title="as a trap bites: ">As a trap that they make to catch deer in the forest, bites when his foot enters it and it bites him and holds onto his foot and he is caught, and the call this (piege in O. F.).</text>
      <text title="they stationed an ambush: ">(Canbel in O. F.) So do those who lie in wait make for a city or on the road.</text>
      <text title="they station: ">Heb. יציבו, like “the garrison (מצב) of the Philistines” (I Sam. 14:4).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="As a cage: ">That is a place where they fatten fowl, and so does Jonathan render it, like a fattening place, and in O.F. (frank).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="they have become thick: ">Heb. עשתו, an expression of “a block (עֶשֶת) of ivory” (Song 5:14), a thick body, and in O.F. enboeront.</text>
      <text title="they transgressed in deeds of wickedness: ">If evil or a sin came into their hand, they did not turn away from it, but transgressed it and committed it.</text>
      <text title="they did not plead the cause of the orphan: ">in order that they prosper.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="An appalling… thing: ">Heb. שמה, a wonder.</text>
      <text title="and horrible thing: ">Heb. ושערורה, a disgraceful thing to all, and what is the appalling thing? The prophets prophesy falsely and say, “Rob and plunder,” and the priests, who are the judges of the people and their overseers, govern the people on the hands of the prophets, that is to say, after them. Comp. (II Sam. 15) “And the king was crossing and all the people were crossing on his hand,” stated concerning David, meaning ‘after him.’ Here too, “on their hands” means ‘after them,’ to do according to the words of the prophets.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="6">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Gather the sons of Benjamin: ">to go to their cities to guard their fortifications.</text>
      <text title="Beth-hakerem: ">That is a place name.</text>
      <text title="raise a standard: ">a standard to gather and fight for your lives.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="The comely and the delicate one have I destroyed: ">Heb. דמיתי. Jonathan renders it as an expression related to (25:37) “And the dwellings of peace shall be destroyed (ונדמוּ).” Also (47: 5), “Ashkelon has been destroyed (נדמתה).”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="Shepherds and their flocks: ">Figurative of kings and their armies.</text>
      <text title="they feed bare: ">Heb. רעו, they eat.</text>
      <text title="his place: ">Heb. ידו [lit. his hand.] His place around him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="Prepare: ">Heb. קדשו.</text>
      <text title="woe is to us: ">at the time the day declines.</text>
      <text title="for the day has declined: ">When it declined to eventide, they ignited the Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="Cut the trees: ">Heb. עצה. This is not a ‘mappiq heh,’ yet it is an expression of a tree (עץ), for the expression of cutting is not appropriate for advice, (עצה), and עצה mentioned here is an expression of many trees, as דגה is an expression of many fish.</text>
      <text title="the city whose sins have been visited upon her: ">Heb. הפקד, whose visitation has come.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="As… lets… flow: ">Heb. כהקיר, an expression of a spring.</text>
      <text title="a well: ">Heb. בַּיִר, equivalent to בְּאֵר.</text>
      <text title="so has she let her evil flow: ">So does their evil flow, constantly increasing and renewing.</text>
      <text title="sickness and wounds: ">Therefore, I brought upon her sickness and wounds.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="Be corrected: ">Heb. הוסרי. Accept correction.</text>
      <text title="lest… be alienated: ">Heb. תקע, lest it be pulled away. יקע is an expression of joining. Comp.“and hang them up (והוקע)” (Num. 25:4), and it is sometimes an expression of detaching. There are many words that are used in such a manner.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="thoroughly glean: ">(grappiller in French). After the vineyard has been gathered, and gleanings are left, and the poor come and glean them, so will they spoil and return and spoil.</text>
      <text title="return your hand: ">You, the enemy, return your hand to spoil a second time, like a vintager who returns his hand for the search, who looks and searches for the gleanings. And so it was when he exiled Jehoiakim and slew him, and crowned Jeconiah, he returned three months later and exiled him. He returned eleven years later and exiled Zedekiah.</text>
      <text title="the branches: ">Heb. סלסלות (reverchedures in O.F). Comp. (Prov. 4:8) “Search for it (סלסלה) and it will exalt you.” So did Dunash (Teshuvoth Dunash p. 21) explain it. Menahem (Machbereth p. 126), however, explains it as an expression of a basket (סל) (paniers in O. F. baskets).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="and warn: ">Heb. ואעידה, an expression of warning.</text>
      <text title="clogged: ">Heb. ערלה, clogged, and so is every expression of ערלה.</text>
      <text title="a disgrace: ">They deride it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="Therefore, I am full of the fury of the Lord: ">My heart is full of the prophecy of the coming of the fury of the Lord upon them.</text>
      <text title="containing: ">Heb. הכיל, like להכיל, to contain ([a] souffrir in O.F.), to tolerate.</text>
      <text title="to pour it out upon the babes: ">to pour it upon the sucklings.</text>
      <text title="in the street: ">in the market.</text>
      <text title="one full of days: ">i.e., one close to death, older than ‘an old man.’</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="fields and wives together: ">shall be turned over to others.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="commit robbery: ">rob money.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="easily: ">It is easy for the false prophets to pronounce with their mouths and to say, “You shall have peace,” and with this thing they heal with their speech the breach destined to come upon them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="They should be ashamed: ">Heb. הובישו, they should be ashamed [from Jonathan].</text>
      <text title="to feel disgrace: ">Heb. הכלים, like להכלים.</text>
      <text title="Neither are they ashamed: ">They are not ashamed of their evil deeds.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="rest: ">Heb. מרגוע.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="And I have stationed lookouts over you: ">That is that they station men on the towers at the time of strife. A man looks and sees. If a troop is approaching the city he sounds a shophar and warns the people to arm and to come on the wall. I too appointed prophets who inform you about the impending retribution to alert yourselves and to mend your ways so that you be saved and that is like the shophar sounded by the lookout. Hearken to the sound of this shophar and arm yourselves.</text>
      <text title="And I have stationed: ">Heb. והקמותי. This means: I have already stationed for them. And so did Jonathan render: ואקימית, and I stationed.</text>
      <text title="lookouts: ">(Badetes in O.F.).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="what is within them: ">i.e., the evil that is in their hands.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="the fruit of their thoughts: ">the retribution for their thoughts.</text>
      <text title="and they rejected My instruction: ">Heb. וימאסו בה ותורתי. This follows the pattern of (Exodus 15:2) “The strength and destruction of God was my salvation (ויהי לי לישועה),” for he should have said: והיה לי לישועה. So too, here it should have said, ותורתי מאסו בה, but it is the style of Scripture to speak in this manner.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="Why do I need frankincense: ">that you offer up to Me, that comes from Sheba?</text>
      <text title="are not pleasant: ">Heb. ערבוּ.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="They will grasp: ">Heb. יחזיקו, they will take. Comp. (Exodus 4:4) “And he stretched out his hand and took it (ויחזק).” Comp. also (infra verse 24) “trouble grasped us (החזיקתנוּ) held us.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="there is fear: ">Heb. מגור. Another explanation: An expression of gathering. Comp. (Ezekiel 21:17) “Gathered (מגורי) to the sword.” And in this manner Jonathan renders it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="and roll: ">Heb. והתפלשי.</text>
      <text title="a mourning [as] for an only child: ">A mourning for an only son; one who has only one son and he dies.</text>
      <text title="a bitter lamentation: ">Heb. תמרורים מספד. Since it is the construct state, it is vowelized מספד with a ‘pattah,’ and it is not vowelized מספד with a ‘tzere.’</text>
      <text title="upon us: ">So to speak, upon Me and upon you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="I have made you the strong one: ">This was said to Jeremiah. I have made you the strong one in their midst, and you shall know and test their way, that he tested them and they will not heed. בחון is an expression of strength. Comp. (Isa. 32:14) “rampart and tower (בחן) ,” also (ibid. 23: 13) “they erected its towers (בחוניו).”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="extremely perverse: ">Turning away from the road.</text>
      <text title="going tale bearing: ">between copper and iron. They introduce hatred between two princes who have the power to provoke one another. That is what I heard. But I say, they are tale bearers, and they are as strong as copper and iron to maintain their falsehood. Jonathan, however, renders this word רכיל as an expression of guile (נוכל). They go with guile as one mixes copper with iron. נוכל is an expression of plot. Comp. (Gen. 37:18) “And they plotted (ויתנכלו) against him to slay him.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="The bellows is heated: ">This is an allegory. When they refine silver, they blow with a bellows, and they always put lead into the crucible, which helps for the refining. But youI have come to refine you. The bellows is heated and parched because of the fire, and the lead is completely consumed. נחר is an expression related to (Job 42:7) “My wrath has been kindled (חרה) ” ; (ibid. 30: 30) “And my bones are burned (חרה) with heat,” (esrast in O.F.).</text>
      <text title="in vain: ">In vain does the founder refine, for it is of no avail</text>
      <text title="and the wicked ones have not been separated: ">from their evil way. That is to say that the prophets toiled to reprove, but it did not avail them.</text>
      <text title="Separated: ">Heb. נתקו, (furent de… in O.F.). (Another version:) and the wicked ones. This is like רשעים.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="Refuse silver: ">which cannot be refined with any toil.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="7">
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord, etc.: ">Three times a year you appear before Me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Will you steal, murder, etc.: ">This is a question. Will you do all these, and should the Temple of the Lord avail for you?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="Has… a cave of profligate men?: ">Was this house in your eyes? This is a question.</text>
      <text title="behold I have seen: ">that it is so in your eyes.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="as I did to Shiloh: ">in the days of Eli.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="as I cast, etc.: ">the ten tribes.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="star-shaped cakes: ">Heb. כַּוָנִים, the shape of a star.</text>
      <text title="to the queen of heaven: ">The largest star they would call מלכתהשמים, an expression of a queen, (מלכּה), and so did Jonathan render it: לכוכבתשמיא, to the female star of heaven.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="reaches: ">Heb. נתכת, falls and reaches. Comp. (Exodus 9: 33) “and rain did not reach (נתּך) the earth” ; did not reach.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="your burnt offerings: ">that you offer up completelyit would be better for you to add them to your peace-offerings and sacrifice them as peace-offerings and eat the flesh, for they are not acceptable before Me. Why, then, should you lose them?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="on the day I brought them forth: ">The beginning of the condition was only (Exodus 19: 5): “If you hearken to My voice and keep My covenant, you shall be a peculiar treasure to Me.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="in the view: ">Heb. בשררות, in the view of their heart, an expression related to (Num. 24:17) “I see him אשורנו.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="sending them day [after day] every fresh morn: ">Every day sending them early.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="So tear off your diadem: ">Heb. נזרך גזי, tear out your hair. Comp. (Num. 11:31) “And He caused quails to fly (ויגז) ” ; also (Job 1:20), “And he shaved (ויגז) his head.” Another explanation is that נזרך means ‘your diadem,’ an expression of greatness, and so did Jonathan render: רברביך your great ones, and so did Menahem classify it (p. 83).</text>
      <text title="and abandoned: ">Heb. ויטש.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="the high places of Topheth: ">That is Molech, which was of copper, and they would heat it up from underneath it with its hands spread out and heated. And they would place the child on his hands, and he would be burnt and moan, and the priests would beat drums so that the father should not hear his son’s voice and take pity. It is called Topheth because of the drum (תּוף), Hinnom because of the child’s moaning (נהמת).</text>
      <text title="Hinnom: ">Because of the child’s moaning.</text>
      <text title="which I did not ordain: ">with commandments that they offer up their children as sacrifices, and I did not speak to any of the prophets, and when I did speak to Abraham to slaughter his son, it did not enter My mind that he slaughter, but only to make his righteousness known.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="and no one will frighten them: ">i.e., no one will frighten the fowl from the carcasses.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="8">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="And spread them before the sun: ">And the Chaldeans shall dwell when they besiege the city, in the graves of the princes, that were as beautiful as palaces.</text>
      <text title="for dung: ">For fertilizer.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And death shall be preferable to life: ">Although they see the dead being subjected to disgrace, the distress of the living is worse than that, and they will choose death.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="Shall they fall and not rise: ">Is it good for them to cast themselves into a fall from which there is no rising?</text>
      <text title="if he repents, will He not return?: ">If they wish to repent of their wickedness, will the Holy One, blessed be He, not return from His decree? Another explanation: If they repent, the repentance will not be permanent, for they will quickly return to their wickedness, and in this manner Jonathan rendered it: If to repent, it is revealed before Me that they will not repent.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="a perpetual backsliding: ">Heb. משבה נצחת, a perpetual backsliding, like נצח, perpetual.</text>
      <text title="They have held: ">Heb. החזיקו.</text>
      <text title="to deceit: ">Heb. בתרמית.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="not… properly: ">Heb. לא כן, not right, cf. (Num. 27:7)"The daughters of Zelaphehad speak justly (כּן).</text>
      <text title="Each one turns away in his course: ">[lit. in their course.] In the first way. They sin and repeatedly sin. מרוצתם is korse in O.F.</text>
      <text title="like a frightening: ">effaye in French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="Even the stork: ">(Cigogne in French).</text>
      <text title="her seasons: ">The time they pass to the islands of the sea because of the cold, and the time of their return.</text>
      <text title="await: ">Heb. שמרו.</text>
      <text title="and the turtledove and the crane and the swallow: ">Jonathan renders: ושפנינא וכורכיא וּסנוּניתא. כּורכיא is (grue in French), a crane. סנוּניתא is (hirondelle in French), a swallow.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="Verily, behold it is in vain: ">Behold your wisdom is in vain within you to heal you lightly.</text>
      <text title="he made a false scribes’ pen: ">i.e., your prophet.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Wise men were ashamed: ">i.e., wise men like you. And what is the shame? Behold, they rejected the word of the Lord, now what wisdom have they?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="And they healed: ">Heb. וירפו, similar to וירפאו.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="They shall be put to shame: ">Shame and embarrassment shall come upon them.</text>
      <text title="Neither are they ashamed: ">They are not ashamed of their evil deeds to take heart to repent.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="I will utterly consume them: ">This is an expression of destruction. Comp. (Zeph. 1:2) “I will utterly consume (אסף אסף) everything from upon the face of the earth.”</text>
      <text title="There shall be no grapes on the vine: ">Nothing will be left over.</text>
      <text title="even the leaves will be withered: ">Heb. נבל, an expression of withering (fleirit in French). Comp. (Isa. 34:4) “and as a withered fig (וּכנבלת) from a fig tree.” Also (ibid. 1:30), “like an elm whose leaves are wilting (נבלת).”</text>
      <text title="for what I gave them they transgressed: ">All this shall befall them because I gave them statutes and they transgressed them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="and there let us sit in silence: ">And let us be silent there. Let us sit there silent and mournful.</text>
      <text title="poisoned water: ">Jonathan renders: the cup of the curse, like the venom of serpents. The venom of the serpents is the poison that is in his teeth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="From Dan is heard: ">Because they worshipped the calf that was in Dan.</text>
      <text title="the snorting of their horses: ">The sneezing of his nostrils.</text>
      <text title="the neighing of their stallions: ">The neighing of joy of his horses, and we find elsewhere that horses are called אבּירים (Jud. 5:22) by reason of the prancings, “the prancings of their mighty ones (אבּיריו) ,” an expression of (Nahum 3:2) “a prancing horse.” And Jonathan renders: from the sound of the steps of their mighty ones.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="serpents, adders: ">After seventy years, the snake becomes a צפע, which shuts its ear so that it will not hear the voice of the charmer who charms him, as it is stated (Psalms 58:5), “Like a deaf asp that shuts up its ear.” That is the meaning of “that cannot be charmed.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="Were I to suppress my grief: ">Heb. מבליגיתי, my suppression, and it is a noun, (mes estenimenc in O.F.). That is to say, if I said, I will suppress and keep in my grief.</text>
      <text title="my heart is sick within me: ">From the voice of the prophecies that are revealed to me of the coming retributions.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="Hark the voice… the cry of the daughter of My people: ">I hear that eventually they will cry from a distant land, but why is all this necessary? Is not the Lord in Zion? If they return to Him, He will allow Himself to be found by them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="The harvest is past, the summer is ended: ">We looked forward to the aid of Egypt, but it did not come. We said, “Let the harvest pass, and they will be free, and they will come.” Now behold, the time of harvest has passed in Iyar, and the summer season in Tammuz, and they have not come.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="I mourn: ">lit. I am darkened, an expression of blackness and darkness.</text>
      <text title="dismay: ">Heb. שמה, wonder.</text>
      <text title="has taken hold of me: ">Has held me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="Is there no balm in Gilead: ">For balm comes from there, as it is said (infra 46: 11) “Go up to Gilead and take balm.” That is to say, Did they not have any righteous men from whom to learn so that they should improve their ways?</text>
      <text title="the health of: ">lit. the cure of, (emplatre in O. F.), plaster, dressing.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="9">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="a company of traitors: ">Companies of traitors.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="They have directed: ">Lit. trodden. This expression is appropriate for the preparation of the bow to shoot an arrow, and a bow (קשת) is (arbalete in French), and they tread it with their feet. Therefore, he calls it treading, and the prophet compared their tongue to a treacherous bow, for they directed their tongue like a treacherous bow.</text>
      <text title="from evil to evil: ">From sin to sin.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="forges plans: ">He lays traps.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="they commit iniquity [until] they are weary: ">They wearied themselves and toiled to pervert their way. העוה is like (Exod. 8: 11) “and making heavy (והכבּד) his heart,” to commit iniquity.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="Your habitation is in the midst of deceit: ">When they sit, they devise plans of deceit, and with deceit they have exchanged fear of Me and refused to know Me.</text>
      <text title="because of deceit: ">Heb. בּמרמה.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="I will refine them: ">with torments.</text>
      <text title="because of the daughter of My people: ">Because of the sins of the congregation of Israel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="Their tongue is a deadly arrow: ">Heb. שחוט, drawn. Comp. (I Kings 10: 16) “malleable gold” (שחוט). Also, (Hos. 5:2) “And the extent of their turning away (ושחטה),” (tirer in French), pulling. Another explanation is that it is actually an expression of slaughter (tranchant in French, cutting). In this manner Menahem classified it (Machbereth Menahem p. 172), and in this manner Jonathan rendered it: כּגיר די מחרף, like a sharpened arrow.</text>
      <text title="but in his heart: ">lit. in his midst. Jonathan renders: in his innards.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="for the mountains: ">i.e., for the destruction of the mountains.</text>
      <text title="for the dwellings of the wilderness: ">The dwelling of the shepherds in the wilderness. נאות is an expression of a dwelling. Comp. (Psalms 83: 13) “the dwellings (נאות) of God,” also (ibid. 93:5) “to Your house, the dwelling (נאוה) of sanctity.”</text>
      <text title="they are withered: ">Heb. נצתו. An expression of aridness. Comp. (v. 11) “withered (נצתה).”</text>
      <text title="have fled and are gone: ">i.e., they are destined to go. For fifty- two years no one passed through Judah; from the exile of Zedekiah until the order of Cyrus, king of Persia, were fifty-two years. An allusion to the matter [is that the numerical value for] “and the beast” (בּהמה) amounts to fifty-two, and the computation is exact, in Tractate Megillah [should read: Yoma 54a].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="heaps: ">Heb. דגורין heaps.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="Who is the man so wise: ">Who will understand this, and who is the prophet to whom the mouth of the Lord has spoken, that he may declare it? And who will declare why the land is ruined and all this retribution has come?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="with wormwood: ">Bitter grass.</text>
      <text title="poisonous water: ">Snake venom.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="they have cast down our dwellings: ">Heb. השליכו משכנותינו, [our dwellings] have cast out their inhabitants. We can also explain: For the enemies have cast our dwellings to the ground.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="from the streets: ">Heb. מחוץ, from the street. Comp. (I Kings 20:34) “And you shall make yourself streets in Damascus.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="Let not the wise man boast: ">Do not boast, saying, “We are wise.” Behold, you have rejected My words, so what wisdom do you have? If you understand and know Me, then you can boast of your wisdom.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="that he understands: ">Heb. השכיל, like (Exod. 8:11) “making heavy (הכבד)” (Enteliant in O. F.).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="every circumcised one for his uncircumcision: ">Every circumcised one who has a foreskin, even an uncircumcised heart, and surely I will punish the heathens.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="Egypt etc.: ">These were the neighbors of Eretz Israel, and they were punished shortly after her, as it is written in Ezekiel (29), and explained in Seder Olam (ch. 26).</text>
      <text title="cast off to the corners: ">Heb. פאה, an expression of an end, those cast off to the corner of the desert.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="10">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="Of the way of the nations you shall not learn: ">Of the way of the nations you shall not learnand then, from the signs of the heavens you will not be dismayed, from the eclipse of the sun or the eclipse of the luminaries.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="a carpenter: ">Heb. חרש, a craftsman.</text>
      <text title="a small axe: ">Dolodojjre in O.F.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="with nails: ">clous in French.</text>
      <text title="and with sledge hammers: ">A hammer, marteau in French.</text>
      <text title="it does not bend: ">Heb. יפיק, it does not kneel with its knees. Comp. (I Sam. 25: 31) “a stumbling block (פוקה) ” ; (Nahum 2:11) “and tottering (ופיק) of the knees.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="Like a palm tree they are beaten: ">He hammers them with a hammer until it has an upright stature like a palm tree.</text>
      <text title="fear them not: ">if you separate from them for they will not harm you.</text>
      <text title="neither is it in them to do good: ">If you worship them. היטיב is like להיטיב to do good.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="for it befits You: ">It is proper for you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="But with one thing they are brutish: ">i.e., the heathens, and what is that one thing? Their vanities of wood for which they will be punished, and they will be punished for it. יבערו is an expression of foolishness, so is ויכסלו.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Silver beaten into plates: ">Heb. מרקע.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="But the Lord God is true: ">Why? Because He is a living God and the King of the world. Therefore, He can make His words come true. A mortal person, however, plans to do something and dies or becomes weak or loses his property, and has no ability to execute his plans.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="So shall you say to them: ">This is a letter that Jeremiah sent to Jeconiah and those exiled with him in exile, to reply to the Chaldees in Aramaic, a reply if they tell them to worship idols.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="He stretched out: ">Tendre in French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="At the sound of His giving: ">At the time the sound comes that He is giving a multitude of water in the heavens.</text>
      <text title="clouds: ">Heb. נשאים, clouds.</text>
      <text title="lightning: ">plaindres in old French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="brutish: ">Heb. נבער. Comp. (Psalms 92:7) “a brutish (בער) man” ; also here (infra 10:21), “the shepherds have become brutish (נבערו).”</text>
      <text title="his molten images: ">Heb. נסכו. An expression of מסכה, a molten image.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="at the time of their visitation: ">When I will visit retribution upon them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="Gather in from the land your merchandise: ">Heb. כנעתך. Hide, gather in from the land your merchandise. Comp. (Hos. 12:8) “The trafficker (כּנען) in his hand are deceitful scales.” Menahem explains כנעתך as an expression of humility (הכנעה) and lowliness. And אספי is an expression of bending down. Bend down and humble yourself more than the lowliness of the earth, you Jerusalem, that dwells now in a fortified city (Machbereth p. 107).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="sling: ">as one slings a stone with a slingshot.</text>
      <text title="that: ">they may find their just deserts.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="grievous: ">Heb. נחלה, an expression of sickness (חלי).</text>
      <text title="and I will bear it: ">Heb. ואשאנו. Jonathan renders. And I will bear it ([a] souffrir lui in O. F.).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="have left me: ">Heb. יצאוני, have left me, Jerusalem says this.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="For the shepherds: ">The kings.</text>
      <text title="they have not prospered: ">They have not prospered in their kingdom. Comp. (Prov. 17:8)"To all that he turns, he will prosper (ישכיל).</text>
      <text title="their flocks: ">Heb. מרעיתם, lit. their pasture, the flocks of their pasture.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="man’s way is not his: ">For the evil inclination that You created in him leads him astray from the way. Another explanation is: I know, O Lord, that man’s way is not his; not every man has the power to make his way prosper, and if it were not for Your command, the enemy would have no power to destroy Your Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="but with justice: ">With chastisements.</text>
      <text title="with justice: ">(justice in French).</text>
      <text title="but with justice: ">Jonathan renders: but with mild judgment.</text>
      <text title="not with Your wrath: ">lest there be complete destruction.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="they have devoured: ">(devorerent in French). The same applies to “and consumed him” (ואכלהוּ).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="11">
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="“Amen, O Lord”: ">that he be cursed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="For I warned: ">Heb. העידתי, an expression of warning.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="And I brought upon them all the words of this covenant: ">The curses stated in the covenant for the things that I commanded to do and they did not do.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And they shall go the cities of Judah: ">From the cities of Judah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="cry nor prayer: ">This follows the Targum.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="What has my beloved to do in My house: ">What reason has My treasured people to come anymore into My house?</text>
      <text title="[seeing that]… perform evil design: ">That she does the evil design of her sinful plans.</text>
      <text title="the many: ">of them.</text>
      <text title="and the holy flesh they remove from you: ">Even the circumcision through which they were hallowed to Me, they have abolished from their flesh.</text>
      <text title="for [with] your evil, then you rejoice: ">When you commit a transgression, you rejoice.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="to the sound of a great tumult: ">Heb. המולה, an expression of the tumult of a large multitude that will come upon them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="And the Lord let me know: ">So said the prophet, The Holy One, blessed be He, let me know their retribution.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="And I was like a lamb [and] a bull: ">that will be brought to the slaughter.</text>
      <text title="brought: ">Since I let them know of the evil, they plan to kill me.</text>
      <text title="like a lamb [and] a bull: ">Heb. אלוף ככבש. Dunash and Judah son of Kudish (Karish) interpreted it as a lamb and a bull, brought to the slaughter. And אלוף is like (Deut. 28:4) “the offspring of your cattle (אלפיך).” Although it was not stated ואלוף, we find similar cases, e.g., (Habukkuk 3:11) “The sun [and] the moon (ירח) stood on high” ; (Isaiah 38:14) “Like a crane [and] a swallow (עגור) so I chirp.” And Menahem interpreted אלוף ככבש, a large lamb (see Psalms 58:9, Rashi ad loc.), and Jonathan supports him, since he renders like a choice lamb.</text>
      <text title="Let us destroy his food with wood: ">Let us put poison into his food.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="Let me see Your vengeance against them: ">He cursed the people of Anathoth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="upon the men of Anathoth: ">Heb. אל-אנשי ענתות, like ענתות על-אנשי, upon the men of Anathoth.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="12">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="You are right, O Lord, when I contend with You: ">When I debate with You, I know that you will be right in Your words, but I wish to argue with You so that You will let me know Your way.</text>
      <text title="Why has the way of the wicked prospered?: ">That You have given greatness to Nebuchadnezzar the wicked, and you have made him succeed in destroying Your house? Another explanation is that he was crying and complaining about the men of Anathoth.</text>
      <text title="have peace: ">Heb. שלו, an expression of שלוה, peace.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="But You, O Lord, have known me: ">Also, concerning the men of Anathoth You have aided me, for You have known me.</text>
      <text title="Draw them out like sheep to the slaughter: ">Draw them out of life to death (detache les in French, separate them, cut them off). Comp. (Joshua 8:6) “until we have drawn (התיקנו) them from the city.”</text>
      <text title="and prepare them: ">Heb. הקדישם, prepare them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="How long will the land mourn and the grass of all the field dry out?: ">Up to here are the prophet’s words, and the Holy Spirit replies to him, “Because of the evil of its inhabitants, beasts and fowl are ended.”</text>
      <text title="will… mourn: ">Be waste.</text>
      <text title="ended: ">(finira in French, will terminate).</text>
      <text title="for they said: ">i.e., the inhabitants of this land have said.</text>
      <text title="“He will not see our end.”: ">It is not revealed to Him what will be at our end.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="For if you have run with foot men and they wearied you: ">Your kin, the priests like you and the men of your city come to kill you.</text>
      <text title="with footmen: ">Heb. רגלים (pieton in O.F), pedestrian.</text>
      <text title="how will you compete with horses: ">To run with the horses. That is to say, If even your brethren the priests come to kill you, surely the princes of Judah will rise up against you to kill you. This is the reason for My anger against them, and this is the reason for the success of the enemy. And so did Jonathan render: This is the reply, etc. And, according to the Midrash of our Rabbis (Sanhedrin 96a): If you are amazed about the reward for the three steps that Nebuchadnezzar ran in My honor in the days of Merodach-baladan, why I gave him so much greatness, how much more will you be amazed when you see the payment of reward that I will pay the righteous who ran before Me like horses!</text>
      <text title="will you compete: ">(aastir in O.F.).</text>
      <text title="and in the peaceful land that you trust: ">there they wearied you.</text>
      <text title="how will you do in the heights: ">The princes of Judah. The pride of the Jordan is symbolic since it is a place of lions and tigers, and Jonathan taught us this in many places. And here he paraphrased. And how do you expect to do against the wild beasts that are on the height of the Jordan?“And behold, as a lion ascends from the height of the Jordan,” Jonathan renders in two places (infra 49:19, 50:44): like a lion that ascends from the height of the Jordan.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="have called a gang after you: ">Heb. מלא, a group of men.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="My soul’s beloved: ">My treasured people.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="she raised her voice against Me: ">The cry of her violent deeds has ascended before Me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Is… a speckled bird of prey?: ">The ‘heh’ is that of the interrogative. Therefore, it is vowelized with a ‘pattah.’ Are they like a speckled bird of prey, stained with blood, around which other birds gather? Another explanation:</text>
      <text title="Is… a speckled bird of prey: ">One bird is speckled, and all the birds gather around it to eat it because they hate it.</text>
      <text title="Are there birds of prey around her?: ">Are these armies fowl of the heavens, the swift troops that are around her?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="Many shepherds: ">The commanders of the troops of Nebuchadnezzar’s army, as it is stated above (6:3): “Shepherds and their flocks shall come to her.”</text>
      <text title="they have trampled: ">Heb. בססו, an expression of trampling. Cf. (Zech. 10:5) “And they shall be like mighty men trampling (בוסים) the mire of the streets.”</text>
      <text title="My field: ">Heb. חלקתי, (campagne in French), countryside.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="the wasted one mourns before Me: ">Heb. עלי, lit. on Me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="They sowed wheat, but they reaped thorns: ">They prayed, but their prayer was not accepted. Why? Because they did not plow for themselves a furrow of repentance and good deeds. Therefore, they sowed seeds resulting in thorns. A book in which זרעו is vowelized with a ‘chirik’ under the ‘zayin,’ is erroneous.</text>
      <text title="they have become ill: ">Heb. נחלו, an expression of illness. They have become ill with their pain and their cry before Me, but they did not avail.</text>
      <text title="of your increase: ">Of your deeds.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="My wicked neighbors: ">Egypt, Ammon and Moab, Tyre and Sidon, who were neighbors of Eretz Israel and were inflicting harm upon them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="I will return and have pity on them: ">They all suffered close to the destruction of the Temple, and concerning each one it is stated in this Book, “I will return the exile of…”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="if they learn: ">If they proselytize.</text>
      <text title="they shall be built up: ">an expression of building.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="13">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="a girdle: ">(pourceint in O.F.).</text>
      <text title="and do not put it in water: ">to wash it when it will be soaked with sweat, in order that it hasten to decay.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="it was of no use for anything: ">It was not fit for anything.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="and it shall be like this girdle: ">Their pride shall be like this rotten girdle.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="bottle: ">Heb. נבל. This is an earthenware vessel, and it is used to hold wine.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="And I will dash them one against the other: ">I will dash one against the other until they break into small pieces. Cf (Psalms 2:9) “Like a potter’s vessel shall you shatter them (תנפצם)” (ibid. 137:9).“And dash ונפץ your babes”; and so is every expression of נפוץ in Scripture.</text>
      <text title="and the fathers and the sons: ">I will dash one against the other.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="and before your feet stumble: ">Heb. יתנגפו (achopper in French), to stumble.</text>
      <text title="the dark mountains: ">Heb. נשף, the dark mountains when they go into exile.</text>
      <text title="and making it into a thick cloud: ">Heb. ושית, like ולשית, and to make the light into a thick cloud.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="because of your pride: ">Because of your greatness which will be curtailed. Another explanation: Because of the pride of the kingdom of Heaven that will be given over to the idols of Babylon.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="to the king and to the queen mother: ">Jehoiachin and his mother.</text>
      <text title="your greatness has come down: ">Heb. מראשתיכם (vostremijevec in O.F.), your ascent, as it is stated: (II Kings 24: 12) “And Jehoiachin… came out to him (sic), he and his mother and his servants,” and he led all of them in exile.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="The cities of the South are shut up: ">before those coming upon them from the north [i.e.,] the cities of Eretz Israel are shut up because of fear of Nebuchadnezzar.</text>
      <text title="she was exiled peacefully: ">Jehoiachin will not wage war, but he will come out peacefully, and he will exile them. Another interpretation. שלומים (gueredon in O.F.), reprisal. That is to say: she was exiled as the recompense for their iniquity. And Jonathan rendered in this manner: the recompense of their sins was received.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="Lift your eyes and see: ">those coming upon you from the North.</text>
      <text title="Where is the flock that was given you: ">After they are exiled, this will be said to Jerusalem.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="What will you say when He visits: ">i.e., when the Holy One, blessed be He, visits upon you?</text>
      <text title="when you accustomed them to be princes at your head: ">You sent emissaries to the Chaldees to bring their idols from there to worship them, as it is written in Ezekiel (23 16): “And she lusted for them to the sight of her eyes, and she sent emissaries to them, to the Chaldees.” Another explanation of “you accustomed them to be princes over you” : Hezekiah who showed the emissaries of Merodach-baladan his entire treasure house (Isaiah 39:2, II Kings 20:13).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="your skirts: ">The skirts of the garments (tes ourlets in French), your hems. When a woman is stripped in a humiliating way, they turn her chemise upside down.</text>
      <text title="your steps cut off: ">Your ways are cut off. נחמסו is like (Lam. 2:6) “And He cut off (ויחמֹס) like a garden His dwelling.”</text>
      <text title="your steps: ">(traces in O.F.) Travelers have stopped.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="a Cushite: ">Heb. כושי, the name of a black man, who is called Maure in French, a Moor.</text>
      <text title="or a leopard: ">leopard in French.</text>
      <text title="his spots: ">The leopard is spotted, and they are the spots (taches in French), and it is impossible for them to change.</text>
      <text title="to do evil: ">Heb. הרע, like להרע, to do evil.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="the portion of your measures: ">The portion of your measures, a measure for a measure.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="have uncovered your skirts: ">I have uncovered the hems of your garments upon your face.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="your neighings: ">like the neighing of adulterous horses.</text>
      <text title="After when: ">will you ever become purified?</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="14">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="concerning the droughts: ">that He would bring famine upon them, and Menahem (Machbereth p. 47) classified it as an expression of fortification (מִבְצָר) like (Isaiah 25:12) “And the fortress of (וּמִבְצַר) the strength of your walls.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="and her cities: ">Heb. וּשְעָרֶיהָ, lit., her gates.</text>
      <text title="and the cry of Jerusalem: ">Heb. צִוְחַת, the cry of Jerusalem. Comp. (Isaiah 42:11)"from the mountain peaks they shall shout (יִצְוָחוּ).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="upon pits: ">Pits in which the water is usually gathered.</text>
      <text title="their vessels have returned empty: ">for no rain has fallen.</text>
      <text title="and have covered: ">an expression of covering.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="farmers: ">bubirs [?] in O.F.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="has borne and abandoned: ">her offspring, to hunt for pastureland for herself.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="by the rivulets: ">rivulets of water (riveyres in O. F.).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="have testified against us: ">Heb. עָנוּ.</text>
      <text title="do for Your name’s sake: ">Do what You will do with us for the sake of the great name that has spread about You that You rule over all and that we are Your people and the flock of Your pasture, and it is not fitting that You give Your victorious name to the idols. And the Midrash Aggadah explains: for the sake of Your name that is inherent in our name.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="hope: ">מִקְוֵה</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="overcome: ">(d’cru in O.F.) diminished, waned, who withdraws his hand from the battle, and some say (recroyant in O.F.), tiring out, resigned.</text>
      <text title="and Your name is called upon us: ">Therefore, by doing this, it is no longer honor for you.</text>
      <text title="forsake us: ">Its explanation is like תַעַזְבֵנוּ, forsake us.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="So have they loved to wander: ">So, just as I have decreed upon them exile (to Egypt and Babylon - Warsaw edition), they loved it there to go into exile to worship distant idols.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="a thing of naught: ">an expression of אַל, not, a thing which is not.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="very grievous: ">an expression of illness (חֹלִי).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="have gone around: ">They have gone around to seek rescue.</text>
      <text title="to a land [which] they had not known: ">To another land about which they did not know until then.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="or has Your soul despised Zion: ">with the intention of never returning, for, if You have in mind to return, why have You smitten us without a cure?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="for Your name’s sake: ">that you are called merciful.</text>
      <text title="the throne of Your glory: ">The Temple. And according to Midrash Aggadah, Israel who is engraved on the throne of Your glory.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="Does the heaven give raindrops?: ">by itself, except by Your command? This is the interrogative form. In every double question, the first question is preceded by a ‘heh’ and the second one with אִם, like (Num. 13:19) “Are they in open cities (הַבְּמַחֲנִים) or in fortresses (אִם בְּמִבְצָרִים) ?” (Ibid. 13:19) “It is good (הֲטוֹבָה) or bad (אִם רָעָה) ?” (verse 19) “Have You indeed rejected (הֲמָאֹס) Judah, or has Your soul despised (אִםגָּעֲלָה) Zion?” Here, too, “are there among the vanities of the nations those who give rain? Does the heaven…?”</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="15">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Moses and Samuel: ">Both were needed to beg mercy for Israel, but first they induced them to repent, and afterwards they prayed on their behalf, but they had no idea of turning away My wrath until they had induced them to repent. Moses said (Exodus 32:27), “Let each man put his sword…” (v. 20) “and he scattered it on the surface of the water, etc.” And afterwards (v. 30), “I will ascend to the Lord, perhaps I will atone.” Samuel in Mizpah (I Samuel 7:4, 5) “And the children of Israel removed the Baalim,” and afterwards, “‘Gather all Israel to Mizpah, and I shall pray to the Lord on your behalf (sic).’” But you cannot bring them back to Me, therefore do not pray for them.</text>
      <text title="desire: ">Heb. נַפֹשִי lit., My soul.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="Such as are for death, to death: ">Each calamity mentioned later in this verse is harsher than the one preceding it. The sword is harsher than death. Death by the sword is defacing, whereas death in bed is not defacing. And so he says (Psalms 116:15): “Precious in the eyes of the Lord is the death of His Saints.” Famine is harsher than the sword, for this one is agonizing whereas the other is not agonizing. And so Scripture states (Lam. 4:9): “Better are those who die from the sword than those who die from famine.” Captivity - all sorts of death are in it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And I will appoint: ">an expression of appointment and designation.</text>
      <text title="to drag: ">to drag. Cf. (infra. 49:20) “If the young of the sheep do not drag them (יִסְחָבוּם).”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="a horror: ">from the same root as (Esther 5:9), “And he neither rose nor quaked (זָע).” Similarly, גַּאֲוָה pride, from the root (Isa. 16: 6) “Have become very proud (גֵּא).”</text>
      <text title="to all the kingdoms of the earth: ">Anyone who hears the evil that has befallen you will shudder.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="will lament: ">Heb. יָנוּד.</text>
      <text title="and who will turn aside: ">to you, to turn aside from his road to you, to ask of your welfare?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="I am weary of repenting: ">Many times I planned to destroy but repented of the evil. Now I am weary of repenting. הִנָחֵם (Dporpnser in O.F.)</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="with a sieve: ">A sieve called (van in French), like one who winnows barley, so that they should not all be exiled to one place.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="are to Me more numerous: ">His widows are more to Me.</text>
      <text title="upon a mother: ">Upon Jerusalem, which is a city and a mother in Israel.</text>
      <text title="at midday: ">Everything will be exposed before him, all their hidden treasures.</text>
      <text title="I have cast upon her suddenly a city: ">I caused the troops of a city and many terrors to rest upon her. Some interpret עִיר as ‘an enemy.’ Cf. (I Sam. 28:16), “And has become [the supporter of] your adversary (עָרֶ) ” (see also Dan. 4:16).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="She who bore seven: ">Samaria and the nation of the Ten Tribes, from whom rose seven dynasties of wicked kings, has already been cut off and exiled.</text>
      <text title="and their remnant: ">These are Judah and part of Benjamin, who remained in Israel. I shall deliver them to the sword. These are the seven dynasties: Jeroboam son of Nebat and his dynasty, Baasha and his dynasty, Omri and his dynasty, Jehu and his dynasty, Menahem and his dynasty, Pekah and his dynasty, Hoshea and his dynasty.</text>
      <text title="her soul grieves: ">an expression of ‘her soul grieves.’ We translate (Deut. 28:65) “And grieving of the soul (וְדַאֲבוֹן נֶפֹש)” as וּמַפְּחַן נְפֹש.</text>
      <text title="when it is still day: ">Before its time, they hastened to fall. In this manner it is expounded in Tractate Gittin. [See Gittin 88a]. And in the Midrash of Rabbi Tanhuma (Tanhuma Buber, Vayetze p. 153) it is expounded as referring to Jerusalem, and he counts seven wicked men: Jehoram, Jehoash, Ahaz, Manasseh, Amon, Jehoiakim, and Zedekiah. But there are yet to count Rehoboam, Abijah, Amaziah, and Ahaziah.</text>
      <text title="and confounded: ">an expression of shame.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="Woe is to me, my mother: ">Jeremiah was complaining about himself, that his townsmen hated him because of his castigations.</text>
      <text title="and a man of contention: ">a man of quarrel, Cf. (Gen. 6:3) “Let My spirit not contend (יָדוֹן).”</text>
      <text title="I have not lent: ">Cf. (Exodus 22:24) “You shall not be to him as a creditor (כְּנֹשֶה).”</text>
      <text title="they curse me: ">I do not quarrel with them concerning matters of money that I claim from them, neither have they made any claim on me, yet all the people curse me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="1 leave you over: ">I leave you over, an expression of a remnant. In this manner, Menahem (Machbereth p. 181) interpreted it, but Dunash (Teshuvoth Dunash p. 36) interpreted it as an expression of release. And שֵרִיתִי is like (Dan. 5:12) “And untying (וּמֹשָרֵא) knots,” and the interpretation of שֵרִיתִי is so, as it is stated (below 40:4): “Behold I have released you from the chains that are on your hand.” That is to say, on that day that the Lord fulfilled His word, it was said to him, “And now, behold I have released you today from the chains that are on your hand, if it pleases you to come with me to Babylon.” And also, Israel begged him to pray for them, as it was said to him (below 42: 4): “Pray on our behalf to the Lord our Cod, for we remain few from many.”</text>
      <text title="Verily I will: ">lit., if not, an expression of an oath.</text>
      <text title="I will cause [them] to beg you in time of evil: ">with the enemy. When evil befalls them, they will beg you to supplicate God for mercy upon them, for example, Zedekiah said to him, (below 21:2) “Beseech God now on our behalf, etc.” Another explanation. Nebuzaradan will beg you (below 40:4), “If it pleases you to come with me to Babylon.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="Will iron break iron from the north: ">I say that iron that comes from the north is harder than other iron, and this is its interpretation: They were compared to iron (above 6:28), “Going tale bearing like copper and iron.” And concerning Jeremiah it is stated (above 1:18): “I have made you… into an iron pillar and into copper walls,” and his is stronger than theirs, for Nebuchadnezzar will come upon them according to his words.</text>
      <text title="Will…5break: ">Will their iron break yours? Another explanation: Will Pharaoh who comes in your aid, who is as hard as iron, break Nebuchadnezzar, who is iron that comes from the north and copper? Targum Jonathan is inclined toward this direction.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="Your wealth: ">An expression of money.</text>
      <text title="and your treasures: ">He is addressing Israel.</text>
      <text title="and for all your sins: ">And because of all your sins, this will befall you.</text>
      <text title="and throughout all your boundaries: ">For you erected idols in all of them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="Take me not to Your long suffering: ">Jonathan renders. Do not grant a reprieve for my humiliation. Do not take my cause to leave it for Your long suffering, but hasten and avenge me.</text>
      <text title="I bore: ">like סָבַלְתִּי bore.</text>
      <text title="for Your sake: ">for You.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="Your words were found and I ate them: ">eagerly at the beginning, and they were a joy for me, for I thought that now they would listen to me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="because of Your hand: ">Because of the prophecy that came to me from You.</text>
      <text title="I sat: ">alone and bewildered by mourning, for You filled me with a prophecy of fury concerning the destruction of Your House.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="grievous: ">sick. Comp. (II Sam. 12:15) “And he became mortally ill (וַיֵּאָנֹש).” mentioned concerning Bath-sheba’s son.</text>
      <text title="You are to me: ">Heb. הָיו ֹתִהְיֶה.</text>
      <text title="as a failing spring: ">Like a man whose trust has been cut off from him, for you allow me to suffer at their hands. אַכְזָב is a spring that stops (faylayne in O.F:), failing.</text>
      <text title="water that is not faithful: ">to rely upon it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="Therefore: ">Because I suffer from these troubles.</text>
      <text title="so said the Lord: ">to me.</text>
      <text title="If you return: ">You, Israel, through me, and I will return you to Him, He said to Me, “You will stand before Me.”</text>
      <text title="and if you take precious out of the vile: ">If you take a pious man from a wicked man, i.e., if you bring him to repentance.</text>
      <text title="You shall be as my mouth: ">For I make a decree and you annul it.</text>
      <text title="Let them return to you, but you shall not return to them: ">Let them return to your word, but you shall not return to stray after them.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="16">
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="house of mourning: ">feasting. In Sifrei, in the section dealing with Beth-peor (Balak), I saw. They returned to make feasts (מַרְזֵיחִין) for them, but our Rabbis explained מַרְזֵחַ as ‘a mourner.’</text>
      <text title="you bemoan: ">you shall lament.</text>
      <text title="for I have gathered in My peace, etc.: ">When their father Abraham performed charity and justice, I gave his children loving-kindness and mercy, as in Deut. 7:12: “And the Lord your God shall keep for you the covenant and the loving- kindness, etc.” Also (Deut. 13:18), “And He shall give you mercy.” They turned “justice into wormwood, and cast righteousness to the ground” (Amos 5:7). I, too, have returned and gathered in to Me My loving-kindness and My mercies.</text>
      <text title="I have gathered in: ">(ote in O.F.), taken off. Comp. (Gen. 30:23) “God has gathered (אסף) in my disgrace.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="And large and small shall die: ">And since everyone will die, why should you lament?</text>
      <text title="and they shall not cut their flesh nor shall they tear their hair for them: ">It is the custom of mourners to cut and tear their flesh and to tear their hair our of their head. In any case, it is forbidden for Jews, but he mentions it here only as an example of mourning.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And they shall not break [bread] for them: ">an expression of breaking. Comp. (Dan. 5:25) “Mene Mene Tekel Upharsin, (divided).” This alludes to the practice of giving a meal to the mourners in the city square and they break for them the bread upon reciting the blessing of ‘hamotzi.’ (I Sam. 9:13) “For he will bless the sacrifices,” Jonathan renders: He will break (פָרִיס) bread.</text>
      <text title="neither will they give them to drink etc: ">This is the reason for what I said, “Neither go to lament.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="And to a house of feasting: ">that I said to you above, “You shall not go,” this is the reason: Behold, I will cut off from this place, etc.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="and you will serve there other gods: ">Jonathan paraphrases: And you will serve there nations that worship idols day and night.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="Therefore: ">An expression of an oath. Although you betrayed Me, I have an oath that I will redeem you.</text>
      <text title="and it shall no longer be said: ">Our Rabbis expounded: Not that the departure from Egypt shall be uprooted from its place, but the final redemption will be the most important and the departure from Egypt secondary to it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="and they will fish them: ">Just as the fisher takes - it i.e., - the fish from its habitat, so will these capture them within the city, and just as the manner of a fish, that when he is caught he dies, so will I bring killers upon them, and afterwards I will send hunters for the survivors and for those who flee from the sword to the mountains and the hills, and they will hunt them to exile them in captivity.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="the doubling of their iniquity: ">Because they repeated their iniquity to do the iniquities of their fathers. And Jonathan renders in this manner: And I will recompense the second ones like the first ones double.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="and my refuge: ">(mon vantement in French), my boast. And Menahem (Machbereth p. 123) classified it as an expression of a wonder. Cf. (Psalms 60:6) “You have given those who fear You a wonder to be wondrous (נֵס לְהִתְנוֹסֵס).”</text>
      <text title="to You nations will come: ">Eventually, the heathens will come to you and worship You of one accord, and they will say, “How did they make gods for themselves, and they are no gods?”</text>
      <text title="from the ends of: ">Like מִקְצֵה, from the end of.</text>
      <text title="handed down: ">an expression of an inheritance.</text>
      <text title="avail: ">an expression of use (תּוֹעֶלֶת).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="that My name is the Lord: ">As its apparent meaning, a ruler and a sovereign to fulfill My decree.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="17">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="with a pen of iron: ">This is an allegory. That is to say that it is deeply engraved, and cannot be erased. And the Midrash Aggadah explains: with a pen of iron, with a diamond point, preserved by Jeremiah, called ‘an iron wall,’ and by Ezekiel, to whom it was said (3:9): “As a diamond, harder than flint have I made your forehead.”</text>
      <text title="engraved: ">Engraved like one who plows deeply.</text>
      <text title="on the tablet of their heart: ">that they do not forget their idolatry.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="As they remember their children, [so do they remember] their altars: ">Like the remembrance of their children, so was the remembrance of their altars to them, like a man who longs for his son.</text>
      <text title="and their asherim: ">which are by the green trees.</text>
      <text title="by… trees: ">like אֵצֶּל, by. And Jonathan renders in this manner. under every green tree.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="You, who sit upon the mountain in the field: ">Jerusalem that is situated on the mountain of the plain. All around the city is a fielded plain. The structure of הֲרָרִי is like עֲרָבִי, called so because he dwells in the plain (עֲרָבָה) (montanyers in O.F), mountain dwellers (other versions: a mountain dweller).</text>
      <text title="your substance: ">like מָמוֹנְ, your money.</text>
      <text title="Your high places are made for sin: ">Your high places are made in sin for the purpose of idolatry within all your borders.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="And you shall release: ">Perforce you will release your land for the time that it did not rest on your Sabbaths, which I said to you (Lev. 25:2), “And the land shall rest a Sabbath for the Lord.”</text>
      <text title="of you: ">I will avenge Myself of you because of your heritage that I gave you, that you did not perform My will to release it. Another explanation: even of you, from your heritage; I will avenge Myself of you from your heritage, that I will exile you from it.</text>
      <text title="for you have kindled fire in My nostrils: ">Heb. קְדַכְתֶּם.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="who trusts in man: ">In his plowing and his harvest, saying, “I will sow during the seventh year and I will eat.”</text>
      <text title="his arm: ">Like ‘his help,’ and so did Jonathan render: his trust.</text>
      <text title="and whose heart turns away from the Lord: ">Who promised him (Lev. 25:21), “And I will command My blessing to you.” This is what I heard.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="like a lonely tree: ">like a lonely tree, an expression of (Gen. 15:2) “Childless (עֲרִירִי) ,” and some say (degat in O.F) laid waste, and Menahem (Machbereth Menahem p. 137) explained: The name of a tree of the forest trees, and its name is ar’ar, and this is the explanation of (infra 48. 6) “Like an ‘aroer’ in the desert,” one of the trees of the forest.</text>
      <text title="in the plain: ">an expression of a plain.</text>
      <text title="parched land: ">aridness. Comp. (Job 30:30) “Became dry (חָרָה) from heat.”</text>
      <text title="salt-sodden soil: ">Land that is salty and will not be settled.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="and will not see: ">The tree will not see when heat comes.</text>
      <text title="drought: ">an expression of hunger, (famine in French). Another interpretation: בַּצֹרֶת is an expression of fortification (מִבְצָר) , and in this manner, Menahem (Machbereth Menahem p. 47) classified it.</text>
      <text title="will not be anxious: ">will not be afraid.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="The heart is deceitful: ">Full of pretext and deceit of all evil.</text>
      <text title="and when it is sick: ">an expression of sickness, and this is its sickness.</text>
      <text title="who recognizes it?: ">He thinks, “Who recognizes it?” I, the Lord, search it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="The cuckoo calls: ">(Coucou glousse in French).</text>
      <text title="but has not laid: ">This cuckoo draws after it chicks that it did not lay. דָגָר - This is the chirping which the bird chirps with its voice to draw the chicks after it, but those whom the cuckoo called will not follow it when they grow up for they are not of its kind. So is one who gathers riches but not by right.</text>
      <text title="he stands dishonored: ">He is called wicked.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="As a Throne of Glory: ">Since he wishes to state: All that forsake You shall be shamed, he commences with the praise of the Omnipresent, and says before Him, “You, Whose Throne of Glory is exalted from the beginning of the Creation of the world and is directed opposite our Sanctuary.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="The Lord Who is the source of the hopes of Israel: ">sits upon it. Therefore, all that forsake You shall be shamed.</text>
      <text title="and they that turn away from me shall be marked on the earth: ">Those who turn away from my words, who do not hearken to my message, will be marked out in the nether graves of the earth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="for You are my praise: ">I praise myself and boast with You, saying that You are my Savior (vantance in O.F.), boast.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="&quot;Where is the word of the Lord?: ">The retribution which you prophesy.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="But I did not hasten: ">I did not hasten to urge You to bring them because I am a good shepherd, who goes after You to beg mercy for them.</text>
      <text title="and… the woeful day: ">The illness of their retribution I did not desire. Jonathan renders: And I did not hamper Your word from prophesying concerning them to return them to fear You. According to the Targum, אַצְתִּי is an expression of hampering. That is to say, I did not hesitate from telling them Your message and to return them to you if they would hearken to me.</text>
      <text title="What came out of my lips was before Your face: ">to return Your wrath from them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="Let it not be to me for a ruin: ">Let not Your mission be to me for a ruin.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="May my pursuers be shamed: ">i.e., the men of Anathoth alone.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="But they did not hearken: ">i.e., your forefathers did not hearken to what I commanded them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="and to come: ">like וְלָבֹא.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="18">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="on the wheels: ">Jonathan renders: on the wheel. (Formes in French.)</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="that he was making of clay: ">That he was making of the clay was spoiled in the potter’s hand while it was still wet, and this is an inverted verse.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="of its evil for which I spoke concerning it: ">Of its sins for which I spoke concerning it.</text>
      <text title="to uproot and to demolish: ">(depayser [?] in French).</text>
      <text title="I will repent: ">And I will think another thought.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="But they shall say, We despair: ">I know that they will say to you regarding your words that they do not heed them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="disgraceful thing: ">Heb. שַעֲרֻרִת.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="Shall one abandon from rocks of the field the snow of Lebanon: ">Shall a man who needs to drink abandon water that flows from the rock in the fields that comes from the snow of the Lebanon, which is clean?</text>
      <text title="Shall strange cold… water be abandoned?: ">Or shall flowing spring water, which was strange to all people until now, and it is cold, be abandoned? זָרִים means flowing, and this proves it (2 Kings 19: 24): “I dug and drank strange water (זָרִים).” Menahem, however, classified with (Isaiah 1:6) “they have not been sprinkled (זֹרוּ), neither have they been bandaged,” an expression of curative water, and he gave a reason for his statement, and he said that if he wished to speak with an expression of זֶרֶם, a stream, he would double the ‘mem,’ and he would add ‘yud’ ‘mem,’ and he would say זְרוּמִים because of the plural number of מַיִם water, and because they are streams (זְרָמִים).</text>
      <text title="the field: ">like שָדֶה, a field</text>
      <text title="cold: ">(froids in French).</text>
      <text title="flowing: ">(courants in French). And we can also interpret it: “Shall it be abandoned to be strange rejected water, the water that is cold running water?”</text>
      <text title="Heb.: ">צרים According to the first interpretation, it is an expression of a stream [זֶרֶם]. According to the second interpretation, it is an expression of strangeness, i.e., rejected water.)</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="For: ">so have My people done, that they have forgotten Me and burnt incense to vanity.</text>
      <text title="ancient paths: ">The proper paths they said that they are a stumbling block, in order to go…</text>
      <text title="[on] a way that is not trodden down: ">Heb. סְלוּלָה.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="hissing: ">One who passes by ruins that he already saw with good buildings is accustomed to whistle.</text>
      <text title="will be astonished: ">will wonder.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="upon their back and not their face: ">when they flee from before the enemy, I will look upon them and I will not save them.</text>
      <text title="I will look: ">but I will not save them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="And they said, “Come, etc.”: ">Jeremiah was complaining about the men of Anathoth and saying that they say this.</text>
      <text title="Torah… from the priest: ">For it is incumbent upon the priests to teach the Torah, as it is stated (Deut. 33:10): “They shall teach Your ordinances to Jacob.”</text>
      <text title="not speech from the prophet: ">I. e., words of prophecy.</text>
      <text title="Come, let us strike him with the tongue: ">Let us testify falsely against him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="and spill their blood: ">(Bring them down by the sword,) an expression of (Lam. 3:49) “My eye runs (נִגְרָה) ” ; (Micah 1:4) “Like water that runs (מֻגָרִים).”</text>
      <text title="by the sword: ">by troops.</text>
      <text title="and their husbands: ">i.e., the husbands of the widows shall be slain by the angel of death.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="for they dug a pit to seize me: ">that they suspected him of intimacy with a married woman, as it is stated (Prov. 23:27): “For a harlot is a deep pit (ֹשוּחָה).”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="let not be erased: ">let it not be erased. And because it is a feminine gender, he placed a ‘yud’ therein. This too is superfluous, as the ‘yud’ of (Ezekiel 16:17) “And you played the harlot (וַתִּזְנִי) with them.”</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="19">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="a jug: ">Heb. בַּקְבֻּק.</text>
      <text title="potter’s earthen: ">That is to say, of a potter, which is of earthenware.</text>
      <text title="and some of the elders of the people: ">take along with you.“And of the elders of the people” refers back to ‘Go,’ and some of the elders of the people with you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="the Harsith Gate: ">The Dung Gate, where broken pottery is cast, and Jonathan rendered in this manner תְרַע קִלְקַלְתָּא.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="his ears will tingle: ">(tinter in French), an expression similar to “cymbals” (מְצִלְתַּיִם) (Neh. 12:27), “with loud sounding cymbals (בְּצִלְצְלֵי ֹשָמַע) ” (Psalms 150:5).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="and they estranged: ">They made it strange before Me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And I will frustrate: ">and I will empty, an expression similar to (Nahum 2:11), “She is empty and void וּמְבוּקָה) (בּוּקָה,” and because of the jug (בַּקְבֻּק) about which he is speaking, he adopted this expression.</text>
      <text title="the straits: ">An expression of pain, like צוקה.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="[which can no longer be repaired: ">This refers to the people, but the city I will make like the Topheth and purify it in the future.]</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="this city like the Topheth: ">All of it will be full of the slain just as the Topheth, where they slay the children for Molech.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="20">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="and placed him in the prison: ">the name of a place of a prison, and Jonathan rendered: לכיפתא (arvolud in O.F.), a vault.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="Magor: ">Terror.</text>
      <text title="Not Passhur did the Lord call your name, etc.: ">Your name was not called Pashhur except for this matter, that is to say: פֹשַח ֹשָחוֹר, cut off and black like “a tree that was cut off (נִפֹשַח)” (Shevi’ith 4:6, Orlah 1:5). Also (Lam. 3:11), “And He cut me off (וַיִפֹשְחֵנִי).” And so he said to him, Not Pashhur did He call your name, for the expression of Pashhur means a great man and the son of nobles, Pashhur. ‘Pash’ denotes expansion and ‘hur’ nobility. But for this reason your name was called Pashhur, Pashah shahor. ‘Pashah’ means ‘cut off,’ and ‘shahor’ means ‘black.’ Another explanation. ‘Pashah sehor.’ Many will be around you to slay you. Now according to this explanation, מָגוֹר is an expression of gathering, like (Ezekiel 21: 17) “Gathered (מְגוּרֵי) to the sword.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="the wealth: ">money.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="You enticed me: ">to go on your mission.</text>
      <text title="You overcame me: ">You made Your strong hand heavy upon me to go against my will.</text>
      <text title="and You prevailed: ">And You were victorious.</text>
      <text title="everyone: ">All the people mock me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="Whenever I speak: ">Every time I speak to them, I must cry out and raise my voice, and I do not proclaim good for them but prophecies of violence and spoil.</text>
      <text title="for the word of the Lord has been… for me: ">Therefore, they spoke to me with scorn, for they scorn me.</text>
      <text title="and mockery: ">for speech. Comp. (Ezekiel 22:4) “and mockery (וְקַלָּסָה).”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Should I say: I will not mention Him: ">If my heart said to me not to go on Your mission anymore.</text>
      <text title="it would be in my heart: ">i.e., the prophecy.</text>
      <text title="like a burning fire: ">And against my will I must go.</text>
      <text title="confined in my bones: ">And as if the fire were confined in my bones.</text>
      <text title="to contain: ">To endure the fire.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="For I heard: ">I said that I would not mention Him because I heard the speech of many, those who whisper about me.</text>
      <text title="a gathering: ">an expression of gathering, and so did Jonathan render it.</text>
      <text title="tell: ">false testimony against him.</text>
      <text title="and let us tell about him: ">and let us testify against him. And Menahem (Machbereth p. 53) explained ונגידֶנוּ like (Deut. 14:1) “You shall not cut yourselves (לא תתגודדוּ).” He also joined (Job 17:5) “For the sake of flattering, he destroys (יגיד) his friends.” This is an expression of destruction. Comp. (Dan. 4:11) “Cut down (גֹדוּ) the trees.” But Dunash (Teshuvoth p. 54) interpreted it as an actual expression of telling, and this is its interpretation: “Tell false things about him and we will tell about him to the king.” And we have like נַגִידֶנוּ, we will tell about him, many words in the Scriptures that cannot be interpreted unless they are divided into two words or three. Comp. (Gen. 37:4) “And they could not speak with him (דַבְּרוֹ) peacefully.” Also (supra 10:20), “My children have left me (יצאני).”</text>
      <text title="await my destruction: ">Heb. צַלְעֵי Perhaps he will be enticed.</text>
      <text title="to listen to us and to stray after us.: ">and we will prevail against him to bring him to commit idolatry.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="for they did not succeed: ">They did not succeed with their plan.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="Cursed be the day in which I was begotten: ">(engendrer or engenrer in O.F.). That is the time of conception, and through compulsion Hilkiah his father performed the marriage act by day, for he was fleeing from before Manasseh, who was slaying the prophets, and he performed the marriage act and fled.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="making him glad: ">The ‘mem’ is punctuated with a ‘dagesh,’ which is an expression of making others glad, for he made his father glad with his news.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="like the cities that… overturned: ">Namely Sodom and Gemorrah.</text>
      <text title="and did not repent: ">Since He decreed destruction upon them, he did not think another thought to rescind His decree.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="That he did not put me to death: ">I.e., that the angel of death did not put me to death from the womb, and this is one of the verses with brief language.</text>
      <text title="a perpetual pregnancy: ">a pregnancy of eternity.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="toil and grief: ">The destruction of the Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="21">
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="Behold I turn back the weapons of war: ">There are some among you who know how to adjure the heavenly princes in charge of retribution, that each one save them from the evil he is in charge of, and you rely on that. Behold, I will transfer one’s authority to another one, and you will not know whom to adjure.</text>
      <text title="and I will gather them: ">i.e., the weapons of war, into this city, that I will destroy you with pestilence through the angel of death, who is one of the heavenly princes. And in this manner it is explained in the chapter (v. 6): “with a great pestilence they shall die.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="and he will have his life as a prey: ">As a man who plunders booty, and he seizes and goes away, so will his life be plundered from death by the slayers.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="My anger: ">as the Targum, רוּגְזִי My anger.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="from the hand of the robber: ">Its accent is below for it is not a noun but a noun denoting the robber who robs others.</text>
      <text title="with no one to extinguish [it]: ">that no one of you will escape as a survivor.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="O dweller of the valley: ">Jerusalem is in the midst of a valley. Another explanation. That the Holy One, blessed be He, devised a deep plot against you to destroy you.</text>
      <text title="rock of the plain: ">Mountain, entirely surrounded by plain.</text>
      <text title="Who will encamp upon us: ">who will encamp upon us. Comp. (II Kings 6:9) “For there the Arameans are encamped (נְחִתִּים).”</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="22">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="do no wrong: ">This means taunting with words.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="You are [as] Gilead to Me, etc.: ">Even if you are as dear to Me as the Temple, which is high on the mountain peaks, I swear that I will make you a desert.</text>
      <text title="You are [as] Gilead: ">The Temple from which balm and healing emanate to the whole world.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And I will prepare: ">and I will prepare.</text>
      <text title="and they will cut your choice cedars: ">Since he compares him to the Lebanon, this expression is appropriate.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="Weep not for the dead: ">Namely, for Jehoiakim, who will die before the gate, when they drag him into exile.</text>
      <text title="weep for him who goes: ">For Jehoiachin and for Zedekiah. Deduce from here that Jehoiakim’s death, concerning which it is stated (infra 36: 30): “And his carcass shall be cast to the heat by day and to the cold at night,” is preferable to the life of Jehoiachin, about whom it is stated (52:34): “And his meals, regular meals, etc.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="concerning Shallum: ">That is Zedekiah, and that is what he was called in I Chron. (3:14): “the fourth Shallum.” And he called him the Fourth, meaning the fourth to assume the kingship of Josiah’s sons, for first Jehoaha, reigned, then Jehoiakim, and after him Jehoiachin, and after him Zedekiah.</text>
      <text title="who left: ">Even though he hadn’t left yet, he prophesied as if he had already left.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="Woe to him who builds his house: ">He is saying this about Jehoiakim, who was a wicked man, and the end of the section proves this: “Therefore, so said the Lord about Jehoiakim.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="a wide house: ">a large house. Cf. (Num. 13: 32) “Men of great stature (אַנֹשֵי מִדּוֹת) ,” who have what to measure.</text>
      <text title="and he cuts out… for himself: ">And he widens for himself (Some emend: And he opens for himself) Comp. (supra 4:30) “that you enlarge (וַתִּקְרְעִי) … with paint.” Also (Isaiah 63:19), “Had You rent (קָרַעְתְּ) the heavens, had You descended.” They are all an expression of opening.</text>
      <text title="and ceiled with cedar: ">He covers the roof with cedars.</text>
      <text title="and painted with vermilion: ">painted with dyes, so does Jonathan render. בּשָּׁשַּׁר is a color of a type used for painting. Another explanation: וּמָשּׁוֹח ַבִּשָּׁשַּׁר is like a cord used for measuring (חוּט הַמִּשְּׁחָה) ([a] lignant en sinople in O.F.), drawing green lines, delineate with a green color.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="Shall you reign: ">Will you live long that you contend to make your rule oppressive to let all know that you are a king?</text>
      <text title="your father: ">Josiah, who demeaned himself with humility, did he not eat and drink and enjoy pleasure all the days of his life?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="on your gain: ">to steal money.</text>
      <text title="the crushing: ">the crushing of the poor, and עֹשֶק, oppression proves it, for ‘oppressed’ and ‘crushed’ are always juxtaposed in the language of the Scriptures. Cf. (I Sam. 12:3) “Whom did I oppress or whom did I crush?”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="Hoe, his glory!: ">Woe for his glory.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="A donkey’s burial: ">As they drag the carcass of a donkey, so will they drag his carcass. The word יֹשַגְּרוּן used by Targum Jonathan means, they will drag.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="Ascend the Lebanon and cry: ">Go up to the Temple and cry.</text>
      <text title="and on Bashan give forth your voice: ">On Bashan which will be destroyed. And Jonathan paraphrased: And in the gates of the Temple Mount. And I do not know how to explain how the expression ‘Bashan’ fits to the gates of the Temple Mount, unless it is because of the doors which they make from the terebinths of Bashan, and that is the name of a place, or the expression, ‘Bashan’ denotes a place of a wide valley. So is the area of the Temple Mount an open area around the Temple.</text>
      <text title="and cry for Avarim: ">And cry for Megizatha. They are place names.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="in your peaceful times: ">when you lived in peace.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="All your shepherds: ">All your kings.</text>
      <text title="shall be broken by the wind: ">The east wind shall break them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="who nest in the cedars: ">For you placed your nest in the towers of the cedar houses to build wide houses.</text>
      <text title="how gracious shall you be: ">What grace have you found because of the height of your towers, in the eyes of your plunderers, when birth pangs come upon you. And Menahem interpreted נֵחַנְתְּ as an expression of camping, but Dunash interpreted it as an expression of grace.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="a signet: ">Engraved and sealed in the flesh of My arm.</text>
      <text title="I will remove you: ">Cf. (supra 12:3) “Draw them out (התִקֵם) like sheep to the slaughter” (Jos. 8:6) “Until we have drawn (התִקֵינוּ) them.” And the ‘nun’ is superfluous. And, according to the Midrash Aggadah (Pesikta d’Rav Kahana, p. 163a): In the place to which he was removed (נִתַּק), there he was rectified (נִתְקַן) , for he repented in Babylon, and the Holy One, blessed be He, applied for absolution of the oath He had sworn, “Inscribe this man childless.” and Zerubbabel was born to him in Babylon, and it was said to him through the prophet (Haggai 2:23), “On that day… I will take you, Zerubbabel, and I will make you as a signet,” directed toward what He said to his father, “Though… be a signet on My right arm,… I will remove him (sic).”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="And I will cast: ">an expression of throwing.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="they long: ">This is an expression of consolation, that their soul lifts itself to console itself and to say, “We will again return to our land.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="Is… a despised… image: ">It is a rhetorical question. Is this man a broken and despised image, that he was cast away from My face like a vessel in which there is no use?</text>
      <text title="shattered: ">broken. Cf. (Psalms 2:8) “Like a potter’s vessel you shall shatter them (תְּנַפְּצֵם).” [Others annotated: הַעֶצֶב is like the idols (הָעֲצַבִּים).“We may swathe (מְעַצְּבִין) an infant” in Tractate Shabbath 22:6. That is to say, “Are you despised and broken in your eyes like a small infant who is being swathed (emmailloter in French)? This one is not worthy.”</text>
      <text title="cast away: ">thrown, an expression of throwing that has no restoration. Comp. (Psalms 37:24), “If he falls, he will not be cast off (יוּטָל).”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="O land, land, land: ">A land that is a land among lands, the most esteemed of all of them. Another explanation: Eretz Israel had three lands in it. Judea, Transjordania, and Galilee.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="a man who will not prosper in his days: ">Inscribe him.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="23">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Woe to the shepherds: ">The kings of Judah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="and have not taken care of them: ">You were not careful to watch them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="nor shall [any of them] be missing: ">and they shall not be missing. (Cf. Num. 31:49) “And no one of us was missing (נפקד).”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="and prosper: ">Heb. והשכּיל.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="The Lord is our righteousness: ">The Lord will vindicate us during this one’s days.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Because of the prophets my heart is broken within me: ">Because of the words of the prophets who say, “You shall have peace,” my heart is broken.</text>
      <text title="shake: ">sway like the wings of a bird who hovers over his nest, (trenblent in O.F.) tremble.</text>
      <text title="because of the Lord: ">For I heard from Him this evil decree.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="because of oaths: ">False oaths.</text>
      <text title="mourns: ">i.e., is destroyed.</text>
      <text title="their eagerness: ">(course in French,) their course, their running. But Jonathan renders it as an expression of desire.</text>
      <text title="not right: ">Not according to the law.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="both prophet and priest: ">Even these, from whom everyone learns.</text>
      <text title="even in My house have I found their evil: ">For they placed an image in the Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="like slippery places: ">Smooth ground upon which the foot slips and the person falls.</text>
      <text title="like slippery places in the dark: ">Stumbling upon stumbling. On slippery places in the light there is stumbling. In the dark without slippery places, there is stumbling.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="And in the prophets of Samaria I saw unseemliness: ">before they were exiled.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="And in the prophets of Jerusalem: ">I now see.</text>
      <text title="a horrible thing: ">a shameful thing.</text>
      <text title="and they encouraged evil doers: ">They say to the wicked, “You shall have peace.”</text>
      <text title="that none returns: ">So that the evildoers would not return each one from his evil.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="and everyone who follows the view of his heart: ">And to everyone who follows the view of his heart, etc.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="For who stood in the council of the Lord: ">and will hear what is decreed by Him? He who hearkened to the word of His Torah and listened to His commandments, but not these wicked men. The first expression of ֹשְמִיעָה in the verse is actual hearing; the latter expression of ֹשְמִיעָה is an expression of acceptance.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="a whirling: ">A resting storm, a storm which seeks to rest, and it shall rest on the heads of the wicked.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="the plans of: ">an expression of thought.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="And if they stood in My council, they should have let My people hear My word, etc.: ">They should have let My people hear My words and My Torah, rather than cause them to stray away from Me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="Am I a God from near: ">that I do not see but what is close to Me and have I no power to judge the lower creatures that are far from Me and do I not know of their deeds?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="Can a man hide in secret places: ">This is a repetition of the question, ‘Am I a God from near,’ according to the manner of all double questions.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="How long [will this be]?: ">That they will prophesy falsely? Do these prophets who prophesy falsely have in their heart to execute their thoughts that they are thinking to cause My people to forget My name, etc.?</text>
      <text title="deceit: ">an expression of מִרְמָה, deceit.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="let him tell a dream: ">Let him tell it as vain talk like other dreams, and let him not presume it as words of prophecy.</text>
      <text title="What has the straw to do with the wheat?: ">What has falsehood to do with truth?</text>
      <text title="with the wheat: ">like עִם-הַבָּר.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="Is not My word so like fire?: ">They should not have erred to compare their dreams to say that they are prophecy, for the prophetic word, when it comes to a prophet, it comes into him with force like a burning fire, as the matter is stated (supra 20:9): “And it was in my heart like a burning fire,” and (Ezekiel 3:14): “And the hand of the Lord became strong upon me.”</text>
      <text title="and as a hammer: ">(pic in French), a pick. And some say (marteau in French), a hammer.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="those who steal My wards from one another: ">They have spies who spy upon the true prophets, who listen to their expression with which they prophesy and say false prophecies with that same expression, as Hananiah son of Azzur did. He heard Jeremiah prophesying in the upper marketplace, “Behold I break the bow of Elam,” and he prophesied in the lower marketplace, “I have broken the yoke of the king of Babylon” (28:2), as our Rabbis wrote in Sanhedrin 89a.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="those who train their tongues: ">who teach their tongues to say their falsehoods with the expression, “Says the Lord,” like the true prophets, so that they should believe them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="with their bewilderment: ">an expression of wonder (estordisoun in O. F.).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="“What is the burden of the Lord?”: ">This is an expression of derision, for his prophecy is a burden to them.</text>
      <text title="you shall say to them, “What burden? And I will forsake you, etc.”: ">They say to you (sic), “What is the burden?” You are the burden of the Holy One, blessed be He, and He says that He will forsake you and cast you off His arms from heaven to earth. So I heard.</text>
      <text title="and I will forsake: ">Heb. וְעָזַבְתִּי.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="For the burden shall be to the man of His word: ">Although you pervert the massa into a pejorative, the prophecy (משא) of the word of the Lord shall be to the man of His word, and to the man of His counsel He reveals it, but you pervert it to an expression of a burden. This interpretation I did not hear, but it is the main interpretation. But this is how I heard it, namely that the burden shall be a burden of retribution for the one who says it, who asks, “What is the burden?” Another interpretation: משא is an expression of prophecy, and the false prophet would ask the true prophet to tell him the word of the Holy One, blessed be He, in the language in which the expression came to him, and the expression did not explain the speech adequately. Therefore, the false prophet would pervert it to another meaning and would speak after the fashion of the true prophet in order that they should believe him. And so did Hananiah son of Azzur do. Therefore, he says, “Do not ask the prophecy of the Lord,” the language of the expression, but “What did He speak?” or “What did He reply?” The explanation of the words you shall ask the true prophet to tell you what the Holy One, blessed be He, says, and to what His words are inclined.</text>
      <text title="for the prophecy shall be for the man of His word: ">The unexplained expression the Holy One, blessed be He, said unexplained to the man of His counsel, who is not suspected of perverting it, but you ask it in order to pervert it, and you pervert the words of the Holy One, blessed be He, and that is what is stated above (v. 30): “those who steal My words from one another.” This too is a correct explanation.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="So shall you say to the prophet: ">when you come to ask My words of the prophet.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="39">
      <text title="and I will exile: ">an expression of “the sinew that was dislocated (גִיד הַנֹּשֶה) ” (Gen. 32:33), and an expression of “their might has failed (נֹשְתָה),” it jumps and moves from place to place.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="24">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="pots: ">Heb. דּוּדָאֵי.</text>
      <text title="prepared: ">Heb. מוּעדים.</text>
      <text title="the craftsmen and the sentries of the gates: ">Torah scholars who were exiled with Jeconiah, and I already explained in the Book of Kings (II 24:14) הֶחָרָש וְהַמַּסְגֵּר (les maitres, les portiers in French) the masters, the sentries of the gates. Another explanation: הֶחָרָש וְהַמַּסְגֵּר : הֶחָרָש is an expression of silence, וְהַמַּסְגֵּר is an expression of closing. That is to say, great sages in Torah, to the extent that when one of them would speak, everyone would remain silent. מַסְגֵּר means that when they would close the discussion, no one would reopen it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="like the first ripe figs: ">that have ripened completely in the beginning of the ripening of the figs which are dear to all those who find them in their beginning.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="so will I recognize the exile of, etc.: ">This is an inverted verse: So will I recognize for good the exile of Judah which I have already exiled, viz., Jeconiah and his exile.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="and not pluck them: ">an expression of uprooting.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="for a horror [and] for evil for all the kingdoms of the earth: ">For they will hear the evil that came upon them and quake.</text>
      <text title="and for a conversation piece: ">That everyone will repeat and discuss their retribution.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="25">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="in the fourth year: ">The year that their decree was sealed that they be exiled and that they drink the cup of wrath, as he says in this section (v. 15): “Take the cup, etc.,” and before the decree He commanded the prophet to reprove them, perhaps they would repent, and their decree would not be sealed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="twenty-three years: ">Josiah reigned thirty-one years (II Kings 22:1). Subtract twelve years from them (Jer. 1:2). This leaves nineteen, and four of his son amount to twenty-three.</text>
      <text title="arising early: ">This is a present tense. I would arise early and speak constantly.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="the sound of a mill: ">That is an indication of a circumcision feast, since they would grind and crush ingredients for healing the wound.</text>
      <text title="the light of a candle: ">An indication of a feast. So we learned in Sanhedrin (32b).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="all that is written: ">concerning Babylon.</text>
      <text title="in this Book: ">at its end.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="For… will enslave them: ">Like ‘For… shall enslave them,’ i.e., shall enslave the people of Babylon.</text>
      <text title="many nations… too: ">Viz. Media and Persia.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="cup of the wine of fury: ">The prophecy of retribution</text>
      <text title="and you shall give… to drink it: ">Prophesy to them that it will no longer be retracted for any repentance.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="and reel to and fro: ">Jonathan renders: and they shall be confused.</text>
      <text title="and be like madmen: ">an expression of madness, they shall be mad.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="as of this day: ">As they are today. Jeremiah wrote his Book after the destruction.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="And all the allies: ">All the supports (סוּמְכְוָתָא) which are Pharaoh’s guarantee, and he leans upon them for aid.</text>
      <text title="the allies: ">Garantie in French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="and the kings of the isle: ">All these that he counts (ֹשֶמוֹנֶה) until here are neighbors of Eretz Israel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="and all those separated in that corner: ">those separated at the end of that corner.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="the kings of Arabia: ">Heb. עֲרָב, Arabia.</text>
      <text title="and all the kings of the allies: ">The allies of the Arabs.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="Sheshach: ">That is ‘Babylon’ in אתבש.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="and vomit: ">Like a person who drinks too much, who vomits.</text>
      <text title="the sword: ">the strife of war.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="commence: ">מֵחֵל.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="over His habitation: ">He mourns over the destruction of His house.</text>
      <text title="“Hedad!”: ">A cry of “Ha!” that those engaged in hard work cry out aloud to urge each other on to strengthen themselves, and those who tread the winepresses are accustomed to it.</text>
      <text title="He shall call out: ">Every expression of עֲנִיָה, is an expression of a cry with a loud voice.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="He contends: ">He contends in judgment.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="from nation to nation: ">whom I incite against one another.</text>
      <text title="from the ends: ">as the Targum renders it: מִסְיָפֵי, from the ends of.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="Howl: ">an expression of יְלָלָה, howling.</text>
      <text title="and roll: ">i.e., roll in the dust (se vautrer in French).</text>
      <text title="and your scatterings: ">This is a short verse; i.e., to say: and your scatterings shall come near.</text>
      <text title="like a precious vessel: ">That is to say: If you say, “We are important,” there are many precious glass vessels that fall, break, and are lost.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="shall be destroyed: ">an expression of destruction, an expression related to ‘has silenced us (הֲדִמָּנוּ).’ ‘and there let us sit in silence (וְנִדְּמָה).’</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="38">
      <text title="He has left his hut like a young lion: ">The king has gone in exile from his city like a young lion that leaves his hut.</text>
      <text title="because of the wrath of the oppressing sword: ">drunk from wine. So did Jonathan translate. Another explanation: It is an expression of oppression (אוֹנָאָה).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="26">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="In the beginning of the reign: ">This chapter below preceded the above chapter by four years.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="And the princes of Judah heard: ">that the false prophets and the priests had seized Jeremiah.</text>
      <text title="at the entrance of the new gate of the Lord: ">Others annotated: When Jehoiachin went in exile and some of the vessels of the house of our God went with him, Nebuchadnezzar’s army breached the eastern gate, and Zedekiah subsequently repaired it and renewed it. It is therefore called ‘new.’</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="Micah the Morashtite: ">Who was from Maresha.</text>
      <text title="heaps: ">עִיִּים, heaps.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="and he entreated: ">Heb. וַיְחַל, an expression of prayer.</text>
      <text title="but we are doing great harm to ourselves: ">if we kill him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="Also a man was prophesying: ">The one who said this did not say this. I.e., those who related the incident of Micah did not relate the incident concerning Uriah. Up to here are the words of the righteous. Now the wicked who were there arose and said, “Also a man was prophesying, etc.” Just as Uriah was killed, so shall Jeremiah be killed. In this way it is explained in Sifrei (Num. 11:7).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="27">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="In the beginning of the reign of Jehoiakim: ">Three years prior to Nebuchadnezzar’s ascent to the throne, he prophesied about him that he would reign.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="thongs: ">They are the thongs of the yoke that are called kongoijli (cojongles).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And you shall send them to the king of Edom: ">In the days of Zedekiah in the fourth year of his reign, when Nebuchadnezzar made him ruler over five kings, the king of Edom, the king of Moab, the king of the children of Ammon, etc. These five kings Nebuchadnezzar placed under the authority of Zedekiah. Fifteen years they (the bars and thongs) were on his neck, from the first year of Jehoiakim until the fourth year of Zedekiah, when Hananiah son of Azzur broke them off him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="My servant: ">Who will perform My will to requite My enemies.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="and his son: ">Evil-Merodach.</text>
      <text title="and his son’s son: ">Belshazzar.</text>
      <text title="until the time of his own land come: ">When Darius the Mede and Cyrus come and slay Belshazzar.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And to Zedekiah the king of Judah have I spoken, etc.: ">All this Jeremiah said to the ambassadors of the kings.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="“Behold the vessels of the house of the Lord”: ">That were exiled with Jeconiah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="the bases: ">Jonathan renders: בְּסִיסַיָּא Cf.“the washbasin and its stand” (Exodus 35:16).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="when he exiled: ">Heb. בַּגְּלוֹתוֹ like בְּהַגְלוֹתוֹ.</text>
      <text title="the nobles of: ">חֹרֵי, like שֹרֵי the princes of.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="until the day I remember them: ">In the days of Cyrus, as is explained in the Book of Ezra (1:7 11).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="28">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And it came to pass in that year: ">When that time arrived that Nebuchadnezzar gave Zedekiah dominion over the five kings to whom Jeremiah stated his message and sent the thongs and the bars to the kings by the hand of their ambassadors.</text>
      <text title="in the beginning of the reign of Zedekiah: ">In the beginning of his dominion over the five kings. But it is impossible to say that it means at the beginning of his reign, since it says, “in the fourth year.” In that year, he went down to greet Nebuchadnezzar in Babylon, and Seraiah the receptionist was with him, as is stated at the end of the Book (51: 59), and he gave him dominion over the kings.</text>
      <text title="said to me: ">Our Sages state: Who misled Hananiah? He heard Jeremiah prophesying in the upper street, “Behold I am breaking the bow of Elam” (49: 35). And this prophecy was said in the beginning of the reign of Zedekiah, as is explained there, and since Elam is adjacent to Babylon, he stood in the lower street, and expounded. And he derived a major case from a minor one. If Elam, who came only to aid the Chaldeans, the Holy One, blessed be He, said, “Behold I am breaking the bow of Elam,” how much more is this so with the Chaldeans themselves? He came into the lower street and said: So said the Lord: I have broken the yoke of the king of Babylon, as it is in Sanhedrin (89a).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="may… do: ">Fasse in French.</text>
      <text title="May… fulfill: ">An expression of prayer. (These three lines up to “and he brought him to the prison” were not arranged by the author.)</text>
      <text title="Amen! So may the Lord do, etc.: ">Amen! The scholars of Aggadah say: So did he say to him: If only your words were fulfilled! I gain and you lose. I am a priest, and I eat the food hallowed in the name of Heaven if the Temple remains standing. But you are a Gibeonite, as it is written [here], “who was from Gibeon.” And you will be a slave to me, chopping wood and drawing water (Pesikta Rabbathi 27:4, Yalkut Shimoni ad loc.). But Moreh Zedek who did not explain, adopted the reason of our Sages (Sotah 41b) who learned from here that whoever flatters a wicked man will ultimately fall into his hands or into the hands of his son or into the hands of his son’s son, for Irijah, the son of Shelemiah, the son of Hananiah seized him and brought him to prison.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="But, hearken now… The prophet who would prophesy for peace.: ">He said: I prophesy retribution. If it does not come, I am not a liar, for the Holy One, blessed be He, renounces the evil, but the prophet who prophesies for peace, etc., when the word of the prophet comes, etc., but if his word does not come, he is a liar, as it is said, “God is not a man that He should lie, etc.” (Num. 23:19). In this manner Rabbi Tanhuma (Vayera 13) expounded.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="the beasts of the field have I given to him: ">He rode on a lion and tied a serpent on its head.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="this year you shall die: ">And next year you shall be buried.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="in that year, in the seventh month: ">Is it not so that the seventh month is not of the year? Rather, he died on the day preceding Rosh Hashanah and commanded his children to hurry him after Rosh Hashanah, but not before, and they should conceal his death on that day in order to make Jeremiah’s prophecy appear false.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="29">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="and the queen mother: ">The mother of the king.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="mislead: ">An expression of enticing. Cf: “The snake misled me (הֹשִיאַנִי)” (Gen. 3:13).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And you shall call Me and go: ">In My ways. This is an ellipsis.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="concerning the king: ">Zedekiah, who has not been exiled.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="as the loathsome figs: ">Heb. הֹשֹּעָרִים, an expression of, ֹשַעֲרוּרִיָּה, “a disgraceful thing” (Hos. 6:10).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="and for a reproach: ">That they will reproach them, and so is every expression of ירפה in Scripture.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="whom… burnt: ">an expression of “roasted with fire” (Lev. 2:14).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="and they committed adultery with the wives of their neighbors: ">As is explained in Sanhedrin (93a), “So said the Holy One, blessed be He, ‘Lie with my friend.’”</text>
      <text title="and a witness: ">an expression of testimony (עֵדוּת).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="the Nehelamite: ">A place name.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="made you a priest: ">He wrote this to Zephaniah.</text>
      <text title="officers: ">appointees.</text>
      <text title="the prison: ">כִּפָה</text>
      <text title="the stocks: ">a tree trunk (ceps in French).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="Forasmuch as: ">For you should rebuke him since he sent to us to Babylon saying, “Your exile there is long.”</text>
      <text title="Forasmuch as: ">like עַל-אֹשֶר because of which.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="30">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="For, behold, days are coming: ">And you shall not say, Why should I write it, since they all will perish, and no one will read it, neither will anyone remember it anymore, for, “behold, days are coming, etc.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="A sound of quaking we have heard: ">Some interpret this as alluding to the tidings of Babylon, from which those exiled there quaked. But the Midrash Aggadah explains it as an allusion to the war of Gog and Magog.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="whether a male gives birth: ">Whether it is customary for males to give birth, so that labor pains should seize them like a woman in confinement.</text>
      <text title="his loins: ">like מָתְנָיו.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="that day: ">The day of the assassination of Belshazzar and the downfall of Babylon. Another explanation: the day of the downfall of Gog.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="I will break his yoke: ">The yoke of the heathens will be removed from Israel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="And you, fear not: ">Because of all the evils that you will see befalling Babylon in whose midst you are.</text>
      <text title="and at ease: ">like וֹשָקֵט.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="but I will chasten you in measure: ">according to the law of the Torah.</text>
      <text title="and I will not completely destroy you: ">an expression of a sweeping destruction.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="Your injury is painful, your wound grievous: ">(Enfers in Old French).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="to be healed: ">cure. No one thinks that you will have salvation.</text>
      <text title="healing: ">a cure, an expression of availing.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="cruel chastisement: ">chastisements of cruelty. The chastisement is cruel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="Therefore: ">This is an expression denoting an oath.</text>
      <text title="those who plunder you: ">an expression of spoil, and so did Jonathan render it: וִיהוֹן עָדַיִ לַעֲדִי.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="healing: ">Heb. ארכה.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="and the palace: ">The Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="and I will increase them: ">I will make them a numerous nation.</text>
      <text title="and they shall not become few in number: ">like יִמְעָטוּ.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="their prince: ">lit., his mighty one.</text>
      <text title="pledged his heart: ">an expression of a pledge (fermaille, aatine in French).</text>
      <text title="to approach Me: ">to war, to stop Me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="settling storm: ">camping and dwelling an expression of “the land of the sojournings of (מְגוּרֵי) ” (Gen. 37:1), and a similar case is “and a whirling (מִתְחוֹלֵל) storm” (supra 23:19) stated in the other verse is the same as this for both of them are expressions of camping.</text>
      <text title="on the head[s] of the wicked: ">On the heads of the heathens.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="31">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="found favor: ">The generation of the wilderness found favor in My eyes.</text>
      <text title="who had escaped the sword: ">of the Egyptians the Amalekites and the Canaanites.</text>
      <text title="He [therefore] went to give Israel their resting place: ">When He led them to take possession of the land of their rest.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="From long ago: ">In the merit of the Patriarchs.</text>
      <text title="appeared to me: ">I, the prophet, and told me to say to the congregation of Israel, “With everlasting love have I loved you.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="Yet again will I rebuild you, then you shall be built: ">You had two buildings made by men. Therefore, they were destroyed. Yet again will I rebuild you, I by Myself, a third building, and you shall be built forever.</text>
      <text title="shall you be adorned: ">Heb. תַּעְדִּי.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="and redeem [them]: ">in the fourth year, they shall profane their produce by redeeming it with money.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="the watchers shall call: ">The lookouts at the tops of the lofty towers to announce with a voice heard a distance away. Another explanation: נֹצְרִים is like “He keeps (נֹצֵר) lovingkindness” (Exod. 34:7), an expression of keeping. That is to say: There is a day when they will call those who kept the Torah and say, “Rise…” And so did Jonathan render: There are many days and much goodness that is destined to come to the righteous who kept My Torah from days of old.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="and shout at the head of the nations: ">On the lofty towers, so that they should hear from afar.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="the blind and the lame amongst them: ">Even the staggering ones among them I will not reject.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="With weeping will they come: ">Through prayer and repentance.</text>
      <text title="9“He Who scattered”: ">(separant in French, separating.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="and they will stream: ">They will gather like a river.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="fat: ">Heb. דָשֶן.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="A voice is heard on high: ">A voice is heard in the height of the world, the voice of the house of Israel weeping over Jeremiah the prophet when Nebuzaradan sent him from Ramah to return after the exiles to Gedaliah son of Ahikam, as is stated in this Book (below ch. 39).</text>
      <text title="Rachel weeping for her children: ">The Midrash Aggadah states (see Lam. Rabbah Proem 24) that the Patriarchs and the Matriarchs went to appease the Holy One blessed be He concerning the sin of Manasseh who placed an image in the Temple but He was not appeased. Rachel entered and stated before Him “O Lord of the Universe, whose mercy is greater, Your mercy or the mercy of a flesh and blood person? You must admit that Your mercy is greater. Now did I not bring my rival into my house? For all the work that Jacob worked for my father he worked only for me. When I came to enter the nuptial canopy, they brought my sister, and it was not enough that I kept my silence, but I gave her my password. You, too, if Your children have brought Your rival into Your house, keep Your silence for them.” He said to her, “You have defended them well. There is reward for your deed and for your righteousness, that you gave over your password to your sister.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="complaining: ">(Konpljjet in O.F.), an expression of “who will lament for you (יָנוּד) ?” (above 15:5).</text>
      <text title="“You have chastised me”: ">With pains, You, the Holy One, blessed be He.</text>
      <text title="like an ungoaded calf: ">(fut aiguillones in O.F.), was goaded, an expression of “an ox-goad (מַלְמַד הַבָּקָר) ” (Judges 3:31). I was like an ungoaded calf in the beginning. Therefore, I sinned against You.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="I have completely changed my mind: ">I regret my abominations.</text>
      <text title="I had been brought to know myself: ">That I thought of myself that I was treacherous, (aparsoujjge in O. F.).</text>
      <text title="the reproach of my youth: ">That my enemies can reproach me for the sins of my youth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="“Is Ephraim a son who is dear to me?”: ">These are the words of the Shechinah. That is to say, He is complaining, “And as for Me, I have a change of heart to have pity. Is he My dear son (as one who has but one son, whose every wish he grants him)?”</text>
      <text title="dandled: ">(Esbaniement in O.F.)</text>
      <text title="whenever I speak of him: ">Every time that I speak of him. And the Midrash Leviticus Rabbah (2:3) explains: It is enough My speech (דַּי דִבּוּרִי) with which I endowed him, that I taught him My Torah, for Me to have mercy on him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="Set up markers for yourself: ">Signs in the good ways of your ancestors.</text>
      <text title="small palms: ">small palms (תְּמָרִים) planted for a sign on the way. And the simple interpretation of the verse is. Make signs to know the way you traversed from Eretz Israel to Babylon, so that you will return by that road; that is to say that you will surely return from there.</text>
      <text title="the road upon which you went: ">The “kethib” is הָלָכְתִּי, “I went,” and everywhere that you went I went with you Jonathan, however, renders. place “tamrurim” for yourself: Pray with embittered spirit, deriving תַּמְרוּרִים from מַר bitter. (And Menahem [Machbereth p. 119] explained תַּמְרוּרִים as an expression of raising up, and so he explained וְתִמְרוֹת “raising of smoke” (Joel 3:3). In some editions, this is missing.)</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="will you hide: ">will you hide from Me, that you are ashamed to return to Me because of your way? Behold, something new has been created on earth, that a woman shall go after a man to seek him that he should marry her. This is an expression of “and I will go around (וַאֲסוֹבְבָה) in the city; I will seek, etc.” (Song 3:2). And in the name of Rabbi Judah the Preacher I heard: A woman shall turn around to become a man. I gave you like a daughter, who receives a tenth of the property of her father, seven nations out of seventy. Ultimately, you shall take everything like a son, a male, who inherits everything.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="Thereupon, I awoke: ">So said Jeremiah, “All this time I was sleeping deeply while perceiving the prophecy of retribution, but with this prophecy I awoke from my deep sleep.”</text>
      <text title="was pleasant: ">Heb. עָרְבָה.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="seed of man and seed of beasts: ">The good and the foolish of them, I will sow all of them to be My seed. Seed of man and seed of beasts. Jonathan renders. I will set them up (our edition: I will increase them) like people and I will make them succeed like a beast, whose iniquities are not visited upon her.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="unripe grapes: ">A fruit that is not yet ripe, and it sets the teeth on edge.</text>
      <text title="And the teeth of the children shall be set on edge…: ">The children for the fathers’ iniquity.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="to illuminate: ">(esclarzir in Prov. or eclaircir in O.F., eclairer in Modern French), to brighten, and so did Jonathan render: לְאַנְהָרָא, to illuminate.</text>
      <text title="Who stirs up the sea: ">He breaks the sea, moves it and “boils” it, and it becomes wrinkles. Cf.“my skin became wrinkled (רָגַע)” (Job 7:5).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="depart: ">“He would not move away (יָמִיש)” (Exod. 13:22).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="If the heavens… will be measured: ">How much is their altitude.</text>
      <text title="I too will reject… Israel: ">That is to say that just as they can neither be measured nor fathomed so will Israel not be rejected because of all that they sinned.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="39">
      <text title="valley of the dead bodies: ">The valley where the bodies of the camp of Sennacherib fell.</text>
      <text title="and the ash: ">The place where the ashes are poured out, which was outside Jerusalem, they will add to the city and include all this within its walls. Now this prophecy relates to the future, to the final redemption, since it did not take place in the time of the Second Temple.</text>
      <text title="the fields: ">(Kanpanjje in O.F.) (campagne in Modern French, open country.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="32">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="was besieging: ">an expression of a siege (מָצוֹר).</text>
      <text title="in the prison yard: ">an expression of “the prison” (בֵּיתהַמֹּשְמָר).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="until I remember him: ">The remembrance of all mankind. That is death.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="And Jeremiah said, etc.: ">He did not say this to Zedekiah but Scripture explained why he imprisoned him and then returned to its first statement to explain what the word was that came to Jeremiah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="is coming: ">By Divine command.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="the deed of the purchase: ">The deed of the sale.</text>
      <text title="that which was signed, etc.: ">With its signature as it was signed according so the law and the statute.</text>
      <text title="and that which was open: ">Which was confirmed in the court by word of its witnesses, and the judges wrote and signed a judicial confirmation. This is the confirmation of the deeds to make the matter open and publicized lest the witnesses die, and our Rabbis explained this concerning a plain, open document and a folded one in Baba Bathra (160b).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="in the presence of Hanamel my uncle: ">And until now, he calls him “my uncle’s son.” Perhaps there were two. Otherwise, I do not know what it means. Some are inclined to say that Hanamel was both Jeremiah’s uncle and his uncle’s son; e.g. Reuben married the daughter of his brother Simon, and she bore him Jemuel, and Simon had already begotten Jamin. Hence, Jamin is Jemuel’s uncle, since he is his mother’s brother, and also his uncle’s son, since he is the son of Simon, Jemuel’s father’s brother. This is, however, not the method of expression, for we do not find anywhere in the Bible, that the mother’s brother is called an uncle.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="So said, etc.: ">Do not say that I am concealing them for nothing since everyone is going into exile.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="For so says the Lord: ">They will ultimately purchase houses.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="nothing is hidden from You: ">Nothing is hidden; hence You know that we are destined to be exiled, so why did You tell me to buy a field?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="and requites the iniquity of the fathers in the bosom: ">Of this generation who follow their ancestors in their evil way.</text>
      <text title="Great and Mighty: ">But he did not say, “and awesome.” He said. Heathens are dancing in His Temple. Where then are His awesome deeds? In Tractate Yoma (69b).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="and in mankind: ">And in other people. Another explanation: Signs that were equal for Israel and for the Egyptians. How so?“And there was the cloud and the darkness, and it illuminated the night” (Exodus 14:20). That guardian angel that served darkness for the Egyptians, served light for the Israelites Midrash Aggadah (source unknown). And Jonathan renders: And for Israel You performed wonders among people.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="then You caused… to come upon them: ">You caused to happen to them, an expression of a happening (מִקְרֶה).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="and what You have proclaimed: ">Evil upon it has come to pass (lit., has been and has come).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="Yet the city is given: ">Of what avail is the field to me?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="Is… concealed from Me?: ">Are future events concealed from Me?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="since the day they built it: ">On the day that the Temple was founded, Solomon married Pharaoh’s daughter.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="I taught them: ">lit., and teaching them. This is a participle, (apprenant in French).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="Behold I will gather them: ">with mercy from wherever I have driven them with My anger.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="33">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="confined: ">in the prison.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="So said the Lord, the Maker thereof: ">Who makes this.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="Call Me and I will answer you: ">to inform you of future events.</text>
      <text title="and strong things: ">laid up in My heart to perform them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="that are demolished for the mounds: ">To make mounds of them, mounds piled up high which the city dwellers build to ascend the mounds to wage war from upon them with the Chaldeans.</text>
      <text title="and for the sword: ">To strengthen the wall against those who slay with the sword.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="and to fill them with the corpses of the men: ">And the houses that they demolished they make into graves for the corpses of those killed within the city.</text>
      <text title="and that which I have hidden, etc.: ">So said the Lord: Behold, I will bring it, etc.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="a greeting of peace: ">a blessing (salud in O.F., salut in modern French), a greeting.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="a dwelling of shepherds: ">Heb. נְוֵה רֹעִים.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="flocks shall again pass, etc.: ">Israel will come and go under the hands of a king who walks at their head.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="There shall not be cut off: ">permanently, but if it is discontinued, it will ultimately be reinstated.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="for all time: ">There shall not be cut off from them seed fit to offer up a burnt-offering or to burn a meal-offering.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="If you break My covenant with the day: ">If you can break My covenant that I formed with the day and with the night to be in their time, which I formed with Noah and his sons, “And day and night shall not cease” (Gen. 8:22).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="The two families: ">Viz. royalty and the priesthood.</text>
      <text title="and they make My people despise: ">And with these words, they cause My people to despise being a nation to Me.</text>
      <text title="before them: ">According to these words of theirs, that they teach them to say that the Holy One, blessed be He, will no longer return from His anger, and repentance will not avail them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="If not My covenant, etc.: ">If it is possible that the covenant that I formed with day and night to be in their time should be abolished, and if it is possible for the statutes of heaven and earth to be abolished as though I had not placed them, also the seed of Jacob, etc. Our Sages, however, expounded it in regard to the covenant of the Torah and circumcision, to derive from here that because of them heaven and earth were created. But this Midrash does not fit the sequence of the verses.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="34">
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="You shall die in peace: ">Our Sages stated that Nebuchadnezzar died during his lifetime (Moed Katan 28b), for all the days of Nebuchadnezzar his prisoners were not freed from their imprisonment, and when Nebuchadnezzar died, Zedekiah emerged from the prison. He died the next day and was buried with pomp.</text>
      <text title="and with the burnings of your forefathers: ">So was their custom, to burn for the kings their bier and the utensils they used.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="after King Zedekiah had made a covenant: ">In the seventh year of his reign. So we learned it in Seder Olam (ch. 26): “And it came to pass in the seventh year… men came of the elders of Judah (sic) to inquire of the Lord” (Ezekiel 20:1). They said to Ezekiel, ‘The slave of a priest whom his owner soldwhat is the ruling regarding whether he may eat of the priest’s due?’ That is to say, because they wanted to say that they should not be punished for infracting the commandment by returning the slaves.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="behold I proclaim freedom to you: ">from Me, that I am not your master to save you, and you shall be free to the sword and to the famine.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="when they cut the calf in two: ">Whey they returned and forced them to be slaves, they all made a covenant to rebel against the Omnipresent and cut a calf in two and passed between its parts to rebel against Him, and that was a strong covenant and a final one, saying, So shall the one who transgresses be cut and divided.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="who have gone up away from you: ">because of the army of Pharaoh that came out of Egypt, as is explained in this Book (37:5).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="Behold I command: ">that Pharaoh’s army return to his land, and the Chaldeans return upon you.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="35">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="to the house of the Rechabites: ">The sons of Jonadab the son of Rechab, and they were of the sons of Jethro.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="the man of God: ">The prophet of the Lord.</text>
      <text title="the keeper of the vessels: ">Heb. שמר הסף. Jonathan renders: אמרכּלא (tresorier in French,) a treasurer.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="but you shall dwell in tents: ">in the deserts where you dwell. They had no share in the land since they were the children of proselytes.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="And it came to pass when Nebuchadrezzar… came up: ">Perforce we came to the city. Therefore, we are now dwelling in houses.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="36">
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="imprisoned: ">in the jail.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="the new gate: ">That is the Eastern Gate; so did Jonathan translate.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="“We will surely tell the king”: ">Perhaps he will hear.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="to the court: ">Heb. חצרה, equivalent to אל החצר. Every word that requires a ‘lammed’ in the beginning Scripture placed a ‘heh’ at its end.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="and the brazier: ">Heb. האח. Our Rabbis (Shabbath 21a) defined it as wood, called so because they burn with brotherhood. (That is to say that they are ignited one from the other, like brothers, who benefit each other. Omitted in other editions.) And according to its simple meaning, it appears that it is a vessel upon which they kindle fire before the princes.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="three… verses: ">Our Rabbis (Moed Katan 26a) stated. This was the Scroll of Lamentations. They read before him, (1:1) “How…(:2) She weeps… (ibid. 3) Judah has been exiled…(ibid. 4) The roads of Zion are mournful.” Despite all this, he was not troubled. He said, “I am the king over the survivors.” As soon as he read (ibid. 5), Her adversaries have become the head, “ he said,” From now on, I am [no longer] the king." Immediately, he rent it with a scribe’s razor.</text>
      <text title="he rent: ">Heb. יקרעה, like קְרָעָה.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="entreated: ">Heb. הפגעו, supplicated.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="many words like those: ">At first, there were three alphabetical acrostics: (Lam. ch. 1) “O how… remained,” (2) “How… brought darkness,” (4) “How dim… has become.” And he added to it, (3) “I am the man,” in which every letter is tripled.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="37">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="reigned as king: ">Since from now on, i.e., from this point, he comes to tell and to say that the retributions that he prophesied until now were fulfilled, he started to tell in this manner, that when the time of the visitation, when the days drew near that the words should be fulfilled, another king reigned over Judah instead of Coniah the son of Jehoiakim, etc.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="And Jeremiah was coming and going among the people: ">When Zedekiah assumed the throne, he gave an order and they freed him from the jail where Jehoiakim had imprisoned him, for Zedekiah was a righteous man and the people of his generation were wicked, whereas Jehoiakim was a wicked man and the people of his generation were righteous.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="Now Pharaoh’s army had left Egypt: ">to aid Judah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="is returning to his land Egypt: ">They were coming in ships, and the Holy One, blessed be He, signaled to the sea and caused a type of bottles and flasks (i.e., inflated) resembling human skins to float on it. They said to each other, What is this? They replied, These are our forefathers, whom the forefathers of these whom we are going to aid, drowned. They immediately returned to their land.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="to share [land] from there among the people: ">Jonathan [renders]: To share his inheritance among the people, and as long as the Chaldeans were besieging it, he did not leave it, for he prayed that it should not be taken.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="and there was the captain of the guard: ">Appointed to guard so that no man should leave the city to make peace with the Chaldeans.</text>
      <text title="the son of Shelemiah the son of Hananiah: ">That is Hananiah the son of Azzur. He was his grandson, and for the following reason Scripture traced his lineage, [viz.] to teach that whoever flatters a wicked man eventually falls into his hands or into the hands of his son or into the hands of his grandson, and Jeremiah flattered him, for he said to him, “Amen! (28:6) [So may the Lord do.] May the Lord fulfil your words” (Sotah 41b). And [according to] the Midrash Aggadah, Hananiah commanded his son, "See that I am dying because of Jeremiah, and he made me a liar in my prophecy. If you can cause him to stumble, cause him to stumble. And his son commanded his son also in that manner, and when the time came, he caused him to stumble.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="and to the cells: ">Jonathan renders: within the cells. There were cells before that prison.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="from the street of the bakers: ">Heb. מחוץ, from the street of the bakers. Cf: “And you shall make streets (וחצות) for yourself in Damascus” (I Kings 20:34).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="38">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="and he shall have his life as prey: ">His life shall be saved, as if had “plundered” his soul; just as a man profits from plundering booty, so this person will profit [by saving] his life.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="since he weakens: ">(a lacher in O.F.), an expression of weakness.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="cannot: ">Heb. יוּכַל, like יָכוֹל, since he is weakening the hands of, etc.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="the pit of Malchiah: ">lit. the pit Malchiah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="Ebed-melech: ">Baruch the son of Neriah.</text>
      <text title="the Cushite: ">Zedekiah. Just as a Cushite is different in his skin, so was Zedekiah different in his righteousness, from all his generation (Moed Katan 16b). And there is a Midrash that expounds “the Cushite,” as referring to Baruch (Sifrei ibid.).</text>
      <text title="an officer: ">Heb. סריס, a great man.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="He would have died in his place, etc.: ">If they had left him in his place, he would have died by himself in the famine, but they have done harm to bring his death closer.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="thirty men: ">Since they were weakened by the famine, all of them were required.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="worn clouts: ">Heb. בלוי סחבות, worn out garments, that are dragged.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="and the rags: ">Heb. והמלחים, an expression of decay. Cf.“shall vanish (נמלחוּ) like smoke” (Isa. 51: 6).</text>
      <text title="under your armpits: ">So that the ropes should not harm you.</text>
      <text title="armpits: ">Heb. אצילות, aisseles in French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="the third entrance: ">I do not know where it is. Perhaps it is in the Israelites’ Court. The appellation “third” is to say that the hel [the wall surrounding the Temple Court], and the Women’s Court are before it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="“I fear”: ">Heb. דֹאֵג.</text>
      <text title="lest they deliver me: ">[Lest] the Chaldeans [deliver me] into the hands of the Jews, saying, Your king shall be your slave since you have made peace with us first.</text>
      <text title="and mock me: ">[i.e.,] the Jews [will mock me] (engregier in O.F.), complain.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="“Your cohorts”: ">[lit. the men of your peace,] the false prophets, who told you that you would not be caught.</text>
      <text title="into the mire: ">Heb. בבץ, mire, an expression as in (Job 8:11): “Can the rush shoot up without mire (בצה) ?”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="and this city you shall burn with fire: ">It is as though you are burning it with your hands for you are causing it.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="39">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And all the officers of the king of Babylon came and sat in the middle gate, etc.: ">[This] tells [us] that here the above prophecy, “And they will come and place, each one his throne at the entrance of the gates of Jerusalem, etc.” (1:15) was fulfilled.</text>
      <text title="in the middle gate: ">Heb. בשער התוך. Jonathan renders: in the middle gate, the gate of the Temple court, the Nicanor Gate, the Eastern Gate, and it is between the gate of the Women’s Court and the gate of the Temple proper. And our Rabbis (Sanh. 103a) said: The gate where the halachoth were decided (מחתכים). Concerning them, Scripture says. “The place of judgment there is wickedness” (Ecc. 3:16).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="by way of the king’s garden: ">He had a cave from his house to the plains of Jericho, and he went out at night by way of the cave. What did the Holy One, blessed be He, do to fulfill “And I will spread My net over him” (Ezek. 12:13)? He prepared a deer before the Chaldeans walking on the roof the cave outside the city, and they ran after it to seize it, and it ran up to the entrance of the cave, and they saw Zedekiah going out of the cave.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="he called him to account: ">Why did you transgress the oath?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="and… all the nobles of Judah: ">These are the Sanhedrin, because they had annulled the oath.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="the houses of the people: ">The synagogues.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="vineyards and fields: ">Heb. ויגבים, fields to till. Every יגיבה is an expression of digging (a fosser in French), to dig.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="the officers of: ">Heb. רבי, like שָּׂרֵי.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="to Gedaliah the son of Ahikam: ">who defected to the Chaldeans in compliance with Jeremiah’s orders, and when the city was taken, he appointed him governor over those remaining there.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="and they shall be before you on that day: ">And the words shall be before you, for you shall see them fulfilled.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="into the hand[s] of the men: ">into the hand[s] of the Chaldeans.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="40">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="The word that came: ">What is stated at the end of the section (42: 7): “And it was at the end of ten days that the word of the Lord came etc.,” but he first wrote on account of what it was said to him. And the Midrash Aggadah in Lamentations Rabbah (Proem 34): What was the word? “And return to Gedaliah.” He said to him: Either you go down with them and I will remain (?) here, or you remain here and I will go down with them. He replied: If I go down with them, what will I help them? Rather, let their Creator go down with them, for He will help them exceedingly.</text>
      <text title="from Ramah: ">Where he went into exile by himself with them. He would see a group [of youths] joined by a collar and would put his neck between them, etc., as is stated in Pesikta of the Haftarah Divrei Yirmiyahu (p. 113). For it is impossible to say that Nebuzaradan put him in chains since Nebuchadnezzar commanded him, “Do him no harm” (above 39:12).</text>
      <text title="in fetters: ">Heb. באזקים, ceps in French, fetters.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="“The Lord your God spoke”: ">Why are you troubled about them? Did you not prophesy to them and they did not hearken? As it is stated in Pesikta d’Rav Kahana (p. 113a).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="I have released you: ">Heb. פתחתיך, an expression related to “And he untied (ויפתח) the camels” (Gen. 24.32). And so did Jonathan render: Behold, now I have untied you. But Menahem (p. 147) interpreted all of them as an expression of actual opening (פתיחה).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="But he would still not return: ">Despite this, he did not wish to return. The Holy One, blessed be He, said to him, “And return to Gedaliah,” who was appointed over the remaining poor people. They, too, need you, like the rest of the exiles.</text>
      <text title="an allowance and a present: ">Heb. ארחה ומשאת. Jonathan renders: מתנן וּנבזבן.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="and dried figs: ">Heb. וקיץ, dried figs.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="41">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="and officers of the king: ">They were jealous of him that he took a high position.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="to bring to the house of the Lord: ">When they left home, they were unaware of the destruction of the Temple, and en route, they heard of it, and rent their clothing and shaved their beards.</text>
      <text title="and having cut themselves: ">An expression [denoting] laceration.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="through Gedaliah: ">Heb. ביד, [lit. by the hand of Gedaliah]. Since he should have heeded the counsel of Johanan the son of Kareah, and he did not heed, Scripture accounts it for him as though they had been slain by him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="by the great waters: ">[By the pool of great waters.]</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="in Geruth Chimham: ">In the sojourning place that David gave to Chimham the son of Barzilai the Gileadite when he returned from the war of Absalom, as it is stated in the Book of Samuel (II 19:39): “Chimham shall go over with me.”</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="42">
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="the sound of the horn: ">which the lookouts sound to warn the people.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="43">
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="and hide them in the mortar: ">Heb. במלט. This ‘mem’ is a defective radical in the word, like מקום, a place, מעמד, a stand, מעשה, a deed, and its root is לט, cf.“he wrapped (וילט) his face” (I Kings 19:13). Envelop them in the mortar in the framework.</text>
      <text title="in the mortar: ">(Envolopemant in O.F)</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="his pavilion: ">Heb. שפרירו, his tent, and a similar case is [found] in Job 26:13: “By His breath, He made the heavens a tent (שפרה).”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="and he shall wrap up the land of Egypt: ">He shall wrap up all its plunder and leave, as a shepherd wraps up and rolls his garment and casts it over his shoulder when he leads his flock before him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="the monuments of Beth-shemesh: ">The altars that those who proselytized in the days of Hezekiah had made there Sennacherib’s captives whom he brought from Cush and from Egypt before Jerusalem on the day of his downfall, as it is stated “On that day there shall be five cities in the land of Egypt speaking the language of Canaan and swearing to the Lord of Hosts one of which will be called ‘the city of Heres’” (Isa. 19.18). Jonathan renders: The city of Beth-shemesh, which is destined to be destroyed, will be said to be one of them.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="44">
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="They were not crushed: ">Their hearts were not crushed because of their evil.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="only fugitives: ">Jeremiah and Baruch returned from there, for Nebuchadnezzar exiled them when the land of Egypt was delivered into his hand in the twenty-seventh year of his reign (Ezek. 29:17). So we learned in Seder Olam (ch. 26).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="without our husbands: ">Without their knowledge.</text>
      <text title="cakes in her image: ">Heb. כונים להעצבה, molds in the shape of idols (idols in the shape of a young lady as above ch. 22:28).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="And He could no longer bear: ">Heb. ולא יוּכַל, like ולא יָכוֹל, and He could not.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="Pharaoh Hophra: ">Heb. פרעה חפרע, rendered by Jonathan as פרעֹה תבירה, the broken Pharaoh, and this ‘heth’ serves instead of a ‘heh.’</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="45">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="but I have found no rest: ">Heb. ומנוחה. The Shechinah has not rested upon me to prophesy. Cf.“And the spirit rested (ותנח) upon them” (Num. 12:26). “Why am I different from the disciples of the prophets? Joshua served Moses and the Holy Spirit rested upon him. Elisha served Elijah and the Holy Spirit rested upon him. Why am I different?”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="and it is all the land: ">that is being judged with this uprooting and tearing down.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="And you seek great things for yourself?: ">[“Great things” means] prophecies. Cf. “Please tell me all the great things etc.” (II Kings 8:4).“Call to me… and I will tell you great, etc,” (above 33:3). The Holy One, blessed be He, said to him: If there is no vineyard, there is no fence, and if there are no sheep, there is no shepherd. I reveal Myself to the prophets only in the merit of Israel. We learned this in the Mechilta, in the beginning.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="46">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="shield: ">Heb. מגן. It is made of leather, and it is boiled, and when he goes forth to battle, he anoints it with oil.</text>
      <text title="and buckler: ">Heb. וצנה, [made] of wood, in the likeness of our shields.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="polish the spears: ">Heb. מרקו. Cf.“It shall be scoured (וּמֹרַק) and rinsed” (Lev. 6:21), (forbir in O.F., to furbish).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="them breaking: ">The Egyptians.</text>
      <text title="and were not freed?: ">[They were] no longer freed to stand in battle; they had no free time.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="Who… would come up like the Nile: ">Who was wont to bring up troops around him like the waters of a river, to flood its environs.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="would come up like the Nile: ">Was accustomed to coming up.</text>
      <text title="I will destroy: ">Heb. אֹבִידָה, like אֲאַבֵּד.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="and rush madly: ">Heb. והתהללו, an expression of folly.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="and its thirst shall be quenched: ">Heb. ורותה, an expression of satiety. [Another interpretation: It] is an expression of drunkenness; cf. שֵּׁכַר, strong drink, which we translate מְרַוֵי.</text>
      <text title="in the north land: ">For Pharaoh marched on Nebuchadnezzar in Carchemish, and there he fell and his mighty men were slain, and he fled from the battle.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="a mighty man has stumbled upon a mighty man: ">When they were fleeing they would stumble over each other.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="concerning the coming of Nebuchadnezzar: ">This was a second blow, [viz.] that Nebuchadnezzar laid Egypt waste in the twenty-seventh year of his reign (Ezek. 29:17), as we learned in Seder Olam (ch. 26).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="“Stand fast and prepare yourself”: ">for the war. והכן means “and prepare.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="been swept away?: ">Heb. נסחף. Your mighty men have been swept away and have slid. Cf.“sweeping (סֹחֵף) rain” (Prov. 28:3);“His field has been inundated (נסתחפה)” (Kethuboth 1:6). Menahem (Machbereth p. 126) classified it as an expression of complete destruction, and so did he classify סחף מטר. Dunash, however, interprets מטר סחף like מטר סועף, cutting rain. Cf.“Lops off (מְסָעֵף) the branches with a saw” (Isa. 10:33).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="He made many stumbling blocks: ">The Holy One, blessed be He, Who pushed him down, made many stumbling blocks for him.</text>
      <text title="yea, they joined: ">Heb. נפל [lit. fell]. They joined one another, saying, Arise and let us go back to our own people, whence we came to wage war.</text>
      <text title="the oppressing sword: ">Heb. חרב. Jonathan renders: The sword of the enemy, which is like intoxicating wine. היונה. An expression of wine (יין). Another interpretation: It is an expression of oppression (אונאה).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="There they called out: ">In the battle, they proclaimed publicly a reproachful byword.</text>
      <text title="“Pharaoh, king of Egypt, who made a lot of noise”: ">Who would raise the sound of his noise, the noises to boast with his armies.</text>
      <text title="has allowed the appointed time to pass by: ">For he had appointed a set time to go forth and wage war, and he did not go forth, and the day of the appointed time passed by.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="that as sure as Tabor is among the mountains: ">Just as it is a true fact that Tabor is fast among the mountains and Mount Carmel is by the sea, so is it true that this thing shall come upon Egypt.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="equipment for exile: ">When a person embarks on a journey, he prepares for himself a flask and an earthenware cup with which to drink.</text>
      <text title="desolate: ">Heb. ונצחה, an expression of desolation (ציה).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="a fair heifer: ">A beautiful kingdom.</text>
      <text title="destruction: ">peoples that kill [acc. to Jonathan]. קֶרֶץ is an expression of cutting. Cf.“I… was cut (קֹרצתי) out of clay” (Job 33: 6).</text>
      <text title="from the north: ">From Babylon.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="Also her princes: ">Heb. שְׂכִרֶיהָ, her princes. Cf.“with the great razor (הַשְׂכִירָה) ” (Isa. 7: 20).</text>
      <text title="fattened: ">(kopla in O.F., couple in modern French).</text>
      <text title="turn around: ">Turned their back to seek to flee.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="Its voice shall go like [that of] the snake: ">The “snake” comes to teach us about Egypt but ends by learning. For we learn from here that when the Holy One, blessed be He, said to the serpent, “You shall walk on your belly” (Gen. 3:14), He severed his feet, and his voice went to the end of the world. So we learned in the ‘Thirty-two Methods of Rabbi Eliezer the son of Rabbi Jose the Galilean’ (Method 12).</text>
      <text title="for they will march with an army: ">against her.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="They will cut down her forest: ">They have power to cut down her forest.</text>
      <text title="for they are innumerable: ">[lit. it shall not be fathomed, i.e.,] the number of their host.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="upon Amon: ">Heb. אל אמון, [lit. to Amon,] upon Amon, upon the prince Amon. There are some that are an expression of greatness. Cf.“Are you greater than the greatness of No (מִנֹא אָמוֹן) ?” (Nahum 3:8).</text>
      <text title="of No: ">The great Alexandria (les seigneurs d’Alexandria in O.F.).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="and after that: ">At the end of forty years, as Ezekiel stated (29:1 3ff.).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="You fear not: ">The righteous men who were in Egypt, who were exiled there against their will.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="justly: ">With sparing justice, little by little.</text>
      <text title="completely destroy: ">Heb. ונקה [lit. clean,] an expression of sweeping and destroying, and Jonathan too rendered it an expression of destroying.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="47">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="concerning the Philistines: ">Heb. אל פלישתים [lit.] to the Philistines.</text>
      <text title="before Pharaoh struck Gaza: ">When Nebuchadnezzar besieged Jerusalem in the tenth year of Zedekiah, Pharaoh’s army came forth from Egypt, and the Chaldeans withdrew from Jerusalem. Pharaoh heard, invaded Gaza and returned to his land. In Seder Olam (ch. 26).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="the stamping: ">Heb. שעטת. There is no similar [word in Scripture]. And Jonathan rendered it: from the steps.</text>
      <text title="from the noise of his chariots: ">Heb. מרעש לרכבו [lit.] from the noise to his chariots.</text>
      <text title="his wheels: ">The wheels of his chariots.</text>
      <text title="fathers did not turn to sons: ">to save them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="to cut off from Tyre and Zidon: ">The Philistines were aiding them against their enemies.</text>
      <text title="the island of Caphtor: ">(Isls in O.F.)</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="has become a waste: ">Heb. נדמתה.</text>
      <text title="will you tear your flesh: ">Will you tear your flesh in mourning and in weeping?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="sword of the Lord: ">Which the Holy One, Blessed be He, brings to the world.</text>
      <text title="rest: ">Heb. הרגעי, an expression of מרגועַ rest.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="48">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Misgab: ">A place name.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="in Heshbon… Madmen: ">These are place names, and according to their names he mentions their retribution.</text>
      <text title="you shall be a waste: ">Heb. תִּדֹּמִי.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="her youths: ">Jonathan [renders]: Her governors, younger than the kings.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="the ascent of Luhith: ">It is a place name, the ascent of a mountain.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="like Aro’er: ">The tower of Aro’er that is made in the desert, and there is no civilization around it except tent dwellers, and a tower standing without an inhabited region appears as ruins. So did Jonathan render it. (See Isaiah 17:2, Commentary Digest.) But Menahem (Machbereth Menahem p. 137) explained כּערוער as the name of a tree of the forest trees.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Give wings to Moab: ">Heb. ציץ. Give wings to Moab. Every appendage that hangs or protrudes from man or beast is called ציץ. Cf.“And it shall be to you for fringes (לציצית) ” (Num. 15: 39);“And He took me by the locks (בציצית) of my head” (Ezek. 8: 3).</text>
      <text title="for she shall fly away: ">Heb. נצא תצא. For with flight and haste you shall go forth into exile, and נָצֹא will be of the conjugation of נוֹצָה, a feather. So did Menahem (Machbereth Menahem p. 151) classify it, and so “Yea, they fled away (נָצוּ) and wandered” (Lam. 4:15). Jonathan renders: Remove the crown from Moab. Give others the crown of Moab.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="the Lord’s work: ">The work of the destruction of Moab, which is the mission of the Omnipresent.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="did not change: ">Heb. נָמָר.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="men to pour: ">Heb. ציעים, those who pour. Cf.“What must be poured out (צֹעֶה) hastened to be opened” (Isa. 51:14). That is the moving of the bowels by pouring.</text>
      <text title="his jars: ">Heb. נבליהם [lit. their jars], the Moabites’ flasks.</text>
      <text title="smash: ">Heb. ינפצו, they shall break. Cf.“How were they regarded as earthen jars (לְנִבְלֵי) (Lam. 4:2). Also,” Every bottle (נֵבֶל) will be filled with wine" (supra 13.12).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="of Chemosh: ">in whom they trusted.</text>
      <text title="of Beth-el: ">The golden calf.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="Lament for them: ">Heb. נדו, an expression of lamentation. Cf.“and do not lament (תָּנוּד) for him.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="ask those who have fled and escaped: ">Ask those who flee and escape from Moab, what transpired, if anyone escaped from being destroyed</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="and judgment has come: ">Retribution has come.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="Make him drunk: ">Give him to drink [the cup of] weakness until he is drunk.</text>
      <text title="he too: ">Just as Israel was derided by him [i.e., Moab].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="you shake your head: ">Heb. תתנודד. You would shake your head and scoff at their destruction. Another interpretation: For because of your words about him, that you would sing about his destruction, you are going to wander (מתנודד) to go out into exile. And so did Jonathan render: Because you spoke many words about them, therefore you shall wander.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="in the sides of the mouth of a pit: ">The place where the water passes under the high embankments of the bank of a wadi, and when the wadi is diminished, the pit is found to be empty, and the dove nests in one of the sides of the pit. And when the wadi increases, it inundates the nest and she wanders from there. So I heard, but Jonathan did not render in that manner, [but:] Be like a dove, that leaves the opening of the dovecote and goes down and rests at the bottom of a pit.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="his wrath, and it is not so: ">His hatred of Israel is not in truth or in justice.</text>
      <text title="his mighty men: ">Heb. בדיו [lit.] his branches.</text>
      <text title="have not dealt properly: ">They did not recompense justly the seed of Abraham, who fought with the kings and saved Lot, their ancestor.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="Kir-heres: ">A city of the land of Moab.</text>
      <text title="they shall moan: ">Moaning like moaning doves.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="From the weeping of Jazar I will weep for you: ">When this prophecy was said, Jazer had already been destroyed, and that was near Moab.</text>
      <text title="I will weep for you: ">I will weep for you, similar to that other weeping [i.e., for Jazer], for you will be destroyed just like [Jazer].</text>
      <text title="O grape vine of Sibmah: ">It was a land of vineyards.</text>
      <text title="your tendrils: ">Since he compared them to a grape vine, he compared their mighty men to the tendrils of the vine.</text>
      <text title="crossed the sea: ">i.e., they went into exile.</text>
      <text title="your dried figs: ">Heb. קיצך, an expression of dried figs, but קִצֵ (51:13), an expression of (קץ), an end, has no ‘yud’ and its ‘tzaddi’ has a ‘dagesh.’</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="shall be taken away: ">Heb. ונאספה, shall be ended that it shall not be seen.</text>
      <text title="one shall not tread: ">grapes with a voice of shouting, “Hedad!” with joy as they were wont to do.</text>
      <text title="The shouting shall be no shouting: ">The shouting that they will cry will not be the first shouting, but the shouting of fleeing the sword.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="O third born heifer: ">Heb. עגלתשלישיה, mighty province.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="because they dealt haughtily: ">יתרתעשה. Because they dealt haughtily, they perished.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="scratches: ">Heb. גדדת.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="39">
      <text title="Wail, “How was she dismayed?”: ">Wail about her and say, “How was she dismayed?”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="40">
      <text title="like an eagle he shall soar: ">[i. e.,] the enemy [shall swoop] upon Moab.</text>
      <text title="shall soar: ">Heb. ידאה, shall fly.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="41">
      <text title="Kerioth: ">Heb. הקריות, the name of the city.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="43">
      <text title="Fright and a pit: ">These are two hard things, one next to the other, for fright causes him to flee, and the pit is ready to fall into. פַּחַת is (fosse in French) a pit.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="45">
      <text title="In the shadow of Heshbon: ">which is high and has a shadow.</text>
      <text title="stood: ">Those who were fleeing [stood] to rest in the shadow since they had no more strength to flee.</text>
      <text title="from the city of Sihon: ">Heb. מבין, from the city of Sihon. Cf.“the city of (בֶּן) Reuben” in Joshua (15:6).</text>
      <text title="and the crown of the head: ">Heb. וקדקד, (estrit in Provencal or estrif in O.F. [to fight]) and Menahem (Machbereth Menahem p. 158) classified it as an expression of a spring (מָקוֹר) and Jonathan rendered: יַקִּירֵי the esteemed ones, an expression of יְקָר, esteem.</text>
      <text title="the tumultuous ones: ">Heb. בני שאון, those who would raise their voice with boasting.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="49">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Has Israel no sons?: ">The ‘beth’ is weak [without a ‘dagesh’], and the ‘heh’ is vowelized with a ‘hataph-pattah,’ which is an expression of wonder [interrogative].</text>
      <text title="Malcam: ">The deity of the children of Ammon is named Malcam, as it is stated: “And to Milcom, the abomination of the children of Ammon” (II Kings 23: 13), an expression of מֶלֶ, a king.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="for Ai has been spoiled: ">Ai, that is near it, [has been spoiled,] and it is of the land of Ammon.</text>
      <text title="O villages of Rabbah: ">Rabbah of the children of Ammon.</text>
      <text title="and mobilize in companies: ">Heb. והתשוטטנה בגדרות. Jonathan renders: ואתהמכוּן בסיעָן, mobilize in companies. He interprets והתשוטטנה as an expression of armies that run to and fro (משוטטים); and גדרות is an expression of sheepcotes full of flocks, and can be interpreted as “and roll in the dung of the sheepcotes,” an expression of contempt. [Onkelos translates:] “And Esau despised” (Gen. 25:34), ושט עשו.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="You boast: ">Heb. תתהללי (vanter in French).</text>
      <text title="about the valleys?: ">That your land is a land of valleys and lack of rainfall is not harmful to it since the sun does not penetrate into it.</text>
      <text title="Your valley is flowing: ">A misfortune of an overabundance of rain shall come upon it until the water will flow in the valley and inundate the roots of the grain So did Menahem [Machbereth Menahem p. 77] explain it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="each man forward: ">Anyone who can hurry and flee.</text>
      <text title="the wanderer: ">The term [לנדד] derives from נע ונד, “a wanderer and an exile” (Gen. 4:14).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="in the south?: ">Edom is in the south of Eretz Israel, as it is stated.“And your south side shall be from the desert of Zin close by the side of Edom” (Num. 34:3).</text>
      <text title="from the sons: ">Heb. מבנים, from this generation.</text>
      <text title="has spoiled: ">Heb. נסרחה.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="Clear out!: ">Heb. הפנו. Vacate this place. This is an expression of “And they shall clear out (וּפְּנוּ) the house” (Lev. 14:36).</text>
      <text title="Dwell deep: ">to hide in the secret valleys. נֻסוּ הָפְנוּ הֶעְמִקוּ are all in the imperative form.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="If vintagers have come upon you, etc.: ">I have exposed Esau, etc. I have heard tidings, etc. On this order, Obadiah prophesied concerning Edom, but since one watchword is passed to many prophets, but no two prophets prophesy under the same watchword, they differ in several words.</text>
      <text title="will they not leave over gleaning grapes?: ">This is the interrogative. Yet the spoilers who came upon you left over nothing for you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="I exposed: ">Heb. חשפתי, uncovered. Cf.“the exposure (מַחְשֹף) of the white” (Gen. 30:37). And you delivered the survivors of Israel in order that no one remain of them, as it is stated: “Neither should you have delivered his survivors” (Obadiah 1:14).</text>
      <text title="and he could not hide: ">He will seek to hide but will be unable.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="Leave your orphans: ">whom you have orphaned of Israel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="those who do not deserve to drink: ">For they were not brothers to Israel, and if they harmed them, they do not deserve the death sentence like you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="that Bozrah shall become desolation, reproach, waste, and a curse: ">Bozrah was one of the cities of Moab, but because it raised up a king for Edom, as the matter is stated, “And Jobab the son of Zerah from Bozrah” (Gen. 36:33), it will suffer with them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="I have made you small: ">For they have no king who is the son of a king. It was not their custom to set up a king the son of a king.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="Your hastiness: ">Heb. תפלצתך, an expression of haste, for you hurried and were hasty to arouse your hatred for your brother. And there are some who translate this as an expression of fright (פַּלָצוּת), and there are some who translate it as an expression of an image (מפלצת).</text>
      <text title="has enticed you: ">to harm them.</text>
      <text title="you who dwell: ">Heb. שכני, like שׁוֹכֵן.</text>
      <text title="who hold: ">תפשי, like תּופֵשׂ, and the ‘yud’ is superfluous in it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="as a lion: ">that ascends from the heights of the Jordan, which is a place frequented by lions, as Jonathan renders, so shall the enemy ascend upon the strong dwelling place.</text>
      <text title="for I will bring the moment: ">Heb. ארגיעה.</text>
      <text title="I will hasten him away from her: ">Suddenly and successfully he shall destroy her and return in a brief movement to his place. But I say that אריצנוּ מעליה means: I will hasten him over her, that he shall overpower her and be over her. Cf.“Above (ממעל) the expanse” (Gen. 1:7);“Above (ממעל) for Him” (Isa. 6: 2);“Over (מֵעַל) his garments” (I Sam. 17:39).</text>
      <text title="and he who is chosen: ">He whom I have chosen to wreak My vengeance, I will appoint over her. 7</text>
      <text title="and who will appoint Me a time: ">For bartle, to wage war with Me?</text>
      <text title="a shepherd: ">A king.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="if… not: ">An expression of ‘indeed.’</text>
      <text title="drag them: ">Heb. יסחבום.</text>
      <text title="the young of the flock: ">The despised of the nations, and our Rabbis [Yoma 10] expounded that it refers to Persia, who was the youngest of Japheth’s sons.</text>
      <text title="make desolate: ">Heb. ישים, an expression of desolation (שממה).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="Hamath and Arpad are shamed: ">[Hamath and Arpad,] cities of Aram, [are shamed,] for they heard bad news concerning Damascus, which is the head of Aram, as it is stated.“For the head of Aram is Damascus” (Isa. 7:8). Therefore, they melted.</text>
      <text title="there is worry in the sea: ">He compares her worry to the worry of the sea, which cannot be quiet. Every instance of דאגה, worry, is an expression of fear.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="Damascus become feeble: ">Her hands have become too feeble to wage war.</text>
      <text title="trembling: ">Heb. רֶטֶט.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="“How was… not fortified”: ">It was not filled with earth around its wall to strengthen the wall. Cf.“And they fortified (ויעזבוּ) Jerusalem up to the wall” (Neh. 3:8). It can also be interpreted: Why was it not forsaken by this evil, that the evil should not come upon it?</text>
      <text title="the city of my joy: ">So shall her king mourn over her.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="Therefore: ">This is an expression of an oath.</text>
      <text title="shall be destroyed: ">Heb. ידמו, [lit. shall be silent,] shall be destroyed, but it does not deviate from being an expression of silence, for in every ruined city, no voice is heard.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="Concerning Kedar: ">They were desert dwellers, with neither wall nor city.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="terror: ">Heb. מגור (amassment in French). Another explanation: an expression of fear.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="has taken counsel against you: ">And what was that counsel?“Rise and go up to a peaceful nation.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="they dwell alone: ">Confidently alone. They need not gather and dwell among people, for they fear not that an enemy will come upon them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="cast to the ends: ">Separated from one end to the other end of the directions.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="the bow of Elam: ">The might of Elam (other editions: the strength of Elam).</text>
      <text title="the chief of their might: ">The best of their might.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="38">
      <text title="And I will place My throne: ">My siege (מָצוֹר).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="50">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="and raise a standard: ">(Perche in French.) That is a signal for gathering.</text>
      <text title="Bel… Merodach: ">The names of the Babylonian deities.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="a nation… from the north: ">[viz.] Persia and Media.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="are directed hitherward: ">Toward this place, Jerusalem, they shall direct their faces when Babylon will be destroyed and they will leave it with the sanction of Cyrus, king of Persia.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="their shepherds caused them to stray: ">Their kings caused them to stray away from Me.</text>
      <text title="mountains… led them astray: ">To the mountains, to the idol worship that was on the mountains. שׁוֹבְבוּם (esvayent in O.F.), led astray, their kings led them astray. And Jonathan rendered: their governors plundered them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="and the hope of their forefathers: ">Jonathan renders: וְסִבּוּר אֲבָהָתְהוֹן, and the hope of their forefathers.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="Wander out of Babylon: ">Accordingly, go out of there.</text>
      <text title="like the he goats before the flocks: ">It is customary for the he-goats to go before the flock, at the head of the she-goats.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="and they shall set themselves in array against her: ">They shall array themselves in battle against her.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="O spoilers of My heritage: ">Heb. שֹּׁסֵי.</text>
      <text title="as you become fat: ">Heb. תפושו, an expression of fat.</text>
      <text title="a threshing heifer: ">Heb. דשא, a heifer that threshes the grain and eats constantly.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="Your mother: ">Your nation.</text>
      <text title="the end of the nations: ">Although your beginning was great, your end will be a desert.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="shoot at her: ">Heb. ידו, cast stones at her. Cf.“And they cast (וידוּ) stones at me” (Lam. 3:53).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="she gave her hand: ">like a person who has no strength and stretches forth his hand to whomever he sees, to beg mercy and aid. Cf. We gave our hand to Egypt" (Lam. 5:6).</text>
      <text title="her foundations have fallen: ">Heb. אשיותיה. The strength of her foundations. Cf.“And the foundations (וְאֻשַּׁיָא) shall be fastened” (Ezra 4:12). And in the language of the Mishnah: Those who dig for foundations (לְאֻשִׁין) [Baba Kamma 50a]. Cf.“And strengthen yourselves (והתאוששוּ)” (Isa. 46:8), equivalent to והתחזקוּ, and strengthen yourselves.</text>
      <text title="as she did: ">to the city of the Lord.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="Cut off a sower: ">Destroy a king from Babylon and one who grasps a sword in time of slaughter.</text>
      <text title="First… devoured him: ">For he exiled the Ten Tribes.</text>
      <text title="broke his bones: ">He broke his bones, for he finished the leftovers, Judah and Benjamin. עִצְמוֹ (desossa in French), [broke the bones].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="and he shall pasture in the Carmel: ">An expression of pasture.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="the rebellious land: ">Heb. מרתים, which rebelled against Me and provoked Me.</text>
      <text title="Pekod: ">The name of a province. Cf.“Pekod and Shoa and Koa” (Ezekiel 23:23). Jonathan renders [them as] names of provinces.</text>
      <text title="and do according to all that I have commanded you: ">You, Cyrus, through Isaiah the prophet.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="the hammer of the whole earth: ">which would shatter and crush everyone.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="I laid a snare for you: ">Heb. יקשתי, an expression of a snare (מוֹקֵש).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="Come against her from her border: ">From the end of the city, commence upon her, that she not know, and she will be taken suddenly.</text>
      <text title="open her gates: ">Jonathan renders: אִבּוּלָהָא, her gates, but it has no similar instance [in Scripture]. Menahem (Machbereth p. 14) classifies it as an expression of a manger.</text>
      <text title="thresh her: ">Heb. סלוה.</text>
      <text title="stacks: ">Granaries.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="all her bulls: ">Her princes. So is the custom of the prophets to compare the princes to mighty bulls and to he-goats.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="Gather archers against Babylon: ">Heb. השמיעו, an expression similar to: “And Saul called the people together (וַיְשַׁמַע) ” (I Sam. 15:4). Call out that archers assemble against Babylon. Cf.“His archers (רַבָּיו) surround me” (Job 16:13).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="Therefore: ">An expression of an oath.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="in order to give rest to the earth: ">When Babylon falls, there will be rest and peace for all.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="upon the imposters: ">Heb. הבדים, to her diviners.</text>
      <text title="and they shall become foolish: ">with their divining. Similar to this is: “Who frustrates the signs of imposters” (Isa. 44:25), and so did Jonathan render. They are called בּדים because they fabricate (בּוֹדִים) and say false things.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="the allies: ">Heb. הערב. Jonathan renders: סוּמְכותא (garantie in French).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="38">
      <text title="and they are mad upon things of horror: ">Heb. יתהללו, they shall become mad. Another interpretation: (Pour vanter in French) in order to boast. And so did Jonathan render: משתבּחין, they boast, [i.e.,] with the gods of the giants that they had.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="39">
      <text title="martens… with cats: ">Jonathan [renders]: And martens shall meet cats. [These are] species of animals found in ruins.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="44">
      <text title="Behold, as a lion: ">that ascends from the heights of the Jordan, so will the spoiler come to the strong dwelling. So did Jonathan paraphrase: Behold a king with his camp shall ascend upon them like a lion that ascends from the height of the Jordan. We learn that the height of the Jordan is a place of lions. Also, in this manner Jonathan renders: “How will you do in the heights of the Jordan” (12:5): Against the wild beasts of the heights of the Jordan.</text>
      <text title="when I bring the moment: ">Heb. ארגיעה, when I bring the time.</text>
      <text title="over her: ">Heb. מעליה.</text>
      <text title="and who will appoint Me a time: ">for war?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="45">
      <text title="the young of the flock: ">Persia, the youngest of the sons of Japheth.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="51">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Leb-kamai: ">Casdim (Chaldeans) according to cypher of ‘At- bash’ (א -תב ש).</text>
      <text title="the desire of a destroyer: ">The desire of the king of Persia and Media, who is a destroyer. Heb. רוּחַ (talent in O.F.).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="and they shall scatter her: ">Heb. וְזֵרוּהָ.</text>
      <text title="and empty her land: ">Heb. וִיבֹקְקוּ.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="To… the archer shall bend: ">This is an elliptical verse. [The meaning is:] To wherever I say, there the archer shall bend his bow.</text>
      <text title="and he shall not be healed with his coat of mail: ">Heb. יִתְעַל וְאַל.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="For Israel is not widowed: ">He has not forgotten him to avenge him.</text>
      <text title="for their land: ">of the Chaldeans.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="Flee: ">Israel, from within Babylon.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="a golden cup: ">Until now, Babylon was [a golden cup] in the Lord’s hand with which to intoxicate the whole earth with the wine of wrath.</text>
      <text title="therefore, nations are mad: ">They have become drunk and have become mad.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="her judgment has touched the sky: ">Their retribution has reached high up to the sky.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="“The Lord has brought forth our merits”: ">We have been remembered by Him favorably, and the merits of our forefathers have come before Him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="Polish: ">Heb. הברו, an expression of cleaning.</text>
      <text title="the quivers: ">Heb. השלטים, the quivers into which the arrows are placed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="for the Lord both planned: ">already many days.</text>
      <text title="and did: ">His plan. It is customary for Scripture to speak with the word גַם twice, one after the other, and following the latter, comes the former.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="your end has come: ">Heb. קצך, your end.</text>
      <text title="the measure of your violence: ">Heb. אַמַתבִּצְעֵ, the measure of your violence. Another explanation: אַמַתבִּצְעֵ means: the measure of your end. Cf.“When… completes (יִבַצַע)” (Isa. 10:12).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="by Himself: ">(en soi meme in French.)</text>
      <text title="indeed: ">Heb. כי אם, an expression of ‘in truth.’</text>
      <text title="I have… filled you with men: ">I will fill you with camps of peoples, as many as locusts.</text>
      <text title="and they shall raise a battle-cry against you: ">And they shall raise their voice against you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="Every man is brutish: ">[i.e.,] whoever makes a graven image for a god.</text>
      <text title="molten images: ">[As translated], an expression [denoting] molten images.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="at the time of their visitation: ">When the Holy One, blessed be He, visits retribution upon them and upon their worshippers.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="and the tribe of His inheritance: ">Jacob mentioned above at the beginning of the verse.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="for Me a shatterer: ">Heb. מפץ. Until now, I have appointed you as a destroyer and a shatterer of the nations upon whom I decreed exile.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="And I will recompense Babylon: ">After all this, when I complete My vengeance upon the nations through him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="prepare: ">Heb. קַדְשוֹ.</text>
      <text title="a marshal: ">Heb. טפסר, an expression of an army [or an expression of a lord].</text>
      <text title="bristling: ">Heb. סמר. (Herisse in French), covered with spikes. Cf.“It made the hair of my flesh stand up like spikes (תְּסַּמֵר)” (Job 4:15).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="and was in pain: ">Heb. ותחל, an expression of חַלְחָלָה pain.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="failed: ">Heb. נשתה, [lit.] jumped. Compare “the hip sinew (הנשה)” (Gen. 33:32), so called because it jumped [was dislocated] from its place.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="is like a granary at the time it is threshed: ">Behold, now it is full, like a granary at the time they have threshed its grain, when it is full of wheat.</text>
      <text title="A little more time: ">and she shall he emptied and shall resemble a granary at the time of the beginning of the harvest, when it is empty.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="the plundering done me and my food: ">The cry of violence done me and my food, for they have eaten my food.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="38">
      <text title="they growl: ">Heb. נערו, an expression of a braying (נוֹעֵר) donkey.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="39">
      <text title="in their heat, I will place their wine feasts: ">I will intend that their wine feasts shall be in the hot season so that they become drunk.</text>
      <text title="in order that they become joyful and sleep: ">Heb. וישנו, and sleep soundly.</text>
      <text title="a perpetual sleep: ">Heb. שנתעולם, a perpetual sleep, and so it happened to them; out of their wine feast and drunkenness they were destroyed and slain, and the city was captured, as it is written in Daniel (5:2): “Belshazzar said while he tasted the wine, etc.” ; (5: 4), “They drank wine, etc.” ; (5:30), “On that night, Belshazzar, the king of the Chaldeans, was slain” ; (6:1), “And Darius the Mede received the kingship.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="40">
      <text title="like lambs: ">Heb. כברים, lambs (and Jonathan renders:) like bulls.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="41">
      <text title="Sheshach: ">Babylon in the ‘At- bash’ (א -תב ש), cipher.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="42">
      <text title="The sea has ascended upon Babylon: ">A huge army, like the waters of [the sea].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="44">
      <text title="on Bel: ">On the deity of Babylon.</text>
      <text title="what he has swallowed: ">That all the inhabitants of the land were humbled under him.</text>
      <text title="shall no longer stream: ">Heb. יהרו, and shall not gather. Cf.“And all the nations shall stream (ונהרוּ) to it” (Isa. 2:2). Like the waters of the river, all of which go to the sea.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="46">
      <text title="because of the rumor that is heard in the land: ">This rumor concerning Belshazzar that he was slain.</text>
      <text title="for a rumor shall come one year: ">In that very year there will come a rumor that Babylon has been destroyed by itself from heaven as it is stated: “And Babylon, the beauty of the kingdoms the glory of the pride of the Chaldee, shall be like God’s overturning of Sodom and Gemorrah” (Isa. 13: 19).</text>
      <text title="and after it in a year: ">[In] the second [year].</text>
      <text title="a rumor: ">that is good for you [viz.] “So said Cyrus, the king of Persia…, Whoever among you of all His people…” (Ezra 1:2f).</text>
      <text title="and one ruler upon another ruler: ">Darius the Mede reigned one year, and in the second year Cyrus the Persian.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="49">
      <text title="As Babylon: ">was [a cause] for the slain of Israel to fall therein.</text>
      <text title="so in Babylon: ">shall fall the slain of all her land.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="50">
      <text title="Fugitives from the sword: ">Israel, who was exiled into her midst, who escaped the sword of Nebuzaradan.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="51">
      <text title="for we have heard reproach: ">For the Chaldeans were saying and reproaching us, saying, “The hand of our god is exalted for we have destroyed His house.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="52">
      <text title="the mortally wounded shall groan: ">Heb. יאנק. The mortally wounded shall cry. When they kill a person with an arrow or with a spear, and he groans when they remove the spear, that is אנקה.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="53">
      <text title="and should she fortify: ">Heb. תבצר, an expression of a strong fortress.</text>
      <text title="from Me shall spoilers come upon her: ">From Me, from the heavens that are higher than she, shall the spoilers come upon her.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="55">
      <text title="the stirring of their voice was uttered: ">The sound of their cry is heard.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="58">
      <text title="shall be overthrown: ">Heb. תתערער, an expression of digging. An expression like “Dig under it, dig under it (עָרוּ), until its foundation” (Psalms 137:7).</text>
      <text title="for much futility: ">For much futility which it will bring upon them.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="52">
  </chapter>
</book>