<book>
  <chapter id="1">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Now it came to pass in the days of Ahasuerus: ">He was the king of Persia who reigned instead of Cyrus at the end of the seventy years of the Babylonian exile.</text>
      <text title="he was the Ahasuerus: ">He was equally wicked from beginning to end.</text>
      <text title="who reigned: ">He reigned on his own, and was not of royal seed.</text>
      <text title="from Hodu to Cush, etc.: ">He reigned over one hundred twenty-seven provinces as he reigned from Hodu to Cush, which are situated alongside one another, and so [we explain] (I Kings 5:4): “For he had dominion over all [the inhabitants of] this side of the river, from Tiphsah even to Gaza,” meaning that he had dominion over all the inhabitants of this side of the river, just as he had dominion from Tiphsah to Gaza.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="when King Ahasuerus sat, etc.: ">when the kingdom was firmly established in his hand. Our Sages, however, explained it differently in Tractate Megillah (11b).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="the nobles: ">Heb. הַפַּרְתְּמִים, governors in Persian.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="many days: ">He made a banquet for them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="the garden: ">a place where vegetables are sown.</text>
      <text title="orchard: ">where trees are planted.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="white, fine cotton, and blue: ">He spread out various types of colored garments for them for spreads.</text>
      <text title="embroidered with cords of linen and purple: ">embroidered with threads of linen and purple; he spread these out for them on rods of silver and on columns of marble.</text>
      <text title="couches of gold and silver: ">he set [them] up to sit upon for the feast.</text>
      <text title="on a pavement of: ">floors of green and white, etc. Our Sages identified them as kinds of precious stones, and according to the apparent meaning of the verse, these were their names.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And they gave them to drink in golden vessels: ">Heb., like וּלְהַשְּׁקוֹת, and to give to drink.</text>
      <text title="and the vessels differed from one another: ">Heb. שּׁוֹנִים, different from each other, and likewise, (below 3:8) “and their laws differ (שּׁנוֹת),” and our Sages expounded what they expounded.</text>
      <text title="and royal wine was plentiful: ">It was abundant; and our Sages said that he gave each one to drink wine that was older than he.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="according to the law: ">Because there are feasts in which they coerce those seated to drink [the contents] of a large vessel, and some can drink it only with difficulty, but here, no one coerced [anyone].</text>
      <text title="ordained: ">Heb. יִסַד, an expression referring to a foundation (יְסוֹד); i.e., so he instituted and ordained.</text>
      <text title="upon every steward of his house: ">upon all the stewards of the feast: the chief baker, the chief butcher, and the chief butler.</text>
      <text title="to do according to every man’s wish: ">Heb. אִישּׁ וָאִישּׁ, lit. man and man, for each one his desire.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="On the seventh day: ">Our Rabbis said that it was the Sabbath.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="But Queen Vashti refused: ">Our Rabbis said (Meg. 12b): Because leprosy broke out on her, in order that she should refuse and be killed. Because she would force Jewish girls to undress, and work on the Sabbath, it was decreed that she should be stripped naked on the Sabbath.</text>
      <text title="became very wroth: ">because she sent him shameful words.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="for so was the king’s custom: ">For it was the king’s custom in every judgment to present the matter before all who knew law and judgment.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="And the nearest to him: ">to present his words before them were the following: Carshena, Shethar, etc.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="According to the law what [is there] to do: ">This refers back to “And the king said to the wise men.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="has… done wrong: ">Heb. עָוְתֳה, an expression of iniquity (עָוֹן).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="For the word of the queen will spread to all the women: ">that she disgraced the king- [this will cause] all the women to despise their husbands as well.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="the princesses of Persia and Media, etc. will say: ">this word to all the princes; this is an ellipsis.</text>
      <text title="and much contempt and wrath: ">And in this matter, there is much contempt and wrath.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="a royal edict: ">a royal edict of revenge, i.e., that he commanded to execute her.</text>
      <text title="and let it be inscribed in the laws of Persia and Media: ">in the books of the statutes and the customs of the kingdom.</text>
      <text title="and let it not be revoked: ">this statute from among them; this should be a statute and a law for anyone who shows contempt for her husband.</text>
      <text title="that Vashti did not come: ">and therefore, she was executed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="and speak according to the language of his nationality: ">He can compel his wife to learn his language if her native tongue is different.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="2">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="he remembered Vashti: ">her beauty, and he became sad.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And let the king appoint commissioners: ">since each commissioner is familiar with the beautiful women in his province.</text>
      <text title="their ointments: ">These are things that cleanse, like (Lev. 6:21): “it shall be scoured (וּמֹרַק) and rinsed.” [This includes] perfumed oil, various ingredients and spices that cleanse and smoothen the skin.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="a Judean man: ">because he was exiled with the exile of Judah; all those who were exiled with the kings of Judah were called יְהוּדִים [Judeans, Jews] among the nations, even if they were from another tribe.</text>
      <text title="a Benjamite: ">He was from Benjamin. That is the simple meaning, but our Sages explained what they explained.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="for a daughter: ">Heb. לְבַת. Our Sages explained: לבית, for a house, meaning for a wife.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="and he hastened her ointments: ">He was more diligent and quicker with bringing her [ointments] than those of all of them.</text>
      <text title="fitting to give to her: ">to serve her, and so they would do for all of them; and our Sages explained what they explained.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="not to reveal: ">so that they should say that she was from an ignoble family and dismiss her, for if they knew that she was of the family of King Saul, they would detain her.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="and what would be done to her: ">He was one of two righteous men to whom a hint of salvation was given: David and Mordecai. David-as it is said (I Sam. 17:36): “Both the lion and the bear has your bondsman smote.” He said [to himself], “This incident happened to me only to teach me to have faith that I can battle with this one [Goliath].” Likewise, Mordecai said [to himself], “The only reason that this righteous woman was taken to the bed of a gentile was because she is destined to arise and save Israel.” He therefore went around to find out what would be her fate.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="turn: ">Heb. תֹּר, her time.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="whatever she would request: ">any entertainment or types of music.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="to the second house of the women: ">Heb. שֵּׁנִי [Like the usual form] הַשֵּׁנִי.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="in the tenth month: ">the cold season, when one body enjoys [the warmth of] another body. The Holy One, blessed be He, designated that cold season in order to endear her to him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <title>more than all the women: </title>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="and he granted a release: ">In her honor, he released them from the tax that was [levied] upon them.</text>
      <text title="and gave gifts: ">He sent them gifts, and everything was in order to entice her, perhaps she would tell her nationality. But nevertheless-Esther would not tell.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="Esther would not tell her lineage: ">because Mordecai was sitting in the king’s gate; he was encouraging her and hinting to her about it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="to lay a hand: ">to give him poison to drink.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="And the matter became known to Mordecai: ">For they were discussing their affairs before him in the Tarsean language, and they did not know that Mordecai was familiar with seventy languages, for he was one of those who sat in the Chamber of Hewn Stone.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="and it was written in the diary: ">the favor that Mordecai did for the king.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="3">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="After these events: ">this remedy was created to be a salvation for Israel.</text>
      <text title="King Ahasuerus promoted Haman: ">For the Holy One, blessed be He, creates a remedy for Israel’s blow before He brings the blow upon them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="would kneel and prostrate themselves: ">Because he made himself a god; therefore “Mordecai would neither kneel nor prostrate himself.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="whether Mordecai’s words would stand up: ">[i.e., the words of Mordecai,] who said that he would never prostrate himself because he was a Jew, and was warned against idolatry.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="one cast the pur: ">Whoever cast it, cast it, and the verse does not specify who. This is an elliptical verse.</text>
      <text title="that is the lot: ">Scripture explains: and what is the pur? That is the lot. He cast lots [to determine] in which month he would succeed.</text>
      <text title="from day to day: ">in which day of the month he would succeed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="and… the king’s laws: ">to give taxes for the king’s work.</text>
      <text title="it is of no use: ">There is no apprehension; there is no profit.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="let it be written to destroy them: ">Let letters be written to be sent to the governors of the provinces to destroy them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="And the king took his ring off: ">This represents the granting of any great matter that is requested of the king; the one who has the ring on his hand is the ruler over all the king’s affairs.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="And letters shall be sent: ">Heb. וְנִשְּׁלוֹחַ. And letters shall be sent, étre tramis in 0. Fr., to be sent, which is of the [same grammatical] structure as (Jud. 11:25): “did he ever fight? (נִלְחוֹם נִלְחַם) ” ; (I Sam. 2:27): “Did I appear? (נִגְלֹה נִגְלֵיתִי) (Hos. 10:15): ” was silenced (נִדְמֹה נִדְמָה)."</text>
      <text title="on the thirteenth day of the twelfth month: ">On the thirteenth day of that month, which is the twelfth month of the year.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="The copy of the writ: ">Heb. פַּתְשֶּׁגֶן, an Aramaism, the account of the writ, deresmant in Old French, text, contents, account.</text>
      <text title="for an edict to be given: ">The command of the writ was that it proclaimed that the decree of the king should be issued as a statute.</text>
      <text title="published to all the peoples: ">This matter.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="and the edict was given in Shushan the capital: ">the place where the king was situated; there the statute was given on that day, to be ready for the thirteenth day of the month of Adar. Therefore</text>
      <text title="and the city of Shushan was perturbed: ">[i.e] the Jews therein.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="4">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And Mordecai knew all that had transpired: ">The Master of Dreams told him that the celestial beings had concurred about it, because they had prostrated themselves to an image in the days of Nebuchadnezzar and because they had enjoyed Ahasuerus’s feast.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="for one may not enter: ">It is improper to enter the king’s gate dressed in sackcloth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="the king’s orders and his edict: ">When the couriers carrying the letters passed, the edict was given in the city.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="the full account of the silver: ">the explanation of the silver.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="Do not imagine to yourself: ">Heb. אַל תְּדַמִי, do not think, like (Num. 33:56) “And it will be, that which I thought (דִמִיתִי).” Do not imagine to yourself; do not think to escape in the king’s palace on the day of the massacre; because you do not wish to imperil yourself now to come to the king without permission.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="and who knows whether at a time like this: ">And who knows whether the king will desire you next year, which is the time of the massacre.</text>
      <text title="at a time like this: ">For he was presently in Nisan, and the time of the massacre was in Adar of the next year.</text>
      <text title="you will attain the kingdom: ">if you will attain the greatness which you now enjoy.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="contrary to the law: ">for it is contrary to the law for one who is not summoned to enter. And the Midrash Aggadah [explains]: contrary to the law, for until now, I was coerced [to cohabit with him], but now [I will do so] willingly.</text>
      <text title="and if I perish, I perish: ">And just as I have begun to go to destruction [by appearing before Ahasuerus without being summoned], I will go and die. And the Midrash Aggadah (ad loc.) [explains]: As I am lost to my father’s house, so will I be lost to you, for from now on, that I am submitting willingly to a heathen, I will be forbidden to you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="So Mordecai passed: ">i.e., he transgressed the law by fasting on the first festive day of Passover, for he fasted on the fourteenth, the fifteenth, and the sixteenth, since the letters were written on the thirteenth day.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="5">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="regally: ">regal clothing. But our Sages said (Meg. 15a) that divine inspiration enwrapped her, as it is said (I Chron. 12:18): “And a spirit enwrapped Amasai.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="Even to half the kingdom: ">A thing that is in the middle and at the halfway mark of the kingdom. That is the Temple, which they started to build in the days of Cyrus, and he reneged and commanded to discontinue the work, and Ahasuerus, who succeeded him, also discontinued the work. The simple meaning of the verse is: Even if you request half the kingdom from me, I will give it to you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="let the king and Haman come: ">Our Sages stated many reasons for the matter. What did Esther see (i.e., what motivated her) to invite Haman? In order to make the king and the princes jealous of him, that the king should think that he desired her and kill him, and many other reasons.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="to the banquet: ">Heb. (הַמִשְּׁתֶּה) lit. drinking feast. Every banquet is called (מִשְּׁתֶּה) on account of the wine, which is the principal feature.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="and tomorrow I will do the king’s bidding: ">that which you requested of me all these days, i.e., to reveal my nationality and my lineage to you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="restrained himself: ">He strengthened himself to control his anger because he was afraid to take revenge without the sanction of the king. וַיִתְאַפַּק is eseretint in Old French, and he controlled himself.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="is worth nothing to me: ">I do not care for all the honor that I have.</text>
      <text title="every time, etc.: ">Our Sages said that he [Mordecai] would show him a deed that he [Haman] had sold himself [to Mordecai] as a slave because he lacked food when Mordecai and Haman were appointed heads of troops in a war.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="6">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="the king’s sleep was disturbed: ">It was a miracle. And some say that he took to heart that Esther had invited Haman; perhaps she had set her eyes upon him, and he would assassinate him.</text>
      <text title="to bring the book of the records: ">It is customary for kings that when their sleep is disturbed, parables and lectures are recited to them until their sleep is restored. Our Rabbis, however, explained that since he took to heart [the matter of] Haman and Esther, he said [to himself], “It is impossible that none of my friends should know their plan and divulge it to me.” He [thought] again and said [to himself], “Perhaps someone did me a favor, and I did not reward him and they don’t care about me anymore.” Therefore, “he ordered to bring the book of the records.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="And let the raiment and the horse: ">But he did not mention the crown, for he saw that the king became jealous because he said that they should place the crown on a person’s head.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And Mordecai returned: ">to his sackcloth and to his fasting.</text>
      <text title="mourning and with his head covered: ">Our Sages explained the matter in Tractate Megillah (ad loc.).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="before whom you have begun to fall, etc.: ">She said, “This nation has been compared to the stars and to the dust. When they descend, they descend to the dust, and when they ascend, they ascend to the sky and the stars.”</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="7">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="may my life be given me: ">that I should not be slain on the thirteenth of Adar, for you have issued an edict of massacre upon my people and my kindred.</text>
      <text title="and my people: ">shall be given me in my request, that they should not be slain. Now if you ask, “What does it concern you?” (below 8:6): “For how can I see, etc. ?”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="for the adversary has no consideration for the king’s loss: ">He does not care for the king’s loss, for if he sought your benefit, he should have said, “Sell them for slaves and bondswomen and receive the money, or keep them to be your slaves, they and their descendants.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="And King Ahasuerus said, and he said to Queen Esther: ">Wherever it says, “And he said, and he said,” twice, it is to be expounded upon, and the midrashic interpretation of this is: Originally, he would speak to her by messenger, but now that he knew that she was of a royal family, he spoke to her personally.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="was determined: ">the evil, the hatred, and the vengeance were decided.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="and Haman was falling: ">The angel pushed him.</text>
      <text title="On the couch upon which Esther was: ">Their custom was to sit at a meal [leaning] on their sides on couches, as is stated in the beginning of the Book (1:6): “couches of gold and silver” for those who participated in the banquet.</text>
      <text title="Will you even force: ">Heb. הֲגַם. This is an expression of wonder. לְכְבּוֹשּׁ [denotes] to subdue with force, like (Num. 32:22): “and the land is conquered (וְנִכְבְּשָּׁה).”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Also, behold the gallows: ">He also committed another evil, that he prepared the gallows to hang the king’s friend, who saved the king from poison.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="8">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="what he was to her: ">how he was related to her.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="to avert the harm of Haman: ">that his evil plan should not be realized.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="Behold the house of Haman, etc.: ">And from now on everyone will see that I desire you, and whatever you say, everyone will believe that it comes from me; therefore, you do not have to rescind them, but write other letters as you see fit.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="cannot be rescinded: ">It is not fitting to rescind it and to invalidate the king’s writ.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="according to its script: ">with its characters.</text>
      <text title="according to its tongue: ">the spoken language.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="by the couriers: ">the horsemen, whom the king commanded to hasten (lit. to run).</text>
      <text title="the camels: ">Heb. הָאֲחַשְּׁתְּרָנִים. a type of camel that runs swiftly.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="and to take their spoils for plunder: ">as was written in the first [letters], but they “ -upon the spoils they did not lay their hands,” for they showed everyone that it was not done for the sake of money.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="The copy: ">an explicit letter.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="hastened: ">They hastened them to act swiftly, because they had no time, since they had to get ahead of the first couriers to overtake them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="and a wrap of linen: ">Heb. וְתַכְרִיך בּוּץ, a wrap of linen, a shawl in which to enwrap oneself.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="became Jews: ">מִתְיַהֲדִים, became proselytes.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="9">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="and those that conduct the king’s affairs: ">those who were appointed to conduct the king’s affairs.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="The ten sons of Haman: ">I saw in Seder Olam (ch. 29): These are the ten who wrote a [false] accusation against Judea and Jerusalem, as it is written in the Book of Ezra (4:6): “And in the reign of Ahasuerus, at the beginning of his reign, they wrote an accusation against the dwellers of Judea and Jerusalem.” Now what was the accusation? To stop those who ascended from the exile during the days of Cyrus, who had commenced to build the Temple, and the Cutheans slandered them and stopped them, and when Cyrus died, and Ahasuerus reigned, and Haman was promoted, he feared that those in Jerusalem would engage in the construction, and they sent in the name of Ahasuerus to the princes of the other side of the river to stop them.</text>
      <text title="but on the spoil they did not lay their hands: ">so that the king should not cast an envious eye on their money.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="and let them hang Haman’s ten sons on the gallows: ">those who were slain.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="and a decree was given: ">a statute was decreed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="the… villagers: ">who do not dwell in walled cities, [celebrate] on the fourteenth, and those who dwell in walled cities [celebrate] on the fifteenth, like Shushan, and [these cities] must be surrounded [by walls] since the days of Joshua the son of Nun. So did our Sages expound and learn.</text>
      <text title="and… sending: ">Heb. וּמִשְּׁלֹחַ. This is a noun, like מִשְּׁמָר, watch, מִשְּׁמָע hearing. Therefore, the “shin” is vowelized soft (without a “dagesh”).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="And Mordecai inscribed: ">this scroll, as it is. [i.e., in its present state.]</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="For Haman the son of Hammedatha, the Agagite: ">devised to terrify them and destroy them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="And when she came: ">[when] Esther [came] to the king to beseech him.</text>
      <text title="he commanded through letters: ">The king stated orally and commanded to write letters that his evil device return upon his own head.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="therefore, because of all the words of this letter: ">these days were established, and therefore it was written for future generations to know.</text>
      <text title="and what they saw: ">those who did these deeds, that they did them.</text>
      <text title="and what happened to them: ">What did Ahasuerus see that he used the sacred vessels, and what happened to them? That Satan came and danced among them and slew Vashti. And what did Haman see that he became envious of Mordecai, and what happened to him? They hanged him and his sons. And what did Mordecai see that he did not kneel or prostrate himself, and what did Esther see that she invited Haman?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="who join them: ">proselytes who were destined to convert.</text>
      <text title="according to their script: ">that the Scroll [of Esther] should be written in the Ashuri script.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="remembered: ">with the reading of the Scroll [of Esther].</text>
      <text title="and celebrated: ">feasting and rejoicing and a festive day, to give portions [of food to friends] and gifts [to the poor].</text>
      <text title="every family: ">gather together and feast and drink together, and so they took upon themselves that the Purim days would not be revoked.</text>
      <text title="shall not cease: ">Heb. לֹא יָסוּף. This is the Aramaic translation of יִתֹּם, will end, for the Targum of (Deut. 2:14) “ עַד תֹּם” is עַד דְסַף, until it finished, and it is impossible to say that it is derived from the same root as (Gen. 19:15): “lest you perish (תִּסָפֶה) ,” or from the same root as (I Sam. 27:1): “Now I shall perish (אֶסָפֶה) one day,” for if that were so, Scripture should have written: לֹא יִסָפֶה מִזַרְעָם.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="all [acts of] power: ">the power of the miracle of Ahasuerus, of Alaman, of Mordecai, and of Esther.</text>
      <text title="the second: ">In the second year they again sent letters that they should celebrate Purim.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="Now Esther’s order confirmed, etc.: ">Esther requested of the sages of the generation to commemorate her and to write this book with the rest of the Holy Writings, and that is the meaning of “and it was inscribed in the book.”</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="10">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="and accepted by most of his brethren: ">but not by all his brethren, for part of the Sanhedrin disassociated from him when he became close to the government and neglected his studies.</text>
      <text title="to all their seed: ">This refers back to “all his people,” to all the seed of his people.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
</book>