<book>
  <chapter id="1">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Now it came to pass in the days when the judges judged: ">Before King Saul reigned, when the generations were governed by judges, and this was in the days of Ibzan, as our Sages said (B.B. 91a, Targum ad loc.): Ibzan is Boaz.</text>
      <text title="and a man went: ">He was very wealthy, and the leader of the generation. He left the Land of Israel for regions outside the Land because of stinginess, for he begrudged the poor who came to press him; therefore he was punished.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="Ephrathites: ">Heb. אֶפְרָתִים, important people, likewise, (I Sam. 1:1): “the son of Tohu, the son of Zuph, an Ephrathite,” a palace dweller (Ruth Rabbah 2:5). Look how important they were, for Eglon the king of Moab married off his daughter to Mahlon, for the master said (ibid. 9): Ruth was the daughter of Eglon. Another explanation: Ephrathites: Bethlehem was called Ephrath.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="Naomi’s husband: ">Why is this stated? From here they (our Sages) derived (Sanh. 22b): A man does not die except concerning his wife. (And Scripture states, “Naomi’s husband” ; that is to say that because he was her husband and ruled over her, and she was subordinate to him, therefore the divine standard of justice struck him and not her.)</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="both… also: ">What is the meaning of “also” ? First their possessions were smitten, and their camels and their cattle died, and afterwards they too died.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="Then she went forth from the place: ">Why is this stated? It is already stated, “and she returned from the fields of Moab,” and from where would she return if not from the place where she was? But Scripture wishes to tell [us] that the departure of a righteous person from a place is conspicuous, and makes an impression. Its splendor has turned away; its majesty has turned away; the praise of a city has turned away, and likewise (Gen. 28:10): “And Jacob went forth from Beersheba.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="for I have become too old to marry: ">that I should marry someone and bear sons, that you should marry them, for they are not forbidden to you and you are not forbidden to them as far as the prohibition against marrying the wife of a brother who is deceased, for she does not require a levirate marriage because Mahlon and Chilion were not halachically married to them because they were gentiles, and had not converted, and now they were coming to convert, as it is stated (verse 10): “[No], but we will return with you to your people.” From now on, we will become one people.</text>
      <text title="that I should say that I have hope: ">for even if my heart told me that I have hope to marry again and to bear sons.</text>
      <text title="Even if I had a husband tonight: ">and more than this, even if I conceived male offspring tonight.</text>
      <text title="and even if I had borne sons: ">or even if I had already borne sons.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="Would you wait for them: ">Heb. תְּשַּׂבֵּרְנָה. This is a question: Would you wait for them until they grew up? This is an expression similar to (Ps. 146:5): “his hope (שִּׂבְרוֹ) is in the Lord his God.”</text>
      <text title="Would you shut yourselves off: ">Heb. תֵּעָגֵנָה. An expression of being bound and imprisoned, like (Taanith 3:8): “He made a round hole (עָג עוּגָה) and stood within it.” Others interpret it as an expression of עִגוּן, anchoring, being unable to marry, but that cannot be, for if so, the “nun” should have been punctuated with a “dagesh” or it should have been spelled with two “nuns” .</text>
      <text title="for the hand of the Lord has gone forth against me: ">Said Rabbi Levi: Wherever it says “the hand of the Lord,” it refers to a plague of pestilence, and the classic example is (Exod. 9:3): “Behold the hand of the Lord will be.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="Lo, your sister-in-law has returned: ">Heb. שָּׁבָה. In this word, the accent is above (on the first syllable) under the “shin,” because it is in the past tense, but [in the verse] (Esther 2:14): “and in the morning she would return (שָּׁבָה) ,” the accent is below (on the last syllable) on the “beth,” because it is the present tense, and so it is in all similar cases.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="Do not entreat me: ">Heb. תִּפְגְעִי, do not urge me.</text>
      <text title="for wherever you go, I will go: ">From here our Sages derived that a [prospective] proselyte who comes to convert is told some of the punishments [for violating the commandments], so that if he decides to renege, he can renege, for out of Ruth’s words, you learn what Naomi said to her: “We may not go out of the boundary [of 2,000 cubits on all sides] on the Sabbath.” She replied to her, “Wherever you go, I will go.” “We are prohibited to allow a female to be secluded with a male who is not her husband.” She replied, “Wherever you lodge, I will lodge.” “Our people is separated from the other peoples with 613 commandments.” [She replied,] “Your people is my people.” “Idolatry is forbidden to us.” “Your God is my God.” “Four types of death penalties were delegated to the beth din (court) [to punish transgressors].” “Wherever you die I will die.” “Two burial plots were delegated to the beth din [to bury those executed], one for those stoned and those burned, and one for those decapitated and those strangled.” She replied, “And there I will be buried.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="So may the Lord do to me: ">as He has commenced to harm [me], for His hand has gone forth against me to slay my husband and to cause me to lose my property.</text>
      <text title="and so may He continue: ">if anything but death separates me from you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="so she stopped speaking to her: ">From here they derived that we do not overburden him and we are not overly meticulous with him (i.e., with a prospective convert).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="And they both went on: ">Said Rabbi Abbahu: Come and see how dear the proselytes are to the Holy One, blessed be He: Since she decided to convert, Scripture compared her to Naomi.</text>
      <text title="that the entire city was astir: ">The entire city became astir. They had gathered to bury Boaz’s wife, who had died on that very day.</text>
      <text title="Is this Naomi?: ">Heb. הֲזאֹת. The “hey” is vowelized with a “hataf” because it is in the interrogative. Is this Naomi who used to go out in covered wagons and with mules? Have you seen what happened to her because she went out from the Holy Land?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="I went away full: ">with wealth and sons. Another interpretation is that she was pregnant.</text>
      <text title="has testified: ">Heb. עָנָה, has testified against me that I dealt wickedly before Him. Another explanation: The Divine Standard of Justice has humbled me, as (Hosea 5:5): “And the pride of Israel shall be humbled (וְעָנָה).”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="at the beginning of the barley harvest: ">Scripture is speaking of the harvest of the Omer.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="2">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="a kinsman: ">Heb. מוֹדַע, a kinsman. He was the son of Elimelech’s brother. Our Sages said: Elimelech and Salmon the father of Boaz and So-and-So the near kinsman were all sons of Nahshon the son of Amminadab, but the merit of their fathers did not avail them when they left the Land to go abroad.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="I will go now to the field: ">To one of the fields of the people of the city, after one of them, in whose eyes I will find favor, that he will not rebuke me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And she went, and she came, and she gleaned in the field: ">We find in Midrash Ruth [Rabbah]: Before she went she came; Scripture says: And she came, and she gleaned? But rather, she marked the roads before she entered the field, and she went and came and returned to the city, in order to make signs and markings so that she would not stray in the paths and know how to return.</text>
      <text title="and her chance was: ">to come to the portion of the field belonging to Boaz.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="To whom does this maiden belong?: ">Now was it Boaz’s habit to inquire about the women? But rather, he saw her modest and wise behavior. Two ears she would glean but three she would not glean; and she would glean the standing ears while standing and the lying ones while sitting, in order to avoid bending over.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="who returned with Naomi: ">The accent is under the “shin” because it is the past tense, and not the present tense of the verb.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And she said: ">to herself.</text>
      <text title="I will now glean: ">the gleaning of the ears.</text>
      <text title="and gather from among the sheaves: ">the forgotten sheaves.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="And [if] you are thirsty, you may go to the vessels: ">And if you are thirsty, do not be ashamed to go and drink from the vessels of water that the young men will draw.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="but I am not as one of your handmaids: ">I am not as worthy as one of your handmaids.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="and dip your morsel in the vinegar: ">From here [we derive] that vinegar is beneficial for a heatwave.</text>
      <text title="and he handed her parched grain: ">Heb. וַיִצְבָּט, and he handed her. There is no similar word in the Bible, but in the language of the Mishnah (Hagigah 3:1): “the back, the interior, and the handle (בֵּית הַצְבִיטָה).”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="And also, pretend to forget: ">Heb. שֹּׁל תָּשּׂלוּ, you shall forget, pretend that you are forgetting. The Targum for שְּׁגָגָה, inadvertence, is שָּׁלוּתָא, and similarly, (II Sam. 6: 7): “for the error, (הַשַּׁל).” Another explanation: an expression of (Deut. 28:40): “your olive tree will cast off (יִשַּׁל) [its fruit].”</text>
      <text title="bundles: ">Heb. צְבָתִים small sheaves, and there is a similar expression in the language of the Mishnah (Er. 10:1): “If he found them (tefillin) in pairs (צְבָתִים) or in bundles.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="May he who took heed of you: ">the owner of the field who showed you favor [and permitted you] to glean in his field.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="with the living or with the deceased: ">That he sustains and supports the living and occupies himself with the needs of the deceased.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="3">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="our kinsman: ">Heb. מוֹדַעְתָּנוּ our kinsman.</text>
      <text title="is winnowing: ">the chaff, vanner in French.</text>
      <text title="tonight: ">because the generation was unrestrained in theft and robbery; and he would sleep in his threshing-floor to guard his threshing-floor.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="and you shall bathe: ">from the contamination of idolatry.</text>
      <text title="and anoint yourself: ">These are the commandments.</text>
      <text title="and put on your clothes: ">Sabbath garments.</text>
      <text title="and go down to the threshing-floor: ">Heb. וְיָרַדְתְּ. It is written וְיָרַדְתִּי [and I will go down]; my merit will go down with you.</text>
      <text title="do not make yourself known to man: ">to Boaz.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="And she went down to the threshing-floor, and she did: ">She said to her, “And you shall bathe and anoint yourself and get dressed and then you will go down to the threshing-floor,” but she did not do so, but she said, “If I go down when I am dressed up, whoever meets me or sees me will say that I am a harlot.” She therefore first went down to the threshing-floor and afterwards adorned herself, as her mother-in- law had charged her.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="and his heart was merry: ">He engaged in the Torah.</text>
      <text title="and she came softly: ">Heb. בַלָט silently.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="and the man quaked: ">He thought it was a demon and attempted to scream, but she held him and enveloped him with her arms.</text>
      <text title="and was taken around: ">Heb. וַיִלָפֵת, and he was seized, like (Jud. 16:29): “And Samson seized (וַיִלָפֹת). ”</text>
      <text title="and behold a woman: ">He placed his hand on her head and recognized that she was a woman.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="and you shall spread your skirt: ">the skirt of your garments to cover me with your cloak, and this is a term connoting marriage.</text>
      <text title="for you are a near kinsman: ">to redeem my husband’s estate, as it is written (Lev. 25: 25): “then his near kinsman who is closest to him shall come and redeem, etc.” My mother-in-law and I must sell our estate, and now it is incumbent upon you to buy [it]. Acquire me also, along with it, so that the name of the deceased be remembered on his estate. When I come to the field, they will say: This is Mahlon’s wife.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="than the first: ">that you did with your mother-in-law.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And now indeed: ">“If” is written but it is not read, i.e., it conveys the idea of doubt. There is surely a redeemer closer than I. (Other editions: כִּי אִם means a doubt, but it is certain.) Said Rabbi Joshua the son of Levi: Salmon, Elimelech, and Tov were brothers. Now what is the meaning of “that belonged to our brother, to Elimelech” ? A person always calls his uncle his brother, as is stated (Gen. 14: 14): “And Abram heard that his brother was captured.” Now was not Abraham his (Lot’s) uncle? Similarly, Boaz was Elimelech’s nephew, a kinsman of Mahlon, but Tov was closer.</text>
      <text title="closer than I: ">for he is a brother, and I am a nephew.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="Stay over tonight: ">stay over without a husband.</text>
      <text title="as the Lord lives: ">She said to him, “You are dismissing me with words.” He jumped up and swore to her that he would not dismiss her with words. Some of our Rabbis said: He swore to his evil inclination, for his evil inclination was contending with him, “You are single, and she is single; be intimate with her” ; so he swore that he would be intimate with her only in marriage.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="for he said, “Let it not be known: ">This refers back to ” and she rose before one could recognize.“ He rushed her to get up because he said in his heart, ” It does not befit my honor that it should be known that the woman came to the threshing floor."</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="six barleys: ">It is impossible to say six seah, because it is not customary for a woman to carry such a load; it refers literally to six barleycorns, and he hinted to her that a son who would be blessed with six blessings was destined to emerge from her. [The blessings are:] (Isa. 11:2): “a spirit of wisdom and understanding, counsel and heroism, a spirit of knowledge and fear of the Lord,” [referring to the King Messiah].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="until he has resolved: ">[i. e., until] the man [has resolved] the matter today.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="4">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="So-and-So: ">but his name was not written because he did not wish to redeem.</text>
      <text title="So-and-So: ">Heb. פְּלֹנִי אַלְמֹנִי, rendered [into Aramaic] in the Prophets (I Sam. 21:3) as “hidden, secret.” פְּנִי covered and concealed, an expression of (Deut. 17:8): “If [a matter] be concealed (יִפָּלֵא) ” ;(Gen. 18: 14) “Is anything concealed (הֲיִפָּלֵא) from the Lord?” אַלְמֹנִי A widow (אַלְמָן), without a name. (Other editions: אַלְמֹנִי. He was widowed of words of Torah, because he should have interpreted: “an Ammonite, but not an Ammonitess; a Moabite, but not a Moabitess.” Yet he said, “lest I mar my heritage.”)</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="and I will know, for there is no one besides you: ">who is a kinsman, to redeem.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="and from Ruth the Moabitess: ">you must buy, and she agrees only if you marry her.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="lest I mar my heritage: ">my offspring, like (Ps. 127:3): “Behold the heritage of the Lord is sons,” to give my offspring a stigma, as it is said (Deut. 23: 4): “An Ammonite or a Moabite shall not enter the congregation of the Lord,” but he erred by [not interpreting it as] “an Ammonite but not an Ammonitess.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="concerning redemption: ">This is a sale.</text>
      <text title="and exchange: ">This is an exchange.</text>
      <text title="one would remove his shoe: ">This is an act of acquisition, as we acquire title with a scarf in lieu of a shoe, and our Rabbis of blessed memory differed on this matter: who gave [the shoe] to whom. Some say that we perform the act of acquisition with the utensil of the acquirer, and Boaz gave [the shoe] to the redeemer, and others say that we perform the act of acquisition with the utensil of the seller, and the redeemer gave [the shoe] to Boaz.</text>
      <text title="and this was the attestation in Israel: ">the law of testimony.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="to preserve the name of the deceased on his heritage: ">Since his wife comes and goes on the estate and brings in and takes out, people say, “This is Mahlon’s wife,” and his name is remembered upon it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="like Rachel and like Leah: ">Even though they were of the tribe of Judah and of the descendants of Leah, they admitted that Rachel was the mainstay of the household, and they mentioned Rachel before Leah.</text>
      <text title="and be famous: ">lit. and call a name, i.e., may your name become great.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="like the house of Perez: ">from which you are descended.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="And these are the generations of Perez: ">Since he traced David’s genealogy on Ruth’s name, he returns and traces it on Judah’s name.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
</book>