<book>
  <chapter id="1">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="to Joel son of Pethuel: ">The son of Samuel the prophet who persuaded God with his prayer (פִתָּה לְאֵל). Some say that this prophecy was said in those seven years in which Elisha said: “For the Lord has decreed a famine etc.” and they took place during the days of Jehoram son of Ahab.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="Did this come about: ">I.e., what is mentioned below.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="What the shearing locust left over: ">Gazam, arbeh, yelek, hasil are species of locusts and he prophesied concerning them that they would come in those days and destroy all the fruit of the trees and the herbs of the field.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="the strong wine: ">Heb. עָסִיס, good wine.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="For a nation has ascended upon my land: ">He named these locusts as a host of nations.</text>
      <text title="and its molars are like those of a young lion: ">These are the thick teeth with which he chews.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="into a disappointment -Heb.: ">לִקְצָפָה, into a disappointment.</text>
      <text title="he has peeled it and cast it off: ">He has peeled off the bark of the tree and cast it off until the branches of the vine have become white.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="Lament: ">Heb. אֱלִי. Lamentations (קִינָה) is translated into Aramic as א ִילְיָא.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="have been cut off: ">Heb. הָכְרַת, like נִכְרַת. The “hey” vowelized with a short “kamatz” takes the place of a “nun.” Comp. (Job 5:23), “And the beast of the field made peace (הָשְׁלְמָה) with you.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="Be ashamed: ">Heb. הֹבִישוּ</text>
      <text title="plowmen: ">Heb. אִכָּרִים. Those who guide the plowshare.</text>
      <text title="for wheat and for barley: ">This refers back to the plowmen, and concerning the vine dressers, he says…</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="The vines have dried up, and the fig trees have been cut off: ">Heb. הוֹבִישָׁה, it was cut off, its produce terminated.</text>
      <text title="has dried up: ">Heb. הֹבִיש, like יָבֵש</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="Proclaim a fast: ">Heb. קַדְּשׁוּ, designate a fast</text>
      <text title="an assembly: ">Heb. עֲצָרָה, a gathering.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="Woe: ">Heb. אֲהָהּ. An expression of sighing and wailing.</text>
      <text title="and like plunder: ">Heb. וּכְשֹׁד. Like the plunder of brigands.</text>
      <text title="it will come: ">from the Omnipresent.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="from before our eyes: ">I.e., we see it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="have gathered mold: ">Heb. עָבְשׁוּ, have gathered rust and mold. in French moisir, to become moldy.</text>
      <text title="casks of wine: ">Heb. פְרֻדּדוֹת. Jonathan renders: casks of wine.</text>
      <text title="under their bungs: ">Heb. מֶגְרְפֹתֵיהֶם. Jonathan renders: מְגוּפָתֵיהוֹן, the cover of the cask.</text>
      <text title="the storehouses are laid desolate: ">I.e. the storehouses of wine and oil.</text>
      <text title="garners are demolished: ">Granaries of wheat.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="herds of cattle are perplexed: ">They are confounded. They are closed in and astray in the forests and in the wilderness.</text>
      <text title="are laid waste: ">Heb. נֶאְשָׁמוּ. have become spoiled through their guilt.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="the dwellings of the wilderness: ">Heb. נְאוֹת, an expression of a dwelling (נָוֶה).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="Also the beasts of the field: ">I.e., the hind of the field.</text>
      <text title="cry out: ">Heb. תַּעֲרֹג, will cry out, as Dunash (Teshuvoth Dunash, p. 18) interpreted it: ערג is the cry of the hinds. נהם is the roar of the lions; געה is the lowing of the calves; צהל is the whinnying of the horses; צִפצוּף is the chirping of the birds, and נבח is the barking of the dogs.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="2">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Sound a shophar: ">to announce to them that they should repent before the evil befalls them.</text>
      <text title="the day of the Lord: ">which we mentioned above.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="like the dawn, spread over the mountains: ">The increasing locusts and the shearing locusts are spread over the mountains as the dawn is spread over the entire world.</text>
      <text title="the like of which has never been: ">that all these species should come one after the other, but the species of arbeh alone did not equal that of Egypt, concerning which it is stated: (Exodus 10:14) “And after it there shall not be so.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="Fire consumes before it: ">They destroy everything as though a fire consumes before them and a flame blazes after them.</text>
      <text title="like the Garden of Eden: ">was the land before it came, and, after it goes, it leaves the land like a desert wasteland.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="Like the appearance of horses is its appearance: ">I.e., in their running.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="like the sound of a flame: ">A flame, consuming stubble, makes noise.</text>
      <text title="arrayed for battle: ">Heb. עֱרוּ. Since it is in the construct state, it is vowelized with a “hataf segol.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="gather blackness: ">Heb. ק ִבְּצוּ פָּארוּר. Blackness like a pot, Cf. (Num. 11: 8) “And they cooked in a pot (בַּפָּרוּר).” The “aleph” is superfluous, and it is not read.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="and they do not make… crooked: ">Heb. וְעַבְּטוּן. This has no comparison, but its interpretation according to its context is: they do not make crooked.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="and upon the swords: ">Heb. וּבְעַד הַשֶּׁלַח, (verse 9) “through the windows (בְּעַד הַח ַלוֹנִים).” Upon the weapons they fall and camp.</text>
      <text title="they do not receive monetary gain: ">Heb. לֹא יִבְצָעוּ. They do not receive monetary gain. And Jonathan interpreted it (הַשֶּׁלַח) as an expression of an errand. Because of the errand of the Holy One, blessed be He, they cast themselves down, and they do not receive monetary gain.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="In the city they clatter: ">Heb. יָשֹׁקּוּ. This is an expression of making a din. Cf. (Isa. 33:4) “like the roaring (כְּמַשַּׁק) of the cisterns” ; (Prov. 28: 15) “A growling (שּׁוֹקֵק) bear” ; (Zeph. 2:9) “the clattering of (מִמְשַׁק) the thorns.” Jonathan, however, renders it as an expression of arms (נֶשֶק). They are armed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="the heavens tremble: ">Because of the retribution coming upon Israel, they quake and tremble.</text>
      <text title="withdraw their shining: ">Take in their light.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="And the Lord gave forth (upon them) His voice: ">by the statement of His prophets prior to His sending this host of His.</text>
      <text title="for His camp is great: ">I.e, the camp He will send against you if you do not improve.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="and not your garments: ">for I do not pay heed to the rending of your garments. Another explanation: Rend your hearts and you will not need to rend your garments because of mourning.</text>
      <text title="and He repents of the evil: ">I.e., He turns to another thought.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="Whoever knows: ">that he is guilty of iniquity.</text>
      <text title="shall return and repent, and it shall leave: ">I.e., the hasil and the gazam will leave a blessing after it; through the repentance, a blessing will come in the produce.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="assemble the elders: ">Heb. קִבְצוּ. This is of the form of (I Kings 18:19) “Send and gather (קְבֹץ) for me,” an expression which is weak and light.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="a derision: ">Heb. לְחֶרְפָּה</text>
      <text title="for nations to make them an example: ">Heb. לְמְשָׁל, an expression of, (Deut. 28: 37) “for an example (מָשָל) and for a conversation piece.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="And the Lord was zealous for His land: ">Heb. וַיְקַנֵּא, an expression similar to (Num. 11:29) “Are you zealous (הַמְקַנֵּא) for me?” Their distress entered His heart, and He fought their battle and engaged in their necessities. Our Sages explain it as an expression of warning. He warned the locusts concerning His land. [from Sotah 3a]</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="derision: ">Heb. חֶרְפָּה, a derision, that they will call you ill- provided.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="And the northerner: ">Heb. הַצְּפוֹנִי. This can be interpreted as referring to the host of locusts, upon which the expression, “and I will drive him to a land barren and desolate,” fits aptly. Another explanation: The people that come from the north, viz., the kings of Assyria. And our Sages (Sukkah 52a) state: This is the temptation, which is hidden (צָפוּן) in a person’s heart.</text>
      <text title="the western sea: ">the eastern sea. And our Sages, who interpreted it [i.e., הַצְּפוֹנִי] as a reference to temptation, interpreted these two seas as the First Temple and the Second Temple. I.e, they explain הַקַּדְמוֹנִי as first and הָאַחֲרוֹן as last. And so they explained it: Because he directed his face toward the First Temple and the Second Temple and destroyed them. [God says: I will drive him out to a land barren and desolate, where he will find no one to incite. That will be because he set his sights for the First Temple and for the Second Temple and, because he incited the people to sin, they were destroyed. The two Temples, where everyone would gather during the three Pilgrimage Festivals, are symbolized by the sea, where water of the streams gather.] And, according to the Targum , who explains it as a reference to the king of Assyria, we must explain “his face to the eastern sea, and his end to the western sea” to mean that part of his army I will send to the east and part of it to the west.</text>
      <text title="its ill savor: ">Heb. צַחֲנָתוֹ. The word בָאְשוֹ, its stench, indicates concerning that it is an expression of filth.</text>
      <text title="for it did great things: ">I.e, it did a great evil, for it stretched forth its hands upon the great.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="Have no fear, O land: ">I.e, the land of Israel, when you repent.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="the teacher for justification: ">Heb. מוֹרֶה. Your prophets who teach you to return to Me, in order to justify you.</text>
      <text title="the early rain and the late rain.: ">Heb. מוֹרֶה, like (Deut. 11:14) “the early rain (יוֹרֶה) and the late rain (וּמַלְקוֹש).”</text>
      <text title="in the first month: ">In Nissan. Although the early rain is the first rain, which falls on the seeds, and that is in Marcheshvan, that year they sowed in Nissan, as is explained in Tractate Taanith (5a) that the grain grew in eleven days.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="shall roar: ">Heb. וְהֵשִׁיקוּ, an expression of making noise when the stream runs down from the winepress into the vat (הַיֶקֶב), which is the pit before the winepress</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="3">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And it shall come to pass afterwards: ">in the future.</text>
      <text title="upon all flesh: ">I.e, upon anyone whose heart becomes soft as flesh. Comp. (Ezekiel 36:26) “And I will give you a heart of flesh.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="and pillars of smoke: ">Heb. וְתִימְרוֹת. Perpendicular pillars of smoke, as tall as a palm tree.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="shall turn to darkness: ">to embarrass those who prostrate themselves to the sun.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="And it shall come to pass that whoever shall call etc. as… said: ">And where did He say it? (Deut. 28:10), “And all the peoples of the earth shall see that the Name of the Lord is called on you.” [from Mechilta, Ex. 12: 25]</text>
      <text title="and among the survivors: ">And in the remnant that will remain.</text>
      <text title="whom the Lord invites: ">Heb. קֹרֵא, an expression of those invited to a banquet or to the service of the king, an expression of invitation.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="4">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="to the Valley of Jehoshaphat: ">I will descend with them to the depth of justice.</text>
      <text title="Jehoshaphat: ">The judgments of the Lord.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="they cast lots: ">Heb. יִדּוּ. Like (Lam. 3:53) “And they cast (ו ַיַּדּוּ) a stone upon me.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="Are you paying Me recompense: ">Is this the recompense for what Solomon gave Hiram, the king of Tyre, twenty cities (I Kings 9:11)?</text>
      <text title="swiftly: ">Heb. קַל מְה ֵרָה, an expression of eagerness.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="to the Shebaites: ">To the children of Sheba.</text>
      <text title="for the Lord has spoken: ">Now where did He speak? (Gen. 9:25) “A slave of slaves shall he be to his brothers.” So it is explained in Mechilta (Ex. 12:25).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="prepare war: ">if you can wage war against Me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="your plowshares: ">Heb. אִתֵּיכֶם, koltres in O.F:, colters.</text>
      <text title="and your pruning hooks: ">Heb. וּמַזְמ ְרוֹתֵיכֶם, serpes in French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="Gather: ">Heb. עוּשׁוּ. Like חוּשוּ, hasten, so did Menahem associate it. Jonathan, however, renders: they shall gather, and I say that it is an expression of a block of iron (עֶשֶת) , which is gathered together, masse in French, and the “tav” is not a radical.</text>
      <text title="there the Lord shall break your mighty men: ">Heb. הַנְחַת. There in the gathering of the Valley of Jehoshaphat, He will break your might. So did Jonathan render it, but I do not know whether it is an Aramaic expression of lowering (נחת) or an expression of breaking (חתת) , and the “nun” is defective. Cf. (Dan. 2:25) “brought Daniel in (הנְעַל) before the king,” which has no radical but על.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="Stretch out a sickle etc.: ">Draw the swords, you who go on My mission to destroy the nations.</text>
      <text title="for the harvest is ripe: ">I.e, for their time has arrived, and he compared the matter to harvest, which is harvested with sickles when it becomes completely ripe.</text>
      <text title="come press for the winepress is full: ">of grapes. Come and tread them; i.e., the measure of their iniquity is full.</text>
      <text title="press: ">Heb. רְדוּ, an expression of pressing [or ruling]. Cf. (Gen. 1:28) “And rule (וּרְדוּ) over the fish of the sea.”</text>
      <text title="and the vats shall roar: ">The sound of the stream of the wine going down in the vats before the winepresses is heard.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="in the valley of decision: ">For there it is decided that the judgment is true. And so did Jonathan render: the valley of judgment.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="have withdrawn their shining: ">Have taken in their shining.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="shall roar from Zion: ">Because of what they did to Zion.</text>
      <text title="and the heavens and earth shall quake: ">He will deal retribution upon the heavenly princes and then upon the nations.</text>
      <text title="a shelter: ">Heb. מַחֲסֶה, an expression of a cover, abrier in O.F., abri in modern French, a shelter.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="springs: ">Heb. אֲפִיקֵי, a place of the source of water.</text>
      <text title="and water the valley of Shittim: ">According to its apparent meaning, and it will water the valley of Shittim (Targum), and, according to its Midrashic meaning, He will atone for the iniquity of Peor.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="Egypt etc. and Edom: ">He juxtaposed them as regards their retribution. You find that, were it not for Egypt, Edom would not exist, as it is stated: (I Kings 11:16 21) “For Joab and all Israel remained [stationed] there for six months etc. every male in Edom.” And it is stated there: (verse 17) “Adad fled, he and some Edomite men etc. And Hadad pleased Pharaoh very much etc. And Hadad etc. that David slept with his fathers etc.” And, at the end, (verse 25) “And he was an adversary to Solomon (sic).” Said the Holy One, blessed be He: I will destroy both of them.</text>
      <text title="because of the violence done to the children of Judah: ">Because of the violence they did to the children of Judah, viz., that they shed their blood.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="Now should I cleanse, their blood I will not cleanse: ">Even if I cleanse them of other sins in their hands, and of the evils they have done to Me, I will not cleanse them of the blood of the children of Judah. When will this come to pass? At the time the Holy One, blessed be He, dwells in Zion.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
</book>