<book>
  <chapter id="1">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="I will totally destroy: ">An expression of destruction, as in (Jud. 18: 25) “and you will lose your life,” mentioned regarding Micah. The “aleph” is defective in the second word, for it should have been written אֶאֱסֹף There are many [defective alephs] like these, as in (Isa. 13:20) “no Arab shall pitch his tent there,” which is like י ֶאֱהַל.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="and the stumbling blocks with the wicked: ">They are the pagan deities.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="the remnant of Baal: ">that there shall be no remnant of its remembrance.</text>
      <text title="the name of the idolatrous priests with the ancillary priests: ">Their worshippers with their priests.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="who swear by the Lord: ">and go back and swear by their king, their pagan deity. They make the pagan deity the main one, saying, “If you do not believe the oath by God, I swear to you by the pagan deity.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="He has invited His guests: ">He prepared His armies for the appointed day.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="gentile garb: ">Ornaments of the idols.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="who leaps over the threshold: ">Jonathan renders: who follows the customs of the Philistines, who would not step on the threshold of Dagon, as it is stated (I Sam. 5:5): “Therefore, the priests of Dagon… do not tread, etc.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="from the fish gate: ">Jonathan renders: from the gate of the fish; there was a gate in Jerusalem called by that name.</text>
      <text title="from the second gate: ">from the gate of the fowl, which was second to it [the fish gate].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="you inhabitants of Maktesh: ">The Kidron Valley, which is as deep as a mortar. This is according to Targum Jonathan .</text>
      <text title="from the fish gate: ">This is Acre, situated in the bosom of the sea, where many fish are caught.</text>
      <text title="from the Mishneh: ">This is Lod, which is second to Jerusalem.</text>
      <text title="from the hills: ">This is Sepphoris, which is situated at the tops of the mountains like a bird.</text>
      <text title="[11] inhabitants of Maktesh: ">This is Tiberias, which is deeper than all of [the rest of] the land of Israel.</text>
      <text title="for the entire people of Canaan is cut off: ">Jonathan renders: For the entire nation, whose deeds resemble the deeds of the people of the land of Canaan, has been broken.</text>
      <text title="all those laden with silver: ">Jonathan renders: All those wealthy with property, laden with a burden of silver and gold; as in (Prov. 27:3) “The weight of stone, the burden of sand” an expression of a burden.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="I will search Jerusalem with candles: ">I will judge their iniquities strictly.</text>
      <text title="who are settled: ">float on their lees. [As in] (II Kings 6:6) “And the axe blade floated,” rendered in Aramaic: וּקְפָא פַרְזְלָה.</text>
      <text title="who say in their heart, “The Lord shall do neither good…”: ">to those who obey His will.</text>
      <text title="nor harm: ">to those who transgress His will.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="wherein the mighty man cries bitterly: ">The mighty man will cry out with a bitter voice.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="a day of ruin: ">, an expression of desolation.</text>
      <text title="and desolation: ">A greater degree of desolation.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="And I will bring distress upon men: ">Upon Israel, who is called “man.”</text>
      <text title="and their flesh: ">their flesh. In Arabic, flesh is called al laham.</text>
      <text title="like dung: ">dung.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="2">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Gather yourselves together: ">Gather and assemble together as in (Exod. 5:12) “To Gather a gathering.”</text>
      <text title="gather together: ">your deeds. Conform your deeds to the will of Your Maker.</text>
      <text title="O nation that has no desire: ">That has no desire to return to the Torah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="before the decree is born: ">Before the arrival of the decree.</text>
      <text title="as chaff that passes… the sun: ">This is an ellipsis for, “As chaff that passes from before the wind, and as smoke that passes from before the sun.” This is the translation of עָבַר יוֹם, that passes the sun. In this manner, Jonathan renders: And you shall be like the chaff that the wind blows, like smoke that passes from before the sun. Another version: and like the shadow that passes, etc.; this is an expression of a shadow.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="For Gaza shall be deserted: ">For, if you will do so, [as in verse 1,] I will visit retribution upon your evil neighbors; Philistia, Ammon, and Moab. The prophet proceeds to mention them [the neighbors] in [geographical] order.</text>
      <text title="Ashdod at noon they shall drive her out: ">Her name is Ashdod, and, at noon, when the destruction wastes, they shall drive her out, and she shall be plundered. Another explanation. At noon they shall drive her out. [Ashdod] was a place to pasture sheep, and it is hard for the sheep to go out at noontime; so Scripture says (Song 1:7): “How do you make them lie down at noon?”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="the seacoast: ">the border of the sea. The expression חֶבֶל is a measure of land that they measured with a rope, i.e., those close to the sea.</text>
      <text title="the nation of Cherethites: ">the people liable to destruction. Who are the inhabitants of the seacoast of Canaan, the land of the Philistines? The Philistines, who dwell on the coast of the western sea, in the west of Eretz lsrael, within its boundaries. Although Jonathan explains this phrase homiletically as [the nation of] destruction, the nation of the Cherethites is a province of the Philistines; its name is Cherethi. So Scripture states (I Sam. 30:14) regarding Ziklag: “We made a raid upon the south of the Cherethites, etc.” Jonathan translates: on the south of Cherethi. Below (ibid. 30:16) it is written: “Because of all the great spoil which they had taken from the land of the Philistines and from the land of Judah.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="breakfast nooks for shepherds: ">a temporary dwelling where the shepherds eat bread in the morning. כְּרֹת is an expression related to (II Kings 6:23) “He prepared for them a lavish feast.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And it shall be a lot for the remnant of the house of Judah: ">And that border shall be a lot for the remnant. This חֶבֶל is an expression of a lot. In this manner, Jonathan rendered: And it shall be a lot for the remnant of the house of Judah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="who taunted My people: ">When [the people of] Israel were being led into exile toward the land of the Chaldeans, and they were passing through Ammon and Moab, and they would see Israel weeping, sighing, and crying out, they would taunt them and say, “Why are you suffering? Aren’t you going to your father’s house? Your fathers dwelt on the other side of the river from earliest times.” (Josh. 24:2)</text>
      <text title="and they aggrandized themselves on their border: ">And they acted haughtily on their border.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="for Moab shall be like Sodom: ">You, too, shall return to your previous dwelling. Was not your father, Lot, from Sodom?</text>
      <text title="a rattling of nettles: ">The sound made by the nettles growing there because there are no passersby, and they knock against each other and make sounds.</text>
      <text title="and a salt mine: ">a place for digging salt.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="for He weakened: ">He weakened their strength.</text>
      <text title="and… shall prostrate himself to Him: ">when they see that their deity has deteriorated.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="You, too, Cushites: ">When Israel was exiled there to the other side of the rivets of Cush.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="on the north: ">Assyria is on the north, neighboring on Babylon.</text>
      <text title="Nineveh: ">That is the capital of Assyria.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="all the beasts of the nations: ">all the cattle of the nations.</text>
      <text title="the pelican and the owl: ">birds.</text>
      <text title="owl: ">a bird that flies at night (chouette in French), an owl.</text>
      <text title="in its lintels: ">rounded knobs on the top of the roof; pomels in French.</text>
      <text title="Their voice shall sing in the window: ">The voice of the birds chirping in the windows.</text>
      <text title="desolation, in the doorpost: ">The desolation shall be discernible in the doorposts of the house.</text>
      <text title="for the cedarwork has been destroyed: ">For he has uprooted its cedars, as in (Ps. 137:7) “Raze it, raze it.” Jonathan rendered: And they demolished its roof. That is the roof of the house that is ceiled with cedar; even stone houses are ceiled with boards of wood.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="and there is none besides me: ">וְאַפְסִי</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="3">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Woe to her who is filthy and polluted: ">Until now, Zephaniah was speaking of Ninveh, but now he refers to Jerusalem: Woe to her who is destined to be plundered and sullied like dung. It will be polluted with the filth of its iniquity.</text>
      <text title="filthy: ">as in (Lev. 1:16) “its crop” ; and (Nahum 3:6) “And I will make you like dung.”</text>
      <text title="the dove like city: ">Like a silly dove, without a heart.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="wolves of the evening: ">who hasten to devour their prey at night.</text>
      <text title="They did not leave over the bones for morning: ">They did not leave over even the bones to gnaw in the morning.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="they removed the Torah: ">They did not teach it to those who inquired of them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="The Lord is just: ">He caused His Shechinah to rest in their midst; therefore, He cannot look upon their evil deeds. He is just, and there is no injustice before Him.</text>
      <text title="He brings His judgment to light: ">He judges a true judgment to its absolute truth.</text>
      <text title="But the one who commits injustice knows no shame: ">But the unjust judges do not take it to heart, to be ashamed because of the Righteous One Who dwells among them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="I have cut off nations: ">I brought retribution upon the nations so that you should see and fear as He concludes, “I said, ‘Surely you will fear Me.’”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="I said, “Surely you will fear Me… and her dwelling shall not be cut off”: ">Her dwellings shall not be destroyed.</text>
      <text title="all that I ordained upon her: ">And all the good that I ordained to bring upon her shall not be cut off from her.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="That I will rise up to meet: ">When I will rise to meet with you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="From the other side of the rivers of Cush: ">They will bring Me an offering.</text>
      <text title="My supplicants: ">those who pray to me.</text>
      <text title="the community of My scattered ones: ">The gatherings of My scattered ones, whom I scattered.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="you shall not be ashamed of all your deeds: ">Because you have already suffered, and your iniquity has been expiated.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="a humble and poor people: ">A humble people that submits to humiliation.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="your afflictions: ">justice in French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="A Mighty One will save: ">He is a Mighty One, Who will save [Israel] from the enemy.</text>
      <text title="He will be silent in His love: ">He will conceal your transgressions with His love. So did Jonathan render: He will cover your sins with His love.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="Those who are removed from the appointed season: ">I destroyed those removed from My appointed seasons, those who did not keep the Sabbaths and the festivals.</text>
      <text title="I have destroyed: ">lit., I gathered in.</text>
      <text title="they were of you: ">They were of your people.</text>
      <text title="it was a burden of shame upon her: ">That guilt was a burden of shame to you.</text>
      <text title="Those who are removed: ">an expression of taking out, as in (Prov. 25:4) “Take away the dross from the silver”; and (II Sam. 20:13) “When he was removed from the highway.” The only radical letter is the “gimel.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="Behold, I wreak destruction: ">Jonathan rendered: Behold I wreak destruction. It may also be interpreted as an expression of crushing, as in (Mal. 3:21): “And you shall crush the wicked.”</text>
      <text title="throughout all the land where they suffered shame: ">Every place where they were for their shame, there I will make them to be a praise and a name.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
</book>