<book>
  <chapter id="1">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="The prophecy: ">of Zechariah is extremely enigmatic, because it contains visions resembling a dream that requires an interpretation. We cannot ascertain the truth of its interpretation until the teacher of righteousness comes. Nonetheless, I will put my heart to reconciling the verses, one by one, according to the interpretations that resemble it and following the interpretation of Jonathan .</text>
      <text title="In the eighth month: ">Before they commenced resuming the work of the construction, for they commenced it on the twenty-fourth day of the [ninth] month.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="with your fathers: ">who were in the generation of the destruction of the Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="[As for] your fathers - where are they?: ">See that they suffered an evil blow, with famine, with the sword, and with pestilence.</text>
      <text title="But the prophets - do they live forever?: ">And if you ask, “the prophets, too where are they? Have they not died?” I [God] will answer you, “Should the prophets have lived forever?” But their end proves that their words were true; for all My words, and the declarations of the decrees of My retribution that I commanded My servants, the prophets, concerning you - did they not overtake your fathers?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="I saw tonight: ">Our Sages explained [this phrase as] they explained [it] in the Aggadah of the chapter entitled “ Helek ” (Sanh. 93a), but the sequence of the chapter and the language do not fit it.</text>
      <text title="and behold! A man: ">an angel.</text>
      <text title="on a red horse: ">This is an allusion that He would exact retribution upon the Chaldeans, Media, and Persia with the sword and with blood, as He says (verse 15 below): “And I was very wroth with the nations.”</text>
      <text title="and after him were red, etc., horses: ">prepared for the mission of the Omnipresent. That there were among them [horses of] many sorts of colors was a [means of] praise for him.</text>
      <text title="black: ">do not know what color this is. Jonathan rendered קְוָחִין.</text>
      <text title="among the myrtles that were in the pool: ">Among the myrtle trees of Babylon.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="And I said: ">to one angel who showed me all this.</text>
      <text title="“What are these, my lord?”: ">He was the one riding on the red horse.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="to walk to and fro on the earth: ">To see the tranquility of the nations.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And the angel of the Lord replied: ">The angel that was speaking to me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="And the Lord answered the angel who was speaking to me, good words: ">Not that the prophet heard what He answered [the angel], but from what the angel said to him, “Proclaim, saying, ‘I am jealous etc.,’” I know that He answered him good words.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="I am jealous for Jerusalem: ">I am exacting the retribution [for] the cause of Jerusalem from those who oppress her.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="that are at ease: ">Concerning whom these [messengers] say that they sit still and are at rest.</text>
      <text title="for I was wroth: ">with My people, a little.</text>
      <text title="and they helped to do harm: ">In addition to the wrath, [they helped] to do harm.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="and a plumb line shall be stretched out: ">to measure its wall, its length and breadth.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="2">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="These are the horns: ">These are the nations in the four corners of the heavens that gored Judah and Jerusalem with their horns until they scattered them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="four craftsmen: ">Carpenters who know how to saw the horns. And our Rabbis explained in tractate Sukkah (52b) who they are.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="And he said, saying, “These are the horns”: ">that you first saw.</text>
      <text title="that scattered Judah: ">and humbled them to the extent that no man lifted his head, and they did not allow anyone of My people to raise his head.</text>
      <text title="And these came: ">These craftsmen came to cause those horns to quake and to cast them away.</text>
      <text title="to cast away: ">לְיַדּוֹת</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="a measuring line: ">A measuring line to measure Jerusalem, how much its length and its breadth shall be.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And behold, the angel who was speaking with me was coming forth: ">He is the one with the measuring line in his hand.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="Run, speak to this young man: ">You shall no longer go forth to measure, for the Holy One, blessed be He, has taken counsel with His heavenly household [and decreed] that [Jerusalem] will not have a limit or a measure. And now, run and speak to Zechariah: It shall be inhabited like unwalled towns, without a wall, so that all who come there shall settle therein, and it shall grow from day to day.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="But I will be for it: ">as a shield, as though a wall of fire surrounds it. Also, My Shechinah shall dwell in its midst for your glory.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="Ho, Ho!: ">“Ho” is only an expression of proclamation and an announcement of assembly. And so did Jonathan render it: Announce to the scattered ones. אַכְלוּ means announce, as in (II Sam. 22:14): “The Lord thundered from heaven,” which Jonathan renders: אַכְלוּ מִן שְׁמַיַּא</text>
      <text title="Flee from the land of the north: ">The exiles of My people, [flee] from within Babylon and Assyria.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="Ho, Zion ! Flee: ">This too is an expression of announcement: Assemble, O exile of Zion, and flee from the midst of Babylon.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="After glory: ">After your glory I am sent, to magnify your glory. And the Midrash Aggadah (Addendum to Tan. Buber, Devarim 4) states: After the honor - After I pay Esau for the honor that he bestowed upon his father.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="and they shall be prey, etc.,: ">to Israel, who are now slaves to them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="And many nations shall join: ">shall join.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="And the Lord shall inherit Judah: ">as His inheritance and His share.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="Silence all flesh: ">All the rest of the nations.</text>
      <text title="for He is aroused: ">An expression [denoting] arousal and awakening.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="3">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="to accuse him: ">To accuse him because his sons were married to gentile women, as it is written in the Book of Ezra (10:18): “And it was found of the sons of the priests who had taken foreign wives, of the sons of Jeshua the son of Jozadak, etc.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="The Lord shall rebuke you, O Satan: ">The Holy One, blessed be He, shall rebuke you, O you Satan (and then he repeated and said: The Lord shall rebuke you, He who chose Jerusalem Moharaz Margolioth); and He Who rebukes you is the One Who chose Jerusalem, that you shall not enter before Him to accuse this righteous man. Is he not fit, and has he not merited this? For he was saved from the consuming fire.</text>
      <text title="Is this one not a brand plucked from fire?: ">It is related in the Aggadah of [chapter] Helek Helek (Sanh. 93a) that he [Joshua] was cast into the fire with Ahab son of Kolaiah and his colleague.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="was wearing filthy garments: ">This is to be explained according to the Targum: He had sons who had married women who were unfit [to marry into] the priesthood, and he was punished because he did not interfere with the [sons’ marriages].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="“Take the filthy garments off him.”: ">Let his sons separate from their wives, and he will be forgiven.</text>
      <text title="clean garments: ">A change of beautiful garments; i.e., merits. Since he compared the iniquity to filthy garments, he compares the merit to clean garments; beautiful, white garments.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="And I said: ">I, Zechariah.</text>
      <text title="“Let them put a pure miter, etc.”: ">I begged mercy for him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="warned: ">an expression of warning, as in (Deut. 31:28): “And I will warn them before the heaven and the earth.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="If you walk in My ways, etc.: ">Then I, too, will do this for you.</text>
      <text title="you, too, shall judge My house: ">You shall judge and be the officer over My Temple.</text>
      <text title="and I will give you free access: ">According to the Targum: and when the dead will be resurrected, I will resurrect you; and I will give you walkers who walk among these seraphim. According to its simple meaning, he brings him tidings that his sons will be meritorious in the future.</text>
      <text title="who stand by: ">Seraphim and ministering angels, who never sit.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="you and your companions: ">They were Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah.</text>
      <text title="for they are men worthy of a miracle: ">[Jonathan renders:] Men worthy to have miracles performed for them, for a miracle was performed for them, too.</text>
      <text title="for, behold! I bring My servant, the Shoot: ">For now Zerubbabel, the governor of Judah, is insignificant in the king’s court, but I will make his greatness burgeon. I will also give him favor in the eyes of the king, so that he will grant [Zerubbabel’s] request for the building of the Temple and the city, as explained in Nehemiah (1:1): “The words of Nehemiah, the son of Hachaliah.” Nehemiah was identical with Zerubbabel, as we say in Sanhedrin (38a).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="For, behold the stone: ">The foundation of the house that you laid in the days of Cyrus - they stopped you, and that foundation and the thickness of the wall appeared little in your sight, as explained in Ezra (3:12f.) and in the prophecy of Haggai (2:2f.).</text>
      <text title="Seven eyes are directed to one stone: ">It will eventually be widened seven times as much. And so did Jonathan render: On one stone, seven eyes see it. The expression of עֵינַיִם is an expression of appearances. It appears to me that the seven eyes are because of the eyes of the Holy One, blessed be He in Whose eyes and heart it is [planned] to add seven times as much because of the prophecy similar to this one (4:10): “And they shall see the plummet in the hand of Zerubbabel these seven times; the eyes of the Lord they are roving to and fro throughout the land.” This is but to say that He directed His eyes to increase the glory of the Temple in its building.</text>
      <text title="Behold! I untie its knots: ">I untie its knots I thwart the plot of the enemies who wrote an accusation to stop the work.</text>
      <text title="and I will remove: ">Heb. ומשתי.</text>
      <text title="in one day: ">I do not know what day.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="4">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="with its oil - bowl on top of it: ">as in (Josh. 15:19): “The upper springs” . This is an expression for a spring, [hence] a sort of large round bowl.</text>
      <text title="and its seven lamps: ">A type of vessel into which oil and wicks are inserted.</text>
      <text title="seven tubes each: ">Seven small tubes come to every lamp, for the oil flows from the bowl through those tubes into each lamp.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And [there were] two olive trees near it: ">Beside it were two trees upon which olives were growing, one on the right of the bowl, one on the its left, etc. Here [the prophet] does not explain about the two golden vats mentioned below in the chapter, which are the sorts of bowls or vats of the oil press. [These vats] stand beside the olive trees. The olives beat themselves into the vats and are heated there as [if] in a vat or pit where olives are generally packed. There they are pressed in the oil press, and the oil falls into the vats, and from the vats into the bowl, and from the bowl into the tubes, and from the tubes into the lamps. The tubes and the lamps number forty-nine, an allusion to the light, for in the future the light of the sun will be sevenfold the light of the seven days forty-nine times the light of a day of Creation.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="“What are these, my Lord?”: ">What is this, that the olive trees are picked by themselves, and the oil comes into the lamps by itself?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="“This is the word of the Lord to Zerubbabel”: ">This is a sign for you to promise Zerubbabel that just as the olives and this oil are finished by themselves in all respects, so will you not build My house with your [own] power or with your [own] strength.</text>
      <text title="but by My spirit: ">I will place My spirit upon Darius, and he will command you to build and to pay all the building expenses from his [treasury]; and [he will] help you with wheat, wine, oil, and wood, as is explained in Ezra (6, 7): They required no aid from any man.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="Who are you, O great mountain?: ">You, the princes of the other side of the river Tattenai, the governor of the other side of the river; Shethar Bozenai, and their companions (Ezra 6:6), who have stopped the work until now - from now on you shall be before Zerubbabel as a plain; you have no more ruling power or superiority over him.</text>
      <text title="He will bring out the stone of the main architect: ">The main architect will take the plummet in his hand to be the main architect at the head of the builders, and they will build everything according to his words [everything] that he will order concerning a beautiful and glorious building.</text>
      <text title="with shouts of grace, grace to it: ">To that stone, for everyone will say, “How beautiful is this building that was made with this plummet.” [The expression] “shouts of grace” is as (Job 39:7) “the shouts of a driver,” and (Isa. 66:6) “a sound of stirring” both of which are expressions of making a voice heard.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Zerubbabel’s hands founded this house: ">from beginning to end, in the days of Cyrus I.</text>
      <text title="and his hands shall complete: ">it now. The word תְּבַצַעְנָה is an expression of completion, as in (Isa. 10: 12) “when the Lord completes all His work.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="For, whoever despised the day: ">when the Temple was founded which was small in their eyes, as is stated in Ezra (3:12): “But many of priests, etc., who had seen, etc., upon its foundation, wept aloud when they beheld this temple;” and in Haggai (2:3): “Is it not as nothing in your eyes?” - will rejoice now when they see the plummet suspended from the plumb line in the hand of the architect, the head of the builders, with which he directs a line to the corner, and this will be in the hand of Zerubbabel.</text>
      <text title="these, sevenfold: ">Seven times the first foundation in the days of Cyrus. So did Jonathan render: Seven rows of stones like these.</text>
      <text title="the eyes of the Lord are roving to and fro: ">And it appeals to Him to do so; and He saw this Zerubbabel suited for the matter.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="What are these two olive trees?: ">What do they symbolize, and what do the two olive branches (troches in Old French) symbolize? [They are] a cluster of olives on a branch, as if a type of ear of grain.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="beside the two golden vats: ">i.e., beside the two golden vats, as in (II Sam. 14:30): “See, Joab’s field is near mine.”</text>
      <text title="that empty out the gold[en oil] from themselves: ">This oil that is clear and good to illuminate like gold, as in (Job 37:22): “From the north comes gold.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="two anointed ones: ">The horns of the priesthood and the kingdom who are anointed with the anointing oil.</text>
      <text title="who stand before the Lord of all the earth: ">to supplicate Him to return their greatness.</text>
      <text title="the two anointed ones: ">The good inclination and the evil inclination, which is converted to good in the merit of the Torah.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="5">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="a flying scroll: ">Our Sages explained [it] as “double,” and they said that the Torah was written on it. They deduced from here that the world is 1/3,200 of the Torah, as stated in Eruvin (21a). And Jonathan rendered: a flying scroll; i.e., flying in the air. According to the simple meaning of the chapter, it was a scroll of retribution; that was what Ezekiel (2:10) envisioned: “And in it was written lamentations and mourning and woe.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="This is the curse: ">This is [the scroll] in which is written the retribution, the revenge for a false oath. [The scroll] is now coming forth from the Holy of Holies, from before the Shechinah, to walk to and fro upon the face of the entire land; this is the meaning of “its length is twenty, and its width is ten” - as the measure of the entrance to the Temple court and the Temple, through which it shall emerge.</text>
      <text title="for whoever stole: ">until now.</text>
      <text title="was cleared from such as this: ">He was cleared from this retribution, as it delineated on it [i.e., the scroll]. The retribution of individuals who transgressed the Torah was not meted out, but He waited until the measure of all of them was filled, and they all suffered at once with the destruction and the exile. Similarly, everyone who heretofore swore falsely, was cleared of the retribution as delineated in this scroll and was not requited, but from now on…</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="I have brought it forth: ">to walk to and fro in the land and to wreak vengeance upon the thieves and the swearers of falsehoods from now on; and it shall come into the house of the thief, etc.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="Now lift up your eyes and see: ">Yet another is coming forth, that will come out from the Holy of Holies.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="And I said, “What is it?”: ">that is coming forth, that you tell me to see?</text>
      <text title="And he said, “This is the ephah”: ">For you will see a sort of ephah with which they measure coming forth.</text>
      <text title="And he said, “This is [the punishment of those] whose eye [gazes] over the entire land”: ">And, after I saw it, he said, “ This is the measure by which punishment was meted out to those whose eyes were over the entire land, to rob and to oppress, to make the ephah smaller and to make the shekel larger; and punishment was meted out to them, a measure for a measure.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And behold! A talent of lead was being lifted: ">I saw that a weight [made] of a talent of lead was being lifted off the earth into the air, and I saw further that this one woman was sitting in the midst of the ephah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="And he said, “This is Wickedness.”: ">This woman that you see in the midst of the ephah is the character of the way of wickedness, [the way] in which the wicked deport themselves. And behold, now they are placed in its midst to be punished in the midst of that very measure that they meted out, a measure for a measure.</text>
      <text title="And he cast her: ">Heretofore she had been sitting, but he cast her and knocked her into its midst, symbolizing torments and punishments.</text>
      <text title="and he cast the lead weight into her mouth: ">to weigh her down so that they achieve no more greatness and their voice is no longer heard robbing the poor and needy.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="two women were coming forth: ">from the house.</text>
      <text title="the stork: ">the white dayyah (Hullin 63a), voltur in Old French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="and it will be prepared, and they shall place it there: ">And the house shall be prepared, and the ephah shall be placed there with the wicked that are within it.</text>
      <text title="there: ">In that house.</text>
      <text title="on its base: ">On its permanence and on its base. Here He hinted [to Zechariah] that, because of the iniquity of Israel, who measured out [so to speak] with the measure of sins and wickedness, they were punished with the same measure. And there came two nations that ruled together; they were Babylon and the Chaldeans - the army of Nebuchadnezzar - and exiled [Israel] to Babylon where [Israel] stayed fixed on a base, a base that was established for them. That is according to the completion of the seventy years until now, when they returned. This interpretation leans partially toward that of Jonathan. This [phrase] is interpreted in many [other] ways, but they are not satisfactory to me. Our Sages, however, explained and learned from here that the evil inclination was given into the hands of the men of the Great Assembly, and they cast it into a leaden cauldron and covered it with lead, because lead absorbs the sound, as is stated in tractate Sanhedrin (24a) and in tractate Yoma (69b). My interpretation of the kingdom of Nebuchadnezzar as doubled - composed of two nations - I saw in Midrash Psalms (6:2, 18:10), that the following four kingdoms that subjugated Israel were double: Babylon and the Chaldeans, Media and Persia, Greece and Macedon, Edom and Ishmael, and for this reason the Kalir composed (in Piyutim for Shemini Azereth), “It is the fourth; it is the eighth,” concerning Edom.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="6">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="and the mountains were mountains of copper: ">A sign of the strength of these kingdoms, which came to them from between the two mountains, which are hard and strong, as these four chariots are messengers of the Holy one, blessed be He, to give ruling power to the four kingdoms of Babylon, Media, Greece, and Edom.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="red horses: ">They were the ones that caused Babylon to mount, for [Babylon] is red, as it is written (Dan. 2:38): “You are the head of gold” [gold having a red tinge].</text>
      <text title="black: ">[Horses,] to cause Media to mount, for they blackened the faces of Israel in the days of Haman.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="white: ">To cause Persia to mount, and Persia built the Temple.</text>
      <text title="spotted: ">They are spotted. [Their function is] to cause Greece to mount, [as Greece] oppressed Israel with various kinds of decrees</text>
      <text title="ash-colored: ">to cause Edom and Ishmael to mount, but I do not know the expression אֲמֻצִּים. Jonathan rendered: ash-colored.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="These are the four corners of the heavens: ">The heavenly princes of the nations that rule over the four corners of the heavens.</text>
      <text title="coming forth from standing, etc.: ">They came before Him, and He gave them permission from His mouth to rule.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="The one [chariot] the black horses were in was going to the northland: ">to cause Media to ride. Concerning the red ones, he does not write that they were going forth because the kingdom of Babylon had already been destroyed.</text>
      <text title="and the white ones went forth after them: ">to cause Persia to mount both of them, in the north, and they ruled over Babylon.</text>
      <text title="and the spotted ones went forth to the southland: ">to cause Greece to mount so that Greece should take the kingdom from Persia. In Rav Saadiah’s interpretation of Daniel, the king of the south (11:5) is identified with the king of Greece.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And the ash-colored ones went forth and begged: ">of Him that they have a very long rule, to go throughout all the earth.</text>
      <text title="And He said, “Go, walk to and fro on the earth”: ">He gave them permission to rule a great ruling, and that is the kingdom of Edom.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="Look, those going forth to the northland: ">to cause Media and Persia to mount.</text>
      <text title="eased My spirit: ">They caused My anger to subside in Babylon when they destroyed Belshazzar and Nebuchadnezzar’s descendants. This is what Isaiah (48:14) said: “The Lord loves him who shall do His will in Babylon, etc.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="Take from the exiles - from Heldai, etc., who have come from Babylon: ">All these people.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="whose name is the Shoot: ">He is Zerubbabel, mentioned above (3:8): “Behold, I bring My servant, the Shoot,” since his greatness burgeoned little by little. Some interpret this as referring to the King Messiah, but the entire context deals with the [time of the] Second Temple.</text>
      <text title="who will spring up out of his place: ">From royal descent.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="and he shall bear glory: ">The glory of the kingship.</text>
      <text title="And he shall sit: ">The High Priest [shall sit] on the throne of the priesthood.</text>
      <text title="And a council of peace, etc.: ">The king and the Priest shall love one another.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="And the crowns shall be for Helem, etc.: ">This is a transposed verse. It should be understood as: And the crowns shall be in the Temple of the Lord as a good memorial for Helem and for Tobijah, who donated the silver and the gold. Those crowns were hanging in the windows in the height of the Temple, as we learned in tractate Middoth (36a, 3:8).</text>
      <text title="for Helem: ">That is Heldai.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="And it shall come to pass if you hearken: ">And this thing shall come to pass for you if you hearken, etc.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="7">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="And Sharezer and Regem Melech and his men sent to Bethel: ">They were righteous men, and they sent [word] to their kinsmen in Bethel to come to pray before the Lord in Jerusalem for them, and to ask the priests to let them know if they should [still] weep in the month of Av, since the Temple had been rebuilt.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="abstaining: ">To abstain from pleasure, as I have done these seventy years. The word נְזִירָה always means separation.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="and in the seventh [month]: ">That is the fast of Gedaliah.</text>
      <text title="did you fast for Me, even for Me: ">The ‘he’ is vowelized with a ‘hataf pattah’ because it is used as the interrogative: Did you fast in My honor that you should be required to fast now, too?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="And when you eat and when you drink: ">And, if you do not fast, that, too, means nothing to Me. Are not the food and the drink for your own pleasure?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="Was it not the words: ">Who caused you the fast and the mourning? Was it not the words of reproof that the Lord proclaimed, etc.? They brought about your destruction, and therefore you fasted. And these are the words that He proclaimed: Execute true judgment.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="shamir: ">A worm stronger than flint. They would show it to the stone, which would split.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="And it came about; as He called and they did not hearken: ">the Lord said concerning them in those days: So shall they call and I will not hearken.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="I will scatter them: ">in exile. And so I did.</text>
      <text title="they made: ">with their iniquity.</text>
      <text title="desolation: ">And that brought about the fast (and the mourning), but now [I am jealous for Zion, etc.]</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="8">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="I am jealous for her: ">For [not 'to’] her. And you will not need to fast and to mourn. And so is the end of the chapter: “The fast of the fifth month, etc.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="because of old age: ">they will require the staff in their hand.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="As it will be wonderful: ">in their eyes, the great loving-kindness that I will do for them.</text>
      <text title="it will also be wonderful in My eyes: ">how I returned from the great wrath. And our Sages expounded on [this phrase], concerning the slaughter of the evil inclination, in tractate Sukkah (52a).</text>
      <text title="it will also be wonderful in My eyes: ">how the righteous will be able to stand up against [the evil inclination] during their lifetime.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Let your hands be strong: ">to build and to complete [the Temple]; and do not fear the people of the land, who are weakening your hands and frightening you from building it, as is related in the Book of Ezra (4:4).</text>
      <text title="you who hear in these days: ">In the fourth year of Darius</text>
      <text title="these words: ">of consolations from the mouths of the prophets who prophesied for [the people] - on the day the foundation of the house of the Lord was laid, in the second year of Darius - to begin the work. Those prophets were proven with their words to be true prophets in your eyes; therefore, it is also worthy to rely on them for the words of consolation concerning the present time. And in what way were they proven?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="For before those days, there was no hire for man, etc.: ">They prophesied for you that when you would begin the work, a blessing would come into the work of your hands; and their words were fulfilled, for now it is not like the early days.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="and I did not repent: ">of what I had planned to bring upon you, [or] retract it; but I brought it. Neither will I repent of the good that I have planned for you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="and judgment of peace: ">I.e., compromise.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="And let no one think evil of his neighbors: ">He warned them concerning hatred without cause, which brought about the destruction of the Second Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="the fast of the fourth [month]: ">The fast of Tammuz, which is the fourth of the months.</text>
      <text title="the fast of the fifth [month]: ">of Av.</text>
      <text title="the fast of the seventh [month]: ">The third of Tishri, when Gedaliah was assassinated.</text>
      <text title="and the fast of the tenth [month]: ">Of Teveth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="ten men: ">from the seventy nations. This equals seven hundred for each corner. For the four corners of the tallith there will be two thousand and eight hundred.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="9">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="In the land of Hadrach: ">R’ Judah the son of Ilai expounded: This is the Messiah, who is sharp against the nations and soft to Israel. R’ Yose the son of a Damascene mother said to him [to Judah the son of Ilai]: “Judah, our master, how long will you pervert the verses for us? I call heaven and earth to testify for me, that I am from Damascus, and there is a place named Hadrach. [Rabbi Yose continued:] Now how do I explain: 'And Damascus is His resting place?’” That Jerusalem is destined to reach as far as Damascus. ‘His resting place’ means only Jerusalem, as it is said: (Psalms 132:14) “ This is My resting place to eternity.” He said to him [i.e. R’ Judah to R’ Yose]: “Now how do I explain (Jer. 30:18) 'And the city shall be built on its mound?’” He replied: “That it is not destined to move from its place.” So was the baraitha taught in Sifre (Deut. 1:1).</text>
      <text title="for man’s eye shall be to the Lord: ">For on that day man will turn to his Maker, and his eyes will see the Holy One, blessed be He, as [the prophet] states above: Let us go with you. And they and their cities will join the cities of Israel.</text>
      <text title="and all the tribes of Israel: ">They are regarded by God above all the nations. Similarly, Scripture states (I Kings 11:1): “King Solomon loved many foreign women and the daughter of Pharaoh.” Now, was the daughter of Pharaoh not included in the generalization? But the daughter of Pharaoh was as dear to him as all of them. Here, too, all the nations shall belong to the Holy One, blessed be He, and Israel is equal to all of them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="And also Hamath shall border thereon: ">Its border shall reach the border of Jerusalem</text>
      <text title="Tyre and Sidon: ">They, too, shall be its [Jerusalem’s] villages, although it has become exceedingly wise. She [Tyre] became exceedingly wise and thought to be forever a mistress with her wisdom.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And Tyre built a fortification for herself: ">and [Tyre] says, “Who will bring me down to earth?”</text>
      <text title="and she gathered silver like dust: ">and boasts of her wealth.</text>
      <text title="and gold: ">a certain appearance of gold.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="Behold, the Lord: ">Who is the ruler over all.</text>
      <text title="shall impoverish her: ">an expression similar to (I Sam. 2:7) “impoverishes and makes rich.”</text>
      <text title="He shall smite her wealth in the sea: ">And shall cause her wealth to be swallowed in the midst of the seas. He shall cause the sea to rise over it and sink it, as Ezekiel said (27).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="Ashkelon shall see: ">the downfall of Tyre and fear.</text>
      <text title="and Ekron: ">too, shall fear.</text>
      <text title="for the one to whom she looked was ashamed: ">For [Ashkelon] relied on Tyre, which was the head of the sons of Esau, and Ekron, too, belonged to Edom, as our Sages said in tractate Megillah (6a): “Ekron shall be uprooted (Zeph. 2:4).” This is Caesarea, which belongs to Edom, and it originally belonged to the Philistines.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="And the strangers shall dwell in Ashdod: ">And a strange people shall dwell in Ashdod. Those are the Israelites, who were strange in it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And I will remove his blood from his mouth: ">From the mouth of Esau. This is their house of Bamia [one of Edom’s principal deities (Rashi to Megillah 6a)], where they would sprinkle the blood of their sacrifices. Others interpret this to mean the bloodshed, that the [Edomites] would shed the blood of Israel.</text>
      <text title="and it, too, shall remain to our God: ">These are the synagogues and the studyhalls in our exile.</text>
      <text title="and it shall be like a study hall in Judah: ">These are their theaters and circuses, where the princes of Judah are destined to teach Torah in public.</text>
      <text title="and it shall be like a study hall: ">an expression of study and learning.</text>
      <text title="and Ekron: ">shall be to Israel.</text>
      <text title="like Jebusi: ">Jerusalem.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="And I will encamp beside My house against a garrison: ">I will encamp beside My house to protect it from those who set up a garrison and raiders, that they should not set these up against it. A similar word is used in (Isa. 29:7) “and all those stationed around her, and those who trap her.” It is also possible to interpret מִצָבָה as מִצָבָא, with an ‘alef’ [meaning against a host].</text>
      <text title="for now I have seen with My eyes: ">Now I have seen their distress with My eyes, although until now I have hidden My countenance from them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Behold! Your king shall come to you: ">It is impossible to interpret this except as referring to the King Messiah, as it is stated: “and his rule shall be from sea to sea.” We do not find that Israel had such a ruler during the days of the Second Temple.</text>
      <text title="just and victorious: ">saved by the Lord.</text>
      <text title="and riding a donkey: ">This is a symbol of humility.</text>
      <text title="and a foal of she-donkeys: ">as in (Gen. 32:16)"and ten foals.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="And I will cut off the chariots: ">for they will not need them.</text>
      <text title="and his rule: ">וּמָשְׁלוֹ</text>
      <text title="from the sea to the west: ">From its sea to the west, to the end of the world.</text>
      <text title="and from the river: ">The Euphrates.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="You, too: ">shall be saved with him, as he is just and victorious. For with the blood of your covenant, I prophesied for you for the future; and for now, too, from the Babylonian exile in which you are now found.</text>
      <text title="with the blood of your covenant: ">With the merit of the blood of the covenant that was sprinkled upon you at Sinai, as it is written (Exod. 24:8): “Behold the blood of the covenant that the Lord has made.”</text>
      <text title="I have freed your prisoners: ">from the exile.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="Return to the stronghold: ">To your strength and to your glory, even though you are now under the rule of the kings of Persia.</text>
      <text title="you prisoners of hope: ">who hoped for Me until now that My words [would] be fulfilled at the end of seventy years.</text>
      <text title="Also today, I will restore to you a double promise: ">Today I will yet tell you second tidings, besides those of the building. And what is the second narrative that I am returning to repeat to you?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="For I bend Judah for Me: ">Eventually, the Greeks will wrest the kingdom from the Persian kings and inflict harm upon you, and I will bend Judah to be a war bow for me; and Judah will wage war against the Greeks in the days of the Hasmoneans.</text>
      <text title="a bow; I filled [the hand of] Ephraim: ">This is an elliptical verse: Like a bow, I filled the hand of Ephraim; as (II Kings 9:24), “And Jehu put all his strength into his bow.” Ephraim shall be as a quiver full of arrows to Me.</text>
      <text title="and I will arouse your children, O Zion: ">The children of Zion on the children of Javan.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="And the Lord shall appear over them: ">In the book of Josippon (chap. 18), we find that at that time a sign appeared to the people of Jerusalem.</text>
      <text title="shall sound the shofar: ">He shall thunder.</text>
      <text title="and He shall go with the whirlwinds of the south: ">To storm the people of the south; they are the Greeks. And some of our Sages interpreted [the phrase] as referring to Edom in the future.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="and they shall devour: ">the spoils of their enemies.</text>
      <text title="and they shall tread: ">under them.</text>
      <text title="sling-stones: ">They are the Greeks, who are trained to use the bow and to sling stones.</text>
      <text title="They shall make a noise like [those who drink] wine: ">They shall make noise with a voice of joy and happiness, as those who have drunk much wine make noise.</text>
      <text title="and they shall become full: ">Their souls shall become full of all good.</text>
      <text title="like the basin: ">that is full of blood. before the altar.</text>
      <text title="like the corners of the altar: ">where wine is libated. The wine would flow upon it, as we learned in tractate Sukkah (49b). This is an expression of satiety, an expression of drunkenness.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="like the flocks of His people: ">Like the flocks that He caused to travel from Egypt to become His people.</text>
      <text title="for crown stones are exalted on His land: ">For the priests, the sons of the Hasmoneans, who boast of the crown stones in the rows of the breast-plate and the ephod, will be exalted with miracles on their land.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="For how: ">How great is the goodness laid out for that generation.</text>
      <text title="Corn… young men: ">Whch gives strength to young men.</text>
      <text title="and new wine: ">Which causes maids to speak in song and joy. Others interpret יְנוֹבֵב [as that] which will be fruitful and grow in virgin soil, which is superior wine.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="10">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Request rain from the Lord: ">if you need it.</text>
      <text title="rain-clouds: ">Clouds that bring rain</text>
      <text title="for each person, grass in the field: ">For one man and for one grass that requires rain.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="For the teraphim, etc., and the soothsayers envisioned lies, and dreamers: ">who misled your forefathers, saying, “I dreamt.” They would encourage [your forefathers] to rebel against the Holy One, blessed be He. They spoke futility, and they spoke vanity, saying “peace” - but there was no peace. Therefore, they traveled. I, however, am a true prophet for them.</text>
      <text title="they were humbled: ">“to humble yourself before Me.” An expression of humility.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="My wrath is kindled against the shepherds: ">Against the kings of Greece.</text>
      <text title="upon the goats: ">Against their princes, and so did Jonathan render it: My wrath was against the kings and upon the rulers I visit. The Greeks were likened to goats in (Dan. 8:21), “And the rough he-goat is the king of Greece.” Whoever wishes to explain the matter [otherwise] (not as referring to the kings of Greece) will say that הָעַתּוּדִים is an expression of princes, as in (Isa. 14:9), “It aroused the giants for you, all the chiefs of the earth.”</text>
      <text title="as His majestic horse in battle: ">As the horse whose majesty is recognized in battle.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="Out of them shall come the cornerstone: ">Out of them shall come their kings; out of them shall come their princes, and out of them shall come those who wage their wars.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="And they shall be like mighty men, treading the mire of the streets in battle: ">This verse is inverted. It should be understood: And they shall be in battle, walking and treading people as mighty men tread the mire of the streets.</text>
      <text title="treading: ">as in (Ps. 60:14), “And He shall tread down our enemies,” and (Jer. 12:10) “They have trampled My field.”</text>
      <text title="and they shall shame the riders of horses: ">The house of Judah shall shame the riders of horses who come to wage war with them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="And I will strengthen the house of Judah: ">in the war against the Greeks.</text>
      <text title="and the house of Joseph I will save: ">in the place where they were exiled - in Halah and in Habor in the days of Sennacherib.</text>
      <text title="And I will cause them to settle: ">Like וְהוֹשַּׁבְתִּים, an expression of settling.</text>
      <text title="And they shall be as though I had not forsaken them: ">As though I had never forsaken them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="I will whistle to them: ">in the manner of those who whistle as a sign and a signal for those straying on their way to him.</text>
      <text title="and I will gather them: ">at the time of the end in the future.</text>
      <text title="for I have redeemed them: ">When I will redeem them.</text>
      <text title="And they shall multiply: ">in exile as they multiplied in Egypt.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="And I will sow them: ">first among the peoples, as a person sows a seah to bring in many korim.</text>
      <text title="And they shall live with their children: ">אֶת-בְנֵיהֶם</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="and the Lebanon: ">This is the Temple.</text>
      <text title="and it shall not suffice for them: ">Heb. וְלֹא יִמָּצֵא לָהֶם</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="And trouble shall pass through the sea: ">And the trouble shall pass through Tyre, which is situated in the midst of the sea, it is the head of Edom.</text>
      <text title="and He shall strike: ">The Holy One, blessed be He, Who is the One Who strikes.</text>
      <text title="the waves of the sea: ">to sink Tyre.</text>
      <text title="all the depths of the river: ">That is, Egypt.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="11">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Open your doors, O Lebanon: ">Jonathan renders: O peoples, open your gates.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="Wail, O cypress, for the cedar has fallen: ">[The cedar,] which is bigger than the cypress, [has fallen]. Howl, O rulers, for the kings of the nations have fallen.</text>
      <text title="Wail, O oaks of the Bashan: ">Kesnes or chesnes in Old French, chenes in Modern French.</text>
      <text title="for… has gone down: ">For it has been broken. Similar to [this expression] is (Isa. 32:19), “And He shall hail down the breaking of the forest.”</text>
      <text title="the fortified forest: ">The fortified forest, the strong walled cities.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="the shepherds: ">The kings.</text>
      <text title="for their glory: ">אַדַּרְתָּם</text>
      <text title="the roar of the young lions: ">The princes shall weep.</text>
      <text title="for the pride of the Jordan has been spoiled: ">The pride of the Jordan, which is the place of the young lions and the old lions. Our Sages (Yoma 39b) explained “Open your doors, O Lebanon,” as the prophet prophesying about the destruction of the Second Temple; that forty years prior to the destruction, the doors of the Temple proper would open by themselves. Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai rebuked them. He said, “Temple, how long will you terrify yourself? I know that you will eventually be destroyed. Zechariah the son of Iddo has already prophesied concerning you: 'Open your doors, O Lebanon, etc.’”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="Tend the flock of slaughter: ">Prepare shepherds for them; i.e., prophesy concerning their leaders who are destined to lead them from now on.</text>
      <text title="the flock of slaughter: ">Israel, whose shepherds slew them and devoured them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="and not be guilty: ">The kings of the nations among whom I will exile them; this one sells them, and the buyer slays them, without feeling (lit., “and he does not put to his heart”) that there should be guilt in the matter. The seller boasts.</text>
      <text title="Blessed be the Lord: ">Who delivered them into my hand, and behold! I am wealthy.</text>
      <text title="for I have become wealthy: ">And behold! I am wealthy.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And I tended the flock of slaughter: ">All these are the words of the Holy One, blessed be He, to the prophet: And I tended them in the early days.</text>
      <text title="indeed, the poor of the flock: ">Indeed, they were the poor of the flock when I began to tend them.</text>
      <text title="and I took for Myself two staffs: ">At the end of a period of time, I divided them into two kingdoms because of their iniquity.</text>
      <text title="one I called Pleasantness: ">Jeroboam promised to lead them gently.</text>
      <text title="and one I called Destoyers: ">Rehoboam told [his kingdom] that he would flog them with scorpions (I Kings 12:11). [Zechariah] calls their rulers staffs because it is customary to lead flocks with staffs.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="I cut off the three shepherds in one month: ">They corrupted their ways until I rejected them, and I slew all three shepherds in one month. Jehu slew the entire house of Ahab, and the house of Ahaziah the king of Judah, and his brothers, and all the seed of the kingdom of David; and Athaliah slew the rest, save Joash, who hid (II Kings 10, 11).</text>
      <text title="I could not tolerate them: ">“My soul was short with them” I rejected them. And every expression of shortness of soul denotes a distressful or disgusting matter, that a person’s thoughts cannot tolerate. His heart and his reigns are too short to contain it, as Elihu said (Job 32:18), “The spirit of my innards constrains me.”</text>
      <text title="moreover, they were too much for Me: ">Their memory was too big for My innards, and it filled My spirit and constrained My reins. The word בָּחֲלָה was explained by our Sages in tractate Niddah (47a) as an expression of largeness. The Sages depicted the development of a woman with a metaphor: פַּגָּה, unripe figs; בֹּחַל, larger figs, and צֶמֶל, completely ripe figs. She is compared to unripe figs when she is still a child; she is compared to larger figs in the days of her youth, when she is already bigger. They brought this verse as proof of their words.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="And I said, “I will not tend you…”: ">I said in those days, “I will cast them from before Me,” and they shall be free and subject to spoil.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="And I took My [first] staff, [called] Pleasantness: ">I broke the power of the kings of Israel in the days of Jehoahaz the son of Jehu - to the extent that the king of Aram destroyed them and made them like dust to trample (II Kings 13:7) - and in the days of Hoshea the son of Elah, when I delivered them into the hands of Sennacherib and he exiled them (ibid. 17:6).</text>
      <text title="to nullify My covenant that I [had] formed with all the peoples: ">To show them that because they betrayed Me, I nullified My covenant that I formed with all the peoples concerning them, that the [peoples] not harm them. For, on that condition I gave them the Torah, that if they keep it, they will be free from the kingdoms; that no nation or tongue shall rule over them. And do not be surprised if Scripture speaks of their salvation from the hands of the enemy as forming a covenant with the enemy, for we find a similar verse (Hosea 2:20): “And I will make a covenant for them on that day with the beasts of the field, etc.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="knew this: ">The righteous among them who kept My statute understood.</text>
      <text title="that it was the word of the Lord: ">This decree the Holy One, blessed be He, already spoke to us through Moses (Deut. 28:36): “The Lord shall drive you and your king.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And I said: ">to the remaining kings of Judah.</text>
      <text title="“If it pleases you, give [Me] My hire…”: ">Fulfill My commandments, and that will be My payment for all the good that I have given you; as they give hire to a shepherd, I will return and tend you.</text>
      <text title="and if not, forbear: ">And I, too, will not do good for you. We find that the Holy One, blessed be He, said similarly to Ezekiel (3:27): “He that hears, let him hear, and he that forbears, let him forbear.”</text>
      <text title="And they weighed out My hire, thirty pieces of silver: ">Jonathan paraphrases: And they performed My will with a few men. There were a few good men among them, such as the craftsmen and the sentries, Daniel, Hananiah, Mishael, Azariah, and Ezekiel. But I do not know how to explain the expression here of thirty pieces of silver exactly, except that כֶּסֶף is an expression of desire. Our Sages, too, explained it this way in Chullin (92a). They brought proof from (Prov. 7:20), “The bundle of the desirable ones He took in His hand.” The thirty they explained in the following manner: There are forty-five righteous men in every generation. They brought proof from (Hosea 3:2), “a חֹמֶר of barley and a לֶתֶ of barley” - fifteen righteous in Babylon and thirty in Eretz Israel. It is said: “And I took the thirty pieces of silver, and I cast them into the house of the Lord in Eretz Israel.” The number thirty is explained by the Midrash Aggadah (Cf. Gen. Rabbah 49:3, Pesikta d’Rav Kahana 88a), that our father Abraham was promised that no generation would have fewer than thirty righteous in men, the number of (Gen. 15:8): “So shall your seed be.” The word יִהְיֶה has the numerical value of thirty.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="And the Lord said to me: Cast it to the keeper of the treasury: ">like הָאוֹצֵר, the keeper of the treasury. Said the Holy One, blessed be He, to the prophet: Write, and leave over these and their righteousness to be preserved for the end of the seventy years of the Babylonian exile. The Temple shall be built by them. Now what is the treasury? [Cf. below]</text>
      <text title="the stronghold of glory: ">My Temple, the stronghold of My glory.</text>
      <text title="of which I stripped them: ">of which I stripped them so that they should no longer have glory. The expression יָקַרְתִּי means the removal of glory; the “mem” in מֵעֲלֵיהֶם proves it. It is like (Ps. 52:7), “and He shall uproot you from the land of the living” ; and like (Isa. 10: 33), “lops off the branches.” My explanation is similar to Jonathan’s translation. I have seen many variant versions of the explanation of this prophecy, but I cannot reconcile those with the text.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="And I cut off My second staff: ">I exiled Zedekiah.</text>
      <text title="the destroyers: ">The wicked of his generation, for he was righteous, but his generation was wicked.</text>
      <text title="to nullify the brotherhood: ">that the Judahites and the Benjamites were joined in brorherhood, and that they adhered to the abominations of the kings of Israel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="Take for yourself, etc.: ">This is what He said to him above: Tend the flock of slaughter (verse 4). This is a sign that I am destined to deliver the generation of the destruction of this Second Temple into the hands of Esau.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="Those that are cut off: ">The shepherd will not remember to seek the lost ones.</text>
      <text title="the foolish ones he shall not seek: ">Jonathan renders: Those that wandered off he shall not seek. The word הַנַּעַר means the foolish ones that do not know to enter the fold.</text>
      <text title="the one that can stand: ">The one that has a little strength to stand on its feet and requires help, [the one that needs] to be led slowly. Menahem (Machbereth p. 148) explained: and the swollen one, as in (Num. 5:22), “to cause the belly to swell.”</text>
      <text title="he shall not bear: ">Jonathan renders. he shall not bear. It is the custom of the shepherd to carry the lambs in his bosom.</text>
      <text title="And the flesh of the fat one he shall eat: ">He will finish the money of the wealthy.</text>
      <text title="and their hoofs he shall break: ">until they are finished. Daniel (7:7) stated a figure similar to this: “It devoured and broke in pieces, and the residue it trampled with its foot.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="Ho: ">There is reason to cry out concerning this.</text>
      <text title="worthless shepherd: ">a shepherd of nought. א ֶלִיל, is an expression of אַל, naught; he is not a shepherd. [There is also] (in Job 13:4) “worthless physicians.” רֹעִי The “yud” is superfluous; it is instead of a “he,” as “who abandons the flock”; (Deut. 33:16) who dwells (שׁכְנִי) in the bramble “; and (Micha 7:14) ” who dwells alone.</text>
      <text title="who abandons the flock: ">Who leaves them free for anyone who comes to beat, to slay, and to spoil.</text>
      <text title="A sword is on his arm and his right eye: ">And that shepherd carries a slaughtering knife in his hand to slaughter the fat and the healthy, upon which he cast his right eye to know who are the wealthy, to spoil and finish their property</text>
      <text title="his arm shall wither: ">In the future (as in Ezek. 25:14), “I will wreak My vengeance, etc.” The commentators, however, interpreted this as a reference to Zedekiah, an allusion to (II Kings 25:7), “and they blinded Zedekiah’s eyes.” But it is impossible to reconcile “Behold! I am setting up a shepherd in the land” as referring to Zedekiah, for seventy years had already passed after him.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="12">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="The prophecy of the word of the Lord: ">This is the completion of the word that he began to speak about the retribution of those who devour Israel - Esau and his ilk.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="a cup of weakness: ">a vessel of weakness, as in (Exod. 12:22), “in the blood that is in the cup.”</text>
      <text title="weakness: ">an expression of bewilderment, [it means] the clogging of the heart and the limbs, for, like man enwrapped in a garment, they have no strength, as in (Nahum 2:4), “And the cypress trees were enwrapped” ; and (Isa. 3:19) “And the bracelets and the veils.” In the language of the Mishnah (Shabbath 6:6) we find, “Arabian women may go out veiled.” It is involopiment in O. F.</text>
      <text title="and also on Judah: ">the nations that will be in siege against Jerusalem will impose upon Judah, for the house of David will be inside and the gentiles will besiege them. And also, the children of Judah will come, against their will, to besiege Jerusalem. So did Jonathan render it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="a stone of burden: ">A stone of burden placed upon men by order of the ruler, to carry it and to load it on their shoulders. It is very heavy, to the extent that all who bear it become gashed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="I will smite every horse: ">of those gathered there with bewilderment and blindness, and their riders with madness (Shem Ephraim). But upon the [members of the] house of Judah, who are among those gathered against their will, I will open My eyes to protect them from this plague.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="And the princes of Judah shall say to themselves: ">when they see that the others who were gathered are plagued with this plague, and they are saved.</text>
      <text title="The inhabitants of Jerusalem were my strength, etc.: ">The inhabitants of Jerusalem, who know that we came upon them against our will, strengthened my help with their prayer by the Lord, their God.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="I will make the princes of Judah: ">They will return and wage war with those who brought them there.</text>
      <text title="as a fiery stove: ">Like a great bonfire. The word כִּיוֹר is an expression of כִּירָה, a stove. So did Menahem (Machbereth, p. 109) classify it.</text>
      <text title="in its place: ">lit. under it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And the Lord shall first save the tents of Judah: ">Before the inhabitants of Jerusalem come out of the city, they shall have a salvation - to return to their tents and to their homes - and afterwards the salvation shall come to the inhabitants of the city. That is the salvation concerning which it is stated (14:3): “And the Lord shall go forth and wage war.”</text>
      <text title="so that the boasting of, etc., shall not increase: ">to boast over them and to say, “ You were saved only because of us.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="and the weakest among them: ">Heb. הַנִּכְשָׁל</text>
      <text title="like angels: ">Jonathan renders: like great ones, like angels.</text>
      <text title="like the angel of the Lord before them: ">They will prosper like the angel of the Lord before them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="I will seek to destroy: ">I will seek their destruction, and I will be exact in judging their iniquity. And our Sages (Avodah Zarah 4a) explained this verse as concerning merit. I will search in the books of their deeds; if they have merit, I will spare them; otherwise, I will destroy them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="a spirit of grace and supplications: ">That it should come into their mind to supplicate Me, and they will be in My good graces.</text>
      <text title="a spirit: ">Talant in Old French, a desire.</text>
      <text title="they shall look to Me because of those who have been thrust through: ">Jonathan renders: And they shall supplicate Me because of their wanderings. And they shall look to Me to complain about those of them whom the nations thrust through and slew during their exile.</text>
      <text title="and they shall mourn over it: ">Over that slaughter.</text>
      <text title="as one mourns over an only son: ">As a man mourns over his only son. And our Sages expounded this in tractate Sukkah (52a) as referring to the Messiah, son of Joseph, who was slain.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="like the mourning of Hadadrimmon in the Valley of Megiddon: ">Hadadrimmon has no connection to the Valley of Megiddon. These are, rather, two cases of mourning. [The first is] like the mourning of Ahab the son of Omri, who was slain by Hadadrimmon the son of Tabrimmon in Ramoth Gilead, as it is stated (I Kings 22:36): “A cry passed through the camp.” That is the mourning [of Ahab. The second case is] like the mourning of Josiah the son of Amon, who was slain by Pharoah the lame in the Valley of Megiddon, as it is stated (II Chron. 35:25): “And Jeremiah lamented for Josiah, and all the singing men and singing women spoke in their laments, etc.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="the house of Nathan: ">the prophet. Some say that it refers to Nathan the son of David, as it is said (II Sam. 5:14): “Shammua and Shobab, and Nathan and Solomon.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="the house of Levi: ">The priests and the Levites.</text>
      <text title="the family of the Shimeites: ">Shammua the son of David. Scripture first makes a generality about the house of David, and then it specifies each one.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="All the remaining families: ">of the house of David.</text>
      <text title="and their wives apart: ">because of decency. Now why were the families of the priesthood and the kingdom [mentioned]? In order to restore their crowns to them, as it is stated in the beginning of the Book (4:14): “These are the two anointed ones who stand before the Lord of all the earth.”</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="13">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="for purification and for sprinkling: ">and for sprinkling. So did Jonathan paraphrase: I will forgive their sins as they become purified with sprinkling water and with the ashes of the cow of purification; i.e., with the ashes of purification.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="And also the prophets: ">The false prophets.</text>
      <text title="and the spirit of contamination: ">The evil inclination.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="a hairy mantle: ">So is the custom of those who entice or draw away [the people], to enwrap themselves with mantles as though they are righteous men in order that their lies be accepted.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="for a man entrusted me with his cattle: ">Menahem (Machbereth p. 156, second definition.) interpreted as an expression of “livestock of flocks and livestock of cattle” (Gen. 26: 14). He entrusted me from my youth to watch his livestock.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="And one will say to him, “What are these wounds between your hands?”: ">Between your shoulders. There they flog the sinners.</text>
      <text title="in the house of my friends: ">who loved me and reproved me to the straight path.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="O sword, awaken against My shepherd: ">Against the one whom I appointed over the flock of My exile.</text>
      <text title="and against the man who is associated with Me: ">whom I associated with Me to watch My flocks as I do.</text>
      <text title="Smite the shepherd: ">The king of the border of wickedness.</text>
      <text title="and the flock shall scatter: ">The flock subjected to his rule; lit. pressed down under his hand.</text>
      <text title="and I will return My hand: ">And I will repeat My blows a second time.</text>
      <text title="upon the little ones: ">Upon the rulers who are smaller than the kings. And Jonathan renders:</text>
      <text title="and the flock shall scatter: ">And the rulers shall scatter, and he renders:</text>
      <text title="upon the little ones: ">Their officers, who are second to them. And so did Jonathan render this verse as referring to the nations: O sword, reveal yourself against the king and against the ruler, his colleague who is like him, who resembles him, said the Lord of Hosts. Slay the king, and the rulers shall scatter. This wording of the Targum does not apply to Israel, for we do not find in the Targum or in the Scriptures [any words] but “a king and princes” [when referring to Israel], and the Aramaic translation thereof is רַבְרְבִין, great ones.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="and the third shall remain therein: ">They shall proselytize and live.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="And I will bring the third in fire: ">And I will bring the third in straits in the smelting-pot of fire (Jonathan), so that some of the proselytes should bear the birth pang of the Messiah and the war of Gog and Magog with Israel. From there they shall be tested [as to] whether [or not] they are true proselytes. Then, many of those who previously converted to Judaism shall return to their pre-conversion customs and join Gog. We find [this idea] in the Aggadah (Avodah Zarah 3b; Midrash Psalms 2:5, footnote 29).</text>
      <text title="and he shall say, “The Lord…”: ">When he prays, he will pray to the Lord and not to his previous deity.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="14">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Behold! A day of the Lord is coming: ">A day dear to the Lord.</text>
      <text title="and your plunder shall be shared within you: ">Those dwelling within you shall share the plunder that you shall plunder [from] the enemies. And so does Jonathan render: And the house of Israel shall share the wealth of the peoples in your midst, O Jerusalem.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="and the rest of the people: ">Not all of them will be exiled. Now, why will He permit them [i.e., the gentile nations] to exile half of them and to plunder the houses? So that they should not have an excuse, saying, “We have not come for war, but we have come to prostrate ourselves.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="like the day he waged war on the day of battle: ">Like the day He waged war on the Red Sea.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="in the midst thereof: ">lit., from its half</text>
      <text title="toward the east and toward the west: ">From east to west, as he goes on and concludes.</text>
      <text title="and half the mountain shall move to the north, etc.: ">The northern half shall move from its place and draw toward the north, and so…</text>
      <text title="and half of it to the south: ">Toward the south; and the valley between them will have its beginning to the east and its end to the west.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="And you shall flee to the valley of the mountains: ">Jonathan renders. And the valley of the mountains shall be stopped up. Since Jerusalem is surrounded by mountains, and there is a valley between the mountains in the north and the Mount of Olives, and [this is also] so in the south, when half of the Mount of Olives draws toward the mountain in the north, the valley between them will be stopped up. [This will also be] so in the south.</text>
      <text title="shall reach: ">The height of the valley that will be between the mountains.</text>
      <text title="to Azal: ">To the height of the mountaintops that are from either side. So did Menahem classify this (Machbereth p. 32), with (Isa. 41:9) “and from its nobles I called you.” Its meaning is an expression of height.</text>
      <text title="and you shall flee: ">when you see this great wonder.</text>
      <text title="as you fled because of the earthquake: ">[Isa. 6:4] “And the doorposts quaked” on the day that Uzziah was stricken with zaraath.</text>
      <text title="all holy ones: ">Angels.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="there shall be no light, only disappearing light and thick darkness: ">Jonathan renders. There shall not be light, only light that passes away, and thickness, i.e., there shall not be splendrous light, only יְקָרוֹת and קִפָּאוֹן shall [there] be. יְקָרוֹת An expression similar to (Ps. 37: 20), “like the disappearing light over the plains.” Like a sort of light that appears in the morning over the mountains and disappears little by little. וְקִפָּאוֹן Congealed and dark and thick, like ice that is congealed and frozen, as in (Job 10:10), “And like cheese You curdled me.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And it shall be one day: ">And this thing shall be one day of the day of the Holy One, blessed be He. That day shall be known, that it is for the preparation of the salvation by the Holy One, blessed be He.</text>
      <text title="neither day: ">Neither [will it be] a light of splendor, like the light of the world to come, as it is stated (Isa. 30: 26): “The light of the sun shall be sevenfold as the light of the seven days. ”</text>
      <text title="nor night: ">Nor a time of trouble, like the trouble of the preceding subjugation by the kingdoms, shall [these days] be, for they will be the days of the Messiah, and there shall be no subjugation during these days.</text>
      <text title="and it shall come to pass that at eventide: ">Before the thousand years are up there shall be a splendrous light, and all the good promised to Israel [will come]. And so did Jonathan translate: Not like the light of day and not like the darkness of night.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="And it shall come to pass on that day: ">when the Mount of Olives will split from east to west.</text>
      <text title="spring water shall come forth from Jerusalem: ">and flow to the east by way of the crevice to…</text>
      <text title="the eastern sea: ">which is to the east of the world; and half of it will turn to the west, to the western sea. This is the spring concerning which Joel (4:18) prophesied: “And a spring shall emanate from the house of the Lord.” That is the spring concerning which Ezekiel (47:3) prophesied: “And he measured a thousand cubits and he made me pass through the water.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="shall the Lord be one: ">For all the nations shall abandon their vanities and acknowledge Him, that He is one, and [that] no strange deity is with Him.</text>
      <text title="and His name one: ">That His name shall be mentioned by everyone.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="The whole earth shall be changed: ">The whole earth shall be changed to be like a plain. The mountains will be lowered, and the whole world will be a plain; and Jerusalem will be a mountain, so that it should appear higher than everything [else in the world].</text>
      <text title="from the hill of Rimmon: ">We learned in Tosefta of Sotah (11:14): South of Jerusalem is a plain, and the hill of Rimmon is rocks and clods. Rather, so is [the] interpretation [of this phrase]: From the hill of Rimmon, which is a mountainous place from there [the mountains of the world] will begin to be changed, to [be] a plain; and they will be like the south of Jerusalem, which is a plain.</text>
      <text title="but it will be elevated high: ">Since its entire environs are a plain, it will appear high.</text>
      <text title="and remain in its old place: ">in its place</text>
      <text title="until the corner gate, and from the tower of Hananel: ">which will also be in its place; and from there shall extend the length of the city.</text>
      <text title="until the king’s wine-cellars: ">Jonathan renders: the pits off the king, fosec in Old French. [This is] like [a word in] Baba Kamma 50b, “trenches and caves.” And so, all wine cellars in Scripture are expressions of trenches, referring to the pit that is before the wine press, into which the wine flows. And the Midrash Aggadah (Pesikta d’Rav Kahana p. 143a; Song Rabbah 7: 4, cf. Mattenoth Kehunnah, Radal) [identifies] the pits of the king with the ocean: that Jerusalem will reach the end of the whole world, the pits dug out by the supreme King of kings.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="and there shall be no more destruction: ">The city shall no longer be in ruins.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="his flesh will waste away while he still stands: ">This denotes the falling off of the limbs.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="there will be great consternation, sent by the Lord upon them: ">to confuse their wisdom, to bring them about to madness.</text>
      <text title="each one will seize the hand of the other: ">He will seize him to slay him.</text>
      <text title="and his hand shall rise up: ">Whoever is stronger is victorious.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="Yea, even Judah: ">against their will shall fight against Jerusalem.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="similar to this plague: ">which is delineated above, that his flesh shall waste away.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="the festival of Tabernacle: ">As our Sages explained in tractate Avodah Zarah (3a): I have an easy commandment named Sukkah, as is stated in the first halachic discussion.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="rain: ">Actual rain to cause the produce of their land to grow. Now, what reason did He have for decreeing upon them the withholding of rain? That the commandments of the festival are based on the rains: the four species of the lulav and the water libation are to appease God for water. Since the festival of Tabernacles is the time of the rains of the year, no rain will fall on those who entertain doubts concerning the festival of Tabernacles. This is learned in the Tosefta of Sukkah (4:7).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="And if the family of Egypt does not go up: ">and they do not require rain, for the Nile comes up and waters it [i.e., the land of Egypt].</text>
      <text title="it shall not [rain] upon them: ">Their rain shall not be upon them; i.e., the Nile will not water them, and so did Jonathan render: The Nile shall not ascend upon them.</text>
      <text title="the plague will be: ">The plague of famine.</text>
      <text title="with which the Lord will plague: ">This will be the punishment of Egypt and the punishment of all the nations, as He states. “upon them there shall be no rain.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="there will be upon the bells of the horses: ">On the bells that are hung on the horse for beauty between its eyes (Pesachim 50a). Those, too, will be consecrated to make service vessels: sprinkling basins for the blood and pots to cook the flesh of the many sacrifices.</text>
      <text title="Yea, every pot… will be: ">All those that are used to remove the ashes, they too will be of gold and of silver, like the sprinkling basins that are before the altar.</text>
      <text title="the bells of the horses: ">tentinonc in Old French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="and there will no longer be a trafficker: ">They will not require trafficking, as in (Isa. 23: 8): “whose traffickers were the honored of the earth.” Another explanation: There is no poor man here.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
</book>