<book>
  <chapter id="1">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And in the first year of Cyrus, the king of Persia: ">This book is arranged as a continuation of the Book of Daniel, as is explained in Baba Bathra (15a), and the word וּבְשְׁנַת refers back from this [book] to that one, for it is stated in Daniel (9:2): “In the first year of his reign, I, Daniel, contemplated the calculations of the number of the years that the word of the Lord had come to Jeremiah the prophet from the destruction of Jerusalem, seventy years.” And so the entire chapter proceeds to relate [the story] of the destruction of the Temple, the time of the Babylonian exile, and his confession, in which he confessed Israel’s sin. The beginning of this book is as follows: After Belshazzar was assassinated, Darius the Mede reigned, as it says (Dan. 6:1): “And Darius the Mede received the kingdom etc.” and after Darius’ death, this Cyrus, the king of Persia, reigned, and in the first year of his reign, the seventy years for the remembrance of the Babylonian exile, [counting] from the day that Jehoiakim was exiled, were completed, as it says (Jer. 29: 10): “At the completion of seventy years of Babylon, I will remember you etc.” When Israel returned from the Babylonian exile to the land of Israel, in that year, in the first year of Cyrus, Israel laid the foundation of the Temple, and the adversaries of Judah and Benjamin slandered them to Cyrus, the king of Persia, and he commanded [them] to curtail the work, no longer to build the edifice of the Temple; and the Israelites were idle, for they did not build the Temple during the entire reign of Cyrus and Ahasuerus, who succeeded him, until the second year of Darius, the son of Ahasuerus, the king of Persia, who was Darius, the son of Esther. And in the second year of his reign, they began building the Temple until the building was completed. And from the first year of Cyrus until the second year of Darius, the son of Ahasuerus the king of Persia, in whose days the Temple was built, were eighteen years, to fulfill what was said (Dan. 9:2): “from the destruction of Jerusalem, seventy years etc.” And now, in the second year of Darius, seventy years had elapsed since the destruction of Jerusalem; [i.e.,] the destruction of the Temple, when Zedekiah was exiled. From the exile of Jehoiakim until the exile of Zedekiah, when the Temple was destroyed, were eighteen years, and now in the first year of Cyrus, the king of Persia, seventy years since the exile of Jehoiakim, when Israel was exiled to Babylon, were completed, and thereby the verse that states (Jer. 29:10): “for at the completion of seventy years of Babylon I will remember you etc.” was fulfilled. And this is the remembrance, that Israel returned to their soil and built the foundation of the building of the Temple, although it was not yet completed. We find that there were fifty- two years from the exile of Zedekiah, when the Temple was destroyed, until the first year of Cyrus, the king of Persia; and eighteen years after the first year of Cyrus, which is the second year of Darius, when Israel commenced to build the edifice, and they completed it. This is proven in Seder Olam (ch. 29), in Tractate Megillah (11b) and in this book, as I explained.</text>
      <text title="at the completion of the word of the Lord from the mouth of Jeremiah: ">at the time that the word of the Holy One, blessed be He, which Jeremiah spoke, was completed, as it says (Jer. 29:10): “for at the completion of seventy years of Babylon etc.”</text>
      <text title="the Lord aroused the spirit: ">the will.</text>
      <text title="a proclamation: ">He proclaimed a proclamation throughout his kingdom.</text>
      <text title="and also in writing: ">And he also sent his letter throughout his kingdom about this matter.</text>
      <text title="saying: ">And so he said to them in his proclamation that he proclaimed and in his epistle that he sent throughout his kingdom.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="So said Cyrus, the king of Persia… delivered to me: ">that I am the king and ruler over all the kingdoms.</text>
      <text title="and He commanded me: ">He commanded me through Isaiah the prophet to build for Him the Temple in Jerusalem, as it says in the Book of Isaiah (44:28): “Who says to Cyrus, ‘He is My shepherd, and all My desire he shall fulfill,’ and to say to Jerusalem, ‘It shall be built, and the Temple shall be founded.’” (ibid. 45:1): “So said the Lord to His anointed one, to Cyrus, whose right hand I held….” And this prophecy was already stated by lsaiah.</text>
      <text title="in Jerusalem, which is in Judea: ">whch is in the province of Judea.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="Who is among you: ">So did he announce and write to all the kingdoms, “Who is among you of all His people,” [i.e., of the people] of the Holy One, blessed be He, may the Holy One, blessed be He, be at his assistance, and let him ascend to build His house that is in Jerusalem.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="And whoever remains: ">and every Jew who remains in his place, who cannot ascend because he has no money.</text>
      <text title="shall help him: ">I command the people of his place to provide him and help him with silver, gold, possessions and cattle, in order that he be able to ascend to Jerusalem with the donation that the people of his place will donate for the building of the Temple, for also among the nations there were some who contributed donations to the building of the Temple.</text>
      <text title="to the House of God, which is in Jerusalem: ">From “So said Cyrus” until here is the proclamation and the message of the written epistle.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="of Judah and Benjamin: ">the heads of the families of the tribes of Judah and Benjamin.</text>
      <text title="all whom… inspired: ">They ascended to Jerusalem to build the Temple with all those whom God inspired to ascend and to build the Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="And all those around them: ">And all the nations who were Israel’s neighbors assisted and strengthened the hands of the Jews with gold and silver and all these gifts in order that they be able to ascend to Jerusalem.</text>
      <text title="besides all that was donated: ">All this the neighbors of the Jews did, besides what they [the Jews] themselves donated for the building of the Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="and had placed them in the temple of his god: ">that Nebuchadnezzar had placed in the temple of his pagan deity.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="by the hand of Mithderath the treasurer: ">such was the name of Cyrus’s treasurer, and Cyrus commanded [him] to take them out.</text>
      <text title="and he counted them out: ">This treasurer counted them and delivered them to Sheshbazzar, so that he would carry them and transport them to Jerusalem. Our Rabbis said: “Sheshbazzar is identical with Daniel, and why was he called Sheshbazzar? Because he endured six troubles (שֵּׁשּׁ צָרוֹת).”</text>
      <text title="the prince of Judah: ">He is the prince of the tribe of Judah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="their number: ">of the vessels of the House of the Lord.</text>
      <text title="basins: ">Heb. אֲגַרְטְלֵי. They are kinds of vessels.</text>
      <text title="knives: ">Heb. מַחֲלָפִים. They are knives, and this expression refers to the chamber of the knives (בֵּית הַחֲלִיפוֹת). Because they would deposit the knives therein, it was called the chamber of the depository of the knives (לִשְּׁכַּת בֵּית הַחֲלִיפוֹת).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="bowls: ">Heb. כְּפוֹרֵי, bowls, and they were called כְּפוֹרֵי from an expression of wiping, like (Bava Mezia 24b): “who wiped (דְּכָפַר) his hands on his neighbor’s cloak,” because the one who would receive the blood in a bowl would wipe the squirtings of the blood that splattered on his hand on the rim of the bowl.</text>
      <text title="secondary: ">Heb. מִשְּׁנִים, secondary ones, other vessels of another kind.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="All the vessels: ">Now he totals the sum of those counted and those who were not counted all into one number, but the important ones he counts.</text>
      <text title="when the exiles were brought up: ">Heb. הֵעָלוֹת, [a passive] expression.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="2">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And these are the people of the province: ">These are the Children of Israel who are from the province of the land of Israel, who are now coming up to Jerusalem from the captivity that is in the exile.</text>
      <text title="and they returned: ">And now they returned to Jerusalem.</text>
      <text title="and Judea: ">And the people of Judea returned, each one to his city.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="[Those] who came: ">these people of the province, in the beginning, when they went into exile from Israel to Babylon with Zerubbabel etc.</text>
      <text title="Mispar… the number: ">Heb. מִסְפָּר. [This word appears twice in this verse.] In the first one, the “pay” is vowelized with a “kamatz,” and it is the name of a man; in the second, the “pay” is vowelized with a “pattah” , and it is the construct state, [meaning the number of].</text>
      <text title="the important men of the people of Israel: ">These were the great and important people, and the others followed them. Therefore, they were counted after them separately.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="The children of Parosh, etc.: ">There are some in the chapter for whom the father’s name is used for the family name [surname] and there are some who are called by the name of their place, i.e., “the children of such-and-such a place.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="The priests: the children of Jedaiah: ">Until here, he counted the children of Judah and Benjamin, and from now on he counts the priests and the Levites, as he says above (1:5): “So the heads of the families of Judah and Benjamin and the priests and the Levites arose….”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="41">
      <text title="The singers: ">The Levites who were singers, and likewise, the gatekeepers are Levites who were gatekeepers of the gates of the Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="43">
      <text title="The Nethinim: ">Now he counts those Nethinim who were woodcutters and water-drawers for the congregation, and from there they derived their livelihood.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="58">
      <text title="and the children of Solomon’s slaves: ">King Solomon had slaves, and these children were of their descendants.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="59">
      <text title="And these were the ones who ascended from Tel-Mela, etc.: ">And what incident happened to them? They could not tell….</text>
      <text title="and their children: ">[i.e., the children] of their fathers, because they lost their genealogical records and did not know if they were Israelites.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="60">
      <text title="The children of Delaiah: ">They too are included in “these were the ones who ascended from Tel- Melah.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="61">
      <text title="who took: ">Each one of the sons of Barzillai the Gileadite took a wife.</text>
      <text title="and was called by their name: ">And the name of Barzillai was called on their name because they took of his daughters.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="62">
      <text title="These: ">referring to the priests, who had to trace their lineage with that record, and who could not find the record of their lineage.</text>
      <text title="and they were disqualified: ">Heb. וַיְגאַלוּ, for they were defiled and purged from the priesthood that they should no longer perform the service with the remaining priests, because their genealogical record was not found.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="63">
      <text title="Hattirshatha: ">That is Nehemiah, the son of Hachaliah (Neh. 8:9), and our Rabbis said (Yerushalmi Kid. 4:1) that he was named Hattirshatha because the Sages permitted him (הָתֵּר) to drink (שָּׁתָּא) wine of gentiles because he was the king’s butler.</text>
      <text title="of the most holy sacrifices: ">sin-offerings and guilt-offerings, like the other priests.</text>
      <text title="until a priest arises, etc.: ">like a person who says to his friend, “Until the Messiah comes, this matter will not come about.” I cannot interpret it to mean: until a priest arises for the Urim and Tumim in the Second Temple, because we find in Yoma, chapter 1 (21b) that the Urim and Tumim were missing in the Second Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="64">
      <text title="The entire congregation together: ">When they were all together with the priests, the Levites and the Nethinim, they amounted to this number; and the Children of Israel counted above were of the tribe of Judah and Benjamin, and those missing from this number, which you will not find above, were of the other tribes. So it is explained in Seder Olam (ch. 29): “ ‘The entire congregation together was forty-two thousand etc.’ But if you add them up, they are only thirty thousand. Where are the thirteen thousand? They ascended from the other tribes.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="65">
      <text title="Besides their slaves and their bondwomen: ">who were not included in the congregation.</text>
      <text title="and they had two hundred male and female singers: ">because they were going up joyfully from Babylon to the land of Israel, they required male and female singers in order that they should stroll among them in their great joy.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="68">
      <text title="donated: ">They were donating toward the building of the Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="69">
      <text title="According to their ability: ">according to their ability and their money.</text>
      <text title="drachmas: ">Heb. דַּרְכְּמוֹנִים, the name of a golden coin.</text>
      <text title="and priests’ tunics: ">in which to serve.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="3">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="arrived: ">Heb. וַיִגַע like וְהִגִיעַ, it reached.</text>
      <text title="The seventh month: ">That is the month of Tishri, and the Children of Israel who were in the cities, what did they do? They all gathered as one to Jerusalem.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And they set the altar on its bases: ">in order to offer up sacrifices upon it, because they were afraid of the peoples of the land, lest they taunt them and lest they slander them to the king. And they built the altar to offer up burnt offerings upon it, in order that the peoples hear and understand the matter, that they did it with the sanction of the king and therefore they would hesitate to taunt them about the building of the Temple.</text>
      <text title="for the morning and for the evening: ">the daily sacrifice of the morning and the daily sacrifice of twilight.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="and the burnt offering of each day in its day, in the number: ">the sacrifices of the Festivals in their number, according to their ordinance.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="And afterwards: ">And after Succoth they would offer up sacrifices every day, for the morning and for the evening.</text>
      <text title="and for the New Moon: ">lit. and for the months. And at the beginning of the months they would offer up the sacrifices of the New Moon.</text>
      <text title="and for all the appointed seasons of the Lord: ">and for the rest of the appointed seasons of their sacrifices.</text>
      <text title="and for everyone who willingly offered: ">And for all those who willingly offered their free-will offerings, the priests would accept them to sacrifice them, and from the first day of Tishri they commenced to offer up sacrifices, but the foundation of the Temple was not yet built.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="to the Zidonians and to the Tyrians: ">the people of Tyre and Zidon, who were the artisans who built the Temple.</text>
      <text title="to the sea of Jaffa: ">By way of the sea they would bring them.</text>
      <text title="according to the sanction of: ">Heb. כְּרִשְׁיוֹן as the sanction of the king was upon them to build the Temple. כְּרִשְׁיוֹן is an expression of permission (רְשּׁוּת) derived from רשּׁה; since from אבה to want, he says [i.e., derives] אֶבְיוֹן, a needy person; and from צבה, to desire, צִבְיוֹן, desire; and from חזה to see, חִזָיוֹן, a vision; and from רעה, רַעְיוֹן, thought; from חבה, חֶבְיוֹן, hiding; and from רשּׁה, he says רְשּׁוּת, permission; like from, ענה, עֱנוּת, affliction; and from שּׁבה, שְּׁבוּת, captivity; and from ראה, רְאוּת, a sight; and from זנה, זְנוּת, harlotry. The result is that רְשּׁוּת and רִשְׁיוֹן are derived from the same root according to the gauge of grammar, and they are the same expression. Menahem, (p. 34) however, associated it with (Ps. 21: 3): “and the speech of his lips (וַאֲרֶשֶּׁת),” but he was not exact with its root. Nevertheless, these two manners [of defining words] are close to each other in their meanings.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="in the second month: ">That is the month of Iyar.</text>
      <text title="from the captivity: ">all those who came from the captivity to Jerusalem.</text>
      <text title="and they stationed: ">They stationed the Levite singers to harmonize and to recite a song before the builders at the time of the building of the foundation of the Temple.</text>
      <text title="to conduct: ">Heb. לְנַצֵחַ. These two expressions of נִצוּחַ are harmonies of song, like (Ps. 4:1): “To the conductor (לַּמְנַצֵחַ), a song of David.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="And Jeshua… stood: ">They stood and recited the song together around the ones who did the work of the foundation of the Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="And… laid the foundation: ">וְיִסְדוּ This is the strong conjugation of יְסוֹד, like (Ezek. 25:4): “and they will settle (וְיִשְּׁבוּ) their palaces.” Just as וְיִשְּׁבוּ is derived from ישּׁב so is וְיִסְדוּ derived from יסד, and their meaning is, וְיִסְדוּ וְיִשְּׁבוּ in the intensive conjugation with two “yud” s, one for the [continuous] action and one for the radical, and their meaning is that they were laying the foundation, they were settling.</text>
      <text title="And the builders laid the foundation: ">And the builders were laying the foundation [see above] of the Temple of the Lord at the time [that] they were harmonizing in their song, and they stationed the priests attired with elegant garments with trumpets in their hands to sound them.</text>
      <text title="and the Levites the sons of Asaph: ">were the singers.</text>
      <text title="with cymbals: ">Heb. בַּמְצִלְתַּיִם, like (Ps. 150:9): “with loud sounding cymbals (בְּצִלְצְלֵי שָּׁמַע).” They are musical instruments.</text>
      <text title="through David: ">for they were harmonizing and singing songs of David, the king of Israel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="And they sang aloud: ">Heb. וַיַעֲנוּ, an expression of raising the voice in song, like (Exod. 15:21): “And Miriam raised her voice in song to them.”</text>
      <text title="and with thanks: ">and with thanksgivings.</text>
      <text title="for it is good: ">to give thanks to the Lord.</text>
      <text title="and the entire people: ">the rest of the people of Israel.</text>
      <text title="because… was laid: ">They acted with all these rejoicings because of the building of the foundation, which was laid in the House of the Lord.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="when its foundation was laid: ">Heb. בְּיָסְדוֹ, with its foundation. With the noun of יוֹסֶד and from יסד, he says בְּיָסְדוֹ, like from חדֶשּׁ, בְּחָדְשּׁוֹ, and from קדֶשּׁ, בְּקָדְשּׁוֹ.</text>
      <text title="this Temple: ">When they would see the building of this Temple, they would weep because they remembered the large building of the First Temple.</text>
      <text title="and many: ">who had not seen the building of the First Temple, were rejoicing and shouting for joy with a loud voice, out of their great joy that they had emerged from their exile.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="And the people did not recognize: ">Those listeners did not recognize the voice of the shout of joy, because of the voice of the people’s weeping, for the rejoicing people were shouting with a great shout, and the voice of weeping was heard farther and farther away.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="4">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="the adversaries of Judah and Benjamin: ">They are the nations whom Sannecherib settled in the land Israel, as it says (II Kings 17: 24): “And the king of Assyria brought [people] from Babylonia and from Cuthah and from Avvah and from Hamath and from Sepharvaim, and he settled them in the cities of Samaria instead of the Children of Israel.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="and said to them, “Let us build with you…”: ">They said this in order that through them the work of the Temple should be disrupted, that they should build no more.</text>
      <text title="since the days of Esarhaddon the king of Assyria: ">the son of Sannecherib, for after Sannecherib settled them there, as it says (II Kings 29:37, Isa. 37:38): “And he was prostrating himself in the temple of Nisroch his god, and Adramelech and Sharezer, his sons, slew him by the sword etc., and his son Esarhaddon reigned in his stead.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="but we: ">Heb. כִּי, but we alone shall build. This כִּי serves in place of אֶלָּא, but.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="the people of the land: ">They are the adversaries of Judah and Benjamin.</text>
      <text title="were hindering: ">to disrupt them from their work.</text>
      <text title="from building: ">Heb. לִבְנוֹת, lit. to build, and so (Gen. 41:49): “until one ceased to count (לִסְפֹּר).”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="And they would hire: ">Heb. וְסֹכְרִים. This is written with a “sammech,” but its meaning is as though it was written with a “sin,” [meaning] that they would hire advisors to disrupt the work.</text>
      <text title="all the days of: ">the reign of Cyrus and the reign of Ahasuerus, who reigned after Cyrus, until the second year of Darius, who reigned after Ahasuerus, the work was stopped.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="And in the reign of Ahasuerus: ">who reigned after Cyrus; he is the Ahasuerus who took Esther.</text>
      <text title="they wrote an accusation: ">not to build the Temple.</text>
      <text title="against the dwellers of Judea and Jerusalem: ">to inform on them and to chide them not to build the Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And in the days of Artaxerxes: ">He is Cyrus, the king of Persia. The numerical value of the letters of כּרֶשּׁ equal the numerical value of the letters of דָּרְיָוֶשּׁ : [כ = 20; ר = 200; שּׁ = 300; total = 520. ד = 4; ר = 200; י = 10; 520 ו = 6; שּׁ = 300; total = 520.] And so we learned in Tractate Rosh Hashanah (3b): “The same one is Cyrus, who is Darius, who is Artaxerxes.” [He was called Cyrus כּרֶשּׁ because he was a worthy (כָּשֵּׁר) king; Artaxerxes, because of the kingdom, and in Seder Olam (ch. 30): “Darius was Artaxerxes (אַרְתַּחְשַּׁשְּׁתָּא), and the entire kingdom was called Artaxerxes, etc.” [meaning that all the kings were called Artaxerxes].</text>
      <text title="wrote with peace: ">wrote his letter with words of peace.</text>
      <text title="Mithredath Tabeel: ">This is the name of a man, one of the adversaries of Judah and Benjamin.</text>
      <text title="and the rest of his colleagues: ">Heb. כְּנָותָיו, his companies and his societies.</text>
      <text title="to Artaxerxes: ">[as translated,] to Artaxerxes.</text>
      <text title="and the script of the epistle: ">Heb. וּכְתָב הַנִשְּׁתְּוָן.</text>
      <text title="written in Aramaic: ">in Aramaic characters.</text>
      <text title="and explained in Aramaic: ">The script was explained in the Aramaic language.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="Rehum was the secretary: ">Rehum was the secretary and the master of words to compose the epistle.</text>
      <text title="and Shimshai was the scribe: ">And Shimshai was the scribe: he is Shimshai the son of Haman. So it is customary to mention the scribe and the secretary together because they need each other; one composes and dictates, and the scribe writes, as it says (I Kings 4: 3): “Eliphoreph and Ahiah, the sons of Shisha, scribes, Jehoshaphat, the son of Ahlud, the secretary,” and in another place it says (Isa. 36:22): “And Eliakim, the son of Hilkiah etc. and Shebna the scribe, and Joah, the son of Asaph the secretary, came.”</text>
      <text title="they wrote a letter: ">These two, Rehum and Shimshai, wrote the letter as Mithredath Tabeel had commanded them, and they all were dwellers of the cities of Samaria.</text>
      <text title="about Jerusalem: ">about the building of the Temple, which is in Jerusalem.</text>
      <text title="as is stated: ">Aram. כְּנֵמָא, as is stated, and that is similar to the expression of the Gemara: “as we wish to say further.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Then: ">Aram. אֱדַיִן, equivalent to the Hebrew אָז.</text>
      <text title="Rehum: ">the name of a man.</text>
      <text title="the secretary: ">Aram. בְּעֵל טְעֵם secretary and master of words.</text>
      <text title="the Dinites, the Apharesattechites, etc.: ">All these are names of nations whom Sennacherib repatriated in the cities of Samaria.</text>
      <text title="the Apharesites: ">They are the Persians whom Sennacherib settled in the cities of Samaria.</text>
      <text title="the Archevites: ">They are the people of Erech, as it says (Gen. 10:10): “and Erech and Accad and Calneh.”</text>
      <text title="the Babylonians: ">the people of Babylon.</text>
      <text title="the Shushanchites: ">the people of Shushan, the capital.</text>
      <text title="the Elamites: ">the people of Elam. Sennacherib settled all of these peoples in the land of Israel, and all of them were settling and concurring with the commission of this letter.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="And the rest of the nations: ">and the rest of the nations that Sennacherib exiled; they have all concurred.</text>
      <text title="Asenappar: ">Sennacherib.</text>
      <text title="the great and honored: ">for he was a great and honored king, as it says (Isa. 36:4): “So has the great king, the king of Assyria, said.”</text>
      <text title="in the cities of Samaria: ">in the cities surrounding Samaria.</text>
      <text title="and the rest of the other side of the river: ">and the rest of the nations that are on the other side of the river; because the river Euphrates intervenes between the land of Israel and Babylon, those nations that are in Israel are on the opposite side of the river of those found in Babylon.</text>
      <text title="and Ke’eneth: ">a name of a place; and all the people of Ke’eneth have concurred with the commission of this letter.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="This is the meaning of the letter: ">and this is the interpretation of the letter.</text>
      <text title="the meaning: ">Aram. פַּרְשֶּׁגֶן like (Esther 3:14): "The meaning of (פַּתְשֶּׁגֶן) the writ.</text>
      <text title="that they sent to him: ">[as translated,] that they sent to him.</text>
      <text title="to Artaxerxes: ">[as translated,] to Artaxerxes.</text>
      <text title="Your servants are the people of the other side of the river and Ke’eneth: ">The people of the other side of the river and the people of Ke’eneth are your servants. All the nations counted here are included in this generalization, for they were all on the side of the land of Israel, which is on the opposite side of the river of those dwelling in Babylon, and this is the beginning of the letter: “Your servants are the people of the other side of the river etc.” until, “… you will have no part.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="Let it be known to the king: ">Let it be a known thing to the king.</text>
      <text title="that the Jews: ">that the Jews who ascended from you upon us have come to Jerusalem.</text>
      <text title="the rebellious and sinful city they are building: ">[as translated,] a rebellious and sinful city they are building.</text>
      <text title="the walls they have completed: ">[as translated,] the walls they have completed.</text>
      <text title="and the walls: ">[as translated,] and the walls.</text>
      <text title="they have joined: ">Aram. יָחִיטוּ, an expression of a thread, like (Gen. 14:23): “not from a thread, (מִחוּטּ) ,” for they are “sewing” and joining the walls one to another.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="Now let it be known: ">Now let it be known to the king.</text>
      <text title="that if this city is built: ">[as translated,] that if this city is built.</text>
      <text title="this: ">[as translated,] this.</text>
      <text title="and the walls are founded: ">[as translated,] and the walls are founded.</text>
      <text title="the king’s due, the head tax, or the meal tax: ">They are types of taxes and the money for the head taxes.</text>
      <text title="they will not give: ">They will no longer pay taxes.</text>
      <text title="and the tax of the kings will suffer: ">[as translated,] and the tax of the kings will suffer, for they will no longer give tax to the kings.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="Now in view of this, that we wish to destroy the Temple: ">Now in view of this matter, that we wish to implement the destruction of the Temple. דִי מְלַח is an expression of destruction and desolation, like Jer. 17:6): “barren (מְלֵחָה) land that is uninhabitable.”</text>
      <text title="we wish to destroy: ">We wish to demolish and to destroy.</text>
      <text title="and… the king’s disgrace: ">Aram. מַלְכָּא וְעַרְוַת, lit. and the king’s nakedness.</text>
      <text title="it is improper: ">Aram. לָא אַרִי, it is improper for us to see. אַרִי means proper, like “Is it proper (אַרִי) or improper (לָא אַרִי) ?” in Tractate Succah (44b).</text>
      <text title="therefore: ">therefore we have sent and notified the king.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="That one should search: ">that a seeker should search and seek in the annals of your fathers, the first kings.</text>
      <text title="and you will find: ">And you will find in the annals, and you will know that this city is a rebellious city, and it injures the kings and the countries.</text>
      <text title="and they have made rebellion in its midst: ">And its inhabitants were making rebellion in its midst, for Israel would rebel against the kings of the nations.</text>
      <text title="since days of yore: ">Aram. מִן יוֹמָת עָלְמָא, from days of yore. Since ancient times, it has been their custom to rebel against the kings of the nations.</text>
      <text title="because of this: ">Because of this, this city was destroyed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="We make known to the king: ">[as translated,] we make known to the king.</text>
      <text title="that if this city: ">that if this city is built, and its walls are founded.</text>
      <text title="because of this: ">In view of this and because of this, you will have no part in the entire other side of the river, because Israel will rebel against you and take everything out of your hands.</text>
      <text title="in the other side of the river: ">That is the entire area of the side of Israel, which is on the other side of the river of those who are in Babylon.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="The king sent a word: ">Aram. מַלְכָּא פִּתְגָּמָא שְּׁלַח</text>
      <text title="to Rehum the secretary: ">to Rehum the secretary, and Shimshai the scribe, and to the rest of their companies, who dwelt in the cities of Samaria, and to the rest of the nations who were on the other side of the river of the side of the land of Israel.</text>
      <text title="Shelam and Ke’eth: ">They are places, like “and Ke’eneth.” Sometimes he calls it this and sometimes that.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="The letter: ">The writ of the letter that you sent to us was explained and read before me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="the order was given: ">And the order was given by me, the matter of a command that I commanded.</text>
      <text title="and they searched and found: ">And they searched in the annals of the kings and found written that this city, from days of yore, would raise itself up and exalt itself over all the kings of the nations, and rebellion and disobedience were committed there to rebel against the kings of the nations.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="And mighty kings: ">and mighty kings were in Jerusalem who were the rulers and governors over the entire side of the river on the side of Israel, as it says regarding Solomon (I Kings 5:4): “For he had dominion over all this side of the river, etc.” And taxes and the head tax were given to them, for the nations paid them tribute.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="Now issue an order: ">Now give out a word to announce in the land to stop these men, the Children of Israel, from the work, and the city of Jerusalem shall not be built until orders are given with my knowledge and my authorization.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="And beware of committing an error: ">And you shall beware of committing any postponement or error. שָּׁלוּ is desto(u)rber in Old French, to violate.</text>
      <text title="of committing… in this matter: ">[as translated,] of committing in this manner.</text>
      <text title="Why should… increase: ">Why should the act of destruction in this city increase to injure the kings? Until here is Cyrus’ reply, which he sent back.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="then: ">[as translated,] then.</text>
      <text title="since the interpretation: ">Since the interpretation of the writ of the letter of Artaxerxes the king-he is Cyrus-this incident took place.</text>
      <text title="was read before: ">for the writ of this letter was read before Rehum and Shimshai and their companies, and they went with speed and haste to Jerusalem, to the Jews, and stopped them with force and might from continuing the construction of the edifice.</text>
      <text title="to the Jews: ">Aram. עַל יְהוּדָיֵא, lit. On the Jews.</text>
      <text title="and they: ">Aram. הִמוֹ, equivalent to הֵם.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="Then: ">Then the work of the building of the House of God, which was in Jerusalem, was suspended until the second year of Darius, the king of Persia; for after Cyrus, Ahasuerus, who married Esther, reigned, and after Ahasuerus, Darius, the son of Ahasuerus, who was the son of Esther, reigned. And from the first year of Cyrus, the king of Persia, until the second year of Darius were eighteen years, which completed the seventy years from the destruction of Jerusalem. For from the destruction of the Temple, when Zedekiah was exiled, until the first year of Cyrus, were fifty-two years, as is explained in Seder Olam (ch. 29). There were then eighteen years from the first year of Cyrus until the second year of Darius, totaling a complete seventy years, and in the second year of Darius they commenced to build the Temple until they completed it.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="5">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Now Haggai the prophet… prophesied: ">And now in the second year of Darius, there came a prophecy to Haggai and Zechariah, the prophets to the Jews who were in the land of Judea and in Jerusalem, in the Name of the God of Israel to them, to build the edifice of the Temple without the authorization of King Darius.</text>
      <text title="to the Jews: ">Aram. עָל יְהוּדָיֵא lit. On the Jews.</text>
      <text title="to them: ">Aram. עֲלֵיהוֹן, lit. on them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="Then: ">[as translated,] then.</text>
      <text title="and commenced: ">They began to build the House of the Holy One, blessed be He, which is in Jerusalem, and with them were the prophets of the Holy One, blessed be He, helping and assisting them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="At that time, there came upon them: ">At that time, there came upon them these adversaries of Judah and Benjamin to accuse and to slander them regarding the matter of the building.</text>
      <text title="the governor of the other side of the river: ">[as translated,] the governor of the other side of the river.</text>
      <text title="and their companies: ">[as translated,] and their companies.</text>
      <text title="and so they said to them: ">[as translated,] and so they said to them.</text>
      <text title="Who issued to you: ">Who ordered you, regarding the matter of building the Temple?</text>
      <text title="and to found these walls: ">Aram. וְאֻשַּׁרְנָא, and to found these walls, like (4:12): “and the walls (וְאֻשַּׁיָא) they have joined,” the building of walls of bricks (לְבֵנִים) so did Menahem (p. 36) associate it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="Then: ">[as translated,] then.</text>
      <text title="as we will say: ">[as translated,] as we will say.</text>
      <text title="they said to them: ">Those adversaries of Judah and Benjamin said to them [i.e.,] to Israel.</text>
      <text title="What are: ">What are the names of the men?</text>
      <text title="who… this: ">who are building this building.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="And the eye of their God: ">And the eye of the Holy One, blessed be He, Who is their God, was on the elders of the Jews to upraise them (sic) in the work of the building.</text>
      <text title="and they did not stop them: ">And they did not stop the builders.</text>
      <text title="until the matter came to Darius: ">And the elders of the Jews answered a word to those adversaries that they should not stop the building until the matter would go to King Darius.</text>
      <text title="and then they would answer: ">And then the Jews would answer the writ of the letter concerning this, concerning Darius’ reply.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="The interpretation: ">the interpretation of the text of the letter.</text>
      <text title="and his companies: ">[as translated,] and his companies.</text>
      <text title="the Apharsechites: ">They are one nation that was in their companies.</text>
      <text title="to King Darius: ">Aram. מַלְכָּא עַל דָּרְיָוֶשּׁ, lit. on King Darius.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="to him: ">Aram. עֲלוֹהִי, lit. on him.</text>
      <text title="and so was written in it: ">and so was written in the letter.</text>
      <text title="all peace: ">All peace shall be his.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="Let it be known to the king: ">Let it be a known thing to the king.</text>
      <text title="that we went: ">that we went to the land of the province of Judea, to the House of the great God.</text>
      <text title="and it is built: ">And it, the House, is built.</text>
      <text title="marble: ">Aram. גְּלָּל (marmre in Old French), marble.</text>
      <text title="and wood is laid in the walls: ">And wood is placed in the walls to reinforce the building in order that it endure for a long time.</text>
      <text title="was done quickly: ">Aram. אָסְפַּרְנָא מִתְעַבְדָה, was done quickly. אָסְפַּרְנָא is (espleytosement in Old French), rapidly.</text>
      <text title="and they succeeded at it: ">Aram. וּמַצְלַח בְּיֶדְהם. And this work was successful in their hands.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Then: ">When we saw the building, we asked these elders.</text>
      <text title="as follows we said to them: ">As we will say immediately following, we said to them.</text>
      <text title="Who issued to you: ">Who issued to you the authorization to build this house and to found these walls?</text>
      <text title="and… wall: ">the building of a wall of bricks.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="also… their names: ">We also asked them the names of the builders, the heads of the construction, in order to let you know.</text>
      <text title="that we should write: ">that we should write to you the names of the men.</text>
      <text title="who are at their head: ">in whose counsel and authorization they arose to build the House.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="And as follows: ">Aram. וּכְנֵמָא, as we shall state the matter.</text>
      <text title="they gave us a reply: ">They answered us a word.</text>
      <text title="We are: ">We are the servants of the God of the heavens and the earth.</text>
      <text title="and we are building the House: ">And we are building the House that was built many years ago.</text>
      <text title="and a great king of Israel: ">And a great king that Israel had, viz. King Solomon, built it and founded it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="But now: ">But now, since our forefathers angered the God of the heavens, He delivered them into the hands of the Chaldean king of Babylon, and he destroyed this House and exiled the people to Babylon.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="But: ">But in the first year of Cyrus, king of Babylon, Cyrus issued a command to build the House.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="And also the vessels: ">the holy vessels of silver and gold, which Nebuchadnezzar had taken out of the Temple that is in Jerusalem and brought to his temple that is in Babylon. Cyrus took them out of the temple of the king of Babylon and delivered them to the hand of Sheshbazzar-Daniel, who was called by that name.</text>
      <text title="and brought them: ">[as translated,] and brought them.</text>
      <text title="had taken out: ">[as translated,] had taken them out.</text>
      <text title="whom he appointed governor: ">for he was a prince and a governor and was called by the name governor.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="And he said to him: ">And so did Cyrus say to Sheshbazzar, “Take these vessels and bring them down into the Temple that is in Jerusalem, and the House of the Holy One, blessed be He, shall be built on its place.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="then: ">[as translated,] then.</text>
      <text title="this Sheshbazzar: ">Aram. דֵּ, came and built the walls of the House of the Holy One, blessed be He, that is in Jerusalem, and from then until now, the House has been built, but the building has not been completed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="And now: ">And now, if it pleases the king, let the matter be known and searched out in the king’s archives, which is located in Babylon.</text>
      <text title="whether it is so: ">whether this incident is so, that permission was issued by Cyrus to build this House, which is in Jerusalem.</text>
      <text title="and the will of the king: ">And the will of the king concerning this he shall send to us.</text>
      <text title="to us: ">Aram. עֲלֶינָא, lit. on us. Until here is the text of the letter that Tattenai and Shethar- bozenai sent.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="6">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Then: ">then when the letter reached Darius’s hand.</text>
      <text title="gave an order: ">The king ordered the matter.</text>
      <text title="and they searched: ">They searched in the library where the archives were stored in Babylon.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="And there was found in a pouch: ">And a text of one scroll was found there in an אַחְמְתָא. So did the interpreters interpret, that it is a receptacle made for letters, written sheets and books, and they established it from the root of (Gen. 21:14): “a skin of water (וְחֵמַת מַיִם) ,” and the “aleph” in the word is not a radical, like the rest of the Aramaic language.</text>
      <text title="in the citadel: ">in that citadel that was in the province of Media.</text>
      <text title="and so was written: ">and so was written therein its memorandum.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="the House of God in Jerusalem: ">regarding the House of God in Jerusalem; what should be with it?“The House should be built.”</text>
      <text title="a place where they offer up sacrifices: ">which is a place where they offer up sacrifices.</text>
      <text title="and its walls should be founded: ">Aram. וְאֻשּׁוֹהִי. And its walls should be founded, like (4: 12): “and its walls (וְאֻשַּׁיָא) they have joined.”</text>
      <text title="its height sixty cubits: ">the height of the House was sixty cubits, and sixty cubits was its width.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="rows: ">Aram. נִדְבָּכִין, an expression for walls. The walls were of marble.</text>
      <text title="marble: ">Aram. גְּלָל (marmre in Old French).</text>
      <text title="and a row: ">and a wall of new wood from within, in the manner of the building of the Temple that Solomon built.</text>
      <text title="and the expenditures: ">And the expenditures for the needs of the House and for the other matters pertaining to the House shall be given them from the royal palace.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="And also the vessels of: ">and also the sacred vessels of the House of God, of gold and silver, which Nebuchadnezzar took out of the Temple in Jerusalem and brought to Babylon.</text>
      <text title="let them be given over: ">[as translated,] let them be given over.</text>
      <text title="and brought: ">which he brought.</text>
      <text title="and brought: ">Let all this work be brought to the Temple that is in Jerusalem, to its place.</text>
      <text title="and it shall be deposited: ">And it shall be deposited in the House of the Holy One, blessed be He.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="Now, Tattenai: ">This is the reply with which Darius answered Tattenai and Shethar-Bozenai.</text>
      <text title="who are on the other side of the river: ">to the side of the land of Israel, which is the other side of the river to those in Babylon</text>
      <text title="distance yourselves from there: ">Distance yourselves from the building of the Temple, so that you do not disturb the workers.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="this: ">[as translated,] this.</text>
      <text title="the governors of the Jews: ">The rulers of the Jews shall do this thing.</text>
      <text title="and to the elders of the Jews: ">And to the elders of the Jews I command.</text>
      <text title="this House of God: ">[as translated,] this House of God.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="And from me shall be issued an order: ">And from me this command will go forth.</text>
      <text title="regarding what you shall do: ">regarding that building, the work that you shall do with these elders of the Jews to build the House of the Holy One, blessed be He.</text>
      <text title="and from the king’s property: ">And from the king’s property they shall make ths building.</text>
      <text title="from the taxes of the other side of the river: ">from the taxes of the other side of the river, which belong to the king.</text>
      <text title="taxes: ">Aram. מִדַּת, tax, like (4:13): “the king’s due (מִנְדָּה), the head tax, or the meal tax.”</text>
      <text title="quickly: ">Aram. אָסְפַּרְנָא. The building shall quickly be built; esploytosemant in Old French.</text>
      <text title="The expenses shall be given: ">The expenses shall be given to these men so that they should not idle from their work.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="And what they require: ">and what they are concerned about.</text>
      <text title="and young bulls: ">young bulls, rams and lambs for burnt offerings to the God of heaven.</text>
      <text title="wheat: ">for fine flour.</text>
      <text title="salt: ">for sacrifices.</text>
      <text title="wine: ">for libations.</text>
      <text title="and oil: ">for the meal-offerings. When the priests who are in Jerusalem will say [what they need], that shall be given to them the requirements of each day on its day.</text>
      <text title="without delay: ">Aram. דִּי לָא שָּׁלוּ (son destorber in Old French).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="That they should: ">in order that they should offer up pleasing sacrificing to the God of the heavens, and that they should pray for the life of the king and his children.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="And an order is issued by me: ">And a command is issued by me, along with the issue of a word regarding any person who disobeys this word.</text>
      <text title="shall be torn: ">Aram. יִתְנְסַח. The beams of his house shall be destroyed. יִתְנְסַח is like (Deut. 28:63): “and you shall be uprooted (וְנִסַחְתֶּם) from the land.”</text>
      <text title="and a gallows upon which to place him: ">And a gallows upon which to hang him shall be [raised up] high, so that he be hanged upon the gallows.</text>
      <text title="and his house shall be made a dungheap: ">and his house shall be made a dungheap because of this. נְוָלוּ connotes filth and excrement.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And God, Who caused His name to rest there: ">[as translated,] and God, Who caused His name to rest there.</text>
      <text title="will cast down: ">will cast down and destroy any such king and any such people that will stretch forth a hand to lay waste and destroy His house that is in Jerusalem.</text>
      <text title="have issued an edict: ">I have issued a command concerning this matter, that the building be constructed swiftly. Until here is Darius’s reply.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="as was said: ">[as translated,] as was said.</text>
      <text title="acted swiftly: ">[as translated,] acted swiftly.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="And the elders of the Jews: ">And the elders of the Jews were building and succeeding in their work, according to the prophecy of Haggai and Zechariah, and they built and founded the building by the command of the God of Israel and by the authorization of Cyrus, the first king of Persia, in whose days the laying of the foundation was commenced, and by the authorization of this Darius, the king of Persia.</text>
      <text title="and Artaxerxes: ">He is Darius, but he was called Artaxerxes because of the province and the kingdom, for all kings of Persia were thus named just as all the kings of Egypt were called Pharaoh.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="And the completion of this House: ">And the end of the completion of this House was until the third day of the month of Adar, which is the sixth year of King Darius; hence the building of the House took four years.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="And they offered up for the dedication: ">They offered up for the dedication of this House these sacrifices, and it was a temporary ruling.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="Now they set up the priests in their divisions: ">for the priests were divided in their service and the Levites in their watches.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="the Passover [offering]: ">Now Israel made the Passover offering on this fourteenth of Nissan, which followed this Adar, when the building was completed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="and for themselves: ">Heb. וְלָהֶם, lit. and for them, and for themselves.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="and whoever separated: ">They are the proselytes, who were separated from the defilement of the nations to cleave to Israel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="and turned the heart of the king of Assyria toward them: ">And the Holy One, blessed be He, turned the heart of the king of Assyria toward the Israelites who were dwelling under his dominion in the land of Assyria, to strengthen them and to assist in the work of the building.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="7">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And after these incidents: ">of the building of the House.</text>
      <text title="Artaxerxes: ">That is Darius.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="and the king granted him: ">[i.e., King] Darius.</text>
      <text title="according to the command of the Lord his God upon him: ">as the Holy One, blessed be He, had commanded him. This verse is transposed [its meaning being]: and the King granted him his entire request, according to the command of the Lord upon him. And our Rabbis said (Meg. 15a) that Ezra and Malachi were one and the same.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="in the seventh year: ">That is a year after the completion of the Temple.</text>
      <text title="of Artaxerxes: ">That is Darius.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="in the fifth month: ">i.e., the month of Av, for the first of the month of Nissan was the beginning of their ascent from Babylon, and on the first of the month of Av they arrived in Jerusalem.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="was the commencement of the ascent: ">the foundation of the commencement of the ascent.</text>
      <text title="according to the… hand of his God: ">as the hand of the Holy One, blessed be He, caused him to succeed, for His hand was good upon him to make him succeed in his way.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="For Ezra…: ">Therefore, he went and prospered in his way, because Ezra prepared his heart, etc. He gives a reason for his words.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="And this is the interpretation of the writ: ">Heb. הַכְּתָב פַתְשֶּׁגֶן.</text>
      <text title="and His statutes to Israel: ">and His statutes that He commanded Israel to keep.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="who has mastered… and Ke’eneth: ">He has mastered it in his hand.</text>
      <text title="the Book of Law: ">[as translated,] the Book of Law.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="An order is issued by me: ">The authorization emanates from me that whoever of Israel, of the priests, or of the Levites, whose heart prompts him to go to Jerusalem, may go with you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="Because of this: ">Because of this, you are sent from the king and his seven advisors who saw the king’s face.</text>
      <text title="and his seven advisors: ">and his seven advisors; they are the seven who see the king’s face.</text>
      <text title="to search out Judea: ">An order to seek and to search out the Jews who are in Jerusalem, to see whether they are engaged in the Torah of the Holy One, blessed be He, which is in your hand.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="And to bring: ">and to bring the silver and gold of the king and his advisors that they donated to the God of Israel, to maintain His House, Whose habitation and House are in Jerusalem.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="And all the silver and gold: ">and all the silver and gold that you will find in the province of Babylon, together with the donations of the people and the priests that they will donate to the House of the Holy One, blessed be He, which is in Jerusalem; you shall take everything to Jerusalem.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="Because of this: ">And because of this, because it is for the service of the Sanctuary, you shall quickly purchase with this money cattle, rams and lambs; sacrifices, meal-offerings, and libations, and you shall offer them up on the altar of the Holy One, blessed be He.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="And what pleases you: ">And what pleases you and your brethren (to do) with the rest of the silver and the gold, according to the will of the Holy One, blessed be He, you shall do.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="And the vessels: ">And the vessels that are given to you for the service of the Holy One, blessed be He, give in their entirety before the Holy One, blessed be He, in Jerusalem.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="And the rest of the necessities: ">and the rest of the necessities that you will require for the House of the Holy One, blessed be He, to purchase, for which you will have to give the money; you shall give from the royal treasury.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="And from me-I: ">And from me-I, King Darius-is issued a command and an authorization to all the treasurers who are on the other side of the river of the side of Israel, who receive my taxes from the nations, that anything that Ezra the priest, the scholar of the Law of the Holy One, blessed be He, requests of you, shall be performed quickly. They should not delay his request up to a hundred talents of silver, with which to purchase sacrifices, and a hundred kors of wheat for meal-offerings, and up to a hundred measures of wine for the libations, and a hundred measures of oil to mingle the meal-offerings, and salt for the sacrifices, according to the matter that is stated (Lev. 2:13): “And every meal-offering you shall salt with salt.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="which is not written: ">And salt, regarding which no measure is written, they shall give according to how much is needed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="Whatever is with the authorization: ">Whatever is with the authorization of the Holy One, blessed be He, and His command, shall be done with alacrity, with the seal of the king for the House of the Holy One, blessed be He.</text>
      <text title="with a seal: ">Aram. אַדְרַזְדָּא, seal in Arabic.</text>
      <text title="for why should there be: ">For why should there be wrath against the realm of the king and his sons? Therefore, the treasurers shall provide all the needs of the House.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="And we are making known to you: ">And we are making known to you that [over] all the priests, the Levites, the musicians, the gatekeepers, and the Nethinites, who are wood cutters and water drawers for the altar, and those who serve in this House of the Holy One, no man shall be empowered over them to levy upon them any tribute or head tax, but they shall be free from the service of the king.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="And you, Ezra, according to the wisdom of your God, which is in your hand: ">and you, Ezra, according to the wisdom of your God, which is in your hand [and which is] greater than that of the judges and the magistrates who judge all the people beyond the river to the side of Israel, the people knowledgeable in the Torah.</text>
      <text title="and whoever does not know: ">and the judge who does not know how to judge, inform him of the judgment that he should execute it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="And whoever does not fulfill: ">and whoever does not fulfill the law of the Holy One, blessed be He, and the law of the king promptly, viz. that he delays the law and the judgment.</text>
      <text title="judgment: ">The judgment shall be inflicted upon him, upon the one who obstructs justice.</text>
      <text title="whether to be executed: ">[as translated,] whether to be executed.</text>
      <text title="uprooted: ">whether to uproot him from the world, him, his offspring and his family (לִשְּׁרשִׁי is desraziner in Old French, to uproot).</text>
      <text title="fined: ">to be punished with money.</text>
      <text title="or tortured: ">or to torture him with tortures. Until here is the writ of the letter that King Darius gave to Ezra the scribe in order that he convey it to Jerusalem to show it to the priests and the Levites and the king’s treasurers, in order that they persist in performing the commandments and worshiping the Lord in the Temple and keeping the Torah properly.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="Blessed be the Lord: ">Ezra wrote this in his Book when he gave thanks to the Holy One, blessed be He.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="and his advisers: ">They are his seven advisers mentioned above (verse 14).</text>
      <text title="according to the hand of the Lord my God upon me: ">as the help of the Holy One, blessed be He, was upon me; and I gathered from the Israelites remaining in Babylon the chiefs of the fathers’ houses and the great men to ascend with me from Babylon.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="8">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And these are the heads of their fathers’ houses: ">of the immigrants.</text>
      <text title="and the lineage: ">and their lineage to which they attributed their descent.</text>
      <text title="Artaxerxes: ">He is Darius.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="Of the sons of Shechaniah, of the sons of Parosh: ">That is one family, and Zechariah was the head of the family.</text>
      <text title="and with him: ">With his lineage, the males of his family traced their lineage.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="Ebed the son of Jonathan: ">That was his name.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="the last ones: ">who were the last ones to go after Ezra.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="to the flowing river: ">Heb. הַבָּא אֶל הַנָהָר, lit. to the coming river.</text>
      <text title="to Ahava: ">to that river.</text>
      <text title="and we encamped there: ">and we were camping there.</text>
      <text title="and I surveyed the people: ">I directed my attention to survey the people who had gathered with me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="And I sent to Eliezer… the heads: ">the great men.</text>
      <text title="the wise men: ">Heb. מְבִינִים, lit. understanding. They were wise men.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="And I commanded them, etc.: ">I sent them and commanded them to speak to Iddo, who was the greatest and most esteemed in Casiphia.</text>
      <text title="to Iddo: ">Heb. עַל אִדוֹ, lit. about Iddo.</text>
      <text title="and I put… into their mouth: ">I put into their mouth words to speak as my emissary to Iddo and his brother, who were placed and settled in Casiphia, to bring us servants to serve in the Temple.</text>
      <text title="in Casiphia: ">the name of a place in Babylon.</text>
      <text title="Ahiv: ">the name of a man.</text>
      <text title="who were settled: ">Heb. הַנְתִינִים, like הַנְתוּנִים, those who were settled. Therefore, it is written with a “vav.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="according to the hand of our God: ">just as the success of the Holy One, blessed be He, was upon us.</text>
      <text title="a man of intellect: ">a wise man.</text>
      <text title="of the sons of Mahli…: ">All these were Levites.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="And of the Nethinites: ">And of the slaves, the Nethnites that King David had appointed, and the chefs of Israel ascended with them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="to fast: ">Heb. לְהִתְעַנוֹת to fast.</text>
      <text title="a straight way: ">that the Omnipresent lead us in peace.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="For I was ashamed: ">For I was ashamed of the king, and I did not wish to request of him chariots and horsemen in order to guide us.</text>
      <text title="for we had said: ">For we had already said to King Darius that the Holy One, blessed be He, benefits those who seek Him and pours out His wrath and His anger upon those who forsake Him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="and He accepted our prayer: ">for we arrived safely in Jerusalem.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="And I separated: ">And when I was there by the river Ahava, I separated some of the chiefs of the priests and weighed out the silver and the gold for them to deposit into the treasuries of the House of the Lord.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="which… had offered: ">which those living in Babylon had offered.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="and one hundred silver vessels by talents: ">one talent for each vessel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="And… sprinkling bowls: ">bowls for sprinkling [the blood of the sacrifices].</text>
      <text title="of one thousand darics: ">a type of coin. There were one thousand darics in these twenty sprinkling bowls of gold.</text>
      <text title="golden: ">of golden copper (or) a type of copper coin.</text>
      <text title="fine: ">Heb. טוֹבָה, the feminine form, modifying copper (נְחֹשֶּׁת).</text>
      <text title="two: ">two vessels.</text>
      <text title="precious as gold: ">Heb. חֲמוּדוֹת כַּזָהָב. He calls the vessels חֲמוּדוֹת in the feminine form.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="to them: ">to these chiefs of the priests.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="the chambers of the House of the Lord: ">in order to deposit them in the chambers of the Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="on the twelfth of the first month: ">on the twelfth of Nissan</text>
      <text title="the hand of our God was upon us: ">to cause us to succeed in the way that we traversed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="Everything was counted and weighed: ">The number of the vessels and their weights was the same when they received them as when they itemized them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="Those coming from captivity, the people of the exile: ">those who came with Ezra.</text>
      <text title="offered up burnt offerings: ">all were burnt offerings, and it was a temporary ruling.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="And they gave the king’s decrees: ">These returnees from exile related King Darius’s mandate to the officers of the king, those who see his face.</text>
      <text title="and the governors: ">Heb. וּפַחֲווֹת, like וְפַחוֹת.</text>
      <text title="the land beyond the river: ">those on the side of the land of Israel, who are considered as being beyond the river of the inhabitants of Babylon.</text>
      <text title="and they exalted: ">They were exalting and assisting.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="9">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="these: ">these incidents that related the kings’ decrees.</text>
      <text title="the chiefs: ">of Israel.</text>
      <text title="saying: ">And so they said to me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="was first in this treachery: ">for they commenced to deal treacherously by intermarrying with the peoples of the lands.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="I rent my garment: ">out of the great pain due to this treachery. bewildered Heb. מְשּׁוֹמֵם miserable and bewildered, like (Ez. 3:15): “… seven days bewildered among them.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="from my fast: ">for I had not eaten on that day.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="we were delivered: ">Heb. נִתַּנוּ, like נִתַּנְנוּ. The “dagesh” in the “nun” is instead of another “nun,” like (II Chron. 14:10): “for we rely (תִשְּׁעַנוּ) on You,” like נִשְּׁעַנְנוּ. (Gen. 34:16): “… then we will give (וְנָתַנוּ) our daughters,” like וְנָתַנְנוּ.</text>
      <text title="as of this day: ">as appears this day, for the Ten Tribes have already been exiled, and many of the exiles still remain in Babylon.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="And now, for a short moment: ">temporarily.</text>
      <text title="favor: ">Heb. תְּחִנָה, like חֲנִינָה</text>
      <text title="and to give us a peg: ">to establish us in the land of Israel.</text>
      <text title="a peg: ">יָתֵד, like (Isa. 22:23): “And I will thrust him like a peg (יָתֵד) in a sure place.”</text>
      <text title="a little life: ">[as translated,] a little life.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="For we are slaves: ">to Darius, king of Persia.</text>
      <text title="has not forsaken us: ">Heb. לֹא עֲזָבָנוּ, a combination of לֹא עָזַב אוֹתָנוּ.</text>
      <text title="and He has extended: ">Heb. וַיַט, an expression of the causative, like מַטֶה. He extended His loving-kindness upon us.</text>
      <text title="a fence: ">for they had created a fence to keep His commandments.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="unclean: ">Heb. נִדָה, unclean and repulsive.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="and you shall cause… to inherit: ">You shall give the land to your children as an inheritance to eternity.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="And after all that has come upon us: ">after all the calamity that has befallen us because of our evil deeds.</text>
      <text title="You have punished less: ">You have held back from our iniquities until below them [i.e., less than them], for our iniquity was lessened by the expiation effected by our exile. We may also interpret it in this manner: You held Yourself back from collecting from us all our iniquity, and You collected from us below [less than] the iniquities, and You requited us according to all our sins.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="If we revert: ">Heb. הֲנָשּׁוּב, if we return.</text>
      <text title="will You not be wroth with us: ">a wonder with an affirmative answer.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="for we cannot: ">lit. for there is nothing; i.e., we do not have the power of good deeds to stand and exist before You, because of this transgression.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="10">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="weeping: ">Heb. בּכֶה, like בֶּכִי.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="and we have taken: ">And we took them in.</text>
      <text title="there is hope: ">There is hope for Israel concerning this, for they can cast out their foreign wives and their offspring and cast out all the children born from these foreign wives.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="by the counsel of the Lord: ">by the counsel and the will of the Holy One, blessed be He.</text>
      <text title="and those who hasten to [perform] the commandment of our God: ">and the God-fearers, they shall cast them out.</text>
      <text title="and according to the Law it shall be done: ">he who performs this act, who will cast out his gentile wife and children.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="and we are with you: ">to agree with you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="a proclamation: ">Heb. קוֹל, lit. a voice, an announcement.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="by three days: ">at the end of three days.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="the ninth month: ">That is the month of Kislev.</text>
      <text title="quaking over the matter: ">They were afraid over the matter. They were afraid of the stumbling block of this transgression.</text>
      <text title="and because of the rains: ">And because of the rains that were falling upon them there, they were shivering and miserable.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="confess: ">Heb. תּוֹדָה, [which, in this case, means] וִדּוּי, confession.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="and it is the rainy season: ">for the rains are falling upon us.</text>
      <text title="and the work: ">And this separation from sin cannot be executed so quickly.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="with the entire congregation: ">Heb. לְכָל הַקָהָל</text>
      <text title="who took in: ">Heb. הַהשִּׁיב equivalent to אֲשֶּׁר הוֹשִּׁיב.</text>
      <text title="until we avert: ">until the burning anger of the Holy One, blessed be He, returns from upon us.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="stood up against this: ">to argue concerning this matter.</text>
      <text title="supported them: ">strengthened their hands.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="to investigate: ">Heb. לְדַרְיוֹשּׁ, like לִדְרוֹשּׁ.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="And they completed everything: ">And they completed the rectification of the matter of the men who had brought in heathen wives, for they cast them out.</text>
      <text title="of the first month: ">until the first day of Nissan.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="And they advised them: ">Heb. וַיִתְּנוּ יָדָם, lit. and they gave their hand, their advice, like (II Sam. 14:19): “Behold Joab’s advice (יַד יוֹאָב) is with you in all this (sic).”</text>
      <text title="for their guilt: ">This was a temporary ruling.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="And of the sons of Immer: ">All these are priests until (verse 23): “And of the Levites, etc.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="44">
      <text title="and some of them had wives by whom they had children: ">And some of them had heathen wives by whom they had children. They cast out all of them, both the wives and the children.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
</book>