<book>
  <chapter id="1">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="The harsh prophecy concerning Nineveh: ">Heb. מַשָׂא. The burden of the cup of the curse [which was] to be given Nineveh to drink.</text>
      <text title="The book of the vision of Nahum the Elkoshite: ">חזון is vowelized with a “kamatz” (חָזוֹן) since it is not in the construct state, and it is unlike “ חֲזוֹן יִשַׁעְיָהוּ,” the vision of Isaiah, which is vowelized with a “hataf pattah.” This is its meaning: A book of vision has already been written concerning it [Nineveh], the prophecy of Jonah son of Amittai; and now, again, Nahum the Elkoshite prophesied this harsh prophecy over it. Elkosh is the name of his [Nahum’s] city. And so did Jonathan paraphrase: In early times, Jonah son of Amittai prophesied concerning it, and they repented of their sins, and when they continued to sin, Nahum of the house of Elkosh prophesied further concerning them.</text>
      <text title="the Elkoshite: ">That city is in the province of Ballynia, which is in the state of Eretz Israel, although it is outside the Holy Land. Proof of the matter is that there is gold, silver, and salt dust near it because the Dead Sea, which is near Eretz Israel, goes there under the earth. In this state they do not crown a king the son of a king [i.e., the throne is not hereditary]; and they are of the seed of Judah. [Sod Mesharim]</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="The Lord is a jealous and vengeful God: ">Nahum prophesied concerning Sennacherib’s descendants, and in the time of Manasseh, as we find in Seder Olalm (ch.20).</text>
      <text title="The Lord is a jealous and vengeful God: ">from the time He avenged Israel upon their enemies, and now too, He is still vengeful and full of wrath.</text>
      <text title="He is destined to wreak vengeance upon His adversaries: ">who destroyed their land and exiled His people.</text>
      <text title="and he bears a grudge: ">Heb. וְנוֹטֵר, lit. watches. He lays up His hatred for His enemies. Rabbi Simon says: These three expressions of vengeance correspond to the three exiles to which Sennacherib exiled Israel, as we find in Seder Olam (ch. 23).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="The Lord is slow to anger and great in power: ">He is great in power, and He has the ability to wreak vengeance. The reason He did not hasten His revenge is that He is slow to anger, but, in any case, He will not acquit.</text>
      <text title="the Lord - His way is with a tempest and with a storm: ">They [the tempest and storm] are His messengers for wreaking retribution upon His enemies, as it is stated concerning Egypt (Exod. 14:21): “with a mighty east wind” ; and concerning the generation of the Flood (Job 4:9): “From the breath of God they perish.” Concerning Tyre, it is stated (Ezek. 27:26): “The east wind has broken you.”</text>
      <text title="and cloud is the dust of His feet: ">That, too, is the way of His vengeance. (Exod. 14:24) “And the Lord looked over the camp of the Egyptians with a pillar of fire and cloud”; also, (Ezek. 30:18) “As for her, a cloud shall cover her.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="He rebukes the sea: ">To be understood [both] according to its apparent meaning, and as a figure describing the nations, who are compared to water, as the matter is stated (Isa. 17: 12): “Like the rushing of mighty waters they rush.”</text>
      <text title="and He has dried up all the rivers: ">Here he prophesies that the Holy One, blessed be He, is destined to crown Nebuchadnezzar in the days of Jehoiakim, and He will deliver Assyria and all the lands to the sword.</text>
      <text title="Bashan and Carmel: ">The good dwelling places.</text>
      <text title="and the blossoms of the Lebanon are cut off: ">The Sages of Israel explained this as an allusion to the various types of sweet fruit that Solomon planted in the Temple, which were gold; and as soon as the gentiles entered the Temple, they withered. [from Yoma 21b, 39b]</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="Mountains quaked because of Him: ">The kings and the princes (of the heathens) shall fear His decree.</text>
      <text title="raised up: ">Heb. וַתִּשָׂא; i.e., raised up a pillar of smoke.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="has reached: ">Heb. נִתְּכָה, has reached the earth, as in (Exod. 9:33) “And rain did not reach (נְתַּ) the earth. ”</text>
      <text title="have been broken up by Him: ">by His fear.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="The Lord is good yea, a stronghold: ">Even when he inflicts retribution upon His enemies, His mercies do not cease to do good to those who fear Him. [This ability is] unlike the trait of [a man of] flesh and blood, who, when he is busy with one thing, is not free to [simultaneously] do another thing, as the matter is stated (Exod. 15:3): “The Lord is a man of war; the Lord is His Name.” [This is] as it is stated in Mechilta (ad loc.)</text>
      <text title="and is cognizant of: ">the necessities of those who trust in Him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="But, with an overrunning flood: ">with flooding wrath.</text>
      <text title="He shall make a full end of its place: ">the place of the land. This refers back to “and the land raised up from before Him,” as is stated above.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="He will make a full end: ">of Nineveh and the kings of Assyria. He will not repeat this to you again.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="For, while the thorns are entangled: ">I.e., their destruction will come upon them suddenly, and they will not descend from their honor gradually, but while the thorns and the briers are [yet] entangled; i.e., strongly rooted.</text>
      <text title="and the drunkards are drinking: ">While they are at their feasts and in their joy. Some interpret כִּי עַד סִירִים as an expression of הֲסָרָה, removal.</text>
      <text title="they are consumed like dry stubble, fully ripe: ">Whose ripening has become full and complete, and it has dried out.</text>
      <text title="fully ripe: ">Heb. מָלֵא; asovir, to be filled, in O.F And so (Exod. 22:28): “Your ripe fruits (מְלֵאָתְ)” ; (Deut. 22:9) “The ripe fruit (הַמְלֵאָה) of the seed.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="From you: ">you, Nineveh.</text>
      <text title="emanated: ">Sennacherib, who plots evil, who thought to destroy the earthly abode and the heavenly abode. One passage reads (II Kings 19:23): “And I will come to its remotest lodge” ; and one passage reads (Isa. 37: 24): “Its remotest height.” “First I will destroy His earthly abode, and then I will destroy His heavenly abode” - as found in the chapter “ Chelek ” (Sanh. 94b).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="Though they be at peace and likewise many: ">Jonathan’s Targum is very appropriate to the verse: If they [the people of Nineveh] are at peace in their counsel, that they will all be of one accord; and likewise, if the people of Nineveh, your enemies, are many, O Jerusalem; and likewise, even if they have crossed the Tigris and passed over the Euphrates to besiege it, they will not succeed, for I have afflicted you; I will no longer afflict you. I have heard further (this rendering):</text>
      <text title="If they are perfect: ">the people of Nineveh, in their greatness.</text>
      <text title="and likewise: ">if they will be still greater and more honored.</text>
      <text title="and so they shall be cut down and pass away: ">And so I will cut them down and take them away. This is like (Exod 1:12) “And the more they would afflict them, the more they would multiply.”</text>
      <text title="and I will no longer afflict you: ">I will afflict you this time with destruction and annihilation, and I will no longer be involved with you. Our Sages expounded upon this concerning the practice of charity in Tractate Gittin (7a), but it does not fit in with the context.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="And now I will break off his yoke from you: ">The Shechinah says this to the prophet, who is of Israel: I will break off the yoke of Assyria from you and from My people.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="And the Lord shall command concerning you: ">Now the king of Assyria is being addressed.</text>
      <text title="No more [offspring] Of your name shall be sown: ">No king shall arise from you.</text>
      <text title="I will make your grave: ">I will make the house of your god your grave, for you shall flee there to escape, and there you shall be slain, as your father was slain in the temple of Nisroch, his god.</text>
      <text title="for you have become worthless: ">in My eyes.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="2">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="pay your vows: ">that you vowed to the Holy One, blessed be He, if He would save you from the hand of Sennacherib, king of Assyria - for now you are saved.</text>
      <text title="for… shall no longer continue to pass through you: ">that wicked one.</text>
      <text title="he has been completely cut off: ">he and his descendants.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="The scatterer who came up before you is besieged by a siege: ">The scatterer, who came up upon the land of Judah before you during the time of Hezekiah, is now besieged by the siege of Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, who has besieged him.</text>
      <text title="Watch the way: ">You men of Judah, watch the crossroads and see those going to besiege him [Sennacherib] and strengthen your loins and fortify your power mightily.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="as the pride of Israel: ">As it was already.</text>
      <text title="the emptiers have emptied them out: ">They have plundered them and emptied them. The expression of בְּקִיקָה is appropriate for a vine.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="The shields of his mighty men: ">The mighty of Nebuchadnezzar, who lay siege to Assyria.</text>
      <text title="are dyed red: ">They are dyed red, and the men of their army are in crimson, dressed in crimson.</text>
      <text title="the chariots are in the fire of torches on the day of his preparation: ">Heb. פְּלָדֹת. On the day that he [Nebuchadnezzar] is prepared to go out in the army, he polishes his iron chariots, but I do not know what פְּלָדֹת means. I say that it is a material that polishes iron well. And some interpret פְּלָדֹת as an expression of a fiery torch (לַפִּיד), by transposing the letters.</text>
      <text title="and the cypresses are enwrapped: ">Jonathan renders: And the heads of the [Babylonian] camps are enwrapped in colored garments.</text>
      <text title="are enwrapped: ">Heb. הַרְעָלוּ, enwrapped. Similar is (Isa. 3:19) “The necklaces and the bracelets and the shawls (הָרְעָלוֹת).” In the language of the Mishnah we learned “shawled (רְעוּלוֹת) Arabian women” in tractate Shabbath (65a).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="shall dash about madly: ">They shall behave madly.</text>
      <text title="they shall clatter: ">Heb. יִשְׁתַּקְשְׁקוּן. Jonathan renders: The sound of the clattering of their weapons is heard. And that is from the expression (Joel 2:24) “And the vats shall roar (וְהֵשִׁיקוּ) ,” and (Isa. 33:4) “Like the roaring (כְּמַשַק) of the cisterns.” It is an expression of making a sound heard.</text>
      <text title="they shatter: ">They shatter their listeners like these lightnings, which agitate the creatures. So did Jonathan render it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="He shall remember: ">The king of Assyria shall remember his mighty men and his heroes, and he shall contemplate going forth and waging war, but [he and his men] shall stumble in their walk.</text>
      <text title="they shall hasten to its wall: ">to flee to run to the wall of the city. Any word requiring a “lammed” in its beginning has a “hey” at its end.</text>
      <text title="and the protector is armed: ">Heb. הַסֹּכֵ. Jonathan renders: They shall build towers. We can also explain וְהֻכַן הַסֹּכֵ : and the king shall be armed with his weapons, as in (Ezek.28:14) “who shelters over a great distance (מִמְשַׁח הַסֹּכֵ),” an expression of ruling.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="The gates of the river: ">The gates of the cities, which are on the sides of the rivers.</text>
      <text title="and the palace has dissolved: ">It has quaked and trembled because of the stones of the catapult hurled against its walls, called bombe.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="And the queen: ">Heb. וְהֻצַּב. She is the queen who stands to the right of the king, as is stated (Ps. 45:10): “The queen stands to your right.”</text>
      <text title="has been exposed and taken away: ">In the open, she has gone into captivity and has been taken away from the city.</text>
      <text title="moan like the voice of doves: ">They moan with a lamentation like the voice of lamenting doves.</text>
      <text title="moan: ">Heb. מְנַהֲגוֹת, gemissant in French.</text>
      <text title="beating their breasts: ">Striking their hand on their heart like the beating of a drum.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="And Nineveh is like a pool of water - it is since days of yore: ">Since the day it was founded, it has been sitting tranquilly with no one disturbing it, like a pool of gathered water that does not move from its place.</text>
      <text title="and they: ">Now, out of their stress, they have learned to flee and are fleeing.</text>
      <text title="Halt! Halt!: ">They say to them, but no one turns his heart to listen and halt.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="Plunder silver! Plunder gold!: ">You who come upon Nineveh.</text>
      <text title="And there is no end: ">There is no count.</text>
      <text title="to the treasures: ">Heb. לְתְּכוּנָה, to their treasures. [It is called תְּכוּנָה] because the silver and gold placed in the treasury is placed there with a count, as you say (II Kings 12:12): “The counted (הַמְתֻכּן) money.” [following Jonathan]</text>
      <text title="to sweep out [Nineveh] of all precious vessels: ">Heb. כָּבֹד, an expression of sweeping, as in (below, 3:15) “You shall be swept out (הִתְכַּבְדִי) like the nibbling locust,” an expression of sweeping the house; escovant, to sweep them out of all their precious vessels. And so did Jonathan render it: All precious vessels have ended. כָּבֹד is like זָכוֹר, to remember, and שָמוֹר, to observe.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="Empty: ">Heb. בּוּקָה.</text>
      <text title="yea, emptied out: ">Heb. וּמְבוּקָה, and emptied out through emptiers.</text>
      <text title="and breached: ">Heb. וּמְבֻלָּקָה, breached in its walls: espartide in O.F.</text>
      <text title="the knees stumble: ">Heb. פִק וּ, the stumbling of the knees, as, in (I Sam. 25:31) “As a stumbling block and a remorse.”</text>
      <text title="have gathered blackness: ">Heb. פָארוּר, blackness like a pot.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="Where is the lions’ den?: ">This is a lamentation over Nineveh, which was the dwellings of kings, hard and strong as lions.</text>
      <text title="where the grown lion and the old lion went: ">The place where the kings would go and leave their children there, like a lion that dwelt securely.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="The grown lion tore enough for his whelps: ">As Jonathan renders it: The kings would bring much plunder, until there was enough for the members of their households.</text>
      <text title="and strangled: ">beasts, for the necessity of his lionesses; i.e., he would increase his treasures for his children (sic).</text>
      <text title="for his lionesses: ">for his wives.</text>
      <text title="and he filled his caves with prey: ">And they filled their treasuries with plunder.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="her chariots: ">The multiplicity of the chariots therein; caraijedic in O.F. -army of chariots. The additional “hey” converts the language to mean many chariots. Simliarly, there is (Ezek 24:6) “The pot in which there is filth (חֶלְאָתָה),” much filth.</text>
      <text title="the voice of your ambassadors: ">Heb. מַלְאָכֵכֵה. The voice of your ambassadors, as Rabshakeh and his colleagues, the ambassadors of Assyria, had already done, “And called in a loud voice in Judean” (Isa. 36: 13).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="3">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="robbery: ">Heb. פֶּרֶק, robbery, that one breaks it away from the hand of its owner.</text>
      <text title="the prey departs not: ">from its [i.e., the city’s] midst, it will never depart.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="The sound of the scourge: ">The sound of striking the horses was always heard therein.</text>
      <text title="and the sound of the noise: ">of the wheels of the chariots.</text>
      <text title="and galloping horses: ">Heb. דֹּהֵר, skipping and jumping. And so it is in (Jud. 5:22) “By reason of the prancings, the prancings of their mighty ones.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="and the blade of the sword: ">Heb. וְלַהַב; lame in French; for a knife and a sword are called לַהַב. [Some mss. have: The blade of every sword is called: לַהַב, as in (Jud. 3:22) “And the haft also went in after the blade (הַלַהַב).”</text>
      <text title="and the burnished spear: ">A burnished spear, with the light glittering from it. Splendor in O.F, a shine.</text>
      <text title="yea, the heaps of corpses: ">They would make many corpses, and there was no count of the bodies of the dead cast therein, to the extent that the passersby would stumble on the bodies of the dead.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="Because of the many harlotries of the harlot: ">Because of the extensive flattery of the city, for they knew how to seduce the kings of the earth to join them, and they would eventually subordinate [these kings] to them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="your skirts: ">Heb. שׁוּלַיִ. They are the hems of a woman’s garments.</text>
      <text title="your nakedness: ">Heb. מַעֲרֵ, your exposure, as in (Micah 1:11) “With your private parts exposed (עֶרְיָה).”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="detestable things: ">Filthy garments, which make you detestable. Scripture speaks according to the topic, for he [Nahum] compared her [Nineveh] to a harlot.</text>
      <text title="like dung: ">Heb. כְּרֹאִי. Like dung, an expression like (Lev. 1:16) “And he shall remove its crop (מֻרְאָתוֹ) with its intestines.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="shall wander away from you: ">Shall distance himself from you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="Are you better than No-amon: ">Why should you rely on your wealth and your might? Are you greater than No-amon? That is, Alexandria of Egypt. Amon is an expression of a pedagogue. [Are you greater] than the great No, which trained the kings of Egypt, for they would anoint the kings there?</text>
      <text title="whose wall was the sea: ">to whom the sea was their rampart and their wall. [This mode of construction is known in Aramaic as] שורה ובר שורה, a wall and the son of a wall [referring to a large wall on the outside, opposite an inside of which is built a small wall].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Cush was [its] strength: ">The Cushites were its strength.</text>
      <text title="Put and the Lubim: ">The Putim and the Lubim, who were your helpers, were also in her [Assyria’s] army.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="She, too, went into exile: ">She, too, went into exile. Nevertheless, their greatness did not stand up before Nebuchadnezzar.</text>
      <text title="were bound: ">Heb. רֻתְּקוּ, were fettered; an expression similar to (Isa. 40:19) “And chains (וּרְתֻּקוֹת) of silver” and (Ezek. 7:23) “Make the chain (הָרַתּוֹק),” meaning a chain.</text>
      <text title="in chains: ">Heb. בַזִּקִּים, chains.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="You, too: ">(Even) according to your greatness, [you] shall become drunk like her with the cup of weakness (Cf. Isa. 51:17), and you shall disappear.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="All your fortresses: ">It shall be easy to conquer all your fortified cities and to ravage all that is in their midst, like the fig trees when they are with their first ripe fruits; when the tree is shaken, the first ripe fruits fall into the mouth of the eaters.</text>
      <text title="fig trees: ">Heb. תְּאֵנִים, fig trees.</text>
      <text title="they be shaken: ">which, if they be shaken hard by a man.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="Draw siege water for yourself: ">When a city is about to be besieged, the people of the city gather much water into its midst in barrels, [so that they will have water] to drink during the days of the siege, when there are no cisterns within it [the city].</text>
      <text title="come into the clay and tread: ">it, to make bricks therefrom, in order to strengthen the cracks in the wall.</text>
      <text title="grasp the brickmold: ">Hold the brickmold, which is made for a mold of the bricks in your hand, to make bricks in it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="You shall be swept away: ">Heb. הִתְכַּבֵּד, with a broom of destruction.</text>
      <text title="like the nibbling locust: ">which finishes and destroys completely all the vegetation of the field. Some interpret: -Heb. הִתְכַּבֵּד כַּיָּלֶק. You shall be covered heavily with troops like the nibbling locust, wherein הִתְכַּבֵּד is an expression of a heavy people (עַם כֶּבֶד).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="the nibbling locust spreads out and flies away: ">They will swiftly go out for commerce like the locust that spreads out [its wings] and flies.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="Your princes: ">Heb. מִנְּזָרַיִ, your princes. The “mem” is a radical and a root of the word, like the “mem” of מִשְׁמַרְתְּ, your watch (Num. 18:3); of מִשְׁמַעְתֶּ, your service (I Sam. 22:14); and of מִנְעָלֶ, your lock (Deut. 33: 25). But sometimes the “mem” is defective; e.g., נְזִיר אֶחָיו, the prince of his brothers (Gen. 49:26); and, similarly, לִנְזָרִים, princes (Amos 2:11).</text>
      <text title="and your marshal: ">Heb. יְטַפְסְרַיִ. Your appointees.</text>
      <text title="like armies of locust: ">Heb. כְּגוֹב גּוֹבָי, like armies of locusts. גּוֹבָי is comme langouste in French, like locusts.</text>
      <text title="which alight on the walls on a cold day: ">So is the habit of the numerous locust, the fly, the finishing locust, and the nibbling locust; during the cold times they adhere to the walls, and when warmth comes they fly away from there and go away. So will all your people be exiled.</text>
      <text title="and it flies away: ">Heb. וְנוֹדַד, and it moves.</text>
      <text title="and its place is not known where they are: ">Where they are and where they went.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="Your leaders slumber: ">Heb. נָמוּ, an expression of slumber</text>
      <text title="are at rest: ">They cannot stand up.</text>
      <text title="are scattered: ">Heb. נָפָשׁוּ, like נָפֹצוּ, as all letters emanating from one source are interchangeable. “Zayin”, “shin”, “sammech,” and “tzaddi” all emanate from the tip of the tongue and the bottom of the teeth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="No one is pained over your destruction: ">No one is troubled over your destruction, for everyone rejoices. כֵּהָה is an expression of a darkened thing.</text>
      <text title="clap hands: ">to rejoice.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
</book>