<book>
  <chapter id="1">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="through the lattice: ">Heb. השבכה, grata in Medieval Latin, lattice. I say that they were accustomed to weave it as a warp and a woof with long boards and short ones, which is called lattes, lathe [in] Fr., cancelli [in Latin]; cancel in O.F., space behind the grating, and they would make it all of holes like a sort of net, and it is called prodne in O.F. And I heard that שְּׂבָכָה is vis in Fr. a screw, and in German schwindel stieg, a spiral staircase, as I explained in (I Kings 6:8): “and with winding stairs they would go up…”</text>
      <text title="and he became ill: ">Heb. וַיָחַל an expression of sickness.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="and Jehoram reigned in his stead: ">He was his brother.</text>
      <text title="in the second year of Jehoram the son of Jehoshaphat: ">Is it possible to say this? Did he not reign in the nineteenth year of Jehoshaphat, for Ahaziah reigned in the seventeenth [year of Jehoshaphat] (I Kings 22:52), and reigned for two years (ibid.), and in a nearby chapter also it is written (3:1) In the eighteenth year of Jehoshaphat, Jehoram reigned. Now Jehoshaphat reigned twenty-five years before Jehoram his son reigned. But, Jehoshaphat was deservant of being killed in Ramoth Gilead, but as a reward for his crying out [to God,] God suspended his death for him seven years, and from that time Scripture counts [the years] to his son.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="2">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="in a whirlwind: ">[lit. in a storm],] i.e., in a storm wind.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="Stay here now: ">He wished to drive him away because of his [Elijah’s] humility, so that he would not see him being taken away.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="your master: ">but not our master. This teaches us that they were equal to Elijah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="and rolled it up: ">He rolled it up in order that it would be easy to strike with it.</text>
      <text title="and he rolled it: ">not exactly rolling but gathering together, which is called koulir in O.F.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="You have made a difficult request: ">It is impossible to give you more than I have in my possession.</text>
      <text title="If you see me taken away from you: ">then I will be able to do for you more and more.</text>
      <text title="it will be so to you, and if not, it will not be: ">for I have not the ability.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="My father! My father! The chariots of Israel: ">Jonathan [renders:] My master! My master! who benefited Israel with his prayer more than chariots and riders.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="Where is the Lord, the God of Elijah?: ">that I was promised [who promised me: Kara] that a double portion of his spirit would rest upon me.</text>
      <text title="He too struck the water: ">He too. In the Chapters of Rabbi Eliezer the son of Rabbi Jose the Galilean, [should read: In the Thirty-two Methods of Rabbi Eliezer the son of Rabbi Jose the Galilean. Shem Ephraim], Elisha’s splitting [the Jordan] was doubly as great as Elijah’s, for in the beginning there was the merit of them both, while here was his merit alone.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="Perhaps a wind from the Lord has carried him off: ">Is it possible that on the day before, they said to him, “Do you know that today the Lord will take your master from you?” (v. 5) and now they did not know where he was? This teaches us that since the day when Elijah was hidden, the holy spirit departed from the prophets, and the holy spirit was no longer widespread throughout Israel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="until he was ashamed: ">He was ashamed because of them, lest they say that he does not want to go to meet his teacher. Since he took over his high position, he does not want him to return. All this I saw in Tosefta Sotah (12:5).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="but the water is bad: ">and because of the water, the land causes people to die, to send them to their graves. If so, what is the meaning of: “the city is a good place to live in?” From here we deduce that a place has charm for its inhabitants.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="to the source of the water: ">from where the water flowed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="and some little boys: ">Heb. וּנְעָרִים, people empty [of any observance of commandments].</text>
      <text title="Go away, baldy: ">Go away from here, for you have made the place bald for us, for until now we would hire ourselves out to bring sweet water from a distance, and we would earn our livelihood thereby. And when the water became sweet, they lost their livelihood. Thus it is explained in Sotah (46b).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="and saw them: ">He saw that neither in them nor in their descendants would there be any ‘sap’ of good deeds.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="3">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And Jehoram the son of Ahab: ">This section too was written here to tell the miracle of Mesha the king of Moab, which was performed through Elisha, for Scripture enumerated for Elijah eight miracles and for Elisha sixteen, to fulfill “a double portion of your spirit to me” (above 2:9), and he wrote them all one juxtaposed to the other. I saw this in the Thirty-two Methods of R. Eliezer the son of R. Jose the Calilean. Now the dividing of the Jordan by Elisha is counted like two miracles of Elijah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="however, not like his father and mother: ">who added the worship of the Baal in order to provoke God.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="Only to the sins of Jeroboam… did he cling: ">And so [did] all kings of Israel, for fear lest the kingdom return to the house of David if they would perform the pilgrimage on festivals. They, therefore, worshipped the calves.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="a sheepman: ">Jonathan [however, renders נֹקֵד as] an owner of livestock.</text>
      <text title="rams with their wool: ">Jonathan [renders:] pasture-fed rams, i.e., with their wool.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="by way of the Desert of Edom: ">for the king of Edom, too, will go with us.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="to deliver them…: ">for they will die of thirst.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="who poured water on Elijah’s hands: ">on Mt. Carmel, and with his pouring, his fingers became like springs of water, until the ditch filled up, and it is fitting for a miracle to be performed for us through him concerning water.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="Don’t [say that], for the Lord has summoned…: ">Jonathan [paraphrases thus]: Please do not mention the sins of that wicked woman. Beg mercy for us, for the Lord has summoned…</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="fetch me a musician: ">Because of his anger, the Shechinah left him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="full of pools: ">Pits full of water.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="And this will be slight: ">And furthermore, this miracle is slight and insignificant in the eyes of the Lord, and He will proceed to act wondrously with you [and perform] another miracle, and He will deliver Moab into your hands.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="and you shall fell every good tree: ">Even though it is stated (Deut. 20:19): “You shall not destroy its trees,” here He permitted it for you, for this is a contemptible and insignificant nation before Him. And so [Scripture] states (Deut. 23:7): “You shall not seek their welfare and their good.” These are the good trees that are among them.</text>
      <text title="good field: ">A sown field (Koumici in O.F.).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="And it was in the morning when the meal offering was offered up: ">The water began falling from heaven in the morning in the land of Edom, and at the time of offering up the meal offering, it came surging into that valley, since the prophet had said, “You shall not see wind neither shall you see rain” (v. 17). In R. Tanhuma’s Midrash.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="at the border: ">at the border that is called marche [in French].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="red as blood: ">Such is the nature of water; when the sun shines on it in the morning, it appears red at a distance. Now, since they had never seen water in that valley, they, therefore, thought that it was blood.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="And they demolished the cities: ">[i.e.,] they were demolishing the cities.</text>
      <text title="and the catapultists surrounded and struck it: ">and each one threw his stonefor they would take stones from the walls until they left all the stones of the walls in the wall with only their clay, i.e., their mortar; that is to say that there were no more stones in the wall. And afterwards the catapultists surrounded that which remained in the field where the wall was not broken, and broke it down.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="And he took his firstborn son: ">In the Pesikta of the section of Shekalim it is expounded that he asked his servants ([in] Pesikta [and] Yalkut: his astrologers), “What is the character of this nation, that miracles such as these were performed for them?” They replied, “Their forefather, Abraham, had an only son. The Holy One, Blessed be He, said to him, Sacrifice him before Me, and he wanted to sacrifice him to the Holy One, Blessed be He.” He said to them, “I too have a first born son. I will go and sacrifice him to the gods.”</text>
      <text title="on the wall: ">Heb. חֹמָה. The ‘vav’ is missing, for he worshipped the sun, חַמָה [i.e., he sacrificed his son to the sun].</text>
      <text title="and there was great wrath: ">For their iniquities were remembered, that they too worship pagan deities and are not worthy of miracles.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="4">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="of the wives of the disciples of the prophets: ">She was the wife of Obadiah. Every expression of b’nei han’viim, the sons of the prophets, in Scripture, is translated in Targum as the disciples of the prophets.</text>
      <text title="and the creditor: ">He was Jehoram the son of Ahab, who would lend him with interest what he used to sustain the prophets in his father’s time. In R. Tanhuma’s Midrash (Mishpatim 9): Therefore it is stated (below 9:24): “And he struck Jehoram between his arms which stretched out to take interest.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="a jug of oil: ">enough oil for anointment, yet the “aleph” is part of the root like the aleph of (Job 13:17) and my speech in your ears, [Heb. וְאַחְוָתִי, from חוה], and the “aleph” of (Ezek. 21:20) the crying of [those struck down] by the sword, [Heb. אִבְחַת, from נבח], to bark.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="And you shall close the door: ">It affords respect to the miracle if it comes about in secret.</text>
      <text title="and the full one you shall carry away: ">from before you, and you shall place another vessel in its place to fill it, but the jug of oil you shall not move from its place, for the Holy One, Blessed be He, is making it as a spring, and it is not customary for a spring to move from its place. I heard this Midrash Aggadah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="they were bringing to her: ">the vessels.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="and the oil stopped: ">coming any more. [This is the] peshat. Mid. Aggadah in Gen. Rabbah 35 explains it literally: and the oil stood up, meaning that the price of oil went. up</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And she came and told…: ">She came to receive advice whether to sell or to wait until it would become more expensive. He said to her, Go sell, for there is enough for all your debt, and for you and your sons to live with the remainder until the dead come to life.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="a prominent woman: ">[lit. a great woman, i.e.,] an important woman. And I saw in Pirkei d’R. Eliezer (ch. 33): She was the sister of Abishag the Shunemitess [who warmed King David in his old age].</text>
      <text title="and it was, whenever he would pass: ">in that city, he would stop at her house to eat a meal.</text>
      <text title="he would stop: ">Heb. יסר, lit. he would stop. This is] the present tense, [i.e.,] he would stop there.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Behold now I know: ">For she never saw a fly on his table or semen on his sheet.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="You have busied yourself on our account: ">[lit.] to us.</text>
      <text title="with all this trouble: ">[lit. all this shudder, i.e.] to put your heart into this task, like (Is. 66:2) “and shudders concerning My word,” [i.e.] is diligent concerning the task that it be accomplished and puts his heart into it.</text>
      <text title="What is there to do for you?: ">What do you need that we do for you, for you busied yourself with all this for us.</text>
      <text title="“I dwell in the midst of my people.”: ">amidst my relatives. No one harms me. I have need neither for the King nor for the general of the army.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="And he said: ">Elisha to Gehazi.</text>
      <text title="“Now what can we do for her?”: ">to reciprocate for this favor.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="At this time next year when you will be alive like now: ">[lit. like the time, alive, i.e.] just as you are alive today, and well, so will you be alive next year at this time and embracing a son.</text>
      <text title="No, my lord: ">Do not say, “embracing a son.” Why do I need to embrace him if I will end up burying him? This is what she said to him when he died, “Did I not say, ‘Do not mislead me’?”</text>
      <text title="do not fail: ">Do not show me something that will fail. You have power to beg mercy, and a son will be given to me. I beseech you, do not give me any but a child who will live.</text>
      <text title="do not fail: ">like (Is. 58:11) “whose water will not fail.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="at this time a year later: ">like this time that she was alive and well. Therefore, the word is voweled כָּעֵת; [i.e., like] the [time].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="My head! My head!: ">I am sick in my head!</text>
      <text title="And he said: ">His father [said] to one of the servants, “Carry him to his mother” .</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="Drive and go forward: ">quickly.</text>
      <text title="Don’t keep back from riding because of me: ">Do not keep back the riding because of me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="And she said, “We are well.”: ">This is an abbreviated verse, So he should have written, “And he asked her, and she said, We are well.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="Did I not say: ">to you, Do not fail your maidservant?</text>
      <text title="“Do not mislead me” ?: ">Do not mislead me concerning a mistaken thing.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="do not greet him: ">[lit. do not bless him.] Do not ask him about his welfare. All this was done so that he would not be engaged in conversation, and he would ask him, “Where are you going?” And he would say, “To revive the dead.” Now, it is not respectful for the one through whom it is coming about, to praise himself He, however, did not do so. Instead, to every inquirer he would say, “My master sent me to revive the dead.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="and he prostrated himself upon him: ">Jonathan renders: וְאַלְהֵי עֲלוֹהִי This is an expression of weariness. [I.e., he lay exhausted upon him.] There is a similar word in the Baraitha of Haazinu and in Sifrei (references obscure). And Menahem interpreted [as follows]: The interpretation of the word according to its context, is: he prostrated himself upon him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="38">
      <text title="set the… pot: ">Place it on the stove</text>
      <text title="a stew: ">Heb. נָזִיד, a cooked dish.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="39">
      <text title="a vine in the field: ">This follows Jonathan.</text>
      <text title="to gather herbs: ">[Heb.] oroth, garden rocket, which they call eruca [in Latin], which brightens the eyes, meir [in Heb.] (Yoma 18b). Others interpret ‘oroth’ as herbs, as (Is. 18: 4) “Like a clear heat on herbs (‘or’).”</text>
      <text title="a vine in the field: ">
      </text>
      <text title="and gathered from it wild mushrooms: ">Wild mushrooms grew from it. That is boljic in O.F: It is poisonous. [It is common that mushrooms grow from old tree stumps and the like. In this case, they grew from a vine.] And in the name of Rabbi Menahem. I heard, and he gathered in addition to the fruit that grew from it, wild mushrooms.</text>
      <text title="and diced them: ">split them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="42">
      <text title="from Ball Shalishah: ">the name of a province. And Jonathan rendered: from the southland.“Baal” is an expression meaning a plain. There are many such expressions in the Bible.</text>
      <text title="bread of the first fruits: ">It was during Passover, when the grain becomes ripe.</text>
      <text title="in their shells: ">Jonathan [renders]: in their garments. [The shell is compared to a garment of the grain].</text>
      <text title="to the people: ">to the students whom he sustained.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="43">
      <text title="How will I give this: ">[i.e.,] each bread.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="5">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Now, Naaman the general: ">He goes on to recount the miracles that were performed through Elisha.</text>
      <text title="the victory to Aram: ">He drew back his bow innocently and killed Ahab.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="went out in bands: ">When they go in groups of one hundred or two hundred by themselves, to plunder whatever they find, that is called a band.</text>
      <text title="a young girl: ">Heb. naarah ketannah, a young girl from the town of Naaran.</text>
      <text title="who ministered to: ">[lit. and she was before Naaman’s wife.] Jonathan [renders]: and she was serving before Naaman’s wife.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="My master’s supplications: ">before the prophet Heb. אֲחֲלֵי, an expression similar to וַיְחַל מֹשֶה, “and Moses prayed” (Ex. 32:11). The supplications of all those who pray for him, shall be that the miracle shall come before the prophet.</text>
      <text title="the supplications: ">אַחֲלֵי I.e., to say that this is the supplication that he requires.</text>
      <text title="And he came: ">[i.e.,] Naaman [came]</text>
      <text title="and told his master: ">the king of Aram.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="and he took in his possession: ">as a gift to the prophet.</text>
      <text title="and six thousand gold pieces: ">[lit.] and six thousand gold.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="saying: ">[“And now when this letter comes…5”]-The letter said to him, “And now, when this letter…”</text>
      <text title="and you shall cure him of his zaraath: ">[lit. and you shall gather him in from his zaraath.] Gathering, as applied to the mezora, is the expression of his cure, for when he is cured, he is gathered in among people, whereas during his illness, everyone stays away from him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="Do I have power from God: ">[after] Jonathan. [Lit. Am I God?] The ‘heh’ at the beginning of the word הַאֱלֹהִים, is voweled with a ‘pathah’ to indicate that it is a question.</text>
      <text title="he is looking for a pretext: ">He is looking for a pretext to engage in strife with me. [Heb. מִתְאַנֶה] an expression of pretext.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="Here I thought: ">[I thought that] the prophet would come out and speak with me, and see the ailment.</text>
      <text title="and he would raise his hand toward the spot: ">of the] zaraath.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="Master: ">[lit. father].</text>
      <text title="would you not do it?: ">Would you not do it even if he ordered you to do something requiring exertion?</text>
      <text title="and surely: ">by a fortiori conclusion, since he said to you to do an easy thing, [viz.] immerse yourself and become clean.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="a gift: ">[lit. a blessing], a gift of peace, of greeting, when a disciple or a slave greets his master (sallud in O.F., a greeting).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="I will not accept: ">for the price of idols was included in it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="Now, if only: ">וָלֹא, an expression of a request, an expression of הַלְוַאי.</text>
      <text title="Now… be given: ">from this soil of the land of Israel, which is holy, a load of earth as carried by a team of mules, and I will carry it off to my city, and I will make it into an altar.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="Beth-Rimmon: ">the name of a pagan deity.</text>
      <text title="and I will prostrate myself: ">against my will when my master bows, since he leans on my hand.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="some distance: ">[Heb.] kivrath eretz, the name of a land measure, like (Is. 5:10) “ten acres of vineyard.” (arpent in French), an old French measure of land, equivalent to about an acre.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="something: ">Heb. מאומה The “aleph” is missing, since this taking was responsible for his being stricken with a blemish. מוּם [in Heb.].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="and he leaned over: ">Jonathan. [Lit. and he fell.]</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="Please: ">swear that he sent you.</text>
      <text title="in two pockets: ">Heb. חֲרִטִים types of garments and kerchiefs, like (Is. 3:22) “and the kerchiefs and the ‘haritim.’” Menahem classified it thus (p. 94). Jonathan, however, translated this as ‘paldesin,’ sheets, (see Targum Jud. 14) and the one in the book of Isaiah as ‘mahachaia,’ a plate covering the genitals. The exegetes say that בִּשְׁנֵי חֲרִטִים, [means] ‘in two long pockets’ brids in O.F.</text>
      <text title="his two servants: ">[i.e.,] Naaman’s.</text>
      <text title="and they carried them before him: ">before Gehazi.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="And he came to a secret place: ">Jonathan renders: to a hidden place.</text>
      <text title="and he took them from their hands: ">from the hands of Naaman’s two servants.</text>
      <text title="and he dismissed the men: ">lest Elisha see them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="Is it time to take the silver: ">to become wealthy and to buy with it clothing and olive trees…</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="6">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And the disciples of the prophets said: ">He continues to enumerate the miracles that were performed for him (sic). Our Sages deduced from here that Gehazi would reject the pupils from before him, and when he was banished, many pupils came, and the place became too cramped for them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="be willing: ">Heb. הואל.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="it is borrowed: ">I borrowed it, and I have not the wherewithal to pay.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="floated: ">floated on the water.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="hidden, secret: ">Jonathan [renders]: covered and hidden. פְּלֹנִי is an expression of (Deut. 17:8) “If it be concealed” (יִפָּלֵא).</text>
      <text title="secret: ">without a name, for he did not want it to be revealed.</text>
      <text title="I will encamp: ">There I will encamp and ambush the king of Israel or his bands who pass to plunder in my land through that place.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="of passing this place: ">[i.e.,] from going there.</text>
      <text title="are encamped: ">Heb. נְחִתִּים.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="And the king of Israel sent: ">He would send and see whether it was true.</text>
      <text title="and cautioned him: ">concerning which the man of God had cautioned him from passing.</text>
      <text title="not once and not twice: ">did he do so for him, but many times.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="about this matter: ">who was revealing his secret.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="where he is: ">where he is.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="who are with us: ">[i.e.,] who are on our side (helping us).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="and said, Please strike…: ">On the curse he did not mention the Name [of God,] but on opening the eyes he mentioned the Name [of God] on both of them, concerning [opening] the attendant’s [eyes], and concerning [opening the eyes] of the troop.</text>
      <text title="with blindness: ">a sickness of confusion; one sees, yet does not know what he sees.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="nor is this the city: ">wherein the prophet is [found]. Now he told them the truth since he had already left it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="Do you slay those you have captured with your sword and with your bow: ">Is it your custom to slay one whom you bring into captivity (and destroy them)?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="And he prepared: ">Heb. וַיִכְרֶה an expression of preparation of a meal.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="dove’s dung: ">[Heb.] divyonim; dung that flows from the doves.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="“Save me, my lord the king!”: ">He thought she was asking for food.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="But she hid her son: ">dead, and wants to eat him alone.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="and the people saw: ">the sackcloth under his garments through the tear.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="If Elisha the son of Shaphat’s head remain: ">for he is able to beg for mercy.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="and he sent a man from before him: ">The king sent [a man] to kill him, and when that messenger had not yet come to Elisha, [and he was] revealed to him through the divine spirit, and he said to the elders…. and behold the messenger was coming down to him and the king was after him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="And he said: ">The king [said]</text>
      <text title="Behold, this calamity is from the Lord: ">This is one of the curses that He cursed through Moses, (Deut. 28:53) “And you will eat the fruit of your womb… during the siege and in the straitness…”</text>
      <text title="What more can I hope for from the Lord?: ">to save? It will surely not avail.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="7">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="Now there were four men: ">Gehazi and his sons.</text>
      <text title="at the entrance of the gate: ">as it is said (Lev. 13:46) “He shall live alone; outside the camp shall be his habitation.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="had caused the Aramean camp to hear: ">It seemed to them as though they were hearing.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="We will incur guilt: ">We will be held guilty by the throne.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="as they were: ">as they were full at the beginning; they did not take out what was in them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="that we are hungry: ">and long to go out to the loot and to the food.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="that are left there: ">within the city, that did not die of hunger.</text>
      <text title="Behold, they are like all the multitude of Israel that are left there: ">If they will say that they are imperiled lest the Arameans kill them, behold they are in this city in peril of famine like the rest of all the multitude of Israel that are left there, and if they die, they are like all the multitude of Israel that have perished from hunger.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="in their haste: ">in their hurry to flee.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="upon whose hand he leaned: ">on the day before, when he came to Elisha’s house.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="8">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Now Elisha had spoken to the woman: ">already seven years before.</text>
      <text title="for the Lord has decreed a famine: ">This is the famine that took place in the days of Joel the son of Pethuel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="about her house and about her field: ">which robbers occupied.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And Elisha came to Damascus: ">to influence Gehazi to repent.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="‘You will recover’: ">Toward Hazael he said that he would live instead of Ben Hadad and occupy the throne.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="He made his face expressionless: ">[lit. he made his face stand. I.e.,] he held in his expression of grief, for he wanted to cry, so as not to cry before Hazael, and he made an effort to stand and control himself.</text>
      <text title="a long time: ">ad bosh, [lit. until he delayed,] like “boshesh” (Ex. 32:1), and he could not control himself and wept.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="you will dash: ">[Heb.] תְּרַטֵשׁ an expression of splitting the intestines. The origin of all of them [is] (Is. 13:18)…“and bows will split (תְּרַטֵּשְׁנָה) the youths.”</text>
      <text title="and their pregnant women: ">their pregnant women.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="a blanket: ">Jonathan renders: “gunva.” [Likewise], (Jud. 4: 18) “And she covered him with a blanket,” he renders, ‘b’gunva.’ It is a garment.</text>
      <text title="and spread it on his face: ">so that he cool off.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="And in the fifth year: ">Jehoshaphat crowned Joram two years during his lifetime. When they returned from the war they had waged with the king of Moab. So it was taught in Seder Olam (ch. 17), in the fifth year of Jehoram, and as regards the fifth year since Jehoshaphat, it was decreed on Jehoshaphat to be killed in Ramoth Gilead, but he was reprieved for seven years because he cried out [to God].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="a kingdom: ">[Heb.] נִיר.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="and they appointed a king over themselves: ">Since the time of David they did not have a king, as it is said. (II Sam. 8:14) “And he placed governors in Edom.” Eight kings reigned in Edom before a king reigned in Israel, viz. those enumerated in the Book of Genesis (36:31). Corresponding to them, eight kings reigned in Israel: Ish bosheth, David, Solomon, Rehoboam, Abiam, Asa, Jehoshaphat, and Jehoram. And Edom had no king. What is written above (3:9) that the king of Edom went with Jehoram the son of Ahab and with Jehoshaphat to war against the king of Moab, presents no difficulty because he was not a real king, but a governor, who is also called a king, and as it is said: (I Kings 22:48) “There was no king in Edom; a governor was king.” They had a governor in lieu of a king.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="who came around to him: ">those near the border.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="Libnah rebelled: ">The inhabitants of Libnah rebelled and rebelled (sic) against the king. I do not know from what nation they were, since Libnah is from Eretz Israel. But I say that they were of the tribe of Judah and rebelled against the king.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="and was buried with his forefathers in the city of David: ">And in II Chron. (21:20) it is stated: in the city of David, but not in the graves of the kings.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="9">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And Elisha the prophet summoned…: ">at that same time that Jehoram was ill in Jezreel.</text>
      <text title="one of the disciples of the prophets: ">It was Jonah the son of Amittai.</text>
      <text title="Gird your loins: ">Every girding of the loins is an expression of quickening of mightiness. Since he was a messenger for a perilous mission, (he needed quickening).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="the lad, the disciple of the prophet: ">the disciple of Elisha the prophet, so did Jonathan render: and the lad, the disciple of the prophet, went.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="You know the man: ">You recognize the man, that he is mad.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And they said, It is a lie: ">that you are saying. You are hiding what he said to you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="on the top step: ">Jonathan [renders]: on the step of the hours, a type of steps made corresponding to the hours of the day, to know each hour when the shade descends one hour. [It was a type of sundial. The word used for step is] gerem, ourle in Old French, an expression of a notch. [Similarly, the word] “Hagramah,” in the laws of “shechitah” is from this derivation, that one slaughters in a straight line, and then cuts downwards, making an appearance of a hillock above.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="If you so desire: ">that I reign.</text>
      <text title="from the city: ">from Ramoth-Gilead.</text>
      <text title="tell: ">[Heb.] לַגִּיד, same as לְהַגִּיד.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="that… were riding together: ">how you and I were riding together after Ahab on the day that he killed Naboth.</text>
      <text title="when the Lord pronounced… upon him: ">this prophecy through the prophet Elijah, and we heard.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="Strike him… in the chariot: ">And in II Chron. (22:9), it is said: “And he sought Ahaziah, and they captured him when he was hiding in Samaria, and they brought him to Jehu.” [The discrepancy between] the verses can be reconciled [thus]: And… fled by way of the garden (sic) from Jezreel to Samaria. There is, however, an uncertainty in the matter, for Jehu had no rule in Samaria until the next day, as it is explained in this account (10:1): “And Jehu wrote letters and sent to Samaria…” Our Rabbis explained in the Aggadah of [the chapter] entitled ‘Chelek’ (San. 102b): “And he was hiding in Samaria, that he would cut out the Divine Names [from the Scriptures] and write [the names of] pagan deities in their place.” According to them, we can say that this hiding was not because of Jehu, but thus is its explanation: And he sought Ahaziah, and they captured him when he was fleeing by way of the garden (sic), and he had been behaving wickedly from the beginning, for he would come to Samaria and hide from the Judean officers to commit this abomination, since the inhabitants of Samaria were idolaters. “And they brought him to Jehu,” [i.e.,] Jehu’s men, who had pursued him. “And he said, ‘strike him… in the chariot.’”</text>
      <text title="at the ascent of Gur: ">for there they brought him to him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="And in the eleventh year of Joram son of Ahab, Ahaziah became king: ">Above (8:25) it is stated, “In the twelfth year.” And you are forced to say that Jehoram his father did not die until the twelfth year of Joram, for in the fifth year of Joram he became king (8:16) and he reigned for eight years (8:17). Now why does it say here, “In the eleventh year?” I say that he reigned one year during his father’s lifetime since he was afflicted with severe maladies, as it is said: “And after all this, the Lord afflicted him with incurable illness. And it was by the end of a year, that his intestines went out because of his illness… And the inhabitants of Jerusalem made Ahaziah… king” (II Chron 21:18-22:1.) Here (8:26) it is stated: “Ahaziah was twenty-two years old when he reigned, and in II Chron. (22:2), ” He was (sic) forty-two years old when he reigned.“ Now all the days of Jehoram his father was forty years, no more, as it is said concerning him: ” He was thirty-two years old when he became king, and he reigned eight years (8:17).“ Now how is it possible for a son to be two years older than his father? Rather, twenty years before he was born, which was two years before his father was born, this decree was issued. From the day that Asa took a daughter of Omri in marriage for Jehoshaphat his son, a decree was issued upon the house of David that it be destroyed with the house of Ahab. And thus it is stated in II Chron. (22:7) ” And from God was Ahaziah’s confusion, to come to Joram…“ Thus it is taught in Seder Olam (ch. 17) and in the Tosefta of Sotah (ch. 12). Nowhere in the Scriptures, however, do we find that Jehoshaphat married Omri’s daughter. I did find, however, in II Chron. (18: 1) ” And he (Jehoshaphat) intermarried with Ahab.“ Perhaps this refers to his sister whom he married. And in the thirty- first year of Asa he married her, as it is said: ” In the thirty- first year of Asa… Omri reigned" (I Kings 15:23). And we learned in Seder Olam (ch. 17) that he reigned over the entire kingdom, for six years prior to then, he reigned over half the people, and when Asa took his daughter in marriage to Jehoshaphat, he gained prestige, and they assassinated Tibni. Proceed and calculate from the thirty first year of Asa until the death of Ahaziah and you will find them to be forty two.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="she adorned her head: ">She adorned her head in order to have charm in Jehu’s eyes so that he would marry her.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="Is there peace: ">Do you wish to be with me in peace?</text>
      <text title="Zimri, assassin of his master: ">If you assassinated your master, this is nothing new, for Zimri too assassinated Elah son of Baasha.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="Who is with me?: ">Who among you will come to my aid?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="“Push her out!”: ">of the window to the ground.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="the skull, the feet: ">Our Rabbis said, that she would dance before bridegrooms with her hands and feet, and shake her head.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="as dung: ">This follows Jonathan.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="10">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="and to those who brought up Ahab’s children: ">lit. to those who brought up Ahab.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="and the chariots and the horses… are with you: ">and they have strength to wage war.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="the two kings: ">Joram and Ahaziah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="Now the king’s sons are seventy men. They are with the elders of the city…: ">All this was written in the letter, “And I know their count seventy men and they are with the elders of the city who are bringing them up.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="two piles: ">[Heb. צִבֻּרִים]. Synonymous with חֳמָרִים in Heb. and דְּגוֹרִין in Aramaic (monticules in French, mounds).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="You are righteous: ">You consider yourselves all righteous, and me you consider wicked since I slew the king. Now look, behold I revolted against my master and slew him. Now who slew all these? But from these you shall know then that it is a decree of the King upon them, and he who slays is righteous and fulfills the commandment of the Omnipresent.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="the meeting place of the shepherds: ">Jonathan [renders]: the house of the gathering of the shepherds.</text>
      <text title="meeting: ">[Heb. עקד], an expression of binding, the place where the shepherds assemble.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="and he said to him: ">[i.e.,] Jehu [said to Jehonadeb].</text>
      <text title="“Is your heart right: ">and fully committed in what I am doing, as my heart is fully with your heart?”</text>
      <text title="“Indeed it is. Give me your hand.”: ">Hold it and pick me up to you to the chariot.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="with cunning: ">[Heb. בְּעָקְבָה] with [guile, an expression of] (Gen. 27:36) וַיַעְקְבֵנִי, “he beguiled me.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="Proclaim an assembly: ">Announce an assembly, that they assemble in the temple of the Baal.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="over the wardrobe: ">Jonathan rendered: to the one appointed over the wardrobe, chests and boxes in which they wrap and store the vestments of the Baal worshippers.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="his life shall be forfeit for his life: ">[i.e.,] the life of the guard shall be forfeit for the life of the escapee.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="cast them out: ">Jonathan [renders]: and the couriers and the mighty warriors cast cadavers, [i.e.,] they cast the Baal worshippers down dead.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="for a privy: ">[the] Kethib is לִמְחֹרָאוֹת, an expression meaning a privy, and likewise, (Isaiah 36:12) “to eat their excrement, חוריהם.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="However,… from the sins of Jeroboam…: ">for fear that the kingdom return to the house of David, as Jeroboam had feared.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="And the Lord said to Jehu: ">through Jonah.</text>
      <text title="your descendants of the fourth generation: ">four generations as reward for your having destroyed the house of Ahab, which reigned for four generations: Omri, Ahab, Ahaziah, and Jehoram.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="to be vexed with Israel: ">[Heb. לְקַצוֹת,] like (Gen. 27:46) בְחַיַי קַצְתִּי, “I am vexed with my life.”</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="11">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="in the bed chamber: ">in the attic of the Holy of Holies, as it says (v. 3): And he was… with her in the house of the Lord. [It was] concerning him that David said, (Ps. 27:5) “For He will conceal me in His Tabernacle, He will hide me in the secrecy of His tent” [Seder Olam, ch. 18]. He calls it the bed- chamber in the manner of (Song of Songs 1:13) “Between my breasts He lodges.” This is what R. Eliezer instituted, “The destruction of the bed-chamber, [may He remember for an atonement” ; i.e.,] may the destruction of Your Temple atone for them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="of the mighty warriors: ">[Heb. לַכָּרִי,] the officers of the hundreds of the mighty warriors and the officers of the hundreds of the couriers. The expression כָּרִי, which he used, and did not say לַכָּרִים, is a noun meaning a company of mighty warriors (barned in O. F.), nobility.</text>
      <text title="and he enacted a covenant with them: ">that they would aid him in crowning the king’s son.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="a third of you, of those who come on the Sabbath: ">The watches would be renewed on the Sabbath (see Taanith 2:6,7), the watches of the priests and the Levites. One would enter and one would leave. He ordered the “mishmar” that was entering, to separate into three parts, one third in the king’s palace, to guard that no one rise up against the king to assassinate him, one third in the Sur Gate, that is the eastern gate of the Temple court, the Hasarah Gate (sic). One third in the gate [called,] “After the Couriers.” That too was one of the gates of the Temple court. Jonathan rendered: in the gate behind which was the gate of the couriers. Through the gate of the couriers one would go from the royal palace to the Temple, as it is stated at the end of this episode (v. 19). And that gate about which it is stated that the Gate of the couriers was behind it, was called in II Chron. (23:4) the gate of the Sippim.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="and you shall keep the watch of the palace without taking your mind off it: ">This watch he commanded them (sic) the first division, concerning whom he said, “And they shall keep the watch of the king’s palace” (sic).</text>
      <text title="from taking your mind off it: ">Guard it very diligently, that you do not take your mind off it, an expression of despair (I Sam. 27:2), that there should be no despair in this matter. The ‘mem’ of מַסָּח is part of the root. [I.e., it is part of a noun. It is not a prefix meaning from.]</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And two thirds of you: ">who I said should be in the Sur Gate and in the Gate of the Couriers, and with them all those who leave on the Sabbath, the men of the departing mishmar.</text>
      <text title="shall keep the watch of the house of the Lord, to guard the king: ">lest harm befall him from within the house of the Lord. Now he did not require all this except on the first Sabbath, until Athaliah was killed and her allies fled from the city.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="and the one who comes within the ranks: ">a stranger who comes within the boundary called “sederoth,” which is the place of the king’s entry from his palace to the house of the Lord. I did not know the origin of the word “sederoth,” and Jonathan rendered it as “rows” [like] “sedarim” [with a] “samech.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="the crown and the testimony: ">the scroll of the Law, as it is written: “And it shall be with him, and he shall read in it all the days of his life” (Deut. 17:19). And our Rabbis said that the crown itself was the testimony, for anyone who is fit for the throne it would fit, whereas anyone unfit for the throne it would not fit.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="on his stand: ">That is the place where the king stands in the house of the Lord.</text>
      <text title="“Revolt! Revolt!”: ">Revolt! There is a revolt here.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="Take her out: ">of the Temple to the ranks and bring her by way of the areas within the ranks to the king’s palace. Do not allow her to leave through the exit of the Temple court through the city, lest she find allies who will join her.</text>
      <text title="and anyone who comes after her: ">to her assistance.</text>
      <text title="is to be slain: ">[lit.] to slay.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="And they made a place for her: ">[Heb. יָדַיִם, lit. hands,] a place (adysnces in O.F.).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="between the Lord and between the king and (between) the people: ">that the king and the people will follow the Lord, and afterwards he enacted a covenant between the king and between the people that they should be servants of the king.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="appointees: ">appointed to watch in the place of their watch according to their law, since Athaliah had abolished the order of the watches of the Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="and they came by way of the gate of the couriers: ">to the king’s palace.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="12">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="all his days, that Jehoiada the priest instructed him: ">but after Jehoiada died, the princes of Judah came to prostrate themselves before the king, and they defiled him. They said to him, One who enters the Holy of Holies is in peril of dying. Yet you hid there for six years. You are fit to be a god. “Then the king listened to them” (II Chron. 24:17).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="the money of anyone who passes the numbering, each one the money of the value of the people, [whose value he vows to donate]: ">Two types of money are mentioned here: (1) the money of anyone who passes the numbering. That is the money of the shekels, concerning which it is stated (Ex. 30:13,14), “Everyone who passes the numbering,” and (2) anyone who volunteers the value of his person; i.e., One who says, My value shall be incumbent upon me to donate.</text>
      <text title="all money which comes upon…: ">[I.e., all money which one desires to give,] such as one who says, It is incumbent upon me to donate a maneh (twenty-five selaim or one hundred dinarim) for the repairs of the Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="The priests shall take for themselves: ">It shall be theirs, and they shall take upon themselves to strengthen the damage of the Temple from their own money.</text>
      <text title="from his acquaintance: ">[Heb. מַכָּרוֹ, like מַכִּירוֹ, i.e.,] from his acquaintance who frequently visits him.</text>
      <text title="damage: ">splits and cracks in the wall.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="Now, take no money: ">anymore, and do not repair the Temple from your money.</text>
      <text title="but give it for the damage of the house: ">If it will be little, let it be little, and if it will be left over, let it be left over.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="near the altar: ">in the Temple court.</text>
      <text title="on the right, where a person comes: ">on the right of the people’s entrance.</text>
      <text title="the guards of the threshold: ">the thresholds of the Temple court, those in charge of the keys of the Temple court, for Jonathan rendered it as “Amarkalia,” and the “Amarkalim” were seven, for the seven gates of the Temple court. Tosefta Shekalim 2:15</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="And it was: ">from day to day.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And they would give the counted money: ">They would give that counted money. After they would take it out of the chest and weigh it, they would give it into the hands of the treasurers who were in charge of the performers of the work.</text>
      <text title="the counted: ">Heb. [הַמְתֻכָּן,] an expression of a number, like (Ex. 5:18) “and the number (וְתֹכֶן) of bricks you shall give.”</text>
      <text title="who were appointed: ">[Heb. הַמֻּפְקָדִים].</text>
      <text title="and they spent it: ">[lit. and they took it out.] An expression of expenditure to hire carpenters.</text>
      <text title="and for the builders: ">They are the architects, the stonesmiths whose colleagues would work under their orders, the supervisors of the crafts.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="And for the masons: ">for the builders of the wall, the apprentices of the architects.</text>
      <text title="and for the stonecutters: ">from the mountain.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="And they would not reckon with the men: ">The supervisors would not make a reckoning with the men, the treasurers into whose hand the supervisors would always give the money to give it to the foremen over the work, since they were not suspicious in their eyes, for they did the work honestly.</text>
      <text title="for they did [the work] honestly: ">They were known to be honest men.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="The money for guilt-offerings and the money for sin-offerings: ">If one set aside money for his sin-offering or for his guilt- offering, and purchased an animal, and there remained of the money.</text>
      <text title="would not be brought to the house of the Lord: ">to repair the damage of the Temple.</text>
      <text title="they would go to the priests: ">who would in turn purchase therefrom burnt- offerings, “fruit” for the altar; the flesh was for a burnt- offering and the hides were theirs. Thus we learned in Temurah (23b). This interpretation Jehoiada the priest expounded on. Everything that comes from the remainder of a guilt-offering shall be used to purchase burnt-offerings.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="Then Hazael the king of Aram went up: ">after the death of Jehoiada, when Joash made himself for a god.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="at Beth- millo: ">in that place.</text>
      <text title="Millo: ">the name of a place.</text>
      <text title="Silla: ">the name of a place.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="And Jozacar the son of Shimeath and Jehozabad the son of Shomer: ">In II Chron. (24:26) it is written, “Shimeath the Ammonitess and Jehozabad the son of Shimrith the Moabitess.” Now why did Scripture specify? To teach [us] that the Holy One, Blessed be He, requited him through people of his type. Let the ungrateful Ammonites and Moabites, who ignored our father Abraham’s favor, which he did for Lot, (viz. that he fought with the kings to rescue him, yet they hired Balaam to curse his descendants,) and requite Joash who ignored the favor of Jehoiada and killed Zechariah his son, as is explained in II Chron. (24:22). This interpretation is in Sifrei.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="13">
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="And the Lord gave Israel a savior: ">Joash the son of Jehoahaz, concerning whom it is stated, (v. 19) “Three times shall you strike Aram.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="In the thirty-seventh year…: ">This verse is contradicted from two sides, and I have not found any reconciliation, for he should have said, “thirty- nine,” since his father rose in the twenty-third year of Joash, and reigned seventeen years. It is found that he died in the thirty-ninth year of Joash. Furthermore, it is stated below in this section (14:1), “In the second year of Joash the son of Joahaz the king of Israel, Amaziah the son of Joash the king of Judah, became king.” It is found that Joash the son of Jehoahaz rose in the fortieth year of Joash, which was his last year, and in the second year of Joash the son of Jehoahaz, Amaziah became king. And even if you say that Amaziah became king in the year of his father’s death, and Scripture calls this the second year of Joash, you, [nevertheless,] deduce that Joash the king of Israel did not become king until the thirty-ninth year of Joash the king of Judah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="and Jeroboam sat on his throne: ">He was his son. There is [reason] to wonder why these two verses were written here, for Scripture continues to relate the events of Joash, and then repeats, “And the rest of the deeds of Jehoash… And Joash slept with his forefathers…” (14:15, 16). I say that these [two verses] were written for the sole purpose of breaking continuity, so as not to juxtapose Elisha’s demise with a verse dealing with idolatry, by saying, “And he did what was evil… And Elisha became ill…”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="“Open the window to the east: ">Opposite the land of Aram, as it is said, (Is. 9: 11) ” Aram from the east."</text>
      <text title="“Shoot!” and he shot: ">This follows Jonathan.</text>
      <text title="And he said, “This is an arrow of salvation…”: ">Elisha said, This arrow is a symbol of salvation for Israel.</text>
      <text title="in Aphek: ">the name of the city.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="And he said, You should have struck five or six times: ">[lit. to strike five or six times.]</text>
      <text title="then: ">Had you done so, you would have struck Aram five or six times, for as a symbol of victory, I placed your hands on the bow.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="would invade the land: ">were wont to come and plunder the land.</text>
      <text title="at the beginning of the year: ">Jonathan [renders]: at the entrance of the year. At the return of the year, when the earth is still full of vegetation, and there is food for their animals, it is customary for bands to set out.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="14">
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="and he called its name Joktheel: ">for it set his teeth on edge, [קִהוּי שִׁנַיִם in Heb; i.e., the results of this conquest were unfavorable for Amaziah] as it is written. (II Chron. 25: 14) “After Amaziah came from striking down the Edomites, he brought the gods of the children of Seir… for deities. And before them he would prostrate himself.” And the prophet castigated him and said to him (v. 16), “I know that God has advised in order to destroy you.” Now what was the advice? That He persuaded him to incite the king of Israel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="Then Amaziah sent messengers… “… let us confront each other.” in war. 9: ">
      </text>
      <text title="The thistle that was in Lebanon: ">Shechem the son of Hamor.</text>
      <text title="sent to the cedar: ">Jacob.</text>
      <text title="and the wild beast that was in Lebanon came: ">Jacob’s sons came upon the slain. Here too, you come to compare yourself to me. This was a degrading comparison, for he likened him to a thistle, and himself to a cedar.</text>
      <text title="and the wild beast that was in Lebanon came and trampled: ">Because you are arrogant, you too, the troops of my armies will trample you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="and the hostage children: ">the children of the princes, who were placed in the king’s palace as security that their fathers would not rebel against him. And so did Jonathan render: the children of the princes.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="And Amaziah… lived…: ">The entire fifteen years, Uzziah his son reigned during his lifetime, for so it is written in II Chron. (25:26): “And since the time that Amaziah turned away from following the Lord, [they rebelled against him in Jerusalem, and he fled to Lachish. And they sent after him to Lachish and assassinated him there].”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="And they revolted against him in Jerusalem: ">since they heard what the prophet said, “That God has given counsel to destroy you.”</text>
      <text title="and he fled to Lachish: ">He was there for the entire fifteen years.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="after the king had slept with his forefathers: ">after the death of his father Amaziah. From here you deduce that Uzziah reigned during his father’s lifetime. Nevertheless, Elath was not given into his hand until after his father’s death, for if he did not reign during his father’s lifetime, why was it necessary to state, “after the king had slept with his forefathers?” And when you count the days of the Temple according to the years of the kings, if you do not subtract these fifteen years, which are counted for Amaziah and Uzziah, you will find that it existed four hundred twenty-five years, [instead of the traditional four hundred and ten (Yoma 9a)].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="He restored: ">from the hand of the kings of Aram.</text>
      <text title="Jonah the son of Amittai: ">He was the one who anointed Jehu, who said to him (10:30), “Your descendants of the fourth generation will occupy…” Our Rabbis, however, deduced from Jonah 3:1, “And the word of the Lord came to Jonah a second time,” [i.e., a second time] but not a third time, since he demanded the honor of the son, [Israel,] but he did not demand the honor of the Father, [God]. This verse was therefore difficult to them [since this would make a third prophecy], and they reconciled it thus. Just like the word of the Lord, which He had spoken through Jonah concerning Nineveh, and the evil decree was changed for good, so was it changed for Israel in the days of Jeroboam the son of Joash, from the distress in which they were found, [i.e.,] that “the king of Aram had destroyed them and made them like dust to trample” (13:7), and now it was changed for the good.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="increasingly severe: ">very vexing (kontrarios in O.F.). Similar to (Jos. 1:18) “who will rebel (יַמְרֶה) against your command” ; (Deut. 9:24) “You have been contrary (מַמְרִים) with the Lord” ; (Gen. 26:38) “And they were of contrary spirit (מֹרַת רוּחַ).” Others interpret מְאֹד מֹרֶה as “very low,” an expression of (Ex. 15:4) “He cast (יָרָה) into the sea.”</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="15">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="In the twenty-seventh year of Jeroboam: ">Is it possible to say so? Did not Uzziah and Jeroboam reign simultaneously, as I explained shortly before this (14:22)? What, then, is the meaning of the verse, “In the twenty seventh year of Jeroboam… Azariah… became king” ? That from that year, he reigned a plagued kingship. We learn that he was stricken with “zaraath” in the twenty-seventh year of his reign.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="And the Lord brought a plague upon the king: ">It is explained in Chronicles (II 26:16-21) that he entered the heichal, the Temple proper, to burn incense on the altar of incense.</text>
      <text title="in a house of retirement: ">[lit. in a house of freedom] He made himself a house in the cemetery, as it is said (Ps. 88: 6), “Among the dead a free man.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="In the thirty eighth year of Azariah the king of Judah, Zechariah… reigned: ">From here too it is possible to deduce that Azariah reigned from the time that Joash king of Israel died, fifteen years during the lifetime of Amaziah his father, for if he did not rise until his father died, it follows that he did not rise until the fifteenth year of Jeroboam the son of Joash. Now, since Jeroboam reigned forty-one years, it follows that Jeroboam died in the twenty-seventh year of Uzziah. Now, how does Scripture say, “In the thirty-eighth year” ? Rather, we are forced [to admit that] Uzziah and Jeroboam reigned simultaneously, except that Jeroboam reigned three years during the lifetime of his father Jehoash. Therefore, Scripture states (13:13), “and Jeroboam had sat on his throne,” meaning that he had already sat. Now Uzziah rose when Joash died and Jeroboam reigned as a full fledged monarch (lit. a full kingship). I saw in Seder Olam (ch. 19) that Jeroboam reigned one year during his father’s lifetime, and I do not know whether it is the copyists’ error, for I cannot reconcile [the verse reading,] “In the thirty eighth year of Azariah… Zechariah… reigned,” except in this manner.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="and struck him before the people: ">Jonathan. [I.e.,] before the eyes of the people.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="and it was so: ">Not that his kingdom deserved to last that long, but to fulfill the word of the King, as it is said, (Is. 55:11) “So shall be My word, which will go forth from My mouth, [it will not return] to Me empty…”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="since he did not open: ">[I.e.,] the mayor of the city did not open the city for him, to accept him as king over them.</text>
      <text title="its pregnant women: ">The pregnant women therein, he ripped open.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="his officer: ">his mighty warrior.</text>
      <text title="near the palace: ">(אַרְגֹּב)</text>
      <text title="and near the lion: ">Every “argov” is an expression of important palaces, and every mention of “terachunin” in Aramaic (See Rashi, Deut. 3:4) means palaces important for the kingdom. [Hence, he assassinated him] in the great chamber that was next to the palace.</text>
      <text title="and near the lion: ">It is possible to say that a golden lion was standing in that palace (or chamber).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="in the twentieth year of Jotham: ">He should have said, “in the fourth year of Ahaz,” since Jotham’s entire reign lasted sixteen years, but since Ahaz was wicked, Scripture preferred to count them (i. e., the years) to Jotham who was in the grave, rather than to Ahaz, who was alive. Thus it is stated in Seder Olam (Ch. 22).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="In those days: ">at the end of Jotham’s days.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="16">
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="and exiled it to Kir: ">The people therein he exiled to a province named Kir.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="until King Ahaz came: ">[i.e.,] before the king came from Damascus.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="And the copper altar… he brought near…: ">It is impossible to say that this was the copper altar that Moses made, since it was hidden. It is also impossible to say that this was the stone altar that Solomon made, and he called it in II Chron. (7:7) the copper altar, for it was impossible to move it from one corner to another without demolishing it. Indeed, we learned (Zebahim 61b): The fire that descended in Solomon’s time, did not leave the altar until Manasseh came and removed it, for he demolished the altar, as we find in the Aggadah of the chapter entitled ‘Chelek.’ I have no way to explain this except as referring to the lavers and the laver stands of copper, which were accessories of the altar and were near the holy altar. Now when Ahaz made the altar for the idols, he removed the laver and brought it near to another side, farther away from the Temple, so as not to intervene between the altar he made and the house of the Lord, and he placed it next to the holy altar on the north. We find that our Rabbis explained [a passage] in a similar manner in Tractate Shabbath 55a: “And they came and stood next to the copper altar” (Ezekiel 9:2). Did the copper altar exist [at that time]? He said to them, “Commence from the place where they recite songs before Me.” Thus we see here that copper musical instruments are called an altar. [Similarly, the copper laver, also an accessory to the altar, is called “the copper altar.”]</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="shall be for me to visit: ">at intervals, when it would enter his mind to visit it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="the insets of the laver stands: ">the rows upon which the laver stands were made as it is said (I Kings 7:28), “And this is the work of the laver stand, they had insets.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="And the Sabbath canopy: ">the roof of a tent, made for shade, to sit under it in the Temple court on the Sabbath day.</text>
      <text title="and the king’s… entrance: ">through which he would come from his house to the house of the Lord through the outside, he switched to a concealed place because of the king of Assyria, lest he covet those vessels, and also the entrance he switched, perhaps he would have to hide and escape surreptitiously.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="17">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="In the twelfth year of Ahaz…: ">It is impossible to say that Hoshea became king in the twelfth year of Ahaz, for in the fourth year of Ahaz, he assassinated Pekah and reigned in his stead (See above 15:30), and when you calculate Pekah’s years you will find it so. Likewise, it is impossible to say that he did not reign more than nine years, for he reigned from the fourth year of Ahaz until the sixth year of Hezekiah, when Samaria was captured. This amounts to more than sixteen years. What then is the meaning of “nine years” ? Since he rebelled against the king of Assyria. This is what we learned in Seder Olam (ch. 23). Now it is impossible to say that in the twelfth year of Ahaz he started to rebel, for if so, you will find the years of his revolt five years during the days of Hezekiah, making eleven years, yet here he states that he reigned nine years. The twelfth year of Ahaz was mentioned only in connection with the following verse, “Shalmaneser the king of Assyria went up against him,” that in the twelfth year of Ahaz, Sennacherib went up against Hoshea and exiled those who were on the eastern bank of the Jordan. Thus we learned in Seder Olam (ch. 22), and a verse is written in Chron. I (5:26): “The God of Israel aroused Pul the king of Assyria… and he exiled the Reubenites and the Gadites…” And he did not explain at what time. Here he explains that it was in the twelfth year of Ahaz. The ten tribes were exiled at three different times (lit. three exiles were the ten tribes exiled): (1) in the twentieth year of Pekah, as it is written above, (15:29)… “Tiglath Pileser the king of Assyria came and took Ijon and Dan… and the entire land of Naphtali (sic) and exiled them to Assyria.” Now this was the fourth year of Ahaz. (2) He waited eight years and came upon them in the twelfth year of Ahaz, and exiled the Reubenites and the Gadites. When Hoshea the son of Elah saw this, he revolted against him and sent messengers to So the king of Egypt. (3) He waited eight years and came and laid siege to Samaria. After three years it was captured, and everyone was exiled. This is the meaning of that which is written (Is. 8:23): “Like the first time, he dealt mildly, the land of Zebulun and the land of Naphtali.” [I.e., just as the king of Assyria dealt mildly with Israel in the first exile by exiling only Zebulun and Naphtali,] so did he deal mildly also in the second exile, for he exiled but two tribes. But “in the last one, he swept (Heb. ‘hichbid’)” . He swept everything out like one who sweeps a house. In any case, according to the figures he wrote here as the number of years of his revolt, [i.e.,] nine years, he did not revolt against him until the fourteenth year of Ahaz, for Ahaz reigned sixteen years; the revolt was three years of Ahaz and six years in the days of Hezekiah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="though not like the kings of Israel: ">for he abolished the sentries who were stationed since the days of Jeroboam, on the roads, to guard lest the Israelites perform the pilgrimage for the festivals, and this one abolished them, for the golden calves had already been exiled in the two exiles. In the first exile “he took Ijon and Dan.” He exiled the calf that was in Dan. And in the second, when Reuben and Gad were exiled, he took the calf that was in Bethel, to fulfill what was stated (Hosea 10:6), “That too, to Assyria will be transported.” Since the sentries were abolished, and they (the Israelites) refrained from performing the pilgrimage, therefore, their verdict was sealed to be exiled in his days, for until now, they had blamed the corruption on their kings, but now they had no one to blame. This is what Hosea the son of Beeri said (Hosea 5:3), “For now you have gone astray, Ephraim; Israel has become defiled.” Now your evil has been revealed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="In the ninth year: ">of Hoshea’s revolt.</text>
      <text title="and exiled the Israelites: ">[Heb. וַיֶגֶל,] like וַיַגְלֶה אֶת יִשׂרָאֵל This is the rule of every word whose verb root [ends] with a mute ‘heh’, [e.g. פנה, to face,] בנה, to build, גלה, to go in exile, זנה to commit harlotry, רבה, to multiply, when one comes to prefix the word with “vav” “yud,” [i.e., the “vav” that converts the verb from future to past,] if the word applies to the doer, [i. e.,] if the verb appears in the light conjugation, involving only one doer, the “yud” will be voweled with a “hirik,” e. g.“and he built (וַיִבֶן) there an altar” (Gen. 12:8);“And Moses turned (וַיִפֶן) and descended” (Ex. 32:15);“And Judah was exiled (וַיִגֶל) off its land” (below 25:21);“And she too went and committed harlotry (וַתִּזֶן) ” (Jer. 3:8);“And the people multiplied (וַיִרֶב) and became very strong” (Ex. 1:20). If, however, one is talking in the causative conjugation, the “yud” will be voweled with a “segol” , [e.g.] “and turned (וַיֶפֶן) tail to tail” (Jud. 15:4);“And exiled (וַיֶגֶל) the Israelites to Assyria” (here);“And he caused the dwellers of Jerusalem to commit harlotry (וַיֶזֶן) ” (II Chron. 21:11);“And He increased (וַיֶרֶב) among the people of Judah grief and lamentation” (Lam. 2:5).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="And they fabricated: ">This interpretation is according to context.</text>
      <text title="from watchtower: ">which is made only to station a lookout to watch. In every high house they erected idols.</text>
      <text title="to fortified city: ">like “from small to big” (Gen. 19:11 and many other places).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="And the Lord warned: ">He warned them.</text>
      <text title="all prophets of all visions: ">Heb. נְבִיאֵי כָל חֹזֶה, prophets of all visions. [Although חוֹזֶה usually means “seer,”] there is [a word] חוֹזֶה that is a noun, such as (Is.28:5) “and with the grave have we made a boundary (חוֹזֶה).”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="two molten calves: ">[lit. a molten image, two calves] - in Bethel and in Dan.</text>
      <text title="the Baal: ">a pagan deity named Baal.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="and they committed themselves: ">[lit.] they sold themselves to that.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="and He sent them away from before Him: ">for they were exiled with Hoshea the son of Elah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="and Israel went in exile: ">[Heb. וַיִגֶל.] This is vowelized with a “hirik,” which is an expression of “went in exile.” It is not an expression of “exiled.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="they did not fear the Lord: ">Even though the pagan nations fear him and call him the God of the gods, in the manner it is written (Malachi 1:14), “and My Name is feared among the nations,” these did not fear Me, for they said, “If He were worthy of fear, He would not have delivered His people into exile.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="the people of Samaria had made: ">[i.e.,] the Israelites while they were still there.</text>
      <text title="each nation its god (sic): ">Every nation (as per R. Joseph Kara), the deity they had worshipped in their land, here, too, each nation did so in the city (as per R. Joseph Kara) which Sennacherib had given them as a possession (or had settled them Kara) there in the cities of Israel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="Succoth benoth: ">a likeness of a hen with her chicks.</text>
      <text title="Nergal: ">the likeness of a rooster.</text>
      <text title="Ashima: ">the likeness of a goat. So they are called in the language of every nation, and so did our Rabbis explain in Sanhedrin (63b).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="Nibhaz: ">the likeness of a dog.</text>
      <text title="Tartak: ">the likeness of a donkey.</text>
      <text title="to Adramelech: ">the likeness of a mule.</text>
      <text title="Anamelech: ">the likeness of a horse.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="as was the custom of the nations whom they had exiled from there: ">Those deities that the nations whom Sennacherib and his armies had exiled from there, worshipped, these they would worship here.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="they do not fear the Lord: ">a complete fear as the custom of the Israelites. Even though they were converted because of the fear of the lions, their fear of the Lord was not a complete fear, (like Jewish practice) as Scripture goes on to elaborate, that they were not engaged in the Torah and the commandments which He (or, which the Lord) commanded the sons of Jacob, neither do they practice according to their statutes and according to their law, which they are duty bound to practice since they converted, but as the priest who was of the people of Samaria, who were idolatrous, instructed them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="And the Lord enacted a covenant with them: ">when He gave them the Torah on Mt. Sinai.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="18">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="in the third year: ">of Hoshea’s rebellion.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="and he called it Nehushtan: ">a pejorative, as though to say, “Why is this necessary? It is nothing but a copper serpent.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="he succeeded: ">[Heb. יַשְׂכִּיל] He succeeded.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="stripped: ">the doors, which were of gold.</text>
      <text title="and the thresholds: ">This follows Targum.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="Tartan and Rabsaris: ">We learned in Seder Olam (?) that the three of them did not come together, but Rabshakeh came alone, as the prophet wrote in the Book of Isaiah (36:2), and Tartan and Rabsaris came on a second mission, when he received word concerning Tarhakah, king of Cush, “and he heard and sent emissaries to Hezekiah…” (Is. 37:9).</text>
      <text title="near the conduit: ">fosed (fosse) in French. A ditch, a trench, a moat.</text>
      <text title="the washer’s field: ">A field where the washers stretch out garments. So did Jonathan render, “a field where the washers stretch out.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="the recorder: ">which judgment came first before the king, that he should first adjudicate.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="You have said but words of the lips…: ">Until now you have said, “I will not pay tribute to the king of Assyria.” It was but words of the lips. As long as he did not leave his place to march upon you, you did not require counsel and might. Now, however, that he has left [his place] and come upon you, you require counsel and might for this war. Now tell upon whom you have depended?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="and it will go into his palm: ">When a person supports himself on a support of a splintered reed, which has broken in his hand, the ends of the scaly envelope will come and puncture his palm.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="Is He not the one Whose high places and altars Hezekiah has removed…: ">It can be deduced from here that Rabshakeh was an apostate Jew, for he admits that the Holy One, Blessed be He, is God, but His will is that we worship idols.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="wager now: ">boast over him. Enter a wager on the condition that if you are able to supply riders for two thousand horses. wager, gajjer in O.F.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="And how can you repulse one captain of… my master’s servants: ">for the smallest of them is captain over two thousand men, and you cannot obtain two thousand men. We deduce from here concerning the heads of the armies, who totaled 185,000, who fell with Sennacherib, that the smallest of them was captain over two thousand men that were with him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="is it with other than the Lord: ">Did I come without permission? Isaiah already prophesied in the days of Ahaz your father (Is. 7:17), “The Lord shall bring upon you and upon your people… the king of Assyria.”</text>
      <text title="and destroy it: ">This he added of his own.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="for we understand: ">We are residents of the palace, and understand the Aramaic language and other languages. Do not speak to us Judean, which all the people understand, and we do not want them to hear.</text>
      <text title="within the hearing of the people: ">For all the people understand Judean, and they are frightened by your words. Since he said to them, “Say now to Hezekiah,” they thought that he did not come to frighten the people. Since Rabshakeh was an apostate Jew, they thought that even though his master’s orders were incumbent upon Rabshakeh [to observe], but his heart was attracted to his family and he would take pity upon them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="to eat their dung: ">in the hunger [brought about] by the siege.</text>
      <text title="their dung: ">[The] kethib [reads] חֹרֵיהֶם - dung that is excreted through the orifice of the anus. Our Rabbis explained to euphemize and read, צוֹאָתָם, i.e., their dung.</text>
      <text title="their urine: ">[According to] kethib, שִׁינֵיהֶם, [however, we explain it as] loose excrement, the glands of the rectum, which is held by three glands. Alternatively, an expression of excrement which comes about through the chewing of the teeth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="Make peace with me: ">[Lit. make a blessing with me - an expression of] a greeting, like (Gen. 47:7) “and Jacob greeted Pharaoh.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="to a land like your land: ">So is my wont to repatriate the nations from province to province. He should have said, “to a land better than yours,” since he came to entice them, but he knew that they would recognize that his statement was false.</text>
      <text title="a land of grain and wine: ">This is Africa.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="He exiled them and twisted them: ">[Heb. וְעִוָה הֵנַע.] The King of Assyria [exiled them and twisted] them; [i.e.,] he destroyed them and exiled them.</text>
      <text title="Now, did they save Samaria: ">and the inhabitants of Samaria worshipped the gods of the Arameans, who were their neighbors.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="with torn garments: ">because they heard blasphemies of the Name of God.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="19">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="and debate: ">that the wicked are debating and showing evidence to their words, saying, “We have power and strength.”</text>
      <text title="children: ">Israel.</text>
      <text title="as far as the birthstool: ">as far as a distress analogous to a woman sitting on the birthstool, and she has no strength to give birth. [The Hebrew is] מַשְׁבֵּר - the name of the seat used by a woman who kneels to give birth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="and he brought proof with the words: ">eprover in French, to prove. He showed evidence to his statement, that he prospered wherever he went.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="and he will hear a rumor: ">and he will withdraw from you and return to his land. [He will] not [return] because of the rumor, but after a while he will return shamefacedly, and I will cause him to fall there by the sword. Now what was the rumor? (v. 9) “And he heard [a rumor] about Tirhakah.” He heard that Tirhakah had gone out to wage war against him. Consequently, he withdrew from Jerusalem and went to Cush, and waged war with Tirhakah, Put and Egypt, who were with him. He defeated him and took their most coveted treasures, and came to Jerusalem, where he fell. In reference to this, Isaiah stated (Is. 45:14), “The toil of Egypt and the merchandise of Cush… will pass by you….”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="and he again sent messengers: ">to notify him that he was returning to his land only to wage war with Cush, and then to return here.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="Eden: ">the name of a province.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="he exiled and twisted: ">[I.e.,] the king of Assyria exiled and twisted them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="Indeed: ">It is true that the kings of Assyria destroyed the peoples and committed their deities to the fire.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="to the heights of mountains: ">the Temple mount.</text>
      <text title="to the end of the Lebanon: ">the Temple which whitens the sins (Heb. מַלְבִּין).</text>
      <text title="and I will cut down its tallest cedars: ">I will not return until I have destroyed it.</text>
      <text title="its remotest lodge: ">[lit. the lodge of] its end.</text>
      <text title="its farmland forest: ">the fullness of its land and the beauty of its splendor.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="I dug and drank strange water: ">I.e., to say, I started all my deeds and completed [them], as one who digs a hole and finds strange water and drinks it. Flowing water he calls “strange” since until now no one knew of them.</text>
      <text title="and I will dry up with the soles of my feet: ">If I would besiege a city reliant upon its rivers, I would bring many troops upon it who would dry up its rivers with their drinking and the drinking of their cattle and by the treading of their feet.</text>
      <text title="and I will dry up: ">This is the present tense. So is my wont always.</text>
      <text title="rivers of the siege: ">all the rivers of the city that is besieged by me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="Have you not heard from afar: ">Why do you boast and aggrandize yourself with this? This is not yours, for you have heard from afar through the prophets, that I decreed upon the nations to bring you upon them, as the matter that is written (Is. 7:4), “Ho, Assyria, the staff of My wrath.” [In Is. 37:26 Rashi adds:] More than seventy years since Amos prophesied two years before the earthquake (Amos 7:17), “and Israel shall be exiled from upon its land.” Since then, you should have heard that I wrought and prepared this retribution.</text>
      <text title="in the days of yore: ">Since the world was created, it entered My thought, as it is said (Is. 30:33), “For Gehinnom is arranged from days of yore; that too was prepared for the king.” This refers to Sennacherib, who was burned in the fire of Gehinnom, as it is said (Is. 31:9), “The word of the Lord, Who has fire in Zion.”</text>
      <text title="Now I have brought it: ">and this is the power that is in your hand</text>
      <text title="and it shall be: ">the coming of My decree [shall be] to make desolate fortified cities into blossoming hills, into piles of earth upon which vegetables grow, for you destroy them because of My decree.</text>
      <text title="to make desolate: ">[לַהְשׁוֹת in Heb.] an expression of desolation, loneliness.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="And their inhabitants became short of strength: ">Those whom weakened before you, and the might is not yours. You are not mighty, but they are weak.</text>
      <text title="like grass of the roofs: ">which hastens to dry.</text>
      <text title="and blast before becoming standing grain: ">like ears of grain, blasted before they hardened to become standing grain.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="And your sitting and your going out and your coming: ">Jonathan paraphrased: And your sitting in counsel, and your going out to wage war, and your coming to the land of Israel, is revealed to Me. It emanated from Me.</text>
      <text title="and your raging against Me: ">And the fact that you will become arrogant and aroused against Me with anger and tumult. (Estomir in O.F.)</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="and your tumult: ">like וּשְׁאוֹנְ.</text>
      <text title="My ring: ">[חַחִי in Heb.] a kind of ring by which they pull an animal whose behavior is bad, as we learned (Shabbath 5:1), “And all animals that are usually pulled with a ring may go out with a ring.”</text>
      <text title="and my bit: ">[Heb. מִתְגִי,] Jonathan rendered זְמַם, which is [made] of iron, and which they insert into the nostrils of a female camel, and she is pulled with it, since her behavior is bad. This is what we learned (Shabbath ibid.) “and the female camel with a nose ring.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="And this will be the sign for you: ">The prophet said this to Hezekiah. And this [prophecy] which I said to you that Sennacherib will fall here, will be a sign for you also for the approaching days, for you are afraid of dying from hunger, since Sennacherib destroyed the land and chopped down the trees.</text>
      <text title="this year you shall eat what grows by itself: ">This year plants will grow for you, and you will be sustained by them.</text>
      <text title="what grows from the tree stumps: ">the chopped off trees that will grow (the products of the trees that will grow), and when you see My word fulfilled concerning the fall of the armies, it will be a sign for you that this promise, too, will be fulfilled.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="the zeal of the Lord of Hosts: ">that He will be zealous for His honor and for His name, not that you have any merit, for Ahaz your father committed many wicked deeds.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="nor shall he advance upon it wlth a shield: ">He shall not set a shield before it. [In Isaiah 37:33, Rashi adds,] Since the Aramaic translation of “before” is קֳדָם.</text>
      <text title="a siege mound: ">[Heb. סֹלְלָה,] a heap of earth to raise a mount upon which to stand to embattle the city. Since one presses it down and beats it with sticks and sledge hammers, so that it be trodden and pressed down with strength, it is called סֹלְלָה, an expression similar to (Is. 62:10) “Beat down, beat down the highway.” [Heb. סֹלוּ סֹלוּ הַמְסִלָה.]</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="And it came to pass on that night: ">when Sennacherib returned from [warring] with Cush, and he came as far as Nob, which was near Jerusalem.</text>
      <text title="one hundred eighty five thousand: ">All of them were heads of companies.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="and dwelt in Nineveh: ">That is the capital of the land of Assyria. [In Isaiah 37:37, Rashi adds,] as it is said (Gen. 10:11), “From that land Ashur came out, and he built Nineveh…”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="the temple of Nisroch his god: ">a board from Noah’s ark.</text>
      <text title="slew him: ">They heard him that he said he would slaughter them before him if they (sic) (he- kara) [would save him so that the princes of the kingdom, whose sons perished because of him, would not kill him].</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="20">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="In those days: ">Three days before Sennacherib’s downfall, Hezekiah became ill, and the third day, when he went up to the house of the Lord, was the day of Sennacherib’s downfall, and it was the [first] festive day of Passover.</text>
      <text title="for you are going to die: ">in this world.</text>
      <text title="and you shall not live: ">in the world to come, for you have not married, as it is stated in Berachoth 10b.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="had not gone out to the inner court…: ">The Holy One, Blessed be He, hastened to inform him of his cure before the report would spread in the city that the death sentence had been decreed as a punishment upon Hezekiah, as is stated in Yerushalmi (Sanhedrin 10:2).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="and I will save you from the hand of the king of Assyria: ">We learn that before Sennacherib’s downfall he became ill.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="a cake of pressed figs: ">[Heb. דְבֶלֶת תְּאֵנִים, lit. a pressed cake of figs.] When they are fresh, they are called תְּאֵנִים, figs, and when they are pressed into a round cake, they are called דְּבֵלָה.</text>
      <text title="and placed it on the boil, and it was healed: ">[This was] a miracle within a miracle, for even healthy flesh - when you place a cake of pressed figs upon it, decays, yet the Holy One, Blessed be He, puts an injurious substance upon vulnerable tissue and it becomes healed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="The shade has advanced ten steps. Shall it come back ten steps?: ">This is an abbreviated verse. The shade has already advanced to the steps (from the steps - Rashi ms., on the steps - R. J. Kara) that are made for the hours of the day like the clocks (horloge in French) that people (sic) (craftsmen - R. J. Kara; Rashi, Isaiah 38:8; the sectarians Parshandatha ibid.; R. J. Kara in Lublin ed.) make to determine the hours of the day. Do you wish it to wait in the place where it is, as long as it takes to go in ten hours, or should it go back up ten steps so that it will appear as though it is morning?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="It is easy for the shade to recline for ten steps: ">It is an easy thing to recline in its place, reclining and standing still for ten steps. It is not so conspicuous. Not so, but let the shade go back, and the thing will be a marvel, for they saw that the day was turning toward evening, and it returns to be morning.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="that it had gone down on the steps of Ahaz: ">The day that Ahaz died, the day was shortened, and the shade hastened to advance ten steps, lest he be eulogized, and those ten hours returned now to Hezekiah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="for he heard that Hezekiah had been ill: ">and until that time no person had ever been ill and had become well. Now, how did he hear? He was accustomed to eating after three hours had elapsed in the day, and he would sleep until after the ninth hour. Since the sphere of the sun had gone backwards, he awoke after nine hours and found that it was morning. He sought to kill his servants. He said, “You let me sleep a day and a night.” They replied, “The sphere of the sun went back.” He said to them, “Who brought it back?” They said to him, “The God of Hezekiah.” As is stated in Pesikta (d’Rav Kahana p. 14a).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="his treasure-house: ">[Heb. בֵּית נְכֹתוֹ] the storehouse of his spices, like (Gen. 37:25) “spices (נְכֹאת) , balm and lotus.”</text>
      <text title="and the good oil: ">Some interpret this as the anointing oil (Ex. 30:22 33), and others interpret it as balsam oil, which is found in Eretz Israel, as it is said (Ezek. 27: 17), “Judah and the land of Israel, they were your merchants, with wheat of Minnith and Pannag.” I saw in the book of Josephon (book 4, ch. 22), Pannag is balsam, and it grows in Jericho. Because of the aroma (רֵיחַ), it is called Jericho (יְרִיחוֹ).</text>
      <text title="there was nothing: ">Even the Ark, the Tablets, and the Scroll of the Law.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="They have come from a distant country: ">This is one of the three whom the Holy One, Blessed be He, tested and found them to be a vessel of turbid water: Cain, Balaam, and Hezekiah. Cain said (Gen. 4:9), “I know not. Am I my brother’s keeper?” He should have said, Lord of the Universe! Are all hidden things not revealed to You? As it is stated in Tanhuma. Balaam, when the Omnipresent said to him (Num. 22:9), “Who are these men with you?” he should have said, “O Lord God, You know!” as it is said concerning Ezekiel (37:3). Yet he retorted arrogantly (Num. 22:10), “Balak, son of Zippor, king of Moab, sent them to me.” Many people seek me. Hezekiah should have replied to Isaiah, “You are the prophet of the Omnipresent. Yet you ask me?” Instead, Hezekiah commenced to become haughty, and said (Is. 39:3), “They have come to me from a distant land.” Therefore, he was punished, and because he rejoiced over them and served them at his table.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="nothing shall remain: ">You shall be paid in kind, [corresponding to] “There was nothing” (v. 15).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="And…[some] of your sons: ">Hananiah, Mishael, and Azariah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="The word of the Lord… is good: ">since there will be peace in my days.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="and how he made the conduit and the pool: ">in Chronicles.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="21">
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="through His servants the prophets: ">Nahum and Habakkuk, but since Manasseh was wicked, they were not referred to with his name to explain that they were in his time.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="will tingle: ">The root is צלל, an expression similar to מְצִלְתַּיִם, cymbals (tentir in French), to ring, resound.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="and the plumb line: ">That is the line upon which the builders of a wall tie a lead weight to make the wall exact.</text>
      <text title="as one wipes a dish: ">as one cleans a dish.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="22">
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="I have found the Scroll of the Law: ">It was hidden under a layer of stones where they had concealed it when Ahaz burned the Torah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="inquire of the Lord on my behalf: ">He saw written, “The Lord will lead you and your king…”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="to Huldah: ">Our Rabbis said that because a woman is more merciful than a man, he, therefore, did not send to Jeremiah. Others say that Jeremiah was not there since he went to bring back the ten tribes.</text>
      <text title="in the study-hall: ">[Heb. בַּמִּשְׁנֶה] (Jonathan renders:) in the study hall. There is a gate in the Temple court, named “the Gate of Huldah.” [This is found in] Tractate Middoth, 1:3. Others interpret בַּמִּשְׁנֶה as “outside the wall,” between the two walls, which are double [around] the city. [בַּמִּשְׁנֶה She was teaching the Oral Law to the elders of the generation. That is the Mishnah. Annotation of R.A.) His identity is unknown. בַּמִשְׁנֶה, From (Deut. 1:1) “These are the words,” until (ibid. 34:12) “before the eyes of all Israel,” and likewise all the things that are repeated in the Torah, she expounded on in public, and revealed the punishments and the exiles which were doubled for those who transgress the secrets and the allusions of the Torah, the secret of equity.]</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="and you shall be gathered into your graves in peace: ">And what is the peace?</text>
      <text title="and your eyes shall not see: ">the destruction of the Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="23">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="on his place: ">the place where the king would stand in the Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="and the priests of the second rank: ">the assistants of the priesthood, who were in second rank to the high priests.</text>
      <text title="and the guards of the threshold: ">the superintendents appointed over all the necessities of the Temple, and the keys of the Temple court were in their charge.</text>
      <text title="in the plains of Kidron: ">in the plains of Kidron.</text>
      <text title="and he carried their ashes to Bethel: ">to an unclean place, where he defiled the altar that Jeroboam had made, and he burnt the priests of the high places upon it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="and who had burnt incense: ">and those who had burnt incense on the high places in the cities of Judah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="the houses devoted to pagan worship: ">[Heb. בָּתֵי הַקְדֵשִׁים,] the houses of immorality</text>
      <text title="where the women weave enclosures: ">curtains.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="However,… would not go up: ">The priests who burnt incense on the high places to idots, may not ascend anymore to serve on the altar of the Lord.</text>
      <text title="they would eat unleavened cakes: ">meal-offerings, and likewise, all hallowed things.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="the Tofeth: ">This was the Molech. Since priests would bang on drums so that the father would not hear the groans of the child when he would be burned by the hands of the pagan image, Molech, they called it Topheth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="the horses: ">Those who prostrated themselves to the sun, had horses ready to go out toward the sun in the morning.</text>
      <text title="Nethan-melech: ">That was his name.</text>
      <text title="in the outskirts: ">[Heb. בַּפַּרְוָרִים.] I do not know what they are.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="and he hurriedly removed them: ">and he eliminated them from there.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="the Mount of the Destroyer: ">The Mount of Olives, which is known as the Mount of Oil (הַר הַמִּשְׁחָה). Since he mentioned its name in reference to idolatry, he changed its name to a pejorative.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="“What is this marker?”: ">He saw a grave, one side of which was overgrown with thorns and thistles, and whose other side was [graced with] myrtles and spices. He wondered about it and said, “What is this?” And they replied,…</text>
      <text title="The grave of the man of God: ">and the false prophet, who commanded his sons that they bury him next to him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="that were in the cities of Samaria: ">for Josiah was king over all Israel, those who returned from the ten tribes through Jeremiah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="such a Passover sacrifice had not been performed: ">So many people had not assembled at any Passover sacrifice as assembled at this one.</text>
      <text title="since the days of the judges: ">In II Chron. 35:18, it is written, “Since the days of Samuel,” because Samuel, too, led Israel to improve [their ways], and he assembled them to Mizpah (I Sam. 7:5, 6). Alternatively, such a Passover had not been performed to the Lord in Jerusalem. Since the kings of Israel and the kings of Judah reigned, all Israel did not perform a Passover sacrifice in Jerusalem, because the kingdom had been divided in two since Jeroboam, and they would go to the calf in Bethel and in Dan until now that the ten tribes were exiled, and Jeremiah brought them back, and Josiah reigned over them, and they all came to Jerusalem.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="the teraphim: ">images that speak through sorcery, and the one who makes them must determine one hour in the year and one year that is fit for this.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="and anointed him: ">He required anointing only because Jehoiakim his brother was two years older than he, as is explained in this episode.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="each one according to his assessment: ">according to his wealth.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="24">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="Indeed, it was by the order of the Lord: ">all the calamity that befell Judah through these bands.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="And Jehoiakim slept with his forefathers: ">not in his bed, for Nebuchadnezzar bound him with copper chains to take him to Babylon, and they were dragging him, and he died in their hands, as it is said (Jer. 22:19), “The burial of a donkey you shall be buried, dragged and thrown [past the gates of Jerusalem.]” And in II Chron. 36:6, it is written that Nebuchadnezzar bound him to take him to Babylon.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="went out of his land: ">to aid Jehoiakim</text>
      <text title="for the king of Babylonia had taken…: ">for he defeated him in battle in the fourth year of Jehoiakim in Carchemish on the Euphrates River, as is written in the Book of Jeremiah (46:2.)</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And Jehoiachin, the king of Judah, came out to the king of Babylonia: ">that he should do to him as he wishes, not for war.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="the craftsmen and the sentries of the gates: ">[Heb. וְהַמַסְגֵר הֶחָרָשׁ] Jonathan rendered: the craftsmen and the sentries of the gates, [translating harash as craftsmen, as in Ex. 28:11, and masger as closing, i.e., those who close the gates.] Our Rabbis, however, said that these were great Torah scholars, that when one would open his mouth to speak, all would remain silent, as it is written (Is. 41:1), “Keep silence (הַחֲרִישׁוּ) before Me, O islands.” “Masger,” all would sit before him and learn from him, as it is said (Is. 22:22), “And he will open, and no one will close, and he will close, and no one will open.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="and the dignitaries of the land: ">These are the dignitaries of Judah and Benjamin, who were righteous men. Concerning them the Scripture states (Jer. 24:5), “Like these good figs, so will I recognize the exiles of Judah.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="seven thousand: ">Yet above (v. 14) he states, “ten thousand.” The third verse comes to reconcile the difference between them. In Jeremiah 52:28, [we read], “This is the people whom Nebuchadnezzar exiled in the seventh year, three thousand Judeans.” We deduce from here that three thousand were of the tribe of Judah and seven thousand of Benjamin and other tribes. Also in Seder Olam ch. 25 I learned this.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="and he changed his name to Zedekiah: ">May the Lord justify (יָהּ יַצְדִּיק) the judgment upon you if you rebel against me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="Because the wrath of the Lord was…: ">Therefore, Zedekiah rebelled against the king of Babylonia. The Holy One, Blessed be He, gave [the desire] into his heart to rebel against him in order that he would be exiled.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="25">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="in the ninth year of his reign: ">[i.e., the reign] of Zedekiah.</text>
      <text title="works of siege: ">Jonathan renders: Karkom [which is the Aramaic term for works of siege].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="by way of the gate between the two walls: ">A cave went from his house until the plains of Jericho, and he fled through the cave. The Holy One, Blessed be He, ordained a deer walking on the roof of the cave. The Chaldeans pursued the deer, and when they reached the entrance of the cave in the plains of Jericho, they saw him and captured him. This is what Ezekiel said, (12: 13) “And I will spread My net over him, and he shall be caught in My net…”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="and called him to account: ">He debated with him concerning the oath.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="and all the houses of the dignitaries: ">[lit. the house of every great one.] Synagogues wherein Torah and prayer are aggrandized, and the houses of the princes.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="and the defectors: ">who obeyed Nebuchadnezzar and went out to him from the city, like (I Chron. 12:20) “When he went to Ziklag, of Manasseh… defected to him.”</text>
      <text title="and farmers: ">Heb. יגבים, diggers of the earth, an expression of wine vats (יְקָבִים).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="and the height of the capital was three cubits: ">and in the beginning of the book (I Kings 7:16) he says, “five cubits.” There I reconciled the verses.</text>
      <text title="and a net: ">[coffe in French] like a sort of hat.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="the scribe of the general of the army: ">who knew the number of every city, how many men it sends forth to the army.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="all the officers of the armies: ">who had vacated the city to hide in the strongholds and in the boulders and in the rocks (sic) and in the forests.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="Evil-Merodach… lived: ">for Nebuchadnezzar died, and Evil-Merodach reigned in his stead.</text>
      <text title="On the twenty-seventh day of the month: ">In Jeremiah (52:31), Scripture states, “On the twenty- fifth.” Rather, on the twenty-fifth Nebuchadnezzar died. He was buried on the twenty-sixth. On the twenty-seventh, Evil- Merodach removed him from his grave and dragged him about, in order to nullify his decrees, as it is said, “and you have been cast out of your grave like a despised sapling…” (Is. 14:19).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="And he spoke with him kindly: ">words of consolation.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
</book>