<book>
  <chapter id="1">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="and behold, a man came from the camp: ">It is found in Pesikta (D’Rav Kahana ch. 3:143, Rabb. ch. 12:9) that this was Doeg, but it does not seem plausible to me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="a shudder has seized me: ">The Midrash Aggadah explains. Because of the iniquity of Nob, the city of priests, which he had slain, concerning whom it is stated: כתנת תשבץ (“a tunic of checkered work”) (Ex. 28:4)</text>
      <text title="For as long as my life is within me: ">Hasten and put me to death. It is better for me that you put me to death than these (men)slay me and mock me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="the crown which was on his head and the armlet which was on his arm: ">and the phylactery which was on his arm.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="Your blood be upon your head: ">There is no penalty for your death except to yourself.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="And he said to teach the sons of Judah the bow: ">And David said, Since the heroes of Israel have fallen, the sons of Judah must teach them (to wage) war and to draw the bow.</text>
      <text title="Behold, it is written in the book of the just: ">In the Book of Gen., which is the book of the just: Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob. Now, where is it implied?“Your hand be on the nape of your enemies.” (Gen. 49:8) What type of warfare is it wherein one directs his hand against his forehead which is opposite his nape? We must say that this is the bow.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="O beauty of Israel! On your high places shall lie the slain?: ">O support of Israel (Saul and Jonathan)! At the peak of your strength you have fallen slain! So did I render this.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="O mountains of Gilboa: ">The mountains which are in Gilboa.</text>
      <text title="nor shall you be fields of heave offerings: ">Let there not be in you enough grain from which to separate a cake (חלה).</text>
      <text title="for there the shield of the mighty was rejected: ">They had leather shields, which, upon departure to battle, they would anoint with oil, to that the weapon which would strike it would glide off, as it is stated: “Arise, O princes, anoint the shields” (Is. 21:5). And here, with this lamentation, he lamented this: There the shield of the mighty was purged. It rejected its oil and it did not adhere to it. Hence, it became as though not anointed with oil. Every הגלה is an expression of something which casts off that which is placed therein, like: “His bull impregnates and does not cast off (his semen)” (Job 21:10).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="did not turn back: ">was not accustomed to turn back.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="they were swifter than eagles: ">To perform the will of their Creator.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="who dressed you in crimson with delights: ">who would dress you in colorful clothing and bring you delights.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="on your high places you were slain!: ">At the peak of your strength you were slain (explaining ‘high places’ figuratively).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="How have the mighty fallen and the weapons of war perished!: ">Saul and Jonathan who were Israel’s weapons of war (perished).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="2">
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="and brought him over to Mahanaim: ">He expounded a scriptural passage that two kings were destined to arise from Benjamin, for the Holy One, blessed be He, said to Jacob, “And kings will come out of your loins” (Gen. 35: 11), And all his sons had been born except Benjamin.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="‘the territory of those slain by the sharp swords’: ">‘the territory of the slain,’ named צורים for the swords, as it is stated: “also you turned back the blade (צור) of his sword” (Ps. 80:44).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="under the fifth (rib): ">(Heb. אל החמש) like the fifth rib; the place where the liver and gall bladder are suspended (San. 49a). Jonathan renders: לסטר ירכה - to the side of his hip.</text>
      <text title="and he died in his place: ">i.e., he died immediately.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="had you not spoken: ">if you had spoken so. לולא is like לו. It may also be interpreted according to its usual meaning. Had you not spoken what you said, Let the boys get up now and play.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="the Bithron: ">the name of a section.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="nineteen men and Asahel: ">Now, was not Asahel included among David’s servants? Why then, was he counted separately? Because he was equal to all of them. Similarly, “go and see the land and Jericho” (Josh. 2:1), and similarly: “and King Solomon loved many foreign wives and Pharaoh’s daughter” (I Kings 11:1).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="3">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="and his second, Chileab of Abigail: ">Elsewhere the Scripture calls him: “And his second, Daniel” (I Chron. 3:1). Said Rabbi Isaac: Since the scorners of the generation were saying that Abigail was pregnant from Nabal, his features were changed, so that he resembled his father. And our Rabbis said that he would embarrass (מכלים) Mephibosheth in legal matters.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="of Eglah, David’s wife: ">This was Michal who was very dear to him (and was affectionately called Eglah, a heifer) and similarly the Scripture states: “If you had not plowed with my heifer” (Jud. 14:18). Now, is it not stated: “And Michal the daughter of Saul did not have a child to the day of her death” (infra 6:22)? Until the day of her death she did not have children after that incident (when she showed contempt for David). Prior to that incident, however, she did have a child.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="was exerting great effort: ">with all his might, upon the House of Saul to support its kingdom.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="“Am I the head of the dogs which belong to Judah?”: ">Am I not even as esteemed as the watchman of David’s dogs? But, according to the punctuation, that the accent is under הראש (separating it from the following word) and כלב אנכי are joined by a hyphen, this is its explanation: Shall I desire to be a head in your house? Is it better for me to be a dog and a plain person in the house of David. And so did Jonathan render.</text>
      <text title="Shall I do kindness today: ">From now on is it proper for me to do kindness with the house of Saul and with all his friends as I have done until now and I have not delivered you into David’s hands?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="from his place, saying: ">(Heb. תחתיו) from his place saying, I swear by the One who created the earth.</text>
      <text title="To whom the land belongs: ">An expression of an oath: By the One to whom the earth belongs. Another explanation is: under him. He mentioned his name first in the letter, and afterwards he mentioned David’s name. Therefore, he was punished. He wrote: from me, Abner, the general of the army of Israel, to David, King of Israel, peace.</text>
      <text title="To whom the land belongs: ">To the one to whom the kingdom properly belongs, I send, saying, make your covenant, etc.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="namely that: ">(lit., saying) you first bring (lit., before your bringing). Your bringing of Michal must precede your seeing of my face.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="from a man: ">Jonathan renders: from her husband.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="walking and weeping: ">for the commandment which was leaving him, for all those years he thrust a sword between himself and her in the bed and did not sin with her.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="And the word of Abner had been: ">previously.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="about David: ">lit., to David. However, it is not far in meaning from ‘to’ [David].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="from pursuing a troop: ">(lit., from the troop) They raided a troop to plunder the enemy.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="from the well of thorns: ">The well was situated among thorns. Therefore, this became the name of the place. Our Rabbis, however, stated: A well and a thorn caused Abner to be killed, for he did not support David’s statement concerning the flask of water which he took from near Saul’s head, and also concerning the skirt of Saul’s cloak. He said, Perhaps one of the thorns was caught upon it and tore it, (and perhaps one of the youths forgot the flask in a well and David found it.)</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="into the midst of the gate: ">before the tribunal, to be judged concerning the killing of Asahel his brother.</text>
      <text title="unwittingly: ">for Abner did not know that he was plotting to assassinate him. Transpose the verse so that it reads: And Joab caused him to turn aside unwittingly into the midst of the gate to speak with him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="May it rest: ">May the (punishment for the) blood of Abner rest. It refers to the above verse, in which he said, I and my kingdom are innocent of the blood of Abner. May (punishment for) his blood rest upon the head of Joab. His blood which is mentioned in the above verse.</text>
      <text title="or one who leans on a staff: ">one who leans on his staff because of a foot ailment.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="slew Abner: ">(Heb. הרגו לאבנר) like את אבנר (the usual form for the definitive object). Similar to this is: “Rob me (from the Angel of Death), Be a surety for me” (Is. 35:14). עשקה לי instead of עשקה אותי; and so: “please heal her” (Num. 12:13), Heb. רפא נא לה, instead of, רפא אותה; and similarly: “He sent his princes, Benhail, Obadiah, etc. to teach in the cities of Judah” (II Chron. 17:7, Heb. שלח לשריו לבן חיל לעובדי) and its meaning is as though it were written: חיל שלח את שריו את בן.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="die like a wicked man: ">as a wicked man dies, by the sword.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="Your hands were not bound: ">So how did a mighty man like you fall before these wicked men?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="to serve: ">(Heb. להברות) an expression of a meal.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="39">
      <text title="And today I am tender and just anointed king: ">And I am today a lowly person, yet anointed king.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="4">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="And Saul’s son had two men, the heads of troops: ">(lit., And two men, the heads of troops were Saul’s sons) were to Saul’s son (or Saul’s son had), like: “to the appointed time which Samuel” (I Sam. 13: 8, meaning ‘which was to Samuel’ or ‘of Samuel’).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And the Beerothites had fled to Gittaim: ">when Saul died, for the Israelites abandoned the cities in the environs of the Philistines, as is mentioned above (I Sam. 31:7). Then the Beerothites fled.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="And Jonathan the son of Saul had: ">Scripture goes on to recount how the kingdom was taken away from the house of Saul. He and his son were killed. This one remaining son was killed in bed, and Jonathan’s son fell and became lame (hence unfit for the throne).</text>
      <text title="lame in his feet: ">having broken feet.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="and they came to the middle of the house: ">with merchants who were buying wheat.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="who (expected) me to give him a reward for good tidings: ">who thought to make me happy in order that I give him a reward for his good tidings</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="5">
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="to the Jebusites: ">Mezudath Zion is called Jebus. Now they (the inhabitants of the area) were of the seed of Abimelech, and they were in possession of two statues, one blind and the other lame, symbolizing Isaac (who was blind in his latter years. See Gen. 22:1) and Jacob (who turned lame as a result of his bout with the angel. See Gen. 32:26), and in their mouths was the oath that Abraham had sworn to Abimelech (Gen. 22:23). For this reason they (the Israelites who had conquered the land) did not drive them out, for when they took Jerusalem they failed to take the stronghold, as it is stated: “And the Jebusites, the inhabitants of Jerusalem, the people of Judah were unable, etc.” (Josh. 15:63) - it was learned: R. Joshua b. Levi said: They were indeed able but were not permitted.</text>
      <text title="and he spoke to David: ">the one who spoke</text>
      <text title="the blind and the lame: ">these were their idols.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="Whoever smites the Jebusites and reaches the tower: ">Whosoever kills the Jebusites and is first to capture the city.</text>
      <text title="and the lame: ">and he also smites the lame and the blind and those despised by the soul, etc.</text>
      <text title="wherefore they say: ">On (account of) that which they say,</text>
      <text title="The blind and the lame (etc.: ">So long as the blind and the lame be here… he shall not, etc.</text>
      <text title="David shall not come hither.: ">This is an incomplete verse for it states: “Whosoever smites the Jebusites and reaches the tower…” but fails to specify what will be done unto him. In I Chron. (15:6), however, the explanation is provided: “Whosoever smites the Jebusites first shall be chief and captain.” Similarly we find; “Whosoever slays Cain…” (Gen 4:15) where it does not specify what will be done unto him. However it can be understood in itself to be an expression of rebuke and chastisement.</text>
      <text title="and reaches the tower: ">צינור is a term for the most elevated point of the tower, for it is there where they would place their statues. In the days of David, the generations mentioned in the covenant had already passed on.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="the mound: ">A low walled enclosure which is filled with earth and [where] the top of the mound is in the center with a gradual decline in all directions. This is called a ‘milloh’ and upon it David constructed houses. This milloh encircled the stronghold.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And David perceived: ">upon seeing all his actions prospering and gentile kings sending to him gifts.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="and they spread themselves: ">and they stretched themselves out.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="to Baal-peratzim: ">the plain of Peratzim.</text>
      <text title="like the breach of waters: ">as waters breach through the embankments.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="and David and his men burned them: ">This follows Jonathan.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="in the valley of Rephaim: ">It is near Jerusalem, in the Book of Joshua (16:8).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="from against the mulberry trees: ">from opposite the trees.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="the sound of steps in the tops of the mulberry trees: ">which are the sounds of angels treading in the treetops whom I have lent to your aid.</text>
      <text title="then you shall bestir: ">You shall raise the cry of battle and whet your sword[s]; ‘glapir’ in French. Similarly, “A dog did not whet his tongue” (Ex. 16:7).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="6">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And David continued: ">to gather.</text>
      <text title="All the chosen men of Israel, thirty thousand: ">Since they had gathered to him when they coronated him in Hebron, and this being a second gathering, it states; “And David continued again.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="from Baale-judah: ">which is Kiriath-jearim as it is stated in Josh.; “And the border circled to Baaleh which is Kiriath- jearim” (Josh. 15:9). Similarly in Chron. “And David and all of Israel went up to Baalah which is Kiriath-jearim (I Chron. 13:6).” Now ‘Baal’ is a plain.</text>
      <text title="and David arose and went… from Baale-Judah: ">for they had gathered there to carry up from there the ark, etc.</text>
      <text title="Which is called a name, the name…: ">which is called to it (To the ark) a name. And what is the name? That the name of the Lord of Hosts was upon it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="upon a new cart: ">He erred in a matter that even school children know: “Because the service of the holy things belonged unto them, they shall bear them upon their shoulders” (Num. 7:9). But since he had remarked “Your Statues have been like songs unto me in the house of my sojournings” (Ps. 119:54) he was punished (for exhibiting undue confidence in his knowledge of Torah) by way of coming to this, and Uzzah died because of him. Therefore, when they brought it (the ark) from the house of Oved- Edom, they brought it upon their shoulders; as it is stated (in I Chron. 15:12); “And he said unto them, You are the chief of the fathers of the Levites; sanctify yourselves and your brethren and you shall bring up the ark… for [because] at first you did not [lift it], the Lord our God caused a breach in us, for at first we sought him not in a proper manner.”</text>
      <text title="with the ark of God: ">This is an abbreviated verse which is to be taken as: ‘And they came with the ark of God.’</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="with all manners of cypress wood: ">From which musical instruments are constructed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="the oxen swayed it: ">for the oxen swayed it and shook it. Now Jonathan also translates it in this manner; ‘For the oxen caused it to sway’ parallelin g his translation of: “And his hand strokes with the axe” (Deut. 19:5) as: And his hand swayed with the iron.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="for his error: ">for his mistake for he should have concluded ‘a fortiori’: If it lifted its bearers over the Jordan certainly it was able to lift itself.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="Oved-edom: ">He was a Levite (as stated in I Chronicles 26:4); one of the gatekeepers.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="and the Lord blessed… all his household: ">His wife and eight daughters-in-law gave birth to sextuplets as it is written: “Peulthai the eighth (son), etc. Threescore and two were of Oved edom” (I Chron. 26:5).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="danced: ">a dance.</text>
      <text title="a linen ephod: ">a linen robe, ‘porceint’ in French. Jonathan translates it ‘a sleeved tunic,’ just as he interprets the robes of Tamar the sister of Absalam to have been sleeved tunics (II Sam. 13:18).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="and a portion of meat: ">one sixth of a bullock.</text>
      <text title="a barrel of wine: ">(containing one ephah)</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="One of the idlers: ">lit. one of the empty ones.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="and if I be demeaned: ">before Him (God) more than I have demeaned myself now.</text>
      <text title="with them will I get me honor: ">They do not shame me. Instead I am prestigious in their eyes for this.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="had no child: ">from that day on.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="7">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="had given him rest: ">He remarked: Behold it has been fulfilled: “And when he offers you rest from all your enemies, etc.” (Deut. 12:10). What is written afterwards? “Then there shall be a place which [the Lord your God] shall choose, etc.” If so, it is incumbent upon us to build the Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="And it came to pass on that very night: ">R. Haninah b. Papa said: “The Holy One blessed is He said to Nathan: This man that I am sending you to is hasty. Perhaps he will hire workers and I will find Myself incurring him loss. Hurry and tell him [it is] not you who will build the house.” R. Simon said: “This man that I am sending you to is wont to make vows just as it is stated… ‘how he swore unto the Lord and vowed unto the Mighty One of Jacob, if I will enter the tent which is my house…’ (Psalms 122:2). Perhaps he will say I will not eat nor will I drink until I do that (build the Temple) and I will find Myself incurring him loss.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="in a tent: ">The tabernacle of Shiloh did not have a ceiling but consisted of a stone edifice below and curtains above.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="have I spoken: ">it is the interrogative form and therefore the diacritical dotting of the ה is ‘chataf patach’ and the ד is weak.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="from the sheepcote: ">a shepherd’s shed, similar to; “sheds where shepherds bake” (Zephaniah 2:6).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="like the name of the great ones: ">This is a reference to what we say; the shield of David.</text>
      <text title="and I have cut off all your enemies: ">accordingly it has entered your heart to build the house, as it is written in this Torah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="And I will appoint a place: ">I yet desire to bring calm in order to offer ease and security for my nation in the days of your son.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="And even from the day that I commanded: ">To be linked with the preceding verse; ‘and shall not continue to afflict them as before’ prior to the period of the Judges, and ‘as they have done’ from the days of the Judges until now.</text>
      <text title="and the Lord has told you: ">today through me, that a house will be made for you by (setting) your son on your throne and in this manner establish a house of royalty for you. Now he will be the one to build the house.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="with the rod of men: ">This refers to Hadad and Rezon the son of Elyada.</text>
      <text title="and with the stripes of the sons of Adam: ">This is the demon Ashmadai who chased him from his throne. Now the demons are the children of Adam since for the duration of one hundred and thirty years that Adam was estranged from his wife after the death of Abel, the spirits became heated (pregnant) and gave birth from him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="and sat before the Lord: ">Before the ark.</text>
      <text title="thus far: ">that you have made me king.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="also… of Your servant’s house: ">to make rule my son after me.</text>
      <text title="and is this the manner of man: ">in interrogative form. It is befitting to offer such tidings to flesh and blood? A second explanation is: You have done to me as You have done to Adam to whom You showed the generations that were destined to come forth from him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="And what more can David say ?: ">What more can I request.</text>
      <text title="for You know Your servant: ">You have provided me with all my needs. This is similar to: “The righteous man provides the needs of his animal’s soul” (Prov. 12:10).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="for the sake of Your words: ">to make stand that which You had spoken to Samuel to make me king.</text>
      <text title="and according to Your own heart: ">only because it is Your will and not because I merit it.</text>
      <text title="to make Your servant know it: ">the glad tidings that you have brought me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="whom God went: ">Moses and Aaron, as it is written: “I have made you a ruler over Pharaoh” (Exod. 7:1). Now this is also Jonathan’s interpretation; “whom messengers of God went…”</text>
      <text title="to redeem to Himself a people: ">This the messengers said to the Israelites.“The Holy One blessed is He sent us to redeem to Himself a people, and to make to Him a name, and to accomplish for you the greatness.”</text>
      <text title="and fearful things: ">You did for Your land after they came out of there (Egypt). Now what were these fearful things that You did from before Your people? To drive out nations and their gods. This verse appears to be missing the word לגרש (to drive out), since in I Chron. 17:21 it specifies: “to drive out from before Your people nations and their gods.” However it is not missing; for when the text states: “from before Your people… nations,” we may infer from it banishment and driving out.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="You (alone) art God: ">a ruler, and You have the power to fulfill.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="please You.: ">a desire.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="8">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Metheg-ammah: ">Now in I Chronicles 18:1, it is written: “And David took Gath out of the hand of the Philistines.” It (Gath) is called Metheg-ammah (lit., an ox goad) because it was the rod that governed over all of the Philistines. [It was] a metropolis of Kings; since we do not find among all the Philistine lords of Gaza, Ashdod, Ekron, and Ashkelon, a name of a kingdom except in Gath where we find Achish the king of Gath.</text>
      <text title="metheg: ">Agojjlon in French.</text>
      <text title="ammah: ">a wooden ox-goad.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="and he measured two cord lengths: ">because they had killed his father, mother, and brothers. For it states, “And he led them before the king of Moab” (I Sam. 22:4) and we do not find mention of their departure from there.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="as he went: ">as Hadadezer went.</text>
      <text title="to extend his dominion: ">To be interpreted like its Targum: ‘To modify his border.’ For he conquered of the territory outside the border of his country and extended his border.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="and David houghed all the chariots (horses): ">because of the commandment: “He shall not multiply horses unto himself” (Deut. 17:16).</text>
      <text title="And left over of them for a hundred chariots: ">which he needed for his cavalry. Now a chariot consists of four horses as it is stated; “A chariot for six hundred shekels of silver and a horse for a hundred and fifty.” (II Chron. 1:17) from here it is derived that a chariot consists of four horses.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="the quivers of gold: ">these are the quivers of gold in which arrows are placed similar to the saying (lit., what you say): “make bright the arrows fill up the quivers” (Jer. 51:1). All these chapters are connected to the previous chapter dealing with the holy Temple, since from all these battles David assembled [the] objects dedicated for the needs of the Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="and David made for himself a name: ">For he buried the dead that were killed of Edom. Now this resulted in a good name for Israel for (granting) burial to their enemies. Similarly it is stated concerning the battle of Gog and Magog; “and all the people of the land shall bury them; and it shall be for them for a name.” (Ezek 39:13). And how do we know that David buried them? Because it is written in the Book of Kings (Kings I, 2:15): “For when David was in Edom and Joab the captain of the hosts had gone up to bury the slain.”</text>
      <text title="eighteen thousand: ">Now in the book of Psalms 60:2 it states, “twelve thousand.” From here it must be concluded that there were two battles.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="governors: ">officers to collect taxes.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="and David administered justice… and Joab the son of Zeruyah was over the host.: ">David caused Joab to be successful over the host because he executed justice and charity, and Joab caused David to execute justice and charity because he would judge and Joab would enforce and chastise for him. Also, because Joab was engaged in the battles David was not busied with them, and was (lit., his heart was) left free to judge righteously.</text>
      <text title="recorder: ">He would call out which case came to him first so that it be decided first.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="the archers and the slingers: ">Jonathan interprets: and Benayahu the son of Yahayada was appointed over the archers and the slingers. Now our Rabbis have said כרתי and פלתי [refer to the] Urim and Tumim.</text>
      <text title="Were chief officers.: ">lit. כהנים (priests).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="9">
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="have I given to your master’s son: ">The king has the right to transfer inheritance as it is stated in I Sam. 8:14 in the laws pertaining to the monarchy: “your fields and your vineyards he will take and give to his servants.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="so shall your servant do: as for Mephibosheth, he shall eat at my table: ">Zibah said: “so shall your servant do,” and David responded: “as for Mephibosheth, he shall eat at my table.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="the inhabitants of Zibah’s house: ">his sons and servants.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="10">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="just as his father showed me kindness: ">And what was this kindness? When David was fleeing from Saul, his father, mother and brother came to him (I Sam. 22:4) and he brought them before the king of Moab and said to him: Please allow my father and mother to live with you. Nevertheless he killed them excepting one that fled and escaped to the land of the sons of Ammon, to Nahash Midrash of R. Tanhuma in p. Va’yerah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="Do you think that David honors your father: ">Does it appear to you that David honors your father? They are warned; “Do not seek their peace.” and he seeks your peace?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="garments: ">their robes.</text>
      <text title="buttocks: ">Heb. שתותיהם, their buttocks.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="and Shobach the captain of the host of Hadadezer: ">Because he was very strong and ruthless, they are referred to by his name.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="11">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="going out of kings to battle: ">There is a time of year that it is customary for the armies to go out; when the land is filled with stalks and the horses find grain in the field to eat.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="from her uncleanliness: ">from her menstrual impurity.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="send me Uriah: ">He intended that he lie with his wife so that it be assumed that she had conceived from him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="the king’s food: ">a king’s feast.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="so that he will be smitten and die: ">in order that she should be retroactively divorced and, consequently he would not have had relations with a married woman; for anyone who departs to war writes his wife a divorce on the condition that he die in battle.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="Jerubesbeth: ">This is Gideon who made strife with the shameful one, which is the Baal.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="strengthen your battle against the city and destroy it: ">Until here are the words of the message.</text>
      <text title="and encourage him: ">David said to the messenger: and encourage him, meaning Joab, with words of consolation lest his heart become faint.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="12">
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="wayfarer: ">The evil inclination is first compared to a traveler who stops by on his way, then to a guest who lodges, and finally to a man, who is master of the household.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="liable to death: ">One who robs the poor is as if he takes his life, for it is written: “the life of the owners he [the thief] takes” (Prov. 1:19).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="he shall repay fourfold: ">This [actually] happened to him, that he was smitten through four children; the child (born to Bathsheba See v. 18.), Amnon (below 13:19), Tamar (below 13:14), and Absalom (below 18:15).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="and your master’s wives: ">Michal the daughter of Saul.</text>
      <text title="I add: ">I would add for you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="the enemies of the Lord: ">This is a euphemism for ‘the Above.’ Now Jonathan translates it as: Because you have opened the mouths of the enemies of God’s nation.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="became mortally ill: ">Heb. ויאנש, an expression of sickness.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="and he came in and slept lying on the ground: ">and he came into the house and slept the night lying on the ground.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="he did not eat: ">Heb. ברה. A synonym for eating similar to: “that I may eat from her hand” (Heb. ואברה מידה, below 13:6).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="for the Lord’s sake: ">who loved him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="the royal city: ">there were two wall supports in it, an outer and an inner one. The outer one was the royal city, and the inner one was for fortification and support.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="and the crown of Malkam: ">the name of the abomination of the sons of Ammon was Malkam from [the name] Molech.</text>
      <text title="and it was set on David’s head: ">Ittai the Gittite renounced it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="saws: ">A knife indented with numerous consecutive nicks.</text>
      <text title="harrows: ">A threshing sledge. It is grooved with numerous indentations and is called lime [in French].</text>
      <text title="brick kiln: ">in the mud of the streets. And so did I translate it: and they dragged them in the streets.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="13">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="a fair sister whose name was Tamar: ">who was the daughter of his mother.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="making himself sick: ">until he took sick.</text>
      <text title="for she was a virgin: ">and was hidden within the house, refusing to go outside. Consequently: “it seemed difficult in Amnon’s eyes, etc.” It was concealed and hidden from him what excuse he would be able to seek to lie with her. [This is] similar to: כי יפלא ממך : (Deut. 17:8) which Onkelos translates: “if it be hidden from you.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="sly man: ">for evil.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="thin: ">lean, similar to: “lean and ill-formed” (Gen. 41:19).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="the food: ">Heb. הבריה, a light meal.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="and she prepared the dumplings: ">She scalded. Fine flour scalded first with boiling water and afterwards with oil.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="the pan: ">Heb. משרת. The Targum of מחבת [a shallow panLev. 2:5] is מסריתא.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="for he will not withhold me from you: ">For I am permissible to you since my mother conceived me when she was yet a gentile, a beautiful woman which David had taken in battle. Now whoever has a son or daughter from a [gentile] maidservant he is not considered his son in any respect.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="And Amnon hated her with very great hatred: ">She attached a hair to him and made him into one that is mutilated at the membrum.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="do not: ">Do not do this evil act of sending [me] away which is greater [in it’s wickedness] than the other [act] that you had done with me by forcing me for you will only add an even greater wrong than it by sending me away.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="had sheepshearers: ">and it was their custom to make a feast when they sheared their sheep.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="If not, please let… go with us: ">If you cannot go, please let Amnon go with us.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="by the mouth of Absalom this had been arranged.: ">By the command of Absalom this order was placed upon his servants, to kill Amnon.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="39">
      <text title="and [King] David longed: ">This is an incomplete verse [which is meant to be read]: “And the soul of David longed.” Now Targum Jonathan also translates it in this manner: “And the soul of David longed” similar to: “yearned and longed כלתה) (נכספה וגם” (Ps. 84:3), an expression of longing.</text>
      <text title="for he was comforted concerning Amnon: ">he accepted consolation.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="14">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="And Joab sent to Tekoa: ">Our Rabbis said, “Because olive oil is found there, [in abundance], wisdom is found there.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="truly I am… a widow: ">Heb. אבל, in truth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="on me be the iniquity: ">It is a euphemism out of respect for him as if to say: You are putting me off by saying: I will give orders about you. Now if I go on away and you do not give orders about me, upon whom then will the iniquity be?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="let the king remember the Lord your God: ">who concerned Himself with the length of the way [to the refuge cities] in order to save lives, as it is stated: “Lest he [the avenger] overtake him because the way is long” (Deut. 19:6). Now this is the meaning of: “So that the avenger of blood destroy not excessively; and you [still] push me off?”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="thought such a thing about the people of God.: ">How have you thought such a thing, i.e., that you suspected Israelites of coming to kill another one with neither witnesses nor [mandatory] warning.</text>
      <text title="that the king in speaking this word has done so accidentally: ">This thing that you decreed for others, i.e., that which you said to me, “not a hair of your son shall fall,” now that I have made it apparent to you that it all related only to your [own] two sons, do not have regrets saying: I stated this accidentally, and behold I am retracting myself, so that the king shall not [be forced to] bring back his son who was banished from him and fled.</text>
      <text title="the king in speaking: ">Eknon parlot in French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="for die we must: ">And it suffices us with that punishment.</text>
      <text title="and God favors not a soul: ">and God favors not a soul of man, from death. Therefore, the king should devise means so that he that is banished, not be [permanently] cast from him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="And now, my coming to speak of this thing to the king: ">by substituting it on myself and my sons.</text>
      <text title="because the people have made me afraid: ">They frightened me from seeking out my lord regarding his son lest he be angry with me.</text>
      <text title="I will now speak: ">in this fashion, for perhaps [the king] will perform, etc.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="For the king will hear, to deliver his maidservant from the hand of the man: ">who comes to kill my son, and destroy us together from the inheritance of God.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="for comfort: ">Once the king has given charge concerning me, his declaration [lit., words] will lead to comfort for my son, since he will not retreat from his word; for ‘as an angel of God so is my lord’ and neither wrath or hatred will retreat him from his favorable statement.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="if anyone can: ">Heb. אש. Just like אם יש, if there is anyone, or היש, is there anyone. So with האש ביתרשע (Micha 6:10), “are there yet in the house of the wicked?” which is [identical to] היש.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="In order to bring about: ">[to allow the story] to evolve until the matter of the king’s son as brought to a favorable conclusion.</text>
      <text title="and my lord is wise: ">and you [therefore] understand that it came forth from Joab.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="near mine: ">Situated near my property in a place where I can damage it.</text>
      <text title="near mine: ">Anmesajjces in French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="let him kill me.: ">Let the king kill me.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="15">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="and fifty men were running before him: ">They all had their spleen and the flesh of the soles of their feet cut off.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="And Absalom would rise: ">Each morning.</text>
      <text title="Of one of the tribes of Israel is your servant: ">From such-and-such a tribe.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="I would surely do him justice: ">I would judge him righteously.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="at the end of forty years: ">[from the time] that the Israelites requested a king from Samuel, came about [this] rebellion and drop [of prestige] in the monarchy.</text>
      <text title="allow me to go, I beg you: ">to Hebron.</text>
      <text title="and pay my vow: ">Our Rabbis have stated: “To fetch lambs from Hebron, for there were fat lambs there.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="that were invited and went in their innocence: ">It is explained in T.P. Sotah that he requested his father to write for him that any two people that he would ask to go with him, should go, and he showed this [decree] to two people here, then to two others [elsewhere], and so he did many times.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="at the farthest house: ">in a distant place.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="beside him: ">he stood and they passed by.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="with the king: ">with Absalom.</text>
      <text title="for you are a foreigner: ">Now we flee without provision or food, and because you are a gentile you will not [readily] find [anyone] to take pity.</text>
      <text title="and if you are wont to wander, [go to] your own place: ">and if you wish to wander from the king because you do not desire to be with him, return to your own place, for your travel with me is not advisable, since [just] yesterday you came.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="and today I should move you about with us?: ">For I have no place where I can settle you so that you be spared, since from day to day, I go wherever chance takes me. When I hear that the pursuers are here, I run there. Now Jonathan also translates אתה למקומך וגם גולה as: and if you are wont to wander, go you to your own place.</text>
      <text title="kindness and truth: ">I thank you for the kindness and truth that you have done with me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="go and pass over: ">with the rest of the people, seeing that you do not desire to separate from me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="and all the people passed over: ">from the king and on. Since David was standing still, they are referred to as passing over.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="set down: ">Heb. ויציקו, similar to ויציגו, to set down, [as indicated by Jonathan’s translation]: they set down the ark. They placed it to a side and the people passed by, since David desired to carry it with him.</text>
      <text title="and Abiathar went up until all the people had finished, etc.: ">This is an inverted verse: “They set down the ark of God until all the people had finished passing!”</text>
      <text title="went up: ">On that day he [Abiathar] was removed from the [High] Priesthood because he had inquired of the Urim and Tumim but was not answered and Zadok entered in his stead. So we learned in Seder Olam and Seder Yoma.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="Do you [not] see: ">If you see that it is a sensible plan then return to the city, etc.</text>
      <text title="Your two sons [shall be] with you: ">Through them you can inform me about what you hear from the house of the king, and based on your information I will be able to [plan an] escape.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="by the ascent of the olives: ">by the Mount of Olives.</text>
      <text title="his head covered: ">wrapped around in the manner of mourners.</text>
      <text title="covered: ">wrapped.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="and [someone] told David: ">and the informer told to David.</text>
      <text title="among the conspirators: ">Heb. סכל, make foolishfrustrated [by making foolish] similar to: “And the fool (והסכל) multiplies his words” (Eccl. 10:14).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="coming to the top: ">to the top of the mount.</text>
      <text title="where he would prostrate himself to God: ">Where he was wont to prostrate himself. When he would come to Jerusalem he would see from there the tent containing the ark and would prostrate himself.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="just as I was previously father’s servant: ">as if [it were written]: “and I was previously your father’s servant”; for it is an inverted sentence.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="(was) coming to Jerusalem: ">contemplated coming to Jerusalem.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="16">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="a hundred summer fruit: ">Heb. מאה קיץ, a hundred litras of pressed figs.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="because the Lord said to him: ">Is it possible that a man like him who is the head of the Sanhedrin would curse the king had he not been commanded by the Holy One Blessed be He?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="the tears of my eyes: ">Heb. בעיני, in my eye.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="refreshed himself there: ">in Bahurim.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="Then the hands of all that are with above, you will be strengthened: ">For now they [lit., their hands] are lax to support you for they say in their hearts: “the son will have a change of heart when [he is] near his father and we [alone] will remain despised by David.”</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="17">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="when all shall have returned: ">to you.</text>
      <text title="the man whom you seek: ">the man whom you seek, [if] unto him will be done what you desire, and he will be killed, then all the people will be at peace. This is an incomplete verse.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="the elders of Israel: ">the uncultured old men of Israel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="and your father is a man of war: ">who knows the affairs of battle, its arrays, and the science of ambush, and [undoubtedly] trusts that you will [likely] chase at night to come upon him. Therefore he will not lodge with the rest of the people.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Behold now he is [surely] hidden: ">And when you come upon the campsite of the people with him, he will not be there for you to kill him.</text>
      <text title="and it will come to pass, if there fall among them at the first: ">I have told you that his men are [both] mighty and of embittered spirit. Now if they kill from among your people and they shall be felled in this first battle, then who ever hears from among all the Israelites that come to join you will declare that there has been a massacre among Absalom’s people.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="and even if he be valiant: ">Even if the one who hears [of it] be valiant, and his heart is as the heart of a lion, he will utterly melt with fear and shudder, and he will no longer band with you, for he will say: He has already begun to decline and he is being punished for [actions towards] his father, and will [therefore] not succeed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="Therefore I counsel: ">For this is my counsel.</text>
      <text title="and you personally go to battle: ">at the forefront, and you shall go at the head of all of us.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="and we shall light upon him: ">We shall rest upon him. It is an expression of camping (חנייה) , similar to “and they landed (וינח) in all the border of Egypt” (Ex. 10:14); (and) “Aram lights upon (נחה) [Judah] with Ephraim” (Isa. 7:2).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="ropes: ">Heb. חבלים, bands [battalions], similar to “bands of (חבל) prophets” (I Sam. 10:5) and “bands of (חבלי) wicked men” (Ps. 119:6).</text>
      <text title="to the valley: ">We will drag the walls of the city to the valley.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="but pass speedily over: ">the Jordan.</text>
      <text title="lest the king be destroyed: ">Lest the king [Absalom] be told secretly that I did not counsel him well, and he will follow the words of Ahithophel. [The word] יבלע [is to be understood as] it will be told to him in a secretive and concealed [swallowed] manner.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="En-rogel: ">lit. by the launderer’s spring. Launderers of woolen garments would press it there by beating them [the garments] with the(ir) foot.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="covering: ">a curtain.</text>
      <text title="groats: ">Heb. הריפות, “crushed wheat” similar to: “amongst the crushed wheat (הריפות)” (Prov. 27:22).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="forded the river: ">I do not know an interpretation for it in any grouping, and it’s interpretation in keeping with the subject, would be ‘the river current’.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="the daughter of Nahash: ">This is Jesse, David’s father. Our Rabbis stated that he died without sin, only because of the advice of the Serpent (נחש).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="Shobi the son of Nahash: ">The same as Hanun the son of Nahash.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="bowls: ">These are utensils, similar to: “bowls of silver (ספותכסף)” of II Kings 12:14.</text>
      <text title="parched grain: ">Heb. קלי, types of parched grain. Our Rabbis stated: Two types of flour mixed with honey did Barzillai offer David, one of wheat and the other of lentils, as stated here: “… and wheat and parched grain…” which is of bread stuffs;“and beans and lentils and parched grain…” [which is] of those types of beans that are dried in an oven and remain forever sweet. They are then ground and from them a dish called ‘shatitha’ is made.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="and cheese of kine: ">This follows Jonathan.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="18">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="they will not pay attention to us: ">lit., set heart to us. It will not be important to them to overpower us and to boast, since you are not [taking part] in the battle.</text>
      <text title="For now: ">with you in your full glory, you are of equal import to us all.</text>
      <text title="that you be for us from the city as aid: ">And now it is better that you pray for us from the city for support.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="deal gently with the youth: ">If he chances to come before you in battle, take pity on him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="in the forest of Ephraim: ">Now how was there a forest belonging to Ephraim on the Eastern bank of the Jordan since no portion was granted [anyone] there other than to the children of Gad, Reuben, and Menashe? However, because Joshua had placed as a condition [for the division of the Land of Israel] that anyone may pasture in the forests, and since this forest was so close to Ephraim, [but for the Jordan separating them] that they [the people of Ephraim] would pasture their animals there, it was called the forest of Ephraim.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="and the forest devoured: ">the wild beasts of the forest. So did Jonathan translate it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="And Absalom chanced to come: ">Heb. ויקרא, an expression of a chance happening.</text>
      <text title="and he was placed between the heaven and earth: ">Our Rabbis have stated: We drew his sword to cut his hair but saw Gehinnom open up beneath him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="whoever it be: ">into whomever’s hand he enters shall care for him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="I shall no longer request of you: ">I shall no longer make any request of you, but will go [instead] myself.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="I have no son: ">I have no son who will replace me and be of similar stature to me.</text>
      <text title="in order to cause [people] to remember my name: ">I shall erect for myself a stone monument, and it was an impressive structure.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="bring news another day: ">The news of another deliverance.</text>
      <text title="because: ">Because the king’s son died, it is not good for you [to bring] this news.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="since for you there is no [reward] given for the news: ">No reward for the news shall be made available today.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="Come what may: ">As if to say: So what if I gain no reward.</text>
      <text title="and he went ahead of the Cushite: ">[Jonathan renders:] He went ahead of the Cushite.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="a great crowd: ">Tumultuous and moving [constantly] about in battle.</text>
      <text title="when Joab sent the servant of the king and [me] your servant: ">This is surely an inverted verse [which is correctly understood as follows]: אתעבד המלך ואתעבדיך לשלח יואב. After Joab sent the servant of the king [the one who is running behind me].</text>
      <text title="and your servant: ">[referring to himself.] I did not know what transpired afterwards.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="turn aside and stand here: ">Turn to another side and stand here and let us hear what this one has to say.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="19">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="my son, my son: ">My son, my son eight times; seven that brought him forth from the seven levels of Gehinnom, and one that brought him into the world to come.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="covered his face: ">wrapped around his face in the manner of mourners.</text>
      <text title="Heb.: ">לאט Similar to “and he wrapped (וילט) his face in his mantle” (I Kings 19:13) (and) “It is here wrapped (לוטה) in a cloth” (I Sam. 21:10).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="If you do not go forth: ">Heb. כי אינך, if you do not go forth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="but Israel fled: ">Those that were with Absalom.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="argued with one another: ">Heb. כל העם נדון, argued with one another.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="while the talk of all Israel…(to return him) to his house?: ">All this is still part of the charge [to Zadok and Abiathar].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="And to Amasa: ">The general [of Absalom’s army] you shall say: “Behold you are my sister’s son.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="Split the Jordan: ">They split it with their shields.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="and the barge crossed over: ">The ferry with which one crosses the width of the river.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="The first of all the House of Joseph: ">All of Israel have sinned against you and I [have sinned] more than all of them. And behold I have come to beg forgiveness. If you accept me, all of Israel will be assured that you will accept them. And If not they will fear to return to you again.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="be put to death today: ">In interrogative form.</text>
      <text title="That today I am king: ">Heretofore I thought that surely such a great man would not abuse me unless my rule had been terminated by God who had commanded him, ‘Curse David.’ Now, however, that he repents, I know that I am king.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="had not washed his feet: ">Heb. עשה, an expression of ‘setting in order’ [in this instance] the removal of hair of the legs.</text>
      <text title="mustache: ">Heb. שפמו, Grenon, in French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="why had you not gone with me: ">Gone forth from Jerusalem when I departed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="is lame: ">and I cannot go by foot.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="to escort him.: ">Heb. לשלחו, to escort him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="a very great man: ">in wealth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="how many are the days of my life: ">That I have yet to live.</text>
      <text title="that I should go up: ">They are surely few, so what pleasure could I derive from your sustaining me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="discern between good and bad? or can I… taste what I eat: ">between good food and bad food. Now our Rabbis have stated that he was highly promiscuous and therefore aged rapidly.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="a short way shall your servant go past: ">A short distance shall your servant pass over to escort you, once you cross the Jordan.</text>
      <text title="with this reward: ">Which is not [really] good for me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="38">
      <text title="your servant Chimham: ">He was his [Barzillai’s] son.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="43">
      <text title="Because the king is near to us: ">He is from my tribe.</text>
      <text title="has any present: ">Heb. נשאת, similar to משאת (Gen. 43:34); a reward from the house of the king.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="44">
      <text title="we have ten parts in the king: ">for we are ten tribes.</text>
      <text title="to David: ">Although he is related to you, I am more drawn to him since I represent ten parts.</text>
      <text title="why then did you slight me?: ">By preceding me[in the king’s escort]. Had I not spoken first concerning the return of my king? for [indeed] our words to reinstate him came first; as it is written: “And the word of all of Israel came to the king.”</text>
      <text title="And the words of the men of Judah were harsher: ">A similar expression is: “Correct yourselves etc” (Zeph. 2:1). The words of the people of Judah seemed [more] plausible and correct for they showed them a letter that David had sent them [stating]: “Why should you be last to reinstate the king, etc.” (above v. 12). In this manner it is explained in the Aggadah. Now one may also explain ויקש as an expression of harshness and strength. And so did Jonathan translate: ‘were harsher.’</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="20">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="there chanced: ">Heb. נקרא, was summoned there; similar to הקדיש קרואיו“bid his summoned” of Zeph. 1:7, and: ויקרא אבשלום לכל בני מלך“and Absalom invited all the son’s of the king” of II Sam. 13:23. It is synonymous with זימון, an invitation.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="call together for me the men of Judah: ">So that they be here within three days.</text>
      <text title="then be here present: ">After the three days be sure to remain here before mefor David desired to pursue Sheba the son of Bichri.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="and he tarried past the set time: ">He found the rabbis beginning a tractate, as is found in Sanhedrin.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="… take your lord’s servants: ">Since Amasa has tarried and has not brought the army of Judah, take you from among those that are found around me and pursue him.</text>
      <text title="save our eyes: ">And save himself before our eyes. Now this is an abbreviated verse.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="fastened to his loins: ">clinging to his body to the width of his loins and not in a manner that one [customarily] fastens his sword, in order that it should fall easily and not necessitate removal from its sheath…</text>
      <text title="and he went forth: ">towards Amasa.</text>
      <text title="and it fell out: ">i.e., the sword from its sheath, since it was smooth and sharpened and it was not suspended at the side of his hip but [to the] width of his loins. [Thus] almost as soon as he bent toward the ground it fell from its sheath where he grasped it with his right hand without Amasa becoming aware of it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="when he saw that everyone who came upon him stood still: ">When the man saw that everyone who came upon him remained standing [there].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="when he was removed: ">Heb. הגה, when he was taken away, similar to: “take away the dross from the silver (הגו סיגים מכסף)” (Prov. 25:4.), and similar to: “take away the wicked from before the king (הגו רשע לפני מלך)” (ibid. 25:5).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="And he passed through all the tribes of Israel: ">Sheba the son of Bichri, in order to persuade them to appoint him king over them.</text>
      <text title="the Berites: ">Heb. הברים. I do not know what it is.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="with only its inner wall: ">And it stood surrounded by the army. Others interpret ותעמד בחל as an expression similar to חיל וחומה of Lam. 2:8. They felled the outer wall and it [the city] strengthened itself to stand with [only] its inner wall.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="Are you Joab?: ">[Are you the Joab] regarding whom it is said: Who sits in the assembly of the wise?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="Surely they should have spoken first [to hear what they have] to say: ">You first should have spoken to them [to see] if they answer you for peace and open up for you, for then you should not have fought against them.</text>
      <text title="had they inquired of Abel: ">Had the men of your army inquired of the peace of this city whose name is Abel.</text>
      <text title="so would they have made peace: ">Immediately the people of the city would have made peace with you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="peaceful and faithful to Israel: ">I am from those people of the city who are peaceful and faithful to Israel and to the king. Now there is a Midrash Aggadah that she was Serah the daughter of Asher. I am the one who surrendered one faithful to another faithful [i.e., Jospeh to Moses]. Through me Joseph’s casket was revealed to Moses (See Eccl. R. 9:25); and I was the one who notified Jacob that Joseph was yet alive.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="far be it, far be it from me: ">Far be it from me, far be it from the king.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="lifted his hand against the king, against David: ">[Had he rebelled] against a king, even if he were not David, he would be deserving of death. Or against David, who is a great scholar, even if he were not a king, he would be deserving of death. How much more so against the king against David. This is the manner in which it has been expounded in Midrash Koheleth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="And the woman came to the people in her wisdom: ">We learned in the Tosefta (Terumot ch. 7) that she said to them: Since he and they [the soldiers of the city of Abel] shall be killed, present him to them. If he could conceivably save himself; if he were, for example, on the inside [of the city wall] and you were on the outside, and only you were in a state of danger while he could save himself, one dare not disregard one human life for the sake of another human life by killing him in order to save yourselves. Now, however, that he too will be killed together with you, since the walls have been destroyed and we have no strength to save ourselves it is better that he die alone and you die not with him. R. Simeon stated: This is what she told them: Whosoever rebels against the Davidic dynasty is deserving of death.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="And Joab was over the entire army: ">Although David had said to Amasa: “I will appoint you as general in Joab’s stead” (Above 19:14), now that Amasa was dead Joab did not move from his position. Now on account of Joab he was obliged to also make mention of his associates.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="Ira the Jairite: ">Jonathan translates: “Ira the Jairite from [the city of] Tekoah,” and so we find him referred to in this book (below 23:26) as Ira the son of Ikkesh the Tekoite. Now he was called the Jairite because we learned in (T.B.) Men: “Tekoah is famous for oil, since olive oil is [abundantly] found there from which we light the candles.”</text>
      <text title="was a chief official: ">He would give him all his priestly gifts. This is what our Rabbis said. However, the simple meaning of the verse is that he appointed him as an official or judge.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="21">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="it is for Saul: ">[It is] for the wrong [done] to Saul, for he was buried suddenly and secretively since the people of Jabesh Gilead smuggled him out and buried him without eulogizing him in a manner befitting him.</text>
      <text title="and (also) for his bloody house: ">For having killed Nob the priestly city (I Sam. 22:19).</text>
      <text title="because he put to death the Gibeonites.: ">When he [Saul] murdered the priestly city of Nob he killed seven of them [Gibeonites]; two wood cutters and two water drawers, an attendant, a carrier, and a scribe. In this manner it is explained in the Palestinian Talmud Tractate Sanhedrin. But our rabbis (i.e., of T.B.) stated, since he slew the priests who had provided them [the Gibeonites] with food, scripture considers it as though he had slain them. Now do not wonder that the Holy One Blessed be He demands his honor and [simultaneously] demands punishment for his sin, for so it is written: “that have executed his judgment פעלו) (אשר משפטו” (Zeph. 2:3). Where there is found his judgment there can also be found his execution.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="and he said to them: ">Words of appeasement in order that they forgo retaliation and pardon Saul and his household.</text>
      <text title="Now the Gibeonites were not of the children of Israel: ">That is, they exhibited the characteristic of being merciless [which gave indication] that they are not of the seed of Abraham. As a result David decreed upon them that they may not enter the [Israelite] community. He said: This [Israelite] nation possesses three signs; they are compassionate, they are bashful, and they are benevolent. [Only] whosoever possesses these three virtues is worthy of joining it.</text>
      <text title="had sworn to them: ">In the days of Joshua when they were appointed wood cutters and water drawers for the altar.</text>
      <text title="in his zeal for the sake of the children: ">When he made up his mind [lit., his heart] to cleanse and purify Israel and to provide for their needs, be sought to kill them. Now the קנאה of the verse is meant in a positive sense, similar to: “are you zealous (המקנא) for my sake” (Num. 11:29) or: “my zeal (בקנאתי) for God” (2 Kings 10:16) mentioned in connection with Jehu. This is the simple explanation. According to the Midrashic explanation, however, he commanded only to kill the priests, thus the envy stated here is not for good but for bad. He knew that his kingdom would be discontinued from the day he failed to heed the command of the Holy One Blessed be He concerning the Amalekites and there upon became jealous of them [the priests who had harbored David].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="bless the inheritance of the Lord: ">Pray for them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="We have no matters of silver and gold: ">Only of lives. He sought to appease them with money but they refused. He said [to himself], Perhaps they are ashamed before one another [to consent to take money]. He therefore went and appealed each one individually but they nevertheless refused to be appeased. It is on account of this that it is written, “I have no matters of silver and gold, etc.” in singular form. This I have seen in the Jerusalem Talmud.</text>
      <text title="and we [care not] to put to death: ">Any of the other people of Israel who have not wronged us.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="and who devised against us that we be destroyed: ">who planned in his heart, by whom we have been destroyed from remaining etc. i.e., who devised to destroy us.</text>
      <text title="devised against us: ">He devised against us to destroy us.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="hang them: ">Heb. והוקענום, an expression meaning hanging.</text>
      <text title="for the sake of: ">for the Lord’s name, in order to publicize His judgement.</text>
      <text title="chosen of the Lord: ">a heavenly voice came forth and declared: the chosen of the Lord.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="took pity: ">He begged that the ark should not clutch him; for he led them all in front of the ark, and those that the ark clutched [were selected] for death.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="the five sons of Michal: ">Now did Michal bear them? Did not Merab hear them? We conclude that Merab bore them but Michal raised them and they therefore were called after her name; for one who raises an orphan in his house is as if he had begotten them and he is called after his name.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="at the beginning of the barley harvest: ">In the days of Nissan.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="Until water was poured: ">In the rainy season of Tishrei; for they were not given over for burial. But it is not written: “You shall not allow his body to remain overnight” (Deut. 21:22)? However they said: It is preferable that one letter of the Torah be uprooted so that the Divine Name be publicly hallowed for when passersby would inquire: Who are these? They would say to them: They are princes. And what did they do? They stretched out their hands against those who attached themselves but were [proselytes] not accepted. They would then say: There is no nation that one ought to join like this one.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="and he took the bones of Saul: ">For he was told regarding them [Saul and Jonathan]: It is for Saul, since he was not eulogized properly.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="and they gathered the bones: ">of the seven who were hanged here.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="all that the king commanded them: ">To eulogize them in all of Israel’s cities.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="and the weight of his spear: ">Heb. קינו. It is like the sheath at the end of the handle of the spear which is called arestojjl in French, and is made like the hat. Its parallel is [found in T.B.] Zebachim: “What are the blossoms of the robe like, [they are] like the helmets that are on the heads of infants.” Now קולסות are heajjlmes in French.</text>
      <text title="and he was girded: ">With a new outfit. Now I heard that on that day he was initiated into the wearing of armor. Since it is common for the [newly] initiated to perform [an act of] victory and heroism on the day of their initiation in order to acquire a reputation, he therefore thought to smite David.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="aided him: ">He aided him through prayer, as is found in the chapter of Chelek [the 10th perek of Sanhedrin].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="And there was war again: ">This one preceded them all, but is mentioned here only to connect the deaths of the four sons of Orpah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="Elhanan: ">David.</text>
      <text title="the son of Jaare-oregim: ">Heb. אורגים, lit. weavers. For his family wove curtains for the Holy Temple which was called Jaar (see I Kings 10:17, and 10:21).</text>
      <text title="as the weavers’ beam: ">As a weaver’s beam which is called esoble in French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="a man of stature: ">Heb. איש מדין. As its Targum: “A man of measure,” for the root of the word is basically the מ and ד [from מדה, a measure], just as in משאון of Ps. 65:8 [where it is the] ש and א, and מהמון [where it is the] ה and מ. Now in I Chron. 11:23 it is [expressly] written: “a man of measure (איש מדה) ”; that is a man so tall that one [is inclined] to estimate how tall he is.</text>
      <text title="six and six totalling twenty-four: ">Our Rabbis have explained in [T.B.] Bechoroth that it was necessary to state twenty-four so that you should not say that the fingers of his two hands were only six [three on each hand], and the toes of his feet were only six; it therefore mentions twenty-four. Now if it had mentioned twenty-four and not six and six we would say [that he perhaps had] seven on one hand and five on the other. Now what does מספר imply? That all are [to be] counted in the order of fingers on the hand.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="22">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="In the day that the Lord delivered him: ">In his later years when all his troubles had passed over him and he had been saved from them all.</text>
      <text title="and out of the hand of Saul: ">But is not Saul included [among his enemies]? However he was his enemy and pursuer to a greater degree than all the others [and was therefore cited separately]. Similarly [we find]: “nineteen men and Asahel” (above 2:30). Similarly, “And King Solomon loved foreign women, and the daughter of Pharoah” (I Kings 11:1).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="my rock and my fortress: ">Heb. סלעי ומצדתי. They are expressions of strength; סלעי, rock, requires no explanation; מצדתי, fortress refers to the fortresses of the forests which are called pljsdec in French. This is an allusion to the miracle which was performed on his behalf at the rock of Machloketh (I Sam. 23:28), and at the fortresses at Harsha (I Sam. 23:15 19).</text>
      <text title="and a rescuer to me.: ">[He was] my rescuer [when I was] together with the army of Israel engaged in battle. On occasions, [however,] he rescued me when I was alone, as from Ishbi in Nob (Above 21:16).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="my rock: ">Heb. צורי, synonymous with סלע. [He was his rock] since the rock protects travelers from the [force of] the rain and the wind, abriemant in French.</text>
      <text title="under whom I take cover: ">Heb. אחסה, an expression of covering; I would cover myself waiting for [His] aid.</text>
      <text title="my support: ">Heb. משגבי, my support.</text>
      <text title="and my refuge: ">For I would run to Him for aid.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="With praise I call to the Lord: ">Just as its Targum. Upon calling Him I [already] praise Him, for I am confidant that I will be saved. It is also plausible to interpret it: ‘I call and I am saved,’ in present sense.</text>
      <text title="have encompassed me: ">Heb. אפפני, have encompassed me.</text>
      <text title="pains of death: ">As its Targum: ‘Like a woman who sits on the travailing chair.’ This (משבר) is the term for the stone seat on which a woman gives birth.</text>
      <text title="streams of scoundrels: ">Armies that overflow like a stream.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="bands: ">Heb. חבלי, as its Targum: Bands, similar to: “Bands of prophets (חבל נביאים)” of I Sam. 10:10.</text>
      <text title="confronted me: ">came before me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="I call upon… He hears: ">Heb. וישמע lit. He heard. That is the nature of the present tense, it speaks in past and future tense simultaneously.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="the earth shook, etc.: ">Not in reference to the miracles that took place on his own behalf was this said, but in reference to the miracles that were performed on behalf of all Israel. Now the beginning of the verse is connected to the end.</text>
      <text title="when he was angered: ">[The word] כי is used here as ‘when’ with the following interpretation: Now when he was angered by those that rouse His temper, the earth shook and quaked… and the very foundations of the earth did tremble.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="smoke went up in His nostrils: ">So it is with one who is angry, smoke comes forth from his nostrils. Similarly: “These are a smoke from My nostrils” (Isa 65:5). Now this is always the meaning of the term חרון אף; the nose snorts and raises up vapors.</text>
      <text title="and fire out of His mouth did devour: ">Due to the command from His mouth, a fire consumed the wicked.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="and He bent the heavens: ">To avenge Himself of His enemies; i.e., from Egypt and Pharoah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And he fixed darkness, etc.: ">As a booth, just as it stated: “and the cloud and darkness separated between the Egyptians and Israelites!” (Ex 14:20).</text>
      <text title="gathering of waters, thick clouds of the skies: ">Now from where did this darkness emanate? There were thick clouds of the skies that would distill water upon the earth.</text>
      <text title="gathering: ">Heb. חשרת, synonymous with כברה [a sieve] since it distills [the water] onto the earth drop by drop And so it is stated in numerous aggodot: “They [the clouds] distill it [the rain] as a sieve (חושרין אותו ככברה)” Gen. R. 13:10. It is further possible to interpret it as ‘a knotting,’ since the skies become knotted with clouds on account of the water similar to וחשוריהם mentioned in reference to the wheels of the bases (I Kings 7: 33), which are wooden spokes that fasten and join its rings together.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="from the brightness before Him: ">In order that one not [be led to] say that He dwells in darkness [for] there is a brightness from within the partition [of the cloud] and from this brightness that is before Him flame forth coals of fire, which were sent as arrows upon the Egyptians.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="and the depths of the sea appeared: ">The very interior of the earth split. For when the Sea of Reeds split, all the waters of the world [simultaneously] split.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="For they were too powerful: ">When they were too powerful.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="according to the righteousness: ">When they went out after Him into the desert and relied on His promise.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="kind… upright… pure: ">[The three expressions] represent the three forefathers to whom the Holy One, Blessed be He, had paid the reward for their righteousness to their children.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="But with a perverse one: ">Pharoah.</text>
      <text title="crookedly: ">Heb. תתפל. Its meaning is crooked and perverse [compare to Deut. 32:5]. Now in the book [of Psalms 18:27] it is written תתפתל. An alternate explanation is:</text>
      <text title="He sent from on High, He took me: ">He said it regarding himself when he was rushing to escape from Saul at Sela Hamachlekoth and was nearly captured, an angel came to Saul saying: “Make haste and go, for the Philistines have spread out, etc.” (I Sam. 23:27).</text>
      <text title="And recompensed me according to my righteousness: ">for I did not kill him [Saul] when I severed the skirt of his coat (I Sam. 24:5).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="The word of the Lord: ">The word of the Lord is pure; He promises and performs.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="He looseth perfectly my path: ">From every stumbling block, from every sin, and from every fence until it is perfect and paved.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="do bend a brass bow: ">And a brass bow was bent by my hands for I possess the strength to bend it. David had bows hanging in his palace and foreign kings would come and see them and say to each other: Do you suppose that he can actually bend them? They are merely intended to frighten us. And David would overhear and would take them [the brass bows] and crush them before their eyes (sic). Now נחת is an expression of bending. And so we find “Your arrows were flung [by bending the bow] into me” (Ps. 38:3).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="and You have increased your modesty for me: ">You have increased for me Your trait of humility.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="enlarged my steps beneath me: ">When a man keeps his feet one next to the other it is easy [for him] to fall. And so it is written: “When you walk, your steps shall not be narrow” (Prov. 4:12).</text>
      <text title="ankles: ">heels.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="42">
      <text title="They looked about but there was none to save them: ">This is a transposed verse: “They look to the Lord but He answered them not, there was none to save him,” similar to: “man looks towards his Creator (ישעו אדם אל עשתו)” of Isa 17:7 [where it is so be taken as] similar to יפנה, to turn towards. Now Menahem has associated it with וישע ה׳ אל הבל interpreting it as ‘entreaty.’ Now this term is applicable to both the beseecher and the beseeched, as in “And Isaac beseeched the Lord (ויעתר יצחק אל ה׳) ”; “and the Lord hearkened to him (ויעתר לו ה׳)” of Gen. 25:21. Here too ישעו ואין מושיע refers to the beseecher, while וישע ה׳ (Gen. 4:4) refers grammatically to the one who is being beseeched.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="43">
      <text title="stamp them down: ">Heb. ארקעם. Now it is found numerous times in Ezekiel: “and stamp (ורקע) with your foot” (Ezek. 6:11), [and] “and you have stamped (ורקעך) with your feet” (Ezek. 15:6).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="44">
      <text title="contenders: ">From Doeg, Ahithophel, Saul, and the Ziphites.</text>
      <text title="shall keep me as head of nations: ">You have preserved me for this. Now the Midrash Aggadah [interprets it]: Said David, Lord of the Universe, spare me from the judgment of Israel, for if I err or force the Israelites into my service I shall be punished. Place me instead as head of the Philistines for they will serve me and for them I shall not be punished.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="45">
      <text title="deceive me: ">Because of their fear, they lie to me.</text>
      <text title="as soon as their ears hear, they obey me: ">Though they are not before me, they fear me. Hence from the moment their ears hear they turn to obey my command.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="46">
      <text title="will wilt: ">Heb. יבלו. Its usage is as: “and the leaf wilts (נבל) ” (Jer. 8:13); pleistre in French.</text>
      <text title="shall become lame: ">ויחגרו, an expression meaning lame.</text>
      <text title="from their bondage: ">From the great pains of the imprisonment with which I punish them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="47">
      <text title="the Lord lives: ">The One who performs all this for me.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="23">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="the last words of David: ">The concluding words of prophecy of David. Now which were the first [prophetic words of David]? The words of the song of praise that were stated above. However all the [other] songs and praise that he had said are not referred to as ‘words.’</text>
      <text title="raised on high.: ">Heb. הקם על, raised on high.</text>
      <text title="sweet singer of Israel: ">The Israelites do not sing in the Temple [any songs] other than his praises and songs.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="spoke in me: ">He lodged in me the spirit of his holiness which spoke within me. Now all expressions of prophecy are indicated by [the word] דבר, just as with: “Has the Lord indeed spoken only in Moses? Has he not spoken also in us? (הרק אך במשה דבר הלא גם בנו דבר אדבר בו)” (Num. 12:2). The reason for this is that the spirit (of God) enters the prophets and speaks from within him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="concerning me: ">[Rashi renders:] To me spoke etc. To me spoke and commanded the rock of Israel that I be a ruler over man, i.e., over Israel who is known as ‘man,’ as it is written: “You are man (אתם אדם)” (Ez. 34:3); and that I be [both] a righteous ruler and a God fearing man. Now our Rabbis have interpreted it in a different manner. David said, The Lord of Israel spoke to me, to me spoke the rock of Israel; I am the ruler of men. Now who is ruler over me? The righteous man, for I pass a decree and he [has the power to] revoke it. (T.B. Moed. Kat. 15b) However, according to the flow of the verses the first is the more literal interpretation of the text.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="And as the light of the morning when the sun shines: ">And he assured me that my greatness would increase constantly like the light of the morning that grows ever brighter.</text>
      <text title="without clouds: ">a light that does not dim.</text>
      <text title="from the light that follows the rain that falls upon the grass of the earth: ">My morning will shine brighter than the light that comes forth from the rain like a resplendent heat [the sun] upon light. When the rain descends upon land covered with grass and the sun shines upon it, the [moist] grass shines. Now this is its interpretation: More than the light which comes from the rain of the grass of the earth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="for my house is not like that: ">That my light should be cloudy.</text>
      <text title="for an everlasting covenant: ">The Torah [which is an everlasting covenant] that God set before me is fully set forth throughout all my house and is observed.</text>
      <text title="all my salvation and all the desire: ">of my needs are prepared before Him. Now this is an abbreviated verse.</text>
      <text title="will not sprout forth: ">another as king after my kingdom. An alternate interpretation is: An everlasting covenant has He made with my household that my kingdom should attain permanence. Now this covenant has “been set forth by all,” i.e., in the mouths of all the prophets.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="as thorns thrust away: ">as swaying thorns; chardon in French: (as in Ex. 22:5). It is tender when yet small and shakes to and fro, but eventually becomes firm to the degree that it can no longer be taken in hand.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="But if a man touch them he should be armed: ">He must cover his skin with [shields of] iron and load his hand with weaponry in order to cut them down.</text>
      <text title="and with fire they shall be utterly burned: ">They [the thorns] serve no useful purpose other than [for] burning and sitting and warming oneself before them. So it is with the wicked who have no way out other than by being consumed by Gehinnom.</text>
      <text title="in their place: ">Heb. בשבת, when He sits.[When] the Holy One Blessed be He sits on His throne of Justice.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="who sat in the assembly of the wise: ">Sat in the assembly of the Sanhedrin who are the wise. Now he was a three-fold head (ראש השלישי) , since he was leader in terms of beauty, in terms of wisdom and in terms of strength. Now in these three he was [indeed] a leader, as it is stated: “… and he is understanding, handsome, and a mighty warrior” (I Sam. 16:18).</text>
      <text title="Adino the Etznite: ">When he was engaged in the learning of Torah, he would wrap and knot himself as a worm [he would be very flexible] similar to התקשר מעדנות כימה of Job 38:31. But when he would go out to battle he became firm as wood (עץ) and would strike eight hundred dead in one battle.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="the son of Dodo: ">That was his name.</text>
      <text title="among the three mighty men: ">the most prominent of the mighty men.</text>
      <text title="risked their lives: ">When they pledged to fight [the Philistines] and defeat them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="only to strip the slain: ">Jonathan translates: to strip the slain. There was no one to help him in killing, but they would all strip the dead after him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="the mountaineer: ">Heb. הררי, a mountaineer.</text>
      <text title="gathered together into a troop: ">Heb. לחיה, lit. a wild beast. Just as the wild beasts of the field [gather into troops].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="of the thirty: ">Jonathan translates: of the warriors the chiefs of the camps.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="and the garrison of the Philistines was then in Bethlehem: ">The army was encamped in the Valley of Rephaim, but they had sent a garrison of theirs to Bethlehem.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="Oh if one would only give me: ">Our Rabbis said, It was necessary for him to ask a [legal] question of the Sanhedrin who were seated at the gate of Bethlehem.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="poured it out before the Lord: ">He said: This tradition I had handed down to me from the court of Samuel the Ramathite: Whosoever endangers his life for the sake of the word of the Torah [one is to heed the Halachah but not at the cost of life] we are not to state the decision [for which he had endangered his life] in his name. Now how do we explain “and he poured it out before the Lord,” that we state it not in his own name but [anonymously] in the name of the entire academy [in this manner ‘pouring it out’ without due credit to the one who stated it, but simply for the sake of the Lord].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="[shall I drink] the blood of the men: ">Heb. הדם. It is an expression of wonder.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="to the three he did not attain: ">But to the three warriors [of the first order] he did not attain.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="the two mighty men of Moab: ">But our Rabbis stated that he neither left anyone like him, in the [period of the] First Temple nor in the [period of the] second Temple.</text>
      <text title="of Moab: ">because Solomon, who built it, was a descendant of Ruth the Moabitess.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="of the thirty he was most honored: ">Every mention of שלשים in this chapter, Jonathan translates as warriors.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="39">
      <text title="thirty seven: ">Now they are not [all] listed here: I therefore say that it was unnecessary to mention Joab since he was the commander- in-chief. Regarding the others that were missing perhaps the sons of Jesse (Jashan. See above v. 32) were three or four.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="24">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="against Israel: ">I do not know regarding what.</text>
      <text title="He moved: ">provoked.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="of whatsoever they may be: ">כהם implies double, וכהם is twice double or fourfold. Then he continues to increase the progression up to one hundred times. Consequently, Joab’s blessing was greater than that of Moses who stated: “a thousand times what you presently are” (Deut. 1:11). Furthermore, Moses’ blessing was over a lengthy period of time while Joab’s was to take immediate effect, as it stated: “and the eyes of my Lord the king may see it.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="of Gad, and a Jaezer: ">He began with the children of Gad since they were mighty and firm and he reasoned: If only they would fight me and hold me back.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="to the land of Tahtim- hodshi: ">Heb. חדשי. A new settlement where there were yet few people. [He reasoned:] Perhaps in the interim David would have a change of heart and send him a messenger that he return.</text>
      <text title="to Dan: ">Among the children of Dan.</text>
      <text title="Jaan: ">Name of a place.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="sum of the number: ">If sum why number? And if number, why sum? Joab made two lists, a long and a short one. He said: I shall show him the short one but if he gets angry then I will show him the longer one. This is why it says מפקד which is an expression of lacking. So it is explicated in the Pesikta.</text>
      <text title="and Israel consisted: ">Heb. ותהי. Their strength ebbed as that of a female.</text>
      <text title="eight hundred thousand valiant men: ">Now in I Chronicles 21:5 it is written “one million, one hundred thousand.” In the Aggadah of the Amoraim [the post-Mishnaic rabbis of the Talmud] we find: R. Joshua the son of Levi said: The verses add here what they omitted elsewhere, [i.e.,] the two tribes that were not counted, for it is written in I Chronicles (2:6): But Levi and Benjamin he did not number among them; for the king’s word was abominable to Joab. Joab said, From these I can free myself by claiming that the tribe of Levi is not [to be] counted among the other tribes but from one month and above [while the other tribes were counted from ages twenty to fifty]. Now concerning Benjamin it is enough that they were diminished and [nearly] destroyed in the incident of the Concubine in Gibeah (Jud. Ch. 20). Also in the thirty-two rules [of interpretation] of R. Eliezer the son of Rabbi Yosi of Galilee we learned: One verse states that “all of Israel were one million and one hundred thousand… and Judah was four hundred seventy thousand [men],” while another verse states that “Israel consisted of eight hundred thousand… and the men of Judah were five hundred thousand.” We thus find a discrepancy of three hundred thousand between them. What is to be said concerning these three hundred thousand? Comes the third verse (in I Chron. 27:1) and clarifies “And the children of Israel after their number, the heads of father’s houses and the captains of thousands and of hundreds and their officers that served the king, in any matter of the divisions which came in and went out month by month throughout all the months of the year of each division were twenty-four thousand.” We learn from here that these three hundred thousand were written in the royal record and required no [additional] accounting. How [do we derive this sum]? Twenty-four thousand [multiplied] by twelve [tribes] totals two hundred and eighty-eight thousand leaving twelve thousand who were the rulers of Israel."</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="three things I offer you: ">One of three. The same with “with two you shall become my son-in-law” (I Sam. 18:21), [where the intent is] with one of two.</text>
      <text title="three things I offer you: ">Coinciding with the three that you wished [lit. placed] upon Saul: “the Lord will smite him; or his day will come and he will die; or, he will go down to war and perish” (I Sam. 26:10).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="I am greatly oppressed: ">Even the least of them is very harsh.</text>
      <text title="hand of the lord: ">Pestilence, but not sword or famine, for it, too, is [partially] in the hands of the wealthy who store produce. Rabbi Alexandri said: David said, If I should choose the sword, the Israelites would then say that he depends on his mighty warriors that he will not die and only others will die. If I should choose famine they will say he depends on his wealth. Let me therefore choose pestilence in which all are equal.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="from the morning until the appointed time: ">From the time when the daily burnt offering was slaughtered until its blood was sprinkled.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="The Jebusite: ">He was the commander of the citadel of Zion, which was called Jebusite.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="And Aravnah looked afar: ">He was hiding from the angel. So it is written (in I Chron 21:20).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="threshing tool: ">A wooden tool full of incisions. Now this instrument is heavy and is constantly drawn over the straw so that it chops it into feed for the animals.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="Aravnah the king: ">He was the lord of the Jebusites.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="for fifty shekels of silver: ">Now in I Chronicles 21:25 it states: “six hundred shekel; of gold by the weight.” How can this be? He gathered fifty shekels of silver from each and every tribe which totals six hundred [silver shekels] and he presented him with silver equal to the amount of [fifty shekels] of gold. This we learned at the end of Tractate Zev. (116b). i.e., that he gathered silver in the amount of six hundred [shekels] of silver [equivalent to fifty] gold shekels. We also learned it in Sifrei.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
</book>