<book>
  <chapter id="1">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Who shall go up for us first against the Canaanites: ">To the places for which we cast lots but were not yet conquered.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="Judah shall go up: ">The tribe of Judah shall go up first to conquer its portion.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="to Simeon his brother: ">i.e., To the tribe of Simeon.</text>
      <text title="Come up with me into my lot: ">Come up with me and help me conquer that which fell as my portion. Some interpret “Judah shall go up” referring to Othniel, being Yabetz, of whom we say in Tractate Temura (16a), “Judah, the brother of Simeon, is his name,” and Simeon, his brother, he asked to go with him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="in Bezek: ">This is the name of the place.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="Seventy kings…: ">From here you can learn [the extent of] the greatness and wealth of the kings of Canaan [mentioned in Josh. 12:7 24] since Adoni bezek was not even worthy of being counted among the kings of Canaan and [yet] it is so written of him [Sifre Deut. 33: 17].</text>
      <text title="And they brought him to Jerusalem: ">They went from there to wage war against Jerusalem.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="set the city on fire: ">They set a fire throughout all of it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="Caleb’s [younger] brother: ">From his mother.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="that she persuaded him: ">Targum Jonathan renders, וְאַמְלַכְתֵּיהּ, an expression of convincing, that you counsel a person and persuade him in a certain way. So it appears to me.</text>
      <text title="and she leaned: ">Targum Jonathan renders וְאִתְרְכִינַת, she bent over to fall at her father’s feet.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="dry land: ">I.e., A person whose house is arid [devoid] of all earthly good, who has nothing but Torah.</text>
      <text title="springs of water: ">A rain [or, naturally] sustained field, as Targum Jonathan renders אֲתַר בֵּית שַׁקְיָא דְמַיָא [an adequately watered place].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="from the city of date palms: ">That is Jericho. They were given the fat pasture grounds of Jericho to eat until the Temple would be built. The one in whose portion the Temple was to be built would take this [instead], so that all Israel could have a portion in the Temple [i.e., so that the Temple would not be built upon the private property of any particular tribe]. It was given to the children of Jethro for four hundred forty years [until the Temple was built], during which the students among them left it and went to Othniel the son of Kenaz, who is Jabetz, in the desert of Judah, which is in the south of Arad, to study Torah.</text>
      <text title="and dwelt with the people: ">With the students who sat before him. He asked of God to provide for him proper students, as it says, [I Chron. 4:10] “And Jabetz called to God, etc.” And He provided for him these pious people.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="but they could not drive out: ">Targum Jonathan paraphrases: But after they had sinned, they were unable to drive out the inhabitants of the plain.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="the Jebusites that inhabited Jerusalem: ">There was a section in Jerusalem called Jebuse, which was populated by the descendants of Abimelech who were not driven out because of the oath [which Abraham had sworn], until the coming of David. This was because his grandson was still alive and Abraham had sworn [Gen. 21:23] to him, his son, and grandson.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="Beth-El: ">Which fell to their lot. Although the idol of Micah was with them, since Micah was from the tribe of Ephraim, it nevertheless states here, “the Lord was with them.” That is what Daniel said, [Daniel 9: 7] “To You, Lord, there is charity, and to us there is shame of face.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="caused to spy: ">Through others, as Targum Jonathan renders וּשְׁלַחוּ מְאַלְלִין [and they sent spies]. [Num. 13:21] וַיָּתֻרוּ, “And they spied the land,” is said of the spies themselves, and of those that sent spies it is said, וַיַּתִּירוּ [“caused to spy”].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="the entrance to the city: ">They entered the city through a cave over which one hazelnut bush (לוּז) stood at the entrance and one would enter through the bush into the cave.</text>
      <text title="Luz: ">Upon which small nuts grow. Courdre [in Old French a hazelnut bush].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="And he showed them: ">[By pointing] with his finger.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="this is its name until this day: ">Sannacherib did not repatriate it, nor did Nebuchadnezzar destroy it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="And Menasseh did not drive out: ">The Scripture tells of their shame; they began to betray the Holy One, blessed be He, Who commanded them, [Num. 33:52] “You shall drive out all the inhabitants of the land, etc.”</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="2">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And a messenger of the Lord went up: ">We learned in Seder Olam that this was Phinehas.</text>
      <text title="to Bochim: ">This is the name of the place (see below v.5).</text>
      <text title="I will take you up: ">So I intended initially to take you out of Egypt and so I did, on the condition that you drive out my enemies.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And I also said: ">Now I said in my anger.</text>
      <text title="pokers: ">As pokers in your sides with troops and marauders to plunder and spoil.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="And Joshua had sent away, etc.: ">This incident actually occurred earlier, but since the Scripture is coming to tell us (v.11) “And they did that which is evil,” it begins with the following: Before Joshua died and they (Israel) accepted before him to serve God, he sent them each to his inheritance, and they served God all his (Joshua’s) days and the days of the elders, etc., and afterwards, “And the children of Israel did evil, etc.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="that outlived Joshua: ">Heb. הֶאֱרִיכוּ. Lit., their days were lengthened but their years were not, because they were lax with his eulogy. And so it says (v.9) “Mount גָּעַש,” the mountain quaked (געש) over them to kill them (Sab. 105b).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="in Timnath-Cheres: ">It was called so because they erected a picture (תְּמוּנָה) of the sun (חֶרֶס) on his grave as though to say: How unfortunate, the person who stopped the sun (Josh. 10:12) lies in a grave.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="Wherever they went out, the hand of the Lord was against them for evil: ">Concerning Elimelech, Machlon, and Kilyon it was said. In Seder Olam 12.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="And the Lord raised up judges: ">Constantly in each generation, as they are enumerated in this book, judge after judge.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="And when the Lord raised: ">This is in the present tense: And when He raised for them judges, God would be with the judge, etc.</text>
      <text title="for [the Lord] retracted: ">He would retract from the evil. So renders Targum Jonathan .</text>
      <text title="because of their cry: ">Because of their cry that arose before Him because of their enemies.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="they did not diminish, etc.: ">They did not leave over anything for which reason they were reproached through all that befell them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="whether they would keep: ">The “heh” (of הֲשׁוֹמְרִים is vocalized הֲ because it is an expression of question and testing (i.e., would they keep, etc.).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="3">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="through whom to test Israel: ">(To test) the other generation that did not know about the miracles of the battles with Canaan and did not witness the great act and (therefore) rebelled against the Omnipresent.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="Only that… should know: ">Just for this alone did He allow them to remain, to explain to future generations of the children of Israel what sin causes, for now they are required to study warfare.</text>
      <text title="just the earlier ones: ">Who stood in the service of God.</text>
      <text title="did not know thereof: ">These battles and their tactics, and they did not need them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="The five lords of the Philistines: ">These were the nations that He left to test (them).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="And the spirit of the Lord came upon him: ">Rabbi Tanchuma expounded: He contemplated what the Holy One, blessed be He, said to Moses in Egypt, (Ex. 3:7) “I have surely seen (רָאֹה רָאִיתִי) the oppression of my people.” What are these two expressions of seeing? The Almighty said to him, “I have seen that they are destined to go astray by (worshipping) the calf, but nevertheless I have seen the oppression of My people (in Egypt and I will therefore save them).” Thus said Othniel, whether innocent or guilty He must save them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="the city of the date palms: ">Jericho.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="a shriveled right hand: ">Targum Jonathan renders, “a person with a shriveled (גְמִיד) right hand.” Any (word) גְמִיד is an Aramaic expression (meaning) something shriveled by disease. Retrait in O.F. (shortened. Likewise אִטֵּר is found in Sab. 103a.) He had no use of his right hand. In Hebrew (the word) אִטֵּר means “closed” as in, (Psalms 69:16) “Do not close upon me, O well, your mouth.” His right hand was closed up and he had no use of it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="a cubit was its length: ">A short cubit. In German daumen lang , in 0.F. espan courte.</text>
      <text title="on his right thigh: ">Because he controlled his left hand, he would grasp it with his left hand (from his right thigh).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="אִישׁ בָּרִיא: ">Fat.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="that he escorted the people: ">He went back to escort the group of Israelites that had come with him to bring the tribute and he escorted them up to Gilgal.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="And he turned back: ">Alone.</text>
      <text title="from the quarries: ">(Heb. פְּסִילִים) The place where they quarry (Heb. פּוֹסְלִים) stones from the mountain. And so does Targum Jonathan render (מִן מַחֲצָבַיָא) “from the quarries.” Then he came to Eglon and said to him…</text>
      <text title="And he said, “Be quiet,”: ">Eglon said, “Silence everyone from me.” Targum Jonathan renders הָס as (סְלִיק) remove, i.e., remove everyone, (but) nevertheless הַס is a term of silencing.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="in the cool upper room: ">In his summer attic which was ventilated and cool.</text>
      <text title="I have a message from God to you: ">And you must rise.</text>
      <text title="And he stood up from the chair: ">Therefore he merited that Ruth was descended from him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="And the haft: ">This is the metal into which the blade is inserted, which is called hulot in 0.F. (a handle). This holds the sword over the sheath.</text>
      <text title="the blade: ">This is the blade which is called brant in O.F. and lama in O.F.</text>
      <text title="and the fat closed: ">His fat, for he was very fat, and it covered the whole length of the sword.</text>
      <text title="and the excrement came out: ">Targum Jonathan renders (וּנְפַק אוּכְלֵיה שְׁפִי) “and the excrement spilled out.” He interprets it as two words with the “shin” serving both וַיֵּצֵא הַפַּרְשׁ שְׁדוֹנָה“spilled out.” שָׁפָ is rendered שדא (see Lev. 17:4, 13).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="And Ehud went out to the porch: ">From the attic to the מִסְדְּרוֹנָה which Jonathan renders “to a porch”.</text>
      <text title="and locked them: ">With a key.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="Now when he had gone out (his servants came): ">Ehud went out and the servants of Eglon entered.</text>
      <text title="he is covering his feet: ">Targum Jonathan renders עָבִיד צוֹרְכֵיה (doing his needs), i. e., moving his bowels (based on Yeb. 103a).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="until it was late: ">Until they were detained, meaning a long time.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="נמלט: ">Escaped, eschamocrier in O.F.</text>
      <text title="while they lingered: ">(עַד) As in, (Song of Songs 1:12) “ While (עַד) the King was still feasting,” (ibid 2:7) “the love while (עַד) we still desire,” i.e., while we both still desire it.</text>
      <text title="To Seirah: ">To a fine thick forest called brousaille in O.F. (“brush”) which is good for hiding. This word occurs often in the Order of Zeraim that fine branches of trees are called שֵׂעָר as in (Kilayim 4:9) “He turned the branches (שֵׂעָר) ,” (Peah 2:3) “If the branches (שער) adjoined”.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="And it was when he came: ">He crossed the Jordan and came to his place in the land of Canaan.</text>
      <text title="on the mountain of Ephraim: ">Which was in the land of Canaan on the western side of the Jordan, whereas the land of Moab was on the eastern side, and since they ruled over Israel, they had crossed the Jordan and conquered Jericho, as it is written above (v. 13), and they had placed their lords and rulers over Israel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="Follow: ">To kill the Moabites who are on our side of the Jordan.</text>
      <text title="and seized the fords of the Jordan: ">Lest the Moabites cross to flee and return to their land.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="every lusty (man): ">(Targum Jonathan renders שָׁמֵן as) “Every awesome man.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="goad: ">This is the metal of an ox goad, aiguillon in 0ld French.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="4">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="in Harosheth goiim: ">The city was so named because it was powerful and occupied a dominant position.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="oppressed the children of Israel mightily: ">Heb. בְּחָזְקָה. Rabbi Tanchuma (Behar) expounded: With insults, and so it says, (Mal. 3:13) “Your words are unbearable (חָזְקוּ).”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="the wife of Lappidoth: ">She prepared wicks for the Sanctuary.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="under the palm tree: ">She had palm trees in Jericho.</text>
      <text title="between Ramah and Beth-el, in the mountain of Ephraim: ">According to Targum Jonathan’s rendering, we can derive that this verse is not to be taken literally. These were not her places of lodging but rather she was a wealthy woman and from these places she earned a livelihood and dwelt in her city Ataroth. Hence:</text>
      <text title="under the palm tree: ">She had palm trees in Jericho, vineyards in Ramah, olives in the plain of Beth-el where oil was abundant, and (עָפָר חִיוֵר) white earth in the mountain of Ephraim in Tur Malka. I say that this was sold to potters. Some interpret עפר חיור - A sown field like a grain field.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="“Indeed… commanded”: ">Through Moses (Deut. 20:17), “You shall totally destroy them.” So it is stated in the Mechilta.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="went up at his feet: ">(An expression meaning) with him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="Elon-bezaanannim: ">Targum Jonathan renders מֵישָׁר אַגְנַיָא the site of a plain (אֵלוֹן) of pits (בְּצָעִים), mariscusm in 0.F. This (i.e., בְּצָעִים) means אַגְנַיָא, being cavities similar to pits where water gathers, as in (Kiddushin 61a) “They are called pits (אגני) of the ground.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="from Harosheth-goiim, to the brook Kishon: ">He gathered them to go to the brook Kishon from Harosheth-goiim where he dwelt.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="with a garment: ">Targum Jonathan renders בְּגוּנְכָא which Rav Hai Gaon explains: a garment. Coate in O.F.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="the flask of milk: ">She gave him milk because it slackens the body and causes drowsiness.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="Stand in the doorway of the tent: ">(עֲמֹד) is masc.) Hasten like a man. And some interpret עֲמֹד as (לַעֲמוֹד) “to stand”.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="Tent pin: ">Chevilles in 0.F. A peg which is inserted into the ground together with the lower portion of a tent to stretch it out. הַמַּקֶּבֶת, Targum Jonathan renders ארזפתא, martel in Old French (a hammer). בַּלָּאט Targum Jonathan renders בְּרָז i.e., stealthily. וַתִּצְנַח בָּאָרֶץ Targum Jonathan renders וּנְעָצַת בְאַרְעָא : and it pierced through into the ground.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="in his temple: ">Targum Jonathan renders בְצִידְעֵיה (in his temple) tenplia in O.F. She had thrust it through his temple into the ground.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="5">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="When breaches are made in Israel, when the people offer themselves willingly: ">When breaches come upon Israel, for their enemies made breaches in them because they forsook their God and the masses feel motivated to repent, as of now it is proper to bless God (out of thankfulness) for the salvation He has wrought.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="אָנֹכִי אָנֹכִי: ">This word is repeated. I have heard an Aggadic interpretation: The Holy One did not rob (by withholding) the reward of Mount Tabor and Mount Carmel who arrived at the giving of the Torah, expecting it to be given upon them, and turned away in shame. The Holy One said to them, “I will pay you double fold. It was said at Sinai, (Ex. 20:2) ‘(אָנֹכִי) I am the Lord your God,’ at Tabor it will be said, ‘I… I…’ (אָנֹכִי אָנֹכִי). It was said at Sinai, ‘I am the Lord your God (ה׳ אֱלֹקֶי),’ at Carmel it will be said twice, (I Kings 18:39) ‘The Lord He is God, the Lord He is God (ה׳ הוּא הָאֱלֹקִים)’ in the days of Elijah.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="Lord, when You went forth out of Seir: ">This refers to the giving of the Torah as it says, “And He appeared to them from Seir” (Deut. 33:2). The relation here is that thus said Deborah: “The Torah is detrimental to forsake and rewarding to cling to it for amidst awe and might it was given. Therefore Israel was delivered into the hands of their adversaries because they forsook it, but when they decided to engage in it they were saved.” This can be derived from Targum Jonathan’s translation. נָטְפוּ - Dripped a life sustaining dew.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="The mountains melted: ">(Heb. נָזְלוּ) Like flowing water (נוֹזְלִים) they melted away.</text>
      <text title="this (was at) Sinai: ">It is already stated what appeared there. (See Ex. 19:16 19, 20:15.) It was completely in smoke and amidst thunder, torches, and fire.</text>
      <text title="because of the presence of the Lord: ">This is an abbreviated verse: This was at Sinai; that which occurred there was because God descended upon it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="In the days of Shamgar the son of Anath, in the days of Jael: ">(Since they are equated,) This teaches us that Jael also judged Israel in her days.</text>
      <text title="caravans ceased: ">Israel was afraid to travel because of the enemy, hence they followed winding roads in secrecy.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="The open cities ceased: ">Heb. פְרָזוֹן. Open cities (פְּרָזִי), without walls, ceased to be inhabited because of the enemies, and they gathered into the fortified cities.</text>
      <text title="until I (Deborah) arose: ">Heb. שַׁקַּמְתִּי. Interpreted as שֶׁקַּמְתִּי as below (6:17) “שָׁאַתָּה מְדַבֵּר עִמִּי” (That you are speaking with me, understood as שֶׁאַתָּה.)</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="When they chose new gods then there was war in the cities: ">When Israel chose new gods (cf. Deut. 32:17), they were then subject to war within their cities. However, look now when they were willing, will there be seen among Israel a shield or a spear to use in battle against the 40,000 generals the heathens brought upon them. The Almighty confused all of them in the battle with the stars, and the brook of Kishon raked them away.</text>
      <text title="cities: ">(שְׁעָרִים is usually interpreted as gates, however, here it means cities,) as in (Deut. 17:2), “When it will be found among you, within one of your cities” (שְׁעָרֶי).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="My heart…: ">I, Deborah, (my heart) is out to the lawgivers of Israel; to love the wise men of Israel who volunteered to tell the people, “Bless the Lord and return to Him.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="The riders of white donkeys: ">The merchants and nobles who may now ride on the precious white donkeys without fear or worry of the heathens, and those that sit in judgment (מִדִּין is an expression of דַיָּינִים, judges), who were afraid to practice justice publicly, and those that travel on foot, recite and tell of this salvation; (v. 11) that instead of the noise of your adversaries, the ambushers, bandits, and tax collectors who banded together to ambush at the water crossings, there the donkey riders and wayfarers will recite the righteous deeds of the Lord. What are His righteous deeds? Deeds of restoring open cities for Israel, for He granted tranquility to Israel to dwell in open cities and go about scattered, singly, without massing together as a group. Then… went down to the cities They now returned to their home cities whence they had fled to gather in the fortified cities.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="adversaries: ">Heb. מְחַצְצִים. Menachem (ben Seruk, a Hebrew Grammarian,) interprets, “those that wage war and array battles,” therefore he classifies this along with, (Prov. 30:27) “The locusts have no king, yet they march (חֹצֵץ) together;” an expression of “troops”. Another interpretation is מַשְׁאַבִּים מִקּוֹל מְחַצְצִים בֵּין, When you went to the river to draw water, you feared the sound of the pebbles smoothened by the river, Kiesels in German (cailloux in French is of Celtic origin), for their sound is heard when one passes over them, and you feared being detected by the heathens. However, now you do not have to worry about this. Therefore, it is incumbent upon you to give thanks to His name. מְחַצְצִים (is then) an expression of “pebbles smoothened by the river,” as in (Lam. 3:16) “and he broke with the stones (בֶחָצָץ) my teeth.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="Praise! Praise! Deborah: ">(עוּרִי is) An expression of praise, as in its plain meaning: Become firm in your praise. But our Rabbis said, because she praised herself by saying (v. 7) “Until I Deborah arose,” the Divine spirit left her (therefore she had to arouse (עוֹרֵר) it).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="Then ruled a remnant among the mighty: ">יְרַד = ירדה meaning “ruled,” as in (Isaiah 45:1) “Who rules (לְרַד) nations before Him.” The remnants of Israel ruled over the mighty (אַדִּירֵי) gentiles.</text>
      <text title="the Lord dominated the strong for me: ">He gave me dominion (יְרַד לִי) over the mighty of the gentiles.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="Out of Ephraim: ">From Ephraim issued the root (שׁוֹרֶשׁ, referring to Joshua the son of Nun (their prince), to subdue Amalek and weaken him by the sword (Ex. 17:13). This verse is connected to the previous one and explains: The Lord dominated the strong for me by establishing Joshua to subdue Amalek.</text>
      <text title="after you: ">Will arise from the tribe of Benjamin, Saul the son of Kish who will stone him and slacken (עֲמָם) him like dying (עוֹמְמוֹת) embers. We can (also) interpret בַּעֲמָמֶי referring to the army of 200,000 soldiers with which Saul came upon them (I Sam. 15:4).</text>
      <text title="Out of Machir came down officers: ">Outstanding officers who conquered the Amorites. This refers to those who captured sixty cities, the whole royal stretch conquered under Jair (of Menasseh See Deut. 3: 4, 14).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="And the princes of Issachar: ">The princes of Issachar are the Sanhedrin who were occupied in Torah and “knew how to treat the times” (I Chron. 12:32). They are always (cooperating) with Deborah to teach Israel statutes and laws.</text>
      <text title="And the princes of Issachar: ">Heb. שָׂרַי. The “yud” is inconsequential and does not serve any purpose, as the “yud” in (Ps. 8:8) “the cattle of the field (שָׂדַי)” ; (Jer. 22: 14) “Expand the windows (חַלּוֹנָי).”</text>
      <text title="as was Issachar with Barak: ">(The princes) And the rest of the people of Issachar are faithful to Barak in all that he will instruct.</text>
      <text title="into the valley they rushed forth with their feet: ">He sent them for all his errands; to gather the people and for all the needs of war.</text>
      <text title="(But) among the divisions of Reuben: ">But in the divisions of Reuben’s heart were vast חִקְקֵי לֵב, (which Targum Jonathan renders) נִכְלֵי לִיבָּא i.e., shrewdness. And what was his shrewdness? He dwelt by the edges (מִשִׂפְתֵי) of the battle to hear who would win so that he should join with him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="the bleatings of the flocks: ">To hear the sound of the flocks in battle; to whom is the sound of victory and to whom is the sound of defeat.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="abides beyond the Jordan: ">And he did not come to the battle, and likewise Dan gathered his wealth into ships to be prepared to escape.</text>
      <text title="and by his breaches: ">To watch the vulnerable parts of his land.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="Zebulun is a people that jeopardized…: ">He scorned himself and submitted himself to die in battle with Barak, and likewise Naphtali on the high places of the field, on Mount Tabor.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="in Taanach by the waters of Megiddo: ">Jonathan renders: In Taanach they dwelt and reached until the waters of Megiddo. The edge of the camp was in Taanach and it reached until the waters of Megiddo.</text>
      <text title="they took no gain of money: ">Without payment they came to aid Sisera, they asked no reward.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="From heaven they fought: ">(As they sought no gain,) likewise the Holy One sent against them His hosts who do not desire any reward.</text>
      <text title="from their courses: ">The tip of the star being in heaven and its edge upon earth (see following verses). From here it was said: The thickness of the firmament is equivalent to the space between heaven and earth, since the star is inserted in the firmament like a bolt into a door (this refers to an old fashioned bolt which went through the thickness of the door), i.e., the size of its length equaling the thickness of the firmament. Thus from this verse, which attests that from their courses they fought, we derive that the thickness of the firmament is equal to the height between heaven and earth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="swept them away: ">Heb. גְּרָפָם. It swept them from the world like a rake (מַגְרֵפָה) that rakes ashes from an oven.</text>
      <text title="that ancient brook: ">It became a guarantor to the sea concerning this from the days of Egypt as it is stated in Pesachim (118b).</text>
      <text title="tread down, O my soul: ">By using my feet upon the strength (עוֹז) of the mighty of Canaan.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="were pounded the heels of the horses: ">The hoofs of their horses slipped off because the heat of the star would boil the mud and the nail would slip off, as one scalds the feet in boiling water and the hoofs would slip off. And since they slipped off, the feet were stricken (הָלְמוּ) (Mechilta Ex. 14:24).</text>
      <text title="by reason of the prancings, the prancings of their mighty ones: ">They would cause their horses to prance in war as in (Nachum 3:2) “And a horse prancing” (דוֹהֵר). This is an expression of the prancing of a horse.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="“Curse you Meroz,”: ">Some say it was a star and some say he was a prominent person who was near the battle area and yet did not come.</text>
      <text title="said the messenger of the Lord: ">Said Barak as an agent of the Holy One.</text>
      <text title="the inhabitants thereof: ">Those that dwell within his four cubits. With (the blast of) four hundred horns, Barak excommunicated Meroz.</text>
      <text title="to the aid of the Lord: ">Speaking as though it could be done, for he who aids Israel is as if he is aiding the Divine Presence.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="above women in the tent: ">Heb. אֹהֶל. Referring to Sarah of whom it is said, (Gen. 18:9) “She is in the tent,” Rebecca of whom it is said, (ibid. 24:67) “And Isaac brought her into the tent,” and Rachel and Leah of whom it is said, (ibid 31:33) “And he went out of Leah’s tent and he entered Rachel’s tent”.</text>
      <text title="above women in the tent shall she be blessed: ">(Referring to) Jael, because they bore and raised children, but if not Jael, this evil one (i.e., Sisera) would have come and destroyed them. So it states in Genesis Rabbah 48. Another interpretation is that Jael also dwelt in tents (above 4:18), therefore she was mentioned in the blessing of tents.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="(but) milk she gave him: ">To test his state of consciousness, if he could discern between the taste of water and the taste of milk. So does Targum Jonathan paraphrase.</text>
      <text title="in a lordly bowl: ">Heb. אַדִּירִים. In a vessel that one drinks water, since water is called “mighty” (or lordly i. e., אַדִּירִים), as it says, (Ex. 15:10) “In the mighty (אַדִּירִים) waters”.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="to strike the weary: ">Heb. עֲמֵלִים. Referring to Sisera who was exhausted (עָמֵל) and tired.</text>
      <text title="(she) pierced: ">Heb. מָחֲקָה. An expression of piercing (חִיקוּי).</text>
      <text title="and (she) wounded: ">Heb. מָחֲצָה. An expression of wounding (מַחַץ).</text>
      <text title="and penetrated: ">Heb. חָלְפָה means “she made pass through” referring to the pin which pierced his head) coming out on the other side.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="and peered: ">Heb. וַתְּיַבֵּב. An expression of speaking, as in (Isa. 57:19) “The speech (נִיב) of the lips.” But our Rabbis explained (Rosh Hashanah 33b) מְיַבֵּב as an expression of wailing, as in (Num. 29:1), “Of wailing” (תְּרוּעָה) which is rendered יַבָּבָא. However, I say it is an expression of looking, as in, (Zach. 2:12) “The pupil (בָבַת) of his eye,” and so has Menachem classified it. הָאֶשְׁנָב, the window.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="The wisest of her princesses answer her: ">Heb. חַכְמוֹת is interpreted as “the wise of her princesses” (an adjective in the constructive form), therefore the “Heth” is vocalized with a “patach” (“ah” sounding vowel). חָכְמוֹת as a noun is vocalized “hatof kamatz” (an “aw” sound), as in (Prov. 24:7) “Wisdom (חָכְמוֹת) to a fool is like a rare jewel.” However, this form is vocalized חַכְמוֹת and similarly, (Prov. 14:1) “The wise (חַכְמוֹת) of the women establish their house.”</text>
      <text title="answer her: ">The dot in the (second) “nun” replaces the third “nun” (which would be needed to replace the word “her”). It thus means “they answer her.” The dot of a “nun” replaces the word “her” as in (Lev. 6:14) “Scalded he shall bring it,” (lit., her) (תְּבִיאֶנָּה).</text>
      <text title="she too returns answers: ">(Of) Consolation to herself saying: Why am I wondering about my son’s delay? (Are they not, etc.)</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="Are they not finding (and) dividing the spoils?: ">And that is delaying them.</text>
      <text title="two damsels to every man: ">They are ravishing the pretty women of Israel and every one of the men has two or three women in his bed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="So may perish: ">Deborah said, “This is for her a vain consolation, for so may perish all your enemies, O Lord, as he was destroyed.”</text>
      <text title="but they that love Him (should be) as the sun when he goes forth in his might: ">Which will occur in the coming future seven times seven the light of all the seven days of creation which is 343 times as much (as one day). This equals the sum of forty nine times seven. [Tanchuma].</text>
      <text title="And the land rested: ">These are not Deborah’s words, but rather the words of the writer of this book.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="6">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="did that which displeased: ">Until now it was said (above 3: 12, 4:1), “and they continued to do,” because (one) sin was piled on (another) sin, but with this song (ch. 5) they were forgiven for all they had done and it was as though now they were beginning to sin. So it is explained in Aggadath Tehillim .</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="the dens: ">Hiding places (Targum Jonathan), voutes in Old French, and since a small window (מָאוֹר) is placed in an unnoticeable spot they are called מִנְהָרוֹת (as in Job 3:3 נְהָרָה, meaning “light” [Metzudas Zion]), lucerno in French. מְעָרוֹת. (Caves) grotte in French. מְצָדוֹת is palliser in O.F. (strongholds) because (?) they are made in the forest by chopping down trees from all around.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="They and their cattle: ">(Came) to pasture on the grain.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="a prophet: ">This prophet was Phinehas [Seder Olam 20].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="the Abiezrite: ">From the family of Abiezer, of the family of Gilead, of the family of Menasseh.</text>
      <text title="and his son Gideon: ">His father was beating them out (i.e., the wheat), and he was sifting them. He then said, “Father, you are old, and if the heathens come, you will not be able to flee. Therefore you go and I will beat them out.”</text>
      <text title="in the winepress: ">(he beat the wheat) with the beams of an olivepress (בֵּית הַבַּד).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="The Lord is with you, mighty man of valor: ">Since he has granted you such strength.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="if the Lord be with us: ">(… וְיֵשׁ is to be interpreted as) If God is with us, why has… befallen us?</text>
      <text title="which our forefathers told us: ">It was Passover so he said, “Last night my father recited the Hallel and I heard him say, ‘When Israel departed from Egypt, etc.,’ (thus recounting the miracles God performed on behalf of Israel,) but now He has forsaken us. If our forefathers were righteous, let Him perform (wonders) for us in their merit, and if they were wicked, then just as He did for them undeserving wonders, so should He do for us. Where then are all His wonders?”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="And the Lord turned toward him: ">(Not the angel, but) the Holy One, Blessed be He, Himself.</text>
      <text title="with this your strength: ">With the strength of this merit that you advocated defense for my children. So did Rabbi Tanchuma (Shoftim) explain (this passage).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="Behold, my thousand: ">Heb. אַלְפִּי. The thousand (אֶלֶף) among whom I am counted to be under a head of a thousand is the lowliest (thousand) among all the thousands of Menasseh.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="שָאַתָּה: ">Interpreted as if vocalized שֶׁאַתָּה, with a “segol” (“eh” sound).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="unleavened cakes of an ephah of meal: ">We see that it was Passover, the day of the waving of the Omer, therefore it was said, (below 7: 13) “And behold, a roasted cake of barley bread tumbled, etc.” וְהַמָּרָק. The broth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="Alas: ">אֲהָהּ is an expression of “worry” meaning, “What will become (תְּהֵא) of me.”</text>
      <text title="Because I have seen: ">(עַל כֵּן is interpreted as עַל אֲשֶׁר) Because I have seen an angel of the Lord, therefore I worry and cry “Alas.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="and he called it: ">I.e., Gideon called the altar.</text>
      <text title="the Lord is peace: ">The Lord is He Who bestows upon us peace.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="the bullock: ">A young bull (פַּר), because a one day old ox (שוֹר) is (also) called an ox. וּפַר הַשֵּׁנִי And the second bullock.</text>
      <text title="seven years: ">That was fattened seven years for the idols. Eight transgressions were permitted that night. Gideon offered that which was set aside to be sacrificed for idolatry, he used idolatrous utensils, the offering was at night, it was on a private altar and not in the Sanctuary, he was not a priest, sacred vessels were not used, wood from an Asherah was employed, and an animal that was worshipped was used, as is stated in Temurah 28b.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="רֹאשׁ הַמָּעוֹז: ">On top of the rock.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="Will you contend: ">לַבַּעַל ? [The prefix “lamed” does not mean “to” but] for the Baal. אוֹתו ֹתּוֹשִׁיעוּן. Will you avenge him? Similarly, (I Sam. 25:33) “And from avenging (וְהשׁעַ) myself with my own hand,” which David said concerning Nabal.</text>
      <text title="He that will contend: ">לוֹ For him.</text>
      <text title="until morning: ">Tarry until morning.</text>
      <text title="if he be a god: ">Let him contend and avenge himself: He said this in order to delay them until Gideon escaped.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="contend with him: ">i.e., with Gideon. Near (the word) רִיב, the word עִם or אֶת or בּוֹ is used as in, (Gen. 31:36) “And he quarreled with Laban”, but לוֹ cannot be used with this expression. Hence, every לוֹ written here means “for (him)”.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="And a spirit of the Lord: ">A spirit of might.</text>
      <text title="and Abiezer gathered: ">I.e., the entire family.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="38">
      <text title="And it was so: ">There was only dew on the fleece, more so than on other places, as it says, “A bowl full of water.” However, “Upon all the ground it be dry” was not fulfilled because a covenant was made with the dew that it should not cease. וַיָּזַר An expression of “pressed,” and similarly, (Isa. 1:6) “They were neither pressed (זוֹרוּ) nor bandaged,” i.e., they were not pressed to extract the pus.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="7">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="By Gibeath moreh, in the valley: ">(מִגִּבְעַת הַמּוֹרָה בָּעֵמֶק.) by the mountain that overlooks the plain (Targum Jonathan). הַמּוֹרָה is an expression of instructing and looking (וּרְאִיָּה הוֹרָאָה, as in (Prov. 6:13) “Instructing (מוֹרֶה) with his fingers,” because from there, one could see and signal into the valley.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="vaunt: ">vanter in French (i.e., praise themselves)</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="and depart early: ">Heb. וְיִצְפֹּר. I.e., in the morning, as in the Aramaic term צַפְרָא (morning).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="“Every one who laps with his tongue, etc., and (likewise) every one that kneels upon his knees to drink.”: ">Set him (i.e., he who kneels) separately away from your group because they will not go with you since they are thus accustomed to kneel before idols.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="of those that lapped, putting their hand…: ">This is not a kneeling procedure just as one who laps with his tongue (is not considered kneeling).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="נֹפְלִים בָּעֵמֶק: ">I.e., they were encamped in the valley.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="צְלִיל: ">This is written צְלִול (i.e., empty), because the generation was empty of righteous people. צְלִיל לֶחֶם שׂעוֹרִים A roasted barley bread (Targum Jonathan). A cake baked (צְלִי) on coals.</text>
      <text title="barley bread: ">Symbolizing the merit of the Omer sacrificed on Passover.</text>
      <text title="and smote it, and it fell: ">i.e., The tent.</text>
      <text title="and it turned it: ">i.e., The tent was completely overturned, and fell.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="telling of the dream: ">Heb. מִסְפַּר). The story (סִפּוּר) of the dream, (as Targum Jonathan renders) יַת שוּעִית חֶלְמָא וְיַת פִּשְׁרֵיהּ (the telling of the dream and its interpretation).</text>
      <text title="and its interpretation: ">Its exchange; meaning, its interpretation (which takes the place of the dream).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="trumpets… torches: ">To commemorate the merit of the giving of the Torah. However, the simple meaning is that since it was night, as it states (v. 9), it was dark, therefore they took the torches to provide light, and placed them into pitchers lest the torches be discerned.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="You shall look at me: ">At what I do, and do likewise.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="I and all that are with me: ">One of the companies consisting of one hundred men was with him.</text>
      <text title="For the Lord and for Gideon: ">(Targum Jonathan paraphrases:) The sword that kills is prompted by the Lord, and the victory is through Gideon.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="they had but recently awakened: ">I.e., The soldiers previously (had but recently awakened) the guards, who were to guard during the middle watch; for so it is customary for soldiers to set up watchmen, these would watch for the first third of the night, these for the second third, and these for the last third.</text>
      <text title="and they smashed the pitchers that were in their hands: ">(and he told them) to break the pitchers which were in their hands.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="and they trumpeted: ">A blast to disencamp and flee.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="and seize before them the waters: ">Which separate between Edom and Canaan (Text per Rabbi Joseph Karo).</text>
      <text title="and (also) the Jordan: ">For it also separated.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="they brought to Gideon beyond the Jordan: ">In the morning, when Gideon crossed the Jordan in pursuit of Zebah and Zalmunna.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="8">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="What have I done now in comparison with you?: ">Of what importance is what I did at first, compared with what you subsequently did.</text>
      <text title="Are not the gleanings… better: ">Are not the gleanings that came to your hand at the end better than the vintage that I and my family picked in the beginning, considering that in your hands the Lord delivered the kings (i. e., the princes).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="and what was I able: ">to do that would be as outstanding as your deed?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="he crossed, and the three hundred men: ">They were crossing the Jordan after Zebah and Zalmunna who had passed earlier (perhaps even prior to the blockade above 7:24) and laid waste to the land of Reuben, Gad and Menasseh. Therefore, he crossed to take revenge against them also.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="to the men of Succoth: ">Who were Israelites.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="Is the palm of Zebah and Zalmunna now in your hand: ">That you boast that you saved us from Midian?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="the briers: ">Ronzes in O.F.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="were in Karkor: ">The name of a place.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="by the way of the tent dwellers: ">Through the land of Kedar and Arabia, whose people live in the desert in tents, constantly grazing their flock and not residing in houses.</text>
      <text title="on the east of Nobah and Jogbehah: ">Which were Israelite cities. However, he only wanted to go there roundabout, so that they should not be detected, and thereby suddenly surprise them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="when the sun was still high: ">I.e., when the sun had not yet set, while the sun (חֶרֶס) still appears high (לְמַעֲלָה).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="וַיּוֹדַע בָּהֶם: ">And broke with them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="One was as the form of the children of the king: ">Heb. אֶחָד כְּתֹאַר בְּנֵי הַמֶּלֶ. Targum Jonathan renders: One among them appeared like the children of the king. However, we can interpret: As you are, so were they, all of you possessing one appearance (כּמוֹ כְמוֹהֶם אֶחָד); since they appeared like the children of kings (כְּתֹאַר בְּנֵי הַמֶּלֶ).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="But the young man did not draw his sword: ">To kill them, because he was afraid of them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="the crescents: ">Of gold, lunettes in O.F.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="הַשַּׂהֲרוֹנִים וְהַנְּטִיפוֹת: ">The crescents and the pendants [after Targum Jonathan].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="And Gideon made it into an Ephod: ">To serve as a reminder of the great victory, by showing how immense their army was that the nose rings of the nobles amounted to all this gold.</text>
      <text title="and all Israel went astray after it: ">After Gideon’s death.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="Baal- berith: ">This was its name.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="in four companies: ">Lit. in four heads.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="And they did not do kindness with the house of Jerubbaal: ">They killed his sons, as Scripture states below (9: 5).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="9">
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="and hasty: ">פוֹחֲזִים. Hasty in their actions, to do without meditation.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="by the plain of the stones: ">Heb. אֵלוֹן מֻצָּב. Targum Jonathan renders מֵישַׁר קָמָתָא, i.e., a plain (אֵלוֹן) containing monuments (מַצֵּבוֹת).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="the trees went forth: ">This is allegorical.</text>
      <text title="to the olive tree: ">Referring to Othniel the son of Kenaz from the tribe of Judah, which is called an olive tree, as it says, (Jer. 11:16) “Like a fresh olive tree, beautiful in form, etc.” (this refers to the cities of Judah mentioned in v. 13 ibid).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="דִּשְׁנִי: ">This is an expression of “fatness.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="to the fig tree: ">Deborah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="my sweetness: ">(Referring to) the bee’s honey.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="to the vine: ">Referring to Gideon who descended from Joseph of whom it is said, (Gen. 49:22) “A fruitful son is Joseph; blessed as a vine standing by the water” (as per Onkelos).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="which causes God… to rejoice: ">For the Levites do not recite the sacrificial song of praise but during the libations of wine.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="To the thorn: ">Heb. הָאָטָד, epine in O.F.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="If in truth: ">I.e., because I am fit to rule.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="And Abimelech ruled: ">Forcefully and arrogantly he held his position.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="an evil spirit: ">A spirit of hatred, (טלנט), talent in O.F.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="Gaal the son of Ebed: ">He was from another nation.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="וַיַּעֲשוּ הִלּולִים: ">And they made dances [quoting Targum Jonathan].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="Who is Abimelech and who is Shechem: ">Who is Abimelech that he should rule over Shechem, and who is Shechem to be servants to Abimelech? Was not Abimelech the son of Jerubbaal (הֲלֹא בֶן יַרֻבַּעַל) from Ophrah of the Abiezrites?</text>
      <text title="and Zebul (is he not) his officer: ">As for the officer of the city whose name is Zebul, he is (but) an officer of Abimelech; since his master has no right to rule here, neither do his appointees.</text>
      <text title="Serve the men of Hamor: ">If you are coming to acquire for yourselves leaders, come and serve the men of Hamor, who was a previous lord over the land.</text>
      <text title="but why should we serve him: ">I.e., Abimelech.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="And he said to Abimelech: ">(Indirectly;) and Gaal spoke before Zebul to inform Abimelech (as subsequently evident).</text>
      <text title="Increase your army, and come out: ">From the place where you are, and let us see your greatness.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="in secret: ">Heb. בְּתָרְמָה. As in (Gen. 27:35) “בְּמִרְמָה,” and (Jer. 8: 5) “בּתַרְמִית,” i.e., quietly and secretly.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="from the navel of the earth: ">(Targum Jonathan renders) מִן תּוּקְפָא דְאַרְעָא (i. e., from the strength of the land) from its highest mountain. Combine 2 Heb. words אֵלוֹן מְעוֹנְנִים, the plain of Meonenim.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="42">
      <text title="that the people went out to the field: ">The people of Shechem.</text>
      <text title="and they told: ">The informers told Abimelech that the citizens went out to the field to attend their needs.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="44">
      <text title="in the entrance of the gate of the city: ">So that no one could enter.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="46">
      <text title="forest: ">צְרִיחַ in Heb. A forest in which the trees and branches are bent over all around the forest; plissé in O. F.</text>
      <text title="Beth-El-Brith: ">That forest belonged to Baal Brith (above v. 4), the name of their idol. Zalmon (v. 48) also had a forest. Some interpret צְרִיחַ as voutes in O.F., which is made in the ground.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="48">
      <text title="שוֹכַת עֵצִים: ">A bough from a tree.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="53">
      <text title="פֶּלַח רֶכֶב: ">A piece of the upper millstone which is called a רֶכֶב.</text>
      <text title="and crushed: ">וְתָרִץ same as וּתְרוֹצֵץ (a more familiar form).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="54">
      <text title="lest they say of me: ">Lit. lest they say to me.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="10">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="the sons of Dodo: ">Heb. דוֹדוֹ, this was his name.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="עֲיָרִים: ">(Targum Jonathan renders) עוּלִין, i.e., colts.</text>
      <text title="And they had thirty cities: ">And they had thirty unwalled cities. It therefore states עֲיָרִים which is an expression of unwalled cities (עֲיָירוֹת).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="the Baalim, etc.: ">Seven idols are enumerated here.</text>
      <text title="and they forsook the Lord, and did not serve Him: ">Even in conjunction with the idols.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="that year: ">When Jair died.</text>
      <text title="(the children of Israel) that were beyond the Jordan: ">I.e., The land of Reuben, Gad, and half of Menasseh who were their neighbors.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="Did (I) not (save you) from the Egyptians: ">Seven deliverances are mentioned here, corresponding to the seven heathen gods that they served.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="and Maon: ">This is the name of a nation.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="and His soul was grieved by the toil: ">As if one could say, He did not have the expanse to endure and contain the anguish caused Him by the toil (or suffering) Of Israel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="were gathered: ">Heb. וַיִּצְּעֲקוּ. They gathered through announcements.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="11">
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="and the children of Ammon made war: ">(The war) referred to above.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="all his words: ">The stipulation which was between them.</text>
      <text title="before the Lord in Mizpah: ">At the place where they all gathered (above 10:17), since the Divine Presence resides amongst the multitudes of the congregation.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="up to the Red Sea: ">Located south of the land of Edom which is itself located to the south of the land of Canaan.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="Let me pass now through your land: ">From the South to the North to enter the land of Canaan.</text>
      <text title="and also to the king of Moab: ">Whose land was adjacent to the land of Edom along the east, and was to the south of the land of Israel.</text>
      <text title="and he was unwilling: ">Moses hinted this in the Torah (Deut. 2: 29), “As was done to me by the children of Esau who dwell in Seir (Edom) and by the Moabites who dwell in Ar,” implying that just as Edom did not let them pass, similarly Moab did not let them pass.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="And they went through the wilderness: ">From west to east along the southern border of Edom and Moab.</text>
      <text title="and went around the land of Edom: ">Its entire southern border.</text>
      <text title="and the land of Moab: ">The entire southern border, and when they reached the southeastern corner they turned north to compass the eastern border.</text>
      <text title="and they came to the east of the land of Moab, and they encamped on the other side of the Arnon: ">To the end of the eastern border of the land of Moab whence began the land of Sichon and Og. They then conquered the side of the Jordan to the east of the land of Canaan (as the following verses indicate), and then crossed the Jordan, entering the land of Canaan from the east.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="And they possessed… from the Arnon up to the Jabbok: ">That which you say was yours, (in reality) they (i.e., our forefathers) took it from Sichon.</text>
      <text title="and from the wilderness up to the Jordan: ">There were deserts situated east of the Jordan.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="עַל יְדֵי אַרְנוֹן: ">(Lit., on the hands of Arnon) I.e., along Arnon. These cities were from Moab, but they realized that they could not instigate war over them because Israel had conquered them from Sichon who had taken them from the king of Moab.</text>
      <text title="three hundred years: ">Since the land was conquered in the days of Joshua until Jephthah. From here we can derive if the periods of the judges that were mentioned up to this point include the years of oppression by the heathens or not. We have learned in Seder Olam (Ch. 12): Joshua led Israel twenty eight years, but I have no Scripture whence to derive it. Othniel led them forty years including the years of oppression by Cushan- rishathaim (above 3:11); after him was Ehud for eighty years (above 3:30) including the eighteen years of oppression by Eglon. This totals one hundred forty eight years. Deborah led them forty years (above 5:31) including the years of oppression by Jabin. This totals one hundred eighty eight years; afterwards were the seven years of oppression by Midian (above 6:1) and the forty years of Gideon (above 8: 28), then the three of Abimelech (above 9:22), thus totaling two hundred thirty eight years. Afterwards were the twenty three of Tola, and the twenty two of Jair (above 10:2,3), however one same year coincides for both of them; finally, adding the eighteen of Ammon prior to Jephthah’s introduction (above 10:8), this amounts to the three hundred years.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="עָבַר בְּנֵי עַמּוֹן: ">(Lit., he passed the children of Ammon) I.e., he passed over to the children of Ammon.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="Abel Cheramim: ">The plain of vineyards [after Targum Jonathan].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="הַכְרֵע ַהִכְרַעְתִּנִי: ">This is expressed in feminine form (the “tav” being vocalized with a חִירִיק) as in, (Song of Songs 4:9) לִבַּבְתִּנִי אֲחֹתִי כַלָּה (“You drew my heart, my sister, my beloved”).</text>
      <text title="(you) have become one of those that trouble me: ">All my blood is troubled. You have ruined my equilibrium (lit., feet thus causing me to fall).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="and wail: ">Heb. וְיָרַדְתִּי</text>
      <text title="upon the mountains: ">This is an expression of lamenting, as in (Isa. 15:3) “Upon her roofs and streets they all lament, lamenting with a cry יוֹרֵד בַּבֶּכִי)),” as one who is immersed in mourning until his body is broken (since יְרִידָה is also an expression of “breaking,” as in Lamen. 1:13). In an Aggadic interpretation Rabbi Tanchuma (Behukosai) explains “Upon the mountains” as referring to (her) presenting the case before the Sanhedrin (Great Court); perhaps they can find an opening to your (i.e., Jephthah’s) vow.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="38">
      <text title="and she cried over her virginity: ">Heb. בְּתוּלֶיהָ. Since it does not say “over her maidens” (בְּתוּלוֹתֶיהָ) , it implies that this refers to her actual virginity.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="39">
      <text title="and it was a statute: ">They decreed that no one should do this anymore (i.e., they publicized that no one should offer a human being), because had Jephthah gone to Phinehas or vice versa, he would have nullified his (i.e., Jephthah’s) vow (i.e., he would have instructed him what the law is in such an instance). However, they were particular about their honor, and as a result she was destroyed. Consequently, they were punished; Phinehas, by the Divine presence leaving him as it is stated in (I) Chron. (9:20) “Previously God was with him,” so we see subsequently God was not with him; and Jephthah was afflicted with boils and dismemberment as it is stated, (below 12:7) “And he was buried in the cities [pl.] of Gilead.” (His limbs were buried in the various cities.) We can also interpret “And it was a statute in Israel” as connected to the following verse.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="40">
      <text title="from year to year…: ">This they (i.e., the daughters of Israel) accepted upon themselves as a statute. לְתַנּוֹת To lament.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="12">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="and passed to the north: ">They crossed the Jordan (eastward) and went up north to Gilead.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="because the lowest of Ephraim said, (Of what importance are) you Gileadites: ">The lowly of Ephraim belittled Gilead by saying to them, “Of what importance are you Gilead among Ephraim and Menasseh.” So renders Targum Jonathan .</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="And the Gileadites seized the fords…: ">They established guards at the fords.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="Say now 'Shibboleth’: ">(say) this stream (שִׁבֹּלֶת) of the river will I cross.</text>
      <text title="and he was not prepared to pronounce it properly: ">They stumbled in their speech.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="Ibzan: ">This was Boaz (who came from Beth-lehem).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="13">
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="wine or strong drink: ">יַיִן וְשֵׁכָר. New and old wine [after Targum Jonathan].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="וּמוֹרָה: ">(Lit., a thrower.) This is a razor because it casts and throws off hair.</text>    
      <text title="and do not eat any unclean (things): ">Of those things that are prohibited to a Nazir.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="לַנַּעַר הַיּוּלָּד: ">To the lad that will be born.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="after his wife: ">after her counsel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="what shall be the rule for the lad, and his doing: ">What is proper for the lad and what shall be done to him [after Targum Jonathan].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="Let us take you in now: ">Let us ingather you into the house.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="that when your word will come: ">If a message will come from you, by knowing and recognizing your name we will honor you and do that which you request.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="וְהוּא פֶּלִאי: ">I.e., hidden. It is constantly changed and it is not known to what it was changed today.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="וְכָעֵת: ">(Lit., and at a time) I.e., and at this time.</text>
      <text title="He would not let us hear (such things) as these: ">He would not let us hear such news (of our child) if we were deserving of death.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="לְפַעֲמוֹ: ">To come within him at times (לִפְעָמִים).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="14">
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="that he sought a pretense: ">I.e., a pretense to antagonize them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="and he talked to the woman (lit.): ">I.e., concerning the woman, he spoke to her relatives. So renders Targum Jonathan .</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="עֲדַת דְּבוֹרִים: ">(Targum Jonathan renders) דְּדַבַּרְיָתָא קִינָא, a swarm of bees.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="וַיִּרְדֵּהוּ: ">This is an expression of separating anything which is clinging, as by bread clinging to an oven, its removal is called רְדִיָּה (Sab. 117b) “One who separates (הָרוֹדֶה) bread from an oven,” (ibid. 95a) “One who separates (הָרוֹדֶה) from his hive,” since the honey is contained in honeycombs clinging to the walls of the vessel on all sides from wall to wall according to the circumference of the vessel. Likewise Targum Jonathan renders וַיִּרְדֵּהוּ as וְנַסְחֵיהּ (and he separated).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="Now his father went down to the woman (lit.): ">I.e., concerning the woman [after Targum Jonathan].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="מֵרֵעִים: ">companions.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="And it was, on the seventh day: ">Of the week, not the seventh (day) of the feasting but rather the fourth day of feasting. קְרָאתֶם לָנוּ הֲלֹא הַלְיָרְשֵׁנוּ Targum Jonathan renders: Have you called us here (הֲלֹא = הֲלוֹם) to impoverish us?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="the seven days: ">I.e., the remainder of the seven days, from the fourth and onward.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="before the sun set: ">Before sunset, since they still had time until evening.</text>
      <text title="plowed with my heifer: ">This is allegorical (as Targum Jonathan renders): “Had you not interrogated my wife.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="a spirit of the Lord: ">A spirit of might emanating from God (Targum Jonathan). חֲלִיצוֹתָם I. e., the clothing that he removed (שֶחָלַץ has similar construction) from them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="לְמֵרֵעֵהוּ אֲשֶׁר רֵעָה לוֹ: ">She was given to one of his companions.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="15">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="This time I shall be blameless: ">Justly will I harm them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="and turned: ">The tails, tail to tail. וַיִּפֶן implies he himself turned. וַיַּפֶן implies he made others turn. And likewise is conjugated every word whose verb contains a “heh” (at the end which drops such as גלה רבה פנה) as in, (Ex. 1:20) הָעָם וַיִּרֶב (“And the people multiplied”), (Lamen. 2:5) יְהוּדָה וַיֶרֶב בְּבַת (“And He multiplied in Judah grief”), (II Kings 25:21) וַיִּגֶל יְהוּדָה מֵעַל אַדְמָתוֹ (“And Judah exited from his land”), (II Kings 17:6) וַיֶּגֶל אֶת ישְׂרָאֵל אַשּׁוּרָה (“And he exiled Israel to Ashur”) [as per Shem Ephraim].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="the son-in-law of the Timnite: ">The son-in-law of the Philistine who is in Timnah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="Are you accustomed to do like this: ">Perhaps you are accustomed to do such; to give the wife of one to another?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="שוֹק עַל יָרֵך: ">(Lit., leg on thigh) (Targum Jonathan renders) “riders and foot soldiers.” A horse rider is not supported by his thigh but rather by his leg, with one foot inserted into the metal (stirrup) which hangs from the saddle. בִּסְעִיף In the cleft (which is a crevice between the protrusions) of the rock of Etam, and similarly, (Isa. 2:21) וּבִסְעִיפֵי הַסְּלָעִים (“The protrusions of the rocks”), (Isa. 10: 33) מְסָעֵף פֻּארָה (“Will cut down its branches”).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="in Lehi: ">(lit., a jaw) This is the name of a place.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="Why have you come up against us: ">Are we not subservient to you?</text>
      <text title="to bind Samson: ">I.e., so that you should bind him and deliver him to us.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="No, however we will bind you: ">I.e., We will not kill you, however, we will bind you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="A spirit of the Lord: ">A spirit of might emanating from God [quoting Targum Jonathan]. אֲסוּרָיו His bonds.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="טְרִיָּה: ">Moist. I saw in a book of cures that the moisture which issues from a wound is called טְרִיָּה.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="חֲמוֹר חֲמוֹרָתָיִם: ">With the jawbone of a donkey I piled many piles, i.e., with the jawbone of a donkey I heaped them up [after Targum Jonathan].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="אֶת הַמַּכְתֵּש: ">The socket within which the tooth rests, thich is shaped like a mortar (מַכְתֶּשֶׁת). עֵין הַקּוֹרֵא The fountain (מַעְיָן) that came about through the prayers of the one who called (הַקּוֹרֵא) to God.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="16">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="To the Gazites, saying (Lit.): ">To the people of Gaza it was told.</text>
      <text title="And they were quiet: ">They conducted themselves quietly.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="וַיִּסָּעֵם: ">And he uprooted them from their place.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="bowstrings: ">I.e., thin cords.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="and his strength was not known: ">He did not have to exert himself to tear them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="ropes: ">I.e., thick cords.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="מַחְלְפוֹת: ">Locks. Pelous(פלודיש) in O.F.</text>
      <text title="to the roller: ">The wood upon which the weaver spreads out the warp. The name of this wood is ensouple in O.F. The roller (is called) ourdissuire in O.F.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="וַתְּאַלְצֵהוּ: ">And she pressed him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="And Delilah saw that he had told her: ">The words of truth are discernable.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="and she called to the man: ">To the messenger of the lords.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="And they brought him down to Gaza: ">(This was) the location of his first corruption (above v. 1).</text>
      <text title="and he did grind: ">With a mill. This was hard labor. However, our Sages explained that which they explained.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="between the pillars: ">Upon which the building was supported.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="and let me feel: ">Heb. וַהֲמִישֵנִי, Palpare (פלפאר) in O.F. as in, (Gen. 27: 12) “Perhaps my father will feel me” (יְמֻשֵּׁנִי).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="remember me: ">Remember the twenty years that I judged Israel and did not tell one of them “Move this stick for me from one place to another.”</text>
      <text title="the vengeance for one of my two eyes: ">And the reward for the second eye reserve for me for the world to come, but here pay me the reward for one of them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="וַיִּלְפֹּת: ">And he grasped. Embrasser (אינברצא) in O.F. as in, (Ruth 3: 8) “And the man trembled and was grasped” (וַיִּלָּפֵת), he was grasped by the arms of the woman.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="17">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Now there was a man from the mountain of Ephraim: ">Although the following two episodes are written at the end of this book; the one of Micah and the other about the concubine of Gibeah, they, nevertheless, occurred at the beginning of the period of the Judges. This was during the days of Othniel the son of Kenaz (and Cushan, above 3:8 11) as it says, (below 18:31) “And they accepted for themselves the graven image of Micah which he had made, throughout the period that the house of God was in Shiloh,” so we can derive that for the duration of Shiloh (Fourteen years after Israel’s crossing the Jordan, the Tabernacle was erected in Shiloh and remained there for three hundred sixty-nine years.) the image of Micah remained. Also, by the concubine of Gibeah it is said concerning the Jebusites of Jerusalem, (below 19:12) “We will not turn into (this) city of heathens,” so we can derive that they had not yet captured Jerusalem (which was captured by Judah, see above 1:8).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="that was taken to you: ">Heb. לָ. (Lit.) I.e., that was stolen from you (מִמּ). There is a similar verse: (I Sam. 21:6) “But women are withheld from us” (לָנוּ as מִמֶּנּוּ).</text>
      <text title="and (about which) you did curse: ">Anyone who stole it, and you also said the curse in my ears.</text>
      <text title="Behold the silver: ">I admit that it is in my possession because I took it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And he restored the eleven hundred pieces of silver to his mother: ">He said he would return them to her, and wherever they were they would be in her domain.</text>
      <text title="I have dedicated the silver (before the Lord) from my hand for my son: ">I accepted upon myself to transfer them from my possession to your possession for the purpose of a form and a molten image. Give them to me now, and then, from (being in) my possession I will return them to you. Some say that this woman was Delilah because it mentions eleven hundred pieces of silver (as above 16:5), but they are mistaken because Micah preceded Samson many years. However, these sections are adjacent because of the wicked silver which was an equal amount in both of them, and by their both being silver of misfortune.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="a house of idolatry: ">Heb. אֱלֹהִים. And so (is rendered) each אֱלֹהִים stated in this section as being profane with the exception of, (below 18:31) “Throughout the period that the house of God was in Shiloh.”</text>
      <text title="and he initiated (lit., and he filled the hand of) one: ">I.e., he indoctrinated him in the service of the image to be a priest to it. Any initiation whereby a person enters onto a higher level is called (מִלּוּי יָדַיִם) “filling the hands.” Revetir in O.F., and when office is bestowed upon a person it is called Reveture in O.F.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="of the family of Judah: ">And he was a Levite from his mother’s side. However, our Sages said (B.B. 109b) that since he committed deeds like those of Menasseh (i.e., he committed idolatry) who came from Judah he is called “Of the family of Judah,” but he was really a Levite the son of Gershom the son of our teacher Moses, as is stated below, (18:30) “And Jonathan the son of Gershom…”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="(while continuing) to make his way: ">I.e., (while continuing) the way he was travelling.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="where I may find (a place): ">To earn my livlihood.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="for the period: ">(Lit., for the days) I.e., at the end of the year.</text>
      <text title="and a wardrobe of clothing: ">A pair of garments that is suited for all people according to their needs for a year. וְעֵרֶ בְּגָדִים - Appareillement in O.F. וּמִחְיָתֶ I.e., your sustenance.</text>
      <text title="And the Levite followed: ">(lit., went) after his advice.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="18">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="for (until that day) there had not fallen to them: ">An inheritance befitting them in the previously conquered land, as it says, (Joshua 19:47) “And the border of the children of Dan went out from them.” From here we can also derive that this occurred at the immediate beginning of the Judges’ period.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="Who brought you here…: ">There are many questions here. Are you not of the descendants of Moses our teacher of whom it is said: (Ex. 3:5) “Do not draw near here;” (ibid. 4:11) “Who gave speech (פֶּה same letters as פֹּה) to a person;” and (ibid 4:2) “What is this in your hand?”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="Ask now of God: ">(translation follows Targum Jonathan . Rashi, however, explains:) Of the teraphim that speak through magic.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="before the Lord is your way in which you shall go: ">(Lit.) Before the Holy One, blessed be He, it is revealed, however, this one is worthless.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="for there was none in the land to put them to shame for any thing: ">Not one of them ever needs his friend’s assistance that he should have the opportunity to send him back empty-handed and embarass him, as it says, (v. 10) “Where there is nothing lacking.” So I have heard. יוֹרֵשׁ עֶצֶר There are few heirs, consequently, if these are killed there will not remain any other opposition to battle with the occupants of the portion.</text>
      <text title="and they were far: ">From the assistance of the Zidonians.</text>
      <text title="and had no bond (lit., word) with any man: ">(They do not have) any treaty contracted that anyone should come to their aid when necessary.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="What do you: ">(Lit.) Meaning, What do you have to respond? What did you find on the territory of our lot? What about the people, are they strong or weak?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="and you are silent: ">You are slothful.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="and the goods: ">The burdens. (This refers to) any thing which has difficulty in moving, not being able to run if pursued by people. Pezantume in O.F.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="and they turned their faces: ">I.e., the children of Dan to those that called them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="What else have I: ">what remains to me?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="men of embittered souls: ">The tempermental ones of our group.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="Laish: ">This was the name of the city. In the book of Joshua (19:47) it is called Leshem because they found there a precious stone named Leshem (turquoise) which was used on the breastplate (of the High Priest see Ex. 28:19) representing the tribe of Dan. His (i.e., Dan’s) name was written on (the) Leshem, thereby verifying that this was their rightful portion.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="the son of Menasseh: ">Out of respect for Moses (משֶׁה) a “nun” was inserted thereby changing the name (מְנַשֶּׁה). This letter was written suspended to indicate that it was not Menasseh but actually Moses.</text>
      <text title="until the day of the exile of the land: ">In the days of Sancherib, during the first exile.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="19">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="And his concubine turned away from him: ">She turned from his house to the outside. Every expression of זְנוּת implies going out (rendered (נפקת ברא, e.g., departing from her husband to love others.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="Accept now and lodge: ">Overnight.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="has weakened: ">I.e., the sun (has weakened) from its might and has declined to set.</text>
      <text title="it is the resting (part) of the day: ">It is the time that all wayfarers turn to rest indoors.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="but we will journey up to Gibeah: ">Of Benjamin.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="and we will lodge: ">Heb. וְלַנּוּ. To be understood as וְלַנְנוּ, since the “dagesh” of the “nun” replaces the appropriate second “nun”.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="and (I am going) to the House of the Lord: ">I am going to Shiloh (which was in Ephraim).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="and gave fodder to the donkeys: ">And he gave food (יְבוּל) to the donkeys. וַיָּבָל is aprovender in O.F.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="so that we may be intimate with him (lit., know him): ">Homosexually.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="but no one answered: ">Because she was dead.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="20">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="פִּנוֹת כָּל הָעַם: ">The chiefs of the people.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="דִמּוּ לַהֲרוֹג: ">They intended to kill. Adesmernt in O.F.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="that they may do when they come: ">I.e., when they come at this time to Gibeah of Benjamin, according to all the disgrace, etc.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="in unison: ">Agreeing to the same plan.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="throughout all the tribes of Benjamin: ">His ten families were reckoned as ten tribes, so that from Rachel would (also) issue twelve tribes (two coming from Joseph).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="(with a) shriveled right hand: ">Their right hands were shriveled. They had no use of it, as though it was closed, as in, (Psalms 69:16) “Do not close (תֶּאְטַר) upon me, O well, your mouth.”</text>
      <text title="All these: ">I.e., these seven hundred men.</text>
      <text title="at a hair breadth: ">At a thread of a hair breadth. וְלֹא יַחֲטִיא And not miss.</text>
      <text title="Judah first: ">But they did not attempt to ask whether they would be the victor or the vanquished. However, eventually when they did ask, God said, (v. 28) “Go up, for tomorrow I will deliver them into your hand.” Then they (i.e., the Urim and Tummim) agreed (הִסְכִּימוּ) and fulfilled their words.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="and they destroyed: ">They were punished because they were not equally zealous about the incident of the image of Micah which had already occurred.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="at Baal-tamar: ">In the plains of Jericho [quoting Targum Jonathan]. מֵגִיחַ Drew forth, as in, (Job 40: 23) “Draw (יָגִיחַ) the Jordan to his mouth,” and, (Psalms 22: 10)"You draw (גֹחִי) me from the womb.</text>
      <text title="out of Marreh- geba: ">Heb. מַעֲרֵה גָבַע From a narrow place, the naked (עֶרְוָתָהּ) exposed part of Gibeah of Benjamin, i.e., the bare part from where it is easily conquered, as in, (Gen. 42:9) “To see the nakedness (עֶרְוַת) of the land have you come.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="and the men of Israel gave (place): ">Those that were in the field (v. 31) gave a place for Benjamin to flee towards Gibeah, because Israel relied on the liers-in-wait to go out towards them (in battle).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="and the liers-in-wait blew: ">With a horn. Another interpretation is: They drew with the horn the people that were with them into the city.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="38">
      <text title="Now there was an appointed time: ">Initially there was a signal (prepared) between Israel and the liers-in-wait, that the liers-in-wait should raise a great deal of smoke from the city so that Israel should realize that they had conquered Gibeah. מַשְׂאַת הֶעָשָׁן A pillar of smoke (which rises נָשָׂא).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="39">
      <text title="Now as the men of Israel turned: ">Now Scripture returns to the beginning of the episode and repeats to explain about the twenty-five thousand written above (v. 35), how they fell and where they fell.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="42">
      <text title="and (those) of the cities: ">The liers-in-wait that entered the city destroyed them within the tribe within the city (sic).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="43">
      <text title="They encircled (כִּתְּרוּ) the Benjamites: ">Like a crown (כֶּתֶר) that encircles the head, and similarly, (Psalms 22:13) “The strong bulls of Bashan encircled me (כִּתְּרוּנִי) ,” and also in (Hab. 1:4) “Because the wicked encircles (מַכְתִּיר) the righteous.” The expression עֲטָרָה (Lit., crown) is also used to denote encircling, as in, (I Sam. 23:26) “And Saul and his men were encircling (עוֹטְרִים David and his men to capture them.” הִרְדִיפֻהוּ They called upon them a chase, shouting one to another to pursue.</text>
      <text title="(near their) resting places they overtook them: ">Near the cities wherein they rest, there they overtook them. הִדְרִיכֻהוּ I.e., they overtook them, and there is a similar expression in the Talmud, (Kethubos 60b) “He ran after him a parasang in the sand but did not overtake him” (אדרכיה).</text>
      <text title="as far as against Gibeah: ">Eastward of Gibeah (as the verse concludes).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="44">
      <text title="And there fell of Benjamin eighteen thousand men: ">In the field (cf. v. 31) during the battle.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="45">
      <text title="and they gleaned of them: ">Deathblow after deathblow, just as one gleans after the harvest.</text>
      <text title="five thousand men: ">This leads to a sum of twenty- three thousand men.</text>
      <text title="until Gidom: ">This is the name of a place.</text>
      <text title="and killed of them two thousand men: ">This amounts to the twenty-five thousand stated above (v. 35). Concerning the additional hundred written above, it was not explained where they fell.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="48">
      <text title="turned upon the children of Benjamin: ">That were in all the cities.</text>
      <text title="(destroying) from the city: ">They destroyed all the inhabitants of the cities, even the cattle, thus people are included in “destroying” since “ מְתֹם” is an expression of destruction. There is a difficulty concerning the whereabouts of a thousand since twenty-six thousand were numbered from the cities and from Gibeah seven (text amended) hundred (v. 15). However, here the count of the fallen is twenty-five thousand and one hundred (v. 35) plus the six hundred that escaped to the rock of Rimmon. But perhaps (amended) the (undermined) thousand fled to the cities and fell the following day when the children of Israel returned to the Benjamite cities to destroy the women and children (as is stated in this verse).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="21">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="לְהִפָּקֵד: ">That there should be missing.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="And (the children of Israel) reconsidered: ">They repented to plan for them a program of survival.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="four hundred virgin girls: ">They placed them over the openings of barrels of wine. The non- virgin would allow a fragrance to pass whereas the virgin would not allow a fragrance to pass.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="וְלֹא מָצְאוּ לָהֶם: ">(This) was not sufficient for them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="(There must be) an inheritance for the remnant: ">The territory of the tribe has remained empty. Propose a suggestion that the escaped remnant may beget children and occupy their portion so that there should not be blotted out a tribe from Israel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="הַשֶּׁמֶשׁ לִמְסִלָּה מִזְרָחָה: ">On the east side of the highway. Shiloh is to the north of Beth-el and to the south of Lebonah and to the east of the highway that goes from Beth-el to Shechem.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="to quarrel with us: ">to go against us in battle.</text>
      <text title="then we will say to them we took pity on them: ">We took pity on them because they do not know what to do, because we did not take for each man his wife in the war with Jabesh-gilead but only for four hundred of their men. And if you are concerned about your oath, (be assured that) you have no sin in this matter, because you did not give them your daughters (cf. above v. 1) that you should be guilty in this, (rather) peace will be with you, do not fear.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
</book>