<book>
  <chapter id="1">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="But he was not warmed: ">Our Rabbis concluded and said: “He who disgraces clothing will ultimately be deprived of their pleasures. Because David tore the skirt of Saul’s robe (Samuel I 24:5) consequently, they did not warm him” (Berachoth 62b). As David saw the angel of death standing in Jerusalem and his sword in his hand, his blood became cold from fear of him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="A virgin: ">her virginity warms her flesh.</text>
      <text title="A warmer: ">Heb. סכנת a warmer, and similarly “and he who chops wood is warmed (יסכן) by them” (Eccl. 10:9).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="Exalted himself: ">He exalted himself.</text>
      <text title="And fifty men: ">had their spleens removed and the soles of their feet were scraped.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="And his father had not angered him: ">His father never angered him. This episode teaches you that “he who refrains from rebuking his child brings him to his death.”</text>
      <text title="And he too was of very handsome appearance: ">Absalom about whom it is written (Samuel II 14:25) “And as Absalom there was none so handsome.” This caused them, [Absalom and Adoniahu], to be proud.</text>
      <text title="And she bore him: ">his mother.</text>
      <text title="After Absalom: ">This is to say that his mother reared him in the same spoiled manner that Absalom’s mother reared him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="With Joab the son of Zeruiah: ">Because he knew that David bore a grudge against him for having killed Abner, Amasa, and Absalom, and that he would eventually charge his son, who would reign in his place, to deal with him. Joab, therefore, preferred that this one, [Adoniahu] should reign through his help and so that Adoniahu should favor him.</text>
      <text title="And with Abiathar the priest: ">Because he was dismissed from the priesthood at the time when David was escaping from Jerusalem because of Absalom. When Abiathar consulted the Urim and Tumim and was unsuccessful, as it is said, (Samuel II 15:24) “And Abiathar went up.” And he was a descendent of Eli. And Abiathar knew that he would not serve in the days of Solomon, for it was said to Eli “And I will raise Me up a faithful priest and he shall walk before My anointed one” (Samuel I 2:35). Abiathar preferred [therefore,] that Adoniahu become king through his assistance.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="And Nathan the prophet: ">who prophesied to David that Solomon would reign, as it is said in (Chronicles I 22:9) “and Solomon shall be his name.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="And fatlings: ">[These are sheep and] oxen which have been fattened by forceful feeding.</text>
      <text title="The stone of Zoheleth: ">A huge stone with which the young men would test their strength to move or drag it. [Zoheleth is] an expression similar to moving water (זוחלין) or “those that move (זוחלי) on the dust” (Deut. 32:24). Targum Jonathan renders this word זוֹחֶלֶת a ‘lookout stone,’ upon which one could stand and look far into the distance.</text>
      <text title="En-Rogel: ">which was a well used by a clothes washer who would press the woolen clothes which he washed, with his feet, by stamping [on them].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="And his brother Solomon, he did not call: ">for he knew that the prophet had prophesied about him that he would reign [after David’s death].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And you shall save your life: ">and save your soul from the rivalry which will follow the death of the king, for your son will wish to reign as the Holy One, Blessed be He, promised him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="And I and my son shall be considered offenders: ">Instead they will always be lacking and restrained from any greatness.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="Did you say: ">The interrogative.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="For he went down on this day: ">The city was on higher ground and the אֶבֶן הַזוֹחֶלֶת was below in a valley.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="On my own mule: ">This will be a positive sign that he will reign and the beginning of his advancement to greatness since a commoner is forbidden to ride on the king’s horse.</text>
      <text title="To Gihon: ">Gihon and Shiloah are synonymous. From this is derived the custom not to anoint the kings except at the well, to symbolize thereby that his kingdom shall be endless as the waters of a well.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="And he shall anoint him: ">To anoint him between the lids of his eyes in the form of a crown.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="Amen: ">“Long live king Solomon.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="Than the throne of my lord king David: ">From this we may derive that a father does not feel envy when his son surpasses him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="38">
      <text title="And the archers and the slingers: ">The Targum renders this, the archers and the slingers. Our Sages however, maintain that this refers to the אוּרִים וְתֻּמִים.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="39">
      <text title="And Zadok the priest took the horn of oil: ">The special holy oil compounded by Moses in the desert.</text>
      <text title="From the tent: ">Since the Holy Ark was in Jerusalem which was known as the city of David, and the jug of oil of anointment was before it, both were, therefore, in Jerusalem, as we have learned in the Tractate Yoma (52b).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="40">
      <text title="The flutes: ">A flute also in old French.</text>
      <text title="And the earth was rent: ">Prophets [who] made use of exaggerations [in descriptions], as is common by most people.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="43">
      <text title="But our lord: ">Jonathan replied, “… at this moment my report is not of good tidings for you.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="50">
      <text title="And he rose up and took hold of the horns of the altar: ">which was in Gibeon. He said, Those put to death by Beth Din are buried in the graves of Beth Din. I shall die here, and be buried in the graves of my forefathers. Thus did Rabbi Tanhuma expound.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="2">
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="You also know what Joab the son of Zeruiah did to me: ">by showing them the letter which David had sent through Uriah.</text>
      <text title="And shed the blood of war in peace: ">Since they were at peace with him, they were not on guard against him.</text>
      <text title="And he put the blood of war upon his girdle that was about his loins: ">He had girded his sword, attached to his loins, not in the customary manner of those girding swords, and he went out to meet Amasa. He turned the opening downward so that it should easily fall out of the sheath to the ground as it says (Samuel II 20:8) “and he went out towards Amasa and it fell out.” As soon as it fell, Joab [nonchalantly] retrieved it, and held it ready in his hand. Amasa presumed he retrieved it solely to pick it up from the ground, and was not alert to guard himself against an attack from the sword which was in Joab’s hand.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="And do not let his hoary head go down to the grave in peace: ">Do not let him die a natural death [since this will minimize his worldly punishment] and cause him to fall into purgatory for torturous purification.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="Who cursed me with a grievous curse: ">[Others maintain] נִמְרֶצֶת means clear and unquestionable as (we find) in (Job 16:3): “what will bring clarity to you (ימריצך) ,” and (Job 6:25): “how clear (נמרצו) are right words,” the same as נִמְלְצוּ a derivation of the word מְלִיצָה, an interpretation or clarification.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="For you are a wise man: ">Turn your attention to find for him an iniquity justifying a death penalty in another matter.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="And his kingdom was firmly established: ">He was also master and ruler of all heavenly creatures and beings.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="to speak to him: ">to speak on his behalf; on behalf of Adoniahu.</text>
      <text title="for the king’s mother: ">Our Sages said, however, “the king’s mother” is a reference to Ruth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="… ask for him the kingdom also: ">From the moment a commoner uses the scepter of the king, that is the beginning of authority.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="… Who has established me: ">“… and Who has made me a house” a house of royalty as he had spoken through Nathan the prophet.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="Go to Anathoth to your own fields…: ">He was from there.</text>
      <text title="For you are deservant of death: ">Because you rebelled against the kingdom of my father when you were with Adoniahu to appoint him king without the knowledge of my father.</text>
      <text title="Because you did bear the Ark of the Lord God before David my father: ">as my father was escaping from before Absalom.</text>
      <text title="And because you were afflicted: ">with him in those very same afflictions, as it says (Samuel II 17:29) “for they said the people are hungry and weary and thirsty in the wilderness.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="Which He spoke concerning the house of Eli: ">[Scripture predicts the end of the house of Eli:] “And I will raise Me up a faithful priest” (Samuel I 2:35) or “And you shall see a rival in My habitation” (Samuel I 2:32). From the time of the destruction of Shilo, there was no house worthy of the service to the Holy One Blessed be He and now that the Temple will be built, the Holy One Blessed be He fulfilled His word to banish the children of Eli.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="And the tidings came to Joab: ">the report of David’s charge, that he had commanded to kill him, and he [also] knew that Solomon disliked him.</text>
      <text title="For Joab turned after Adoniahu, and after Absalom he did not turn: ">The end of the matter was [that Joab did not follow him], but he did seek to turn after him, but for the fact that he was fearful, because the vigor of David’s might was still present.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="And he said “No…”: ">Two punishments I will not accept upon myself. The curses that your father David cursed me at the death of Abner, “They shall fall upon the head of Joab,” let Solomon accept them upon himself, and afterward I will come out.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="Do as he said: ">I will accept the curses upon myself. Therefore, all these [curses] became attached to the offspring of David. Uzziah was a leper (Chronicles II 26:19), Assa leaned on a staff (Kings I 15:23), Jehoiakim fell by the sword (Jeremiah 22:19), and one who lacked bread was Zedekiah (Kings II 25:30).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="And he was buried in his own house in the wilderness: ">His home was ownerless and unrestricted as a wilderness for all the destitute and needy to use at their convenience.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="And do not go forth: ">in order that he be accessible to him and that he might find him guilty of a crime deserving of death.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="42">
      <text title="And forewarned you: ">Heb. ואעד, an expression referring to the legal warning given to the offender before committing the offense.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="43">
      <text title="And why have you nor kept the oath of the Lord: ">which I made you swear in the name of the Lord?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="46">
      <text title="And the kingdom was established in the hand of Solomon: ">that is to say, he was not punished for any of these deeds.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="3">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And Solomon became allied by marriage: ">as long as Shimei was alive he did not become allied to him in marriage. As a result, our Sages declare, a person should always live in the vicinity of his teacher where his influence and guidance are ever present.</text>
      <text title="Until he completed building: ">and afterward built a house for her.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="Only the people sacrificed in the high places: ">In the name of Heaven, each who so desired would build an altar at the top of his roof or in his yard [and offer his sacrifices there].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And Solomon loved the Lord, walking in the statutes of David his father: ">The first four years, as long as he did not begin to build the Temple. But from the time he began to build and he became allied in marriage to the daughter of Pharaoh this was no longer true. Consequently, the prophet declares “for this city has been to me as a provocation of my anger and of my fury from the day that they built it and until this day” (Jeremiah 32:31). Thus have we learned in Seder Olam (Chap. 15). We learn from this the passages are not written in chronological order.</text>
      <text title="Only he sacrificed… in the high places: ">The text has discussed his dishonor. Since he delayed the construction of the Temple four years.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="That was the great high place: ">That was the copper altar which Moses made in the desert and was instituted in Shilo. Shilo was destroyed in the days of Eli, and they came to Nob. Nob was destroyed in the days of Saul, and they came to Gibeon.</text>
      <text title="Upon that altar: ">in one day.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="And You have kept for him: ">an expression of authentication of his words as, “And the Lord your God shall keep for you the covenant” [means] You have authenticated your words to fulfill to him the kindness which You promised him through Nathan the prophet.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="A little child: ">He was twelve years old. And this is your figuring. And he called his name Jedidjah [Solomon] (Samuel II 12:25). At the same time Amnon violated Tamar, as it says “And it was after this, and Absalom had a sister, etc.” At the end of two years “And Absalom had sheepshearers, etc.,” and he killed Amnon. And Absalom fled and went to Geshur, and was there three years, so we have five years. And Absalom returned to Jerusalem, “and dwelt in Jerusalem two years” (Samuel II 14:28) so we have seven years in Solomon’s life. And he [Absalom] rebelled against his father and was killed. After this (Samuel II 21:1) “And there was famine in the days of David three years,” so we have ten. In the eleventh year he counted the Israelites and they scattered in all the land nine months (Samuel II 24:8). In the year of his death he instituted divisions [among the priests and Levites] as it says “In the fortieth year of David’s reign they were sought for” [Chronicles I 26:31, see Rashi there] so we have twelve years in the life of King Solomon.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="For who is able to judge this Your great people: ">Since they are many there are many transactions, and they come to be judged and I have no time to deliberate over their arguments. Another interpretation of “for who is able to judge this your great people” their decisions are very difficult to make. If a lawsuit comes before me and I take from one and give to the other unjustly, I shall be punished for it with capital punishment, as it says “And He takes the lives of those that steal from them” (Proverbs 22:23).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="And if you walk in My ways… I will lengthen your days: ">The riches and the honor for which I imposed no conditions in my Torah to give to the king, I shall grant you whether deserving or not. However, longevity and a hereditary monarchy I already imposed conditions in my Torah “that he shall not turn aside from the commandment that he may prolong his days in his kingdom, etc.” (Deut. 17:20) and that stipulation I shall not alter. “And if you will walk in My ways… then I will lengthen your days.” And likewise concerning the continuation of the monarchy to his descendants after him God said to him “And if you shall go before me… there shall not cease to be from you a man, etc.” (9:4, 5). Thus is it learned in Sifrei (Deut. 17:20) Rabbi Chanina the son of Gamliel says, “Behold he has said also riches also honor, etc.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="And Solomon awoke, and behold it was a dream: ">and behold he understood that his dream was true. He would hear a bird chirp and understand its language, a dog would bark and he would understand its language.</text>
      <text title="And he came to Jerusalem… and made a feast for all his servants: ">out of the gladness of his heart since he understood that his dream was true.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="But when I looked closely at him: ">I gave my complete attention to scrutinize him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="She is its mother: ">a divine voice which appeared and said ‘She is its mother.’</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="4">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="Was king over all Israel: ">For when they saw his wisdom they all rejoiced in his kingdom.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="Scribes: ">to write the chronicles of the king.</text>
      <text title="the recorder: ">[His duty was to remind the king] which judgment came before him first, that he might decide it first. So I heard.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="Was over the officers: ">He had twelve officers to supply the food of the king and his household.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="Was over the levy: ">which Solomon had raised on the Israelites, as it is said, “And king Solomon raised a levy” (below 5:27).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="Who provided victuals for the king: ">all his meals, and the food of the numerous horses and all the needs of his expenditures.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="The region of Dor: ">Heb. נפתדאר, the region of Dor.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="The region of Argob: ">He was appointed over them to collect the levy of the king, because the rules of the monarchy dictate that his expenditures should be collected from the people, as it is said in the rules of the monarchy in the book of Samuel I (8:11).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="And one officer that was in the land: ">There is a difference of opinion between Rav and Shmuel. One says, [He was the] one who was appointed over all of them. This was Azariahu the son of Nathan, who was mentioned previously in verse 5, and one says, [To provide the victuals of the king] for the thirteenth month of a Jewish leap year.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="5">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="Fat: ">Fattened in the stall.</text>
      <text title="The pastures: ">On the grass.</text>
      <text title="And fatted fowl: ">There are amongst our Sages those who say these were roosters which were fattened [forcefully].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="forty thousand stalls of horses: ">In Chron. II 9:25 it says four thousand [stalls of horses whereas here forty thousand are mentioned]. Our Sages explained there were forty thousand stalls and in each there were four thousand partitions, or there were four thousand stalls and in each there were forty thousand partitions.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="They lacked nothing: ">Even summer fruits and vegetables, as cucumbers in the winter.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="And the barley and the straw: ">These officers [were obligated] not only to provide the necessary food but also to deliver it to the place where the king would be.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="Was greater than the wisdom of all the children of the east: ">What was the wisdom of the children of the east? They were learned in astronomy, as it is stated in the Pesikta of Para Adumah, and all of this chapter is expounded there according to its ordinary sense.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="And he was wiser than all men: ">As its ordinary sense.</text>
      <text title="Ethan, Heman, and Chalcol, and Darda: ">They were all brothers, the sons of Zerach the son of Yehuda as it says (Chron. I 2:6), “And the children of Zerach were Zimri and Ethan.”</text>
      <text title="The sons of Mahol: ">They knew how to compose hymns which are said in dancing. They were songs which the Levites said on their platform in the בֵּיתהַמִקְדָשׁ, hymns which they composed in the book of Psalms. The Medrash Agada in the Pesikta has another interpretation: הָאָדָם מִכָּל this is a reference to אָדָם הָרִאשׁוֹן אֵיתָן הָאֶזְרָחִי this is אַבְרָהָם. הֵימָן this is משה, וְכַלְכֹּל this is יוֹסֵף. וְדַרְדַע this is the generation of the wilderness [known as the דור דעה]. מָחוֹל that they were forgiven for the act of the golden calf.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="Three thousand proverbs: ">Three parabolical studies. It is written three times “The proverbs of Solomon” in the book of Proverbs.</text>
      <text title="And his songs were five: ">These three, The Song of Songs and Ecclesiastes.</text>
      <text title="And a thousand: ">in each it was worthy of studying. And in the Medrash Aggada [we find Solomon’s great wisdom enabled him] to say three thousand allegories in each sentence of the Torah, and in each of the allegories one thousand and five reasons.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="And he spoke of trees: ">which cure is derived from each tree, and that particular wood would be best for that type of building and to plant [a certain tree] in that type of earth. And also of the beasts, what is its cure and the vital elements [necessary] for its upbringing and development and its food. The Midrash Aggada [has another explanation]: Why did God see fit that a ‘metzora’ become clean with the tallest of the tall trees, as the cedar, and the shortest of the short trees? And also of the beasts and the fowl. Why did God see fit that this one, should become permissible by severing one, either the esophagus or the trachea, and this one, the beast, by severing both the esophagus and the trachea, and fish and grasshoppers with neither.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="He could not build a house: ">He was not permitted because of the wars, as the Torah states clearly (Deut. 12:10): “And He will give you rest from all your enemies round about” and afterwards, “Then it shall come to pass that the place [which the Lord your God shall choose etc.] even unto His habitation shall you seek etc.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="Like the Zidonians: ">The Zidonians were neighboring with the forest of Lebanon on one side and part of the kingdom of Hiram.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="I will make them into rafts: ">The prophet Ezra calls them רַפְסוֹדוֹת, in Chronicles [II 2:15]. And in German they are called floss, floats, and in old French res, similar to rafts. They would tie the fallen trees together and float them on the water and conduct them as ships are conducted.</text>
      <text title="To the place that you shall send me: ">That you shall send a messenger to inform me to bring them. there</text>
      <text title="And will separate them there: ">As their binding is untied and they are taken from the water to the beach, each and every log separately, that is called נִיפּוּץ. Any whole object when it is taken apart, that is called נִיפּוּץ, depced in old French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="Food for his household: ">Heb. מכלת, an expression from the word מַאֲכָל, food.</text>
      <text title="beaten oil: ">This oil was pure because the olives were not ground in a mill but rather crushed with a mortar, and this process does not stir up as much dregs as those which are ground.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="And the levy was thirty thousand men: ">which amounted to the wages of thirty thousand men.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="Ten thousand a month alternately: ">When the thousand men were in Lebanon in Tishrei and the twenty thousand men were at home, in Marcheshvan the second ten thousand would alternate and go out to Lebanon and these would return to their homes. And in the month of Kislev the third group of ten thousand go out, and they would go out to Lebanon, and these second ones would return to their homes. And in the month of Teveth the first ones go out and return to Lebanon, and thus they return again and again. So it is found that each group of ten thousand amongst them would be one month in Lebanon and two months at home.</text>
      <text title="And Adoniram was over the levy: ">to collect the levy.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="Seventy thousand that bore burdens: ">to bring the stones from the mountains to the city, and the eighty thousand men were the ones who hewed them in the mountains. There is altogether one hundred fifty thousand men. And they were all proselytes who were drawn and attracted to the Jewish people, that converted because of Solomon’s greatness and hospitality. And it is likewise written in Chronicles II (2: 16) “And Solomon numbered all the strangers that were in the land of Israel… and they were found a hundred and fifty thousand. And he set seventy thousand…”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="The chief officers: ">These were the oppressors and overseers over those who did the work.</text>
      <text title="Three thousand and three hundred: ">And in Chronicles II (2:1) it says three thousand and six hundred. It is, therefore, my opinion that the three thousand three hundred men were in charge of one hundred fifty thousand men, so that each one was in charge of forty five and some odd men, and the three hundred men who were added in Chronicles were in charge of all of them, so that each of these three hundred men was in charge of five hundred and some odd men. And you shall know the evidence in support of my opinion that there are two other passages on this subject, and they contradict one another. For it says on this topic in this book of Kings I (9:23) “These were the chief officers that were over Solomon’s work, five hundred and fifty,” and in the book of Chronicles II (8:10) it says “two hundred and fifty.” There are, therefore, altogether, four verses contradicting one another. But we may explain it thus. Those that are mentioned in the latter verses in I Kings 9:23 and in Chronicles II (8:10), were in charge of all of them. And it is a fact that Solomon had employed these proselytes to be bearers of burdens and to hew stones in the mountains. And, in addition, he had the remaining workers for the store cities which he also built, who were native born Jews. Because these passages are stated there in Chronicles II which discusses the store-cities. And to sum it up then, in the book of Kings he counted the proselyte officers in two separate totals. First, he counted the three thousand three hundred men, the officers who were in charge of forty-five men each, separately. And in (9:23) he combined the three hundred superior officers, who were in charge of these three thousand three hundred men, with the two hundred and fifty men who were in charge of the builders of the store-cities, and totaled together five hundred and fifty officers. And, on the other hand, in Chronicles II he counted all the proselyte officers, the major and minor ones, together, three thousand six hundred men, and they were all proselytes. And the officers in charge of the workers in the store-cities, who were Jews, totaling two hundred and fifty men, he counted separately.</text>
      <text title="Who bore rule over the people that wrought in the work: ">Who bore rule over the people that did the work.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="And they quarried: ">the stones from the mountains. This is an expression of uprooting.</text>
      <text title="Great stones, heavy stones: ">Heb. יקרות, heavy.</text>
      <text title="Hewn stone: ">They were carved and chiseled [precisely to the required measurement]. And if you ask it has already been stated (6:7) “There was neither hammer nor axe nor any tool of iron heard in the house, while it was in building.” How then were the stones cut to a specific size? The explanation is, that although no tool of iron was heard in the house, while it was in building, but he would chisel the stones while still on the outside, and then bring them in and build from the inside. Thus is this explained in the Tractate Sota (48b).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="And they did hew them: ">in the mountains.</text>
      <text title="And the Gebalites: ">a nation whose name was Gebal. And they were skilled in the art of chiseling stones and building. As it is stated in reference to the wise men of Tyre (Ezek. 27:9) “The elders of Cebal and the wise men thereof, were in you your calkers.”</text>
      <text title="And they prepared: ">An expression of designation.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="6">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="In the month of Ziv: ">This is Iyar. The word Ziv means bloom. [It is called Ziv] because [in that month] there is the bloom of the trees. And Targum Jonathan translated this similarly ‘the bloom of the buds.’</text>
      <text title="Which is the second month: ">[Iyar is considered the second month] when numbering the months, since Nissan is the beginning of the year in [the numbering of] the months.</text>
      <text title="Of Solomon’s reign: ">“the fourth year.” [It was] the fourth [year] of Solomon’s reign. And so does he also state in Chronicles II (3:2) “And he began to build in the second month in the fourth year of his reign.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="Sixty cubits: ">[This included] the Temple [proper] and the Holy of Holies together.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And the porch before: ">before the Temple, in it’s entranceway.</text>
      <text title="The length thereof before the breadth of the house: ">The length of the porch was along the width of the Temple [and extended] from the north to the south. All larger [measurements] are called the length, and the lesser [measurements] are called the width. Since in the Temple proper the measurement from the east to the west was greater, that was called the length, and in the porch that the measurement from the north to the south was the larger, therein was called the length from the north to the south, and from the east to the west therein was called the width.</text>
      <text title="Before the house: ">[The porch was] in front of the house [of the Temple], on the eastern side [and was] on the outside.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="Broad within and narrow without: ">Our Sages explained שְּׁקוּפִים as an expression of looking and an opening and an observation. These windows were constructed so that they were open on the outside and closed (אֲטוּמִים) on the inside. [The opening was wider on the outside] and narrow on the inside. This was not in the usual manner of all other windows which are made [expressly] for illumination.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="A chamber: ">Appentis in French, a projecting gallery. This chamber had three names, יָצִיעַ a wing or extension of the building תָּא, a compartment, צֶלָע a side chamber. Thus is this explained in Baba Bathra 61a.</text>
      <text title="Against the walls of the house round about: ">That is to say against the Temple and the house of the Holy of Holies, which is [synonymous with] the דְבִיר, he made chambers on the outside at the south, and at the west and the north. And the end of the sentence is an explanation of the beginning. And he built “on” the wall of the house, meaning “near” the wall of the house, a chamber round about. How did he make it? Against the walls of the house, that is, the Temple and the Holy of Holies, he made chambers.</text>
      <text title="He made: ">Heb. ויעש, like עשה, “he made.” And likewise, “He was (ויהי) my salvation” (Exodus 15:2), like, “He was (היה) my salvation.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="The nethermost chamber: ">On each side [of the Temple] the chambers were [built in] three [tiers], one on the other. And the measurement of its length is not stated here, [only its width]. And in the Tractate Midoth (4:3) we learned [as follows]: There were thirty-eight chambers [in all], fifteen in the north, five on top of five, and five [more] on top of them, and the same [number] in the south. And eight [more were] in the west, three on top of three and two [more] on top of them. The nethermost [chamber] was five [cubits wide] and the middle ones were six [cubits], and the top ones seven. Why [was this difference]? For he made rebatements in [the wall] of the house round about on the outside. The height of the chamber was five cubits, and as the height of the wall of the Temple [proper] reached five cubits he reduced its thickness and recessed it one cubit inward [on the outside], and on that recess he placed the ends of the beams of the roof at the top of the chamber which served as the floor of the middle one. And as the wall reached ten [cubits] he again recessed it one cubit [in order] to place the ends of the beams of the roof of the middle chamber which served as the floor of the upper chamber. We [thus] find the middle one is broader than the lower one by one cubit, and the upper one is broader than the middle one by one cubit.</text>
      <text title="That the beams should not have hold in the walls of the house: ">In order not to join the ends of the beams to the walls through perforations in the walls of the house, since this causes the deterioration of the wall and is [also] not beautiful, architecturally.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="When it was in building, of stone finished at the quarry: ">as it was removed from the mountain, through the worm שָּׁמִיר [which cuts through stones]. Exactly as it came from there, they set it into the wall of the structure, and they did not chisel it further with any metal tools. And the hewn stones which are mentioned above [in 5:31, indicating that the stones were cut to some degree], is a controversy discussed in the Tractate Sota (48b).</text>
      <text title="And hammers: ">Delutta, a chisel, in the Russian language.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="The door of the lowest chamber was in the right side of the house: ">Jonathan rendered this word תִּיכוֹנָה as “the lowest,” not תִּיכוֹנָה [which is] between the upper and lower ones [as is usually translated]. Because the five chambers on the southern side had one opening to the outside which was in the lowest story. And this [second usage of the word תִּיכוֹנָה in this same verse] “and with winding stairs they went up into the middle (תִּיכוֹנָה) chamber,” Jonathan rendered תִּיכוֹנָה; “the middle” because these chambers were not opened to the outside. There were three openings to each [of the chambers]. Thus is this taught in the Tractate Midos (4: 3), “One was to the chamber on the right and one was to the chamber on the left and one to the chamber above.” And the prophet teaches us here that [only] one of the lower [chambers] on the southern side had an opening to the outside and [only] through that opening can we enter all of the chambers on all sides. And the “middle chamber” of the verse, הַצֵלָע הַתִּיכוֹנָה, is not the middle one between the upper and the lower, but the middle one of the five chambers on the southern side which had an opening to the outside in the lowest story. And this is the meaning of “and with winding stairs they went up” עַל הַתִּיכוֹנָה“into the middle chamber” which was above it, signifying that צֵלָע הַתִּיכוֹנָה was below.</text>
      <text title="With winding stairs: ">Jonathan rendered the word לוּל, a winding staircase, and that is called in our language vis (o.f.) and in German Vindelstein, and the commonly used name is schvindel stieg, and that is a structure of stone pillars made in the form of stairs, and he who goes on them is likened to one spiraling around a column and ascending on it several cubits high without inclining the steps as [would be necessary] by an ordinary ladder because its spiral serves as its incline.</text>
      <text title="into the third: ">Heb. שְּׁלִישִׁים, like שְּׁלִישִׁיִּים.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="And he covered: ">An expression of covering of the ceiling.</text>
      <text title="With panelling and joined planks of cedar: ">[There were] two ceilings. [The] one made for beauty was below, and [the] one of planks of cedar was above. That of panelling was the lower one. And Jonathan rendered גֵּבִים as הַנְתּוּכִין, but I do not know what they are. And I did hear in the name of Rabbi Menachem… that they are boards woven beautifully in the form of a design, and it is called in our language (o.f.) celed and in German it [is called] gehimmelt and that is an expression of [something] heavenly [in appearance or in height] as the highest part of the beam. And I say they are hollowed bricks, and they are like half a round reed, which are used as coverings for houses [in German, dekziegel].</text>
      <text title="panelling: ">In Aramaic, vaulted canes.</text>
      <text title="joined planks: ">Planks of cedar were laid over the panels, to provide a footing for when they would go to oversee the maintenance of the house [Temple]. Similarly, Jonathan renders, “and above them [the panels] were rows of joined planks made of cedars beams.” The word רכפת [in the Targum] denotes adjacency [as the planks were adjoining to each other]. Elsewhere (II Sam. 22:12) it says, “thick clouds of the sky” for which the Targum renders: “a cluster of light clouds” [which gave the appearance of thick clouds].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="Five cubits high: ">[was the height] of each chamber. Therefore their [total] height of the three stories was fifteen cubits besides the thickness of the ceiling.</text>
      <text title="And he covered the house: ">That was the upper covering of the roof, and the covering mentioned above (6:9) that was the ceiling of the upper story.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="Within with boards of cedar: ">[He placed the] boards of cedar against the stone wall in order to coat it with gold, as he says below (6: 21) “And Solomon overlaid the house from within with pure gold,” and it is impossible to coat the gold on top of the stones [directly], except with wood and nails.</text>
      <text title="The joists of the ceiling: ">The boards of the attic.</text>
      <text title="The floor of the house: ">[He covered] the entire floor.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="And he built the twenty cubits at the end of the house: ">The twenty cubits which were at the end of the Temple and beyond, and those twenty cubits which were at the end of the house, they are the house containing the Ark cover [that is, the Holiest of Holies].</text>
      <text title="Unto the joists: ">Until the ceiling did he make the walls of cedar to cover the wall of stone in order to coat it [with] gold.</text>
      <text title="And he built it: ">Those [very] twenty cubits.</text>
      <text title="Within for a sanctuary: ">Inward of the partition [called] ‘Amma Traksin’ which separated between the [area of] forty [cubits] and that of twenty. And [it was] that partition which is called ‘Dvir.’</text>
      <text title="For the Holy of Holies: ">He set aside those twenty cubits.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="The Temple before: ">In front of the partition towards the outside.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="And the cedar of the house within was carved with knobs: ">This means: and those boards of cedar which he made for the house within to cover the walls of stone, were carved with figured carvings and forms of fragments resembling knobs, פְּקָעִים lmosjjls in (o. f.).</text>
      <text title="And open flowers: ">Jonathan rendered this: and cords and flowers in the form of chains.</text>
      <text title="Open: ">פְּטוּרֵי is an expression of cords in the language of the Talmud, like “as the rope (כפיטורי) through the loophole” (Moed Katan 29a).</text>
      <text title="Flowers: ">צִצִים is an expression of flowers, like “and it bloomed blossoms (ויצץ ציץ)” (Deut. 17:23). [Translated together it means] cords and blossoms. But Menachem [in establishing the roots of the words], related this word פְּטוּרִי to ‘open,’ maintaining it is of biblical derivation, an expression of “the opening of (פטר) the womb” (Exodus 13: 15) and as “they open (יפטירו) the lip” (Psalms 22:8).</text>
      <text title="All was cedar there was no stone seen: ">[The Targum translates:] All of the house was covered with boards of cedar, no stone was seen.</text>
      <text title="Carved with knobs: ">Jonathan rendered [this:] and engraved was a resemblance of eggs.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="And the Sanctuary in the midst of the house: ">The partition called ‘Amma Traksin.’</text>
      <text title="To set: ">Heb. לתתן, like לָתֵת.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="And within the Sanctuary: ">[Literally, before the partition, that is] within that partition [was] an area of twenty [cubits] long and twenty [cubits] wide.</text>
      <text title="And twenty cubits its height: ">That is to say, [according to literal translation,] the height of the room of the Holy of Holies was lower than that of the Temple.</text>
      <text title="and he overlaid it: ">The ‘Dvir,’ which is the partition.</text>
      <text title="Pure gold: ">Our Sages explained (Yoma 45a) this [word סגור, which means closed, to describe gold, as follows:] at the time this type of gold was opened to be sold, all other stores [selling gold] were closed, because of their comparatively inferior quality. But Jonathan rendered this: good gold. He [most likely,] meant to translate [the word סָגוּר, closed, as follows]: he who has any of this gold ‘locks’ it away for himself.</text>
      <text title="And he covered the altar with cedar: ">That is the golden altar [used for the burning] of incense, but I am perplexed, why was that of Moses hidden?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="The house: ">[This is] the house of the Holy of Holies.</text>
      <text title="And he barred: ">Heb. ויעבר, an expression of [attaching] bolts.</text>
      <text title="With chains: ">Heb. בְּרַתּוֹקוֹת [is translated as] chains.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="And the whole house: ">All of the entire Temple.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="Olive wood: ">olive wood</text>
      <text title="Ten cubits its height: ">And their legs were standing on the ground. One [was] on the north [side] of the Ark and one on the south [side, their wings] covering the Ark and its staffs. The length of the wings covered part of the [width of the] staffs, since the length of the Ark was set to the width of the house and its staffs were protruding at the entrance of the Sanctuary into the curtain which was before the entrance. And the staffs were set at the ends of the length [sides] of the Ark in order that two Levites should be able to enter between them when they were carrying it in the desert.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="Ten cubits were from the uttermost part of its one wing to the uttermost part of its other wing: ">As they are spread. Consequently, the wings of both cherubs, which touched one another, filled the entire space of twenty cubits [the width of the Sanctuary]. And [since] the bodies of the cherubim have not been included in the measurement, [although they, too, occupied part of the twenty cubits, this proves that] it stood by [means of] a miracle.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="And the wing of the one touched the wall: ">[The] north [wall].</text>
      <text title="And the wing of the other Cherub touched: ">The southern wall. They covered the Ark and its staffs.</text>
      <text title="And their wings in the midst of the house: ">the ends of the wings which were towards the center of the house.</text>
      <text title="Touched one another: ">Since the entire space of the house was twenty.</text>
      <text title="And all the walls of the house: ">The wooden walls.</text>
      <text title="He surrounded with figures: ">surrounded with drawings.</text>
      <text title="Carved figures of cherubim: ">Engraved forms of cherubim, and palm trees, and cords, and flowers.</text>
      <text title="From within and for the one without: ">From the house of the ark cover [which is the Holy of Holies,] the one within, and to the Temple, the one without.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="And the floor of the house: ">the entire floor.</text>
      <text title="For the one within and for the one without: ">For the house of the ark cover.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="Olive-wood: ">Heb. עצי שמן, literally wood of oil, meaning olive-wood.</text>
      <text title="The lintel: ">The אֵילֵי of the entrance are the doorposts from this side and the other. They were made round, similar to וְאֵילַמָיו אֵילָיו אֵילִים (Ezekiel 40:10, 9, 21). (Other editions have וְאֵלוֹן אֵלָה, [a type of tree which is tall and curved,] and likewise in all of the structure of Ezekiel (Ezekiel 40) the doorposts of the entrance are called אֵילִים.</text>
      <text title="Sideposts were of five parts: ">The threshold is one, and the sideposts on both sides are two, [together] there are three, and the lintel which is on it was made in two [parts]. Thus have I heard. But I say, מְזוּזוֹתחֲמִשִׁית [means] (there were) five sides to each of the door posts and it was not four-sided. [These posts were in the shape of a pentagon rather than rectangularRabeinu Yashaya.] And he is neither speaking about the threshold nor the lintel, since we do not find the threshold or the lintel called אֵילִים.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="And he spread upon the cherubim: ">He spread the gold in thin sheets [to sink them] into the engraved forms, so that it be sunken into the engraved places and protrude on the protrusions, [and] so that the gold shall not [cover and thereby] destroy the figures, and the figures [engraved] in the wood shall be [clearly] seen in the gold.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="Of four parts: ">The sideposts and frame of the Temple were square and so also did Jonathan translate ‘from their four sides’ [they were] squared.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="And two doors: ">Each [of the doors] was as [large as] half the width of the entrance.</text>
      <text title="The two leaves of the one door: ">Jonathan translated this: [each door had] two hinges, an upper hinge and a lower hinge.</text>
      <text title="Folding: ">Heb. גלילים, oval.</text>
      <text title="And the two leaves: ">Also this word קְלָעִים is translated hinges like צְלָעִים. This expression קְלָעִים I maintain, is of Aramaic derivation [and is] an expression meaning entering, since the hinge enters into the cavity of the threshold.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="And he carved [thereon] cherubim: ">On the doors [of the Temple].</text>
      <text title="Fitted upon the carved work: ">The gold was [set] with exacting care on the carved forms. It was recessed in the place of its engraving, and [it was raised in the place it was protruding, so that the forms engraved in the wood] be recognized in the gold.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="The inner court: ">[This is the courtyard of the priests and the courtyard of the Israelites, and this was located] before the porch, and he calls it “the inner court” because it was [further] inward than the court of women. (We do not find written [anywhere] in the biblical text [the word עֶזְרַת as a reference to the various courts] except in the Mishna [in Midos]).</text>
      <text title="And a row of cut cedar beams: ">A tier of [cut] beams [on three tiers of hewn stone]. He made the wall [in this manner].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="In the fourth year: ">Of King Solomon’s [reign].</text>
      <text title="The foundation of the house of the Lord was laid: ">Its foundation was begun.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="38">
      <text title="In the month of Bul: ">This is known [today] as Marcheshvan. [It is a period when] the grass decays (בָּלֶה) [in the field] and when cattle is given mixed fodder from what is in the house, from the expression “and he gave fodder (וַיָבָל) [to the donkeys]” (Judges 19:21).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="7">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And Solomon built his house thirteen years: ">because in work [of the] Most High he hurried, and in his own way he was sluggish. The text tells of his praiseworthiness.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="The house of the forest of Lebanon: ">Jonathan, [therefore,] translated [this:] a house for the cooling of kings. (The cedar pillars [are those] that stood along the length of the one hundred cubits… Each row was arranged along the length of the one hundred [cubits]. [Therefore,] from the first row until the fourth row [was] fifty cubits, which was the width of the house. An annotation of the author of ‘The Temple Structure.’)</text>
      <text title="And cut beams of cedar: ">The beams of cedar were [arranged] along the length of the house. [There was] a row of pillars on the ground and the cut beams [were placed] from pillar to pillar. (And the second row of pillars was in front of the first row [of pillars] and [facing] the width of the house. And so it was with all four rows. And the covering of the boards [on the beams was to serve] as the floor [of the upper story] of the house, [which was] from one row to the next row on the cut beams. And these pillars were made with many entrances like a porch, and the cut beams were as a lintel which is on the doorposts. And these cut beams were also in order to stand the walls on them; which are the צְלָעוֹת mentioned in the text. And the reason that he said “the walls on the pillars” and did not say, ‘on the cut beams’ because the pillars are the main, since the house rests upon them. And the cut beams were only to strengthen and join one pillar to the other so that the dwelling should be one. And these beams were [flat] on their sides they were not vertical. And when he says “on the pillars” he means to say: on the cut beams which are on the pillars, but it was not called by its own name because of the pillars. It is also possible that the cut beams did not rise above the pillars, since they were not lying on the top but were placed at the top of the pillars and level with the top (but not as a lintel which overlooks the doorposts, but rather as a long peg which joins two pillars. That is, the pillars extended through the beams. And that which he said “and the cut beams on the pillars” [does not mean above the pillars but] on the top part of the pillars. [Now] we find, that that which is on the cut beams is [indeed] on the pillars. Up until here is the commentary of the author of ‘The Temple Structure’).</text>
      <text title="And it was covered with cedar: ">[There was] a ceiling over it from above.</text>
      <text title="On the walls: ">The upper partitions which were on the cut beams. [There were] four partitions next to each other in the width and extended along the length of the house. Each had openings and windows, for this was a summer home made for air. And on those partitions [was] the covering of the ceiling. The ceiling was of forty-five boards, three rows of boards [for the three spaces] [formed by] the four rows of pillars, fifteen boards to each row of the house, [that is, in each space fifteen of them were placed]. Their length was along the width of each row and their width was along the length of the house, one next to the other.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="And there were windows in three rows: ">He also made another covering near the three rows of boards and the three rows of lintels, because the width of fifteen boards did not cover the house in all its length which was one hundred cubits. And he, [therefore,] made near it to cover the house, a covering of small boards placed on small beams which were left (should read ‘placed’) from one row of long cut beams to the other. [There were then,] three small beams one next to the other (should read ‘at the end of the other’) and lintels on both their sides similar to a lintel against which the door strikes. And of those lintels the ends of the small boards were placed, the length of the small boards facing the width of the larger boards which he put there at first.</text>
      <text title="And each window was opposite the other window: ">The ends of the boards of this lintel were opposite the ends of the boards of this lintel.</text>
      <text title="Window: ">The word מֶחֱזֶה is an expression of ‘an edge,’ and Menachem [also] explained it thus and related it to “unto their desired haven (מחוז חפצם)” (Psalms 8:30). And every חָזִית which is in the language of the Mishna is translated thus, as in the order of the priestly function at the daily sacrifice, (Tamid 2:4), and also “he should made a ledge (חָזִית) from the outside” in the chapter of ‘The Partners’ in Baba Bathra (2a). [And as proof this is not a window we see that] Jonathan, too, rendered this: ‘a projection opposite a projection,’ but שְׁקוּפִים אֲטוּמִים (above 6:4), and likewise רְבוּעִים שֶּׁקֶף he translated them all ‘beams.’</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="And all the entrances and posts: ">[They were many] because, generally, a king’s summer home is made with many entrances because of the air [which could enter thereby,] and it was therefore called ‘a forest house’ because it was like a forest [with many wooden posts].</text>
      <text title="Were square also the window: ">Jonathan translated [this:] ‘square and covered the beams’ [meaning] the entrances were covered with thin boards, [and] they were square as other entrances of houses, and they were not made a rounded arch similar to the entrance of a great hall.</text>
      <text title="And each window was opposite: ">And the front of the edge was put facing the other edge. The top of the board [was] towards the top of the other board three times in each board, and I do not know how [this was].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="And the porch of pillars: ">He made a porch before these pillars as an entrance to the house. Its length was fifty cubits along the width of the house, which was also fifty cubits, and thirty cubits its width before the extent of the length of the house, only that the longer measurement is always called the length and the shorter one is called the width.</text>
      <text title="And a porch before them: ">[In addition] he made a high porch around the entire house.</text>
      <text title="And pillars and thick beams before them: ">And on the cut beams of cedar which were no lower pillars he erected on (should read ‘still’) more pillars and joists from pillar to pillar the pillars to connect walls from one to the other, and the joists to cover the ceiling. עב is a joist, as we learn, “And the עֻבִּים, these are the joists.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="And a porch for the throne: ">[Jonathan renders:] And a porch to set the throne of judgment to judge there, he made a vestibule to the house of judgment there.</text>
      <text title="And it was covered with cedar: ">The earth of the floor was covered with cedar.</text>
      <text title="From one side of the floor: ">Jonathan rendered [this] ‘from foundation to foundation’ [meaning,] from the base of this wall and until the base of this other wall [which was opposite. The entire floor was covered.]</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="And his house where he might dwell: ">[Referring to] a complete residence to both eat and sleep there.</text>
      <text title="Within the porch: ">[This house was situated] inward from the porch of the house of the forest of Lebanon.</text>
      <text title="And the house which he would make: ">He planned to make a house for the daughter of Pharaoh.</text>
      <text title="Like this porch: ">Like the work of this porch [whose floors were of cedar].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="All these were of precious stones: ">All of these [structures, the] stones [used for them] were made heavy.</text>
      <text title="According to the measures of hewn stone: ">according to the measures of hewn ‘stone,’ [meaning,] there was one [accepted] measurements for hewn stone in that country.</text>
      <text title="And from the foundation up to the coping: ">This building was made in the height of hewn stones from the foundation until the highest beam.</text>
      <text title="And from the foundation: ">Heb. וממסד, from the expression יְסוֹד, a foundation.</text>
      <text title="The coping: ">The highest beam, as “My right hand had spanned (טפחה) the heavens” (Isaiah 48:13).</text>
      <text title="And from the outside: ">On the outside, the entire length of the walls were [made of] these stones until the great court.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="And the foundation was of great stones: ">And the foundation which was in the ground was of stones greater than the measurement of hewn stones.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="And above were precious stones: ">And above the stones used for the foundation were precious stones, [hewn to precise measurement,] until the coping as he mentioned above.</text>
      <text title="And cedars: ">[Jonathan renders:] ‘and he covered it with boards of cedar’ as [Scripture] said before (7:7), “and it was covered with cedar.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="Was of three rows of hewn stones: ">The wall [around the great court] was made of three tiers of [hewn] stone and one tier of [cut cedar] wood on them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="A coppersmith: ">Heb. חרש, [the common word for which is] אוּמָן.</text>
      <text title="And he was filled with the wisdom and understanding and skill: ">[These are] the three tools with which the universe was created, as it is stated, “[The Lord] by wisdom founded the earth, by understanding He established the heavens, by His knowledge the depths were broken up” (Proverbs 3:19). With these same three the Temple was built.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="The two pillars: ">Which he placed on the porch, [and which were called by the names] Jachin and Boaz.</text>
      <text title="Eighteen cubits was the height of each pillar: ">And in Chronicles II (3: 15) he says their height was thirty-five cubits? [That was because] he cast both [together] as one. [This should have totaled thirty-six cubits together,] but I say the one cubit which [was missing] was because there was one half a cubit at the top of each [pillar] which was not like the work of the rest of the pillar. [Omitting that top one half cubit of each pillar leaves a length of seventeen and one half cubits which together is thirty five cubits. The tops of the pillars were beautifully decorated,] as it is said further on in this subject (7:22), “And on the top of the pillars was lily work.”</text>
      <text title="And a line of twelve cubits did compass it… the other pillar: ">This teaches us that it was four cubits by four cubits in diameter, because every circumference of three hand breadths has a diameter of one hand breadth [that is, the diameter is approximately one third the circumference]. And its thickness was four fingers and it was hollow; thus is this explained at the end of the book of Jeremiah (52:21). And this is an abbreviated verse [because] he disclosed the length of one pillar and the length of the second must be learned from it, and he disclosed the circumference of the second, and the first must be learned from it. And Jonathan, too, [agreed that both pillars measured the same, and] translated thus, ‘and a strung line of twelve cubits did compass it, and so the other pillar.’</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="And two chapiters: ">Pomels in O.F apple shaped knobs.</text>
      <text title="Molten: ">Tresjited in 0.F.</text>
      <text title="Five cubits was the height of the one chapiter: ">And at the end of this book [of Kings] (II 25:17) he says [that each was] three cubits high? [Our Sages, too, were concerned with this apparent inconsistency,] and we learned [in the beraisa of Forty-Nine Measurements] two cubits of the lower part of the chapiters were similar to the pillar because there were no designs in them, and the three upper cubits [which] were extended beyond [the pillars] were surrounded with designs, as it is said (7:17) “nets of checker work” they were surrounded by the likes of the branches of a palm tree, and I say, [therefore,] he did not count those two lower cubits at the end of the book because they were similar to the pillar and the pillar was inserted into the chapiter two cubits [in depth].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="Nets of checker-work: ">The nets which they had were similar to a type of head covering [or cap] which is called cofea (in O.F.).</text>
      <text title="Checker-work: ">Heb. מעשה שבכה. They were encompassed by forms of branches of a palm tree, as in Job (18:8) “and he walks upon a snare (שבכה).” [These branches were designed like meshwork,] and the wreaths [which were braided and twisted together] as chain work.</text>
      <text title="Seven for the one chapiter: ">There were seven branches in each encircling design for each checker-work.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="And two rows: ">Of pomegranates and of brass. The pomegranates were inserted into the chain work which encircled the chapiters, thus is this explained in Chronicles II (3:16) and in the Mishnah of The Forty-Nine Measurements.</text>
      <text title="To cover the chapiters that were upon the top, with pomegranates: ">[Literally, ‘that were upon the top of the pomegranates’ but] this verse is in a disarranged order. [It should read as follows, that] ‘the pomegranates should cover the chapiters which were on the top.’ And thus were the chapiters made according to the order of the apparent translation of the verses. Each one was in the form of two bowls. The receptacle of the lower bowl was facing upward and it is called גוּלָה, a bowl, as it is said in this subject (7:41) וְגוּלֹתהַכֹּתָרוֹת, and Jonathan rendered this ‘and the bowls of the chapiters.’ The upper bowl was inverted on the lower one, its receptacle was facing downward, and this was שְׂבָכָה, a net, as it is said in this subject (7:41), “and the two net- works to cover the two bowls of the chapiters.” It is, [therefore,] found that in the place of attachment it is wide, and it slopes going upward and [then] slopes going downward, and this [place of attachment] is called a stomach, and thus did Jonathan translate מִלְעֻמַתהַבֶּטֶן (7: 20) ‘against the place of attachment.’ And the height of these two bowls was four cubits, and this is what he said (7: 19) “lily work in the porch four cubits.” These [bowls] were decorated inside with the likes of flowers of lilies, in the same manner of decorations which were on the wall of the porches. [This occupied] four cubits [of the five cubits] in height, and the fifth cubit was a small chapiter on [top of] the big one. This is what was said (7:2) “And there were chapiters above [also] upon the two pillars.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="Above also… over against the belly: ">which is beyond the net-work, at the end of the net-work, at its rim, that is at the middle, at the place where it is attached, that the upper net-work is attached to the bowl which is beneath it.</text>
      <text title="And the pomegranates were two hundred: ">Pomegranates made in two rows around, strung together on a chain and encompassing the network.</text>
      <text title="Upon each chapiter: ">This, too, is an abbreviated sentence. [It means,] ‘On the one, and likewise, on the second.’</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="And upon the top of the pillars was lily work: ">A half cubit at the top of each pillar its wall was as thin as a lily, and the rest of the pillar its thickness was four fingers and hollow. Therefore, this cubit was not counted [a half cubit of each pillar] in the description of the pouring of the brass for the pillars in Chronicles II (3:15) because it was not similar to the work of the rest of the pillars.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="Ten cubits from brim to brim: ">Through the middle, since the diameter of every round object is through the middle.</text>
      <text title="And a line of thirty: ">This is what was said: All that have three handbreadths in its circumference have one handbreadth in its diameter. [Here, too,] its circumference was thirty and its diameter ten, and from its midst he pressures [this].</text>
      <text title="The height thereof: ">[Meaning] its depth. And in Chronicles II (4:6) he says that he made it for the priests to bathe in [when they are unclean and] to immerse [themselves] in it [for ritual purification].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="And… there were knops: ">Jonathan rendered וּפְקָעִים : and the form of eggs.</text>
      <text title="Under the brim: ">The knops were located in the lower three cubits which were square, for so did we learn in the tractate Eruvin (14b) “The three lower ones were square and the two upper ones were round,” and it will be impossible for you to contain two thousand measures (of בת) (7:26) which equal one hundred and fifty ritual baths of purity containing forty measures (of סאה) [in each], except in this manner explained by our Sages in Eruvin. It is impossible to say the upper ones were square and the lower ones round, for it is written “its brim was round all about” (7:23) [indicating it was the top which was round]. He, therefore, says by these knops “for ten cubits compassing the sea round about” because in the place that it was square, a perimeter of forty cubits has ten cubits on each side, but in the place that it is round it is impossible to say it has ten cubits on each side around.</text>
      <text title="The knops were cast in two rows, when it was cast: ">Everything, [the sea and the knops,] was poured together. [It was] not [made in a manner] that he attached the knops to it after they had been poured, through nails or through soldering which is called soldedure; soudure in O.F.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="And all their hinder parts: ">Of these oxen.</text>
      <text title="Were inward: ">Their hinder parts were facing towards the bottom of the sea, the three which were in the north towards those in the south, and those in the east towards those in the west.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="And it was a hand-breadth thick: ">[At] its bottom and its walls, except that at its edge it was thin and beaten out and hammered, wrought like the brim of a cup which we drink from, and decorated with flowers and lilies.</text>
      <text title="Two thousand measures: ">Six thousand measures of סְאָה are found to be one hundred fifty ritual baths of purity. Four thousand measures equal one hundred ritual baths, and the two thousand equal fifty ritual baths. And even were you to divide everything according to the measurements by which the Sages measured, a cubit squared by three cubits high for each ritual bath, you will find it to be the same. [The lower part of] the [sea was] three cubits [high by ten cubits] square, [which] equal [one hundred square cubits equaling] one hundred ritual baths. [The upper part of] the [sea was] two cubits [high and] round [with a diameter of ten cubits and contained sufficient water for] fifty ritual baths since the square is greater than the circle by one quarter. And in Chron. II (4:5) it is written “it contained three thousand measures” ? Our Rabbis explained it refers to a dry measure, since the overflow was one third of the capacity of the receptacle.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="And three cubits its height: ">of the base. The height of the wheel upon which it rests was a cubit and a half, and the height of the base was a cubit and a half. The cubit of the height was square but the half cubit was round, as it says (7: 35) “And in the top of the base there was a round compass of half a cubit high.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="They had borders: ">I saw in the Mishnah of Forty-Nine Measurements (See 7:16).</text>
      <text title="They had borders: ">The borders were from the axle of one wheel to the axle of the other wheel. And יַד הָאוֹפָן is the wood which is inserted into the wheel, in the hole, and it is called ajjsel, essieu in O.F. (axle). And the four wheels of the bases had borders on this side and borders on the other side, on all four sides; and it was four cubits wide between one and the other, and above there were blocks, such as boards against the borders, and the ledges were from the lower borders to the upper ones, [since] there were other borders between the ledges, like the work of the legs of the bed of the villagers which are not round but protruding (should read בּוֹלֵט) in order to decorate them with lions and cherubim. And I say, that these ledges were like the rungs of a ladder, a sort of brass rods standing on the borders. There were two or three rods. The borders were set between one rod and the other, [connected] from one ledge to the other. Jonathan, too, rendered this שליביא, ledges.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="And on the ledges which were between the borders: ">Were decorated with forms of lions, forms of oxen and cherubim.</text>
      <text title="And on the ledges there was a base: ">כֵּן is a base, to place the laver on it, above the border which was on their top.</text>
      <text title="And beneath the lions and oxen: ">Which were embroidered or attached on the [outer] borders which were between the ledges.</text>
      <text title="Wreaths: ">a form resembling a male and female joined together.</text>
      <text title="Of thin work: ">Hammered, resembling the hammering of a thin metal plate. They did not protrude with its thickness nor were they engraved in a depression, and Jonathan rendered מוֹרָד לוֹיוֹתמַעַשֵׂה, ‘joined, the work of a welder’, souldriz in O.F.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="And four wheels: ">Two in the front and two in the back of the manner of the large wagons.</text>
      <text title="And tablets of copper: ">Jonathan rendered וְנִסְרִין דִנְחַשׁ [boards of brass,] they are the upper boards which were against the borders.</text>
      <text title="Tablets: ">Heb. סַרְנֵי is like נְסָרִים.</text>
      <text title="And the four corners thereof: ">Of the כֵּן which was above them.</text>
      <text title="They had undersetters: ">They protruded above the boards in the corners of the כֵּן. And under the laver which rested upon the כֵּן the undersetters were molten, [not soldered.] (Other editions have: this teaches us, that the undersetters came from the כֵּן in one pouring, and the undersetters supported the laver so that it should not fall down through the כֵּן.)</text>
      <text title="At the side of each were wreaths: ">At the side of each of the undersetters there was a joining of a male and female decorated. מעבר איש is like איש אל אחיו, “One to another” (Exodus 25:20) which is said by the cherubim. [Here too איש means ‘each one.’</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="And the mouth of it within the chapiter and above was a cubit: ">The mouth of the כֵּן extends outward of the mouth of the chapiter and goes upward a cubit high. And the chapiter is the roof [of the base]. The base is made resembling a hat, sloping on all sides, and in the center a round hole is set, one and one half cubit wide in diameter, and around that hole a resemblance of an enclosure of a fence one half cubit high around. And thus is this explained further on (7:35) in this subject, as it is said, “And in the top of the base there was a round compass of half a cubit high” and that is called “the mouth” of the chapiter. And the כֵּן rests on that enclosure, and the bottom of the כֵּן is inserted into the mouth of the enclosure, and protrudes one cubit above it. And this is what he said here, “And the mouth of it within the chapiter and above was a cubit.”</text>
      <text title="And the mouth thereof was round after the work of a base: ">And the mouth of the chapiter was round as the example of the כֵּן, which was round at the bottom.</text>
      <text title="A cubit and a half: ">Its width in diameter.</text>
      <text title="And also upon its mouth were gravings: ">Forms of flowers.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="And the four wheels were underneath the borders: ">Since the borders [reached] from the axle of one wheel to the axle of the other wheel as I have explained [previously].</text>
      <text title="And the axeltrees of the wheels: ">That is the wood which is inserted into the wheels and is called essieu in O.F. (axle).</text>
      <text title="Were in the base: ">The axles were joined and melted to the base in one pouring.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="Was like the work of a chariot wheel: ">Jonathan renders, as the work of the wheels of a chariot, a wheel within a wheel crosswise, as he said in Ezekiel (10:10) in [reference to the vision of the heavenly chariot.</text>
      <text title="Their axeltrees: ">Essieu moyeux in O.F.</text>
      <text title="And their naves: ">Bojjols in O.F., they are the holes for the axles.</text>
      <text title="And their felloes: ">They are the enclosures around, which bind them together.</text>
      <text title="And their spokes: ">The arms of the wheels which are attached from the holes of the wheel to the other rim, which is called rajjs; rais in O.F.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="And there were four undersetters: ">As I have explained above (7:30) “and the four corners thereof and undersetters,” and he did not mention it here except to say “the undersetters were of the base itself.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="There was a round compass of half a cubit high: ">This is [a reference to] the partition, as I explained above, (7:31), which was around the opening [on top of the base], and the [uppermost] cubit [of the chapiter] was square.</text>
      <text title="And on the top of the base its ledges: ">They are the tablets of brass which were mentioned above. (7:30).</text>
      <text title="And its borders were one piece of it: ">The lower borders were poured together with it [and was therefore all one piece], and he did not attach them afterwards.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="And he graved on the tablets, on its ledges and on its borders: ">On the lower ones. On both of them, [on the ledges and on the borders,] he engraved and inscribed cherubim, lions (and palm trees, this is not [found] in other editions).</text>
      <text title="According to the attachment of each with wreaths: ">He engraved around the likeness of a male and female that are joined by their arms, thus did our Sages explain this.</text>
      <text title="According to the attachment: ">The word במער is an expression of attachment and joining, as a male which is coupled with a female, and its meaning is ‘a man and his attachment.’ According to its ordinary sense, לוֹיוֹת is an expression of attachment; soldore in O.F. This will be translated as ‘there were attachments that were made as the joining of a man,’ and the joining was in the manner we explained [at the beginning of this comment].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="One casting: ">As he cast the first base, he similarly cast them all. The following is an explanation from the author of ‘The Temple Structure’:</text>
      <text title="And the work of the base was in this manner: ">He made four copper wheels as it says (7: 30) “And each base had four copper wheels” as the form of a large wagon. And the height of each wheel was a cubit and a half. And the work of the wheels was like the work of a chariot wheel, a wheel within a wheel, so that he may be able to move them wherever the spirit or will may be to move them there, and move them without being necessary to turn it over this way or that. And the distance which is from one wheel to the next from east to west was four cubits and likewise from north to south, for it was square, not long like our wagons. And this is what he said, (7:27) “four cubits [was] the length of the base, and four cubits the breadth thereof.” A thick and long rod was inserted into the two wheels which were from east to west, the northern ones. And so also, as in those wheels which were in these, a rod placed and inserted in those which were from the north to the south, the eastern ones, and so also in the western ones. And the verse called these rods יָדוֹת, and this is what he said וִידוֹתֵיהֶם And the meaning of וְגַבֵּיהֶם, that is the hub of the wheels in which these rods turn. And they are called גַב, a little hill, because that is the highest part of the wheel when it is lying on the ground. And likewise the hub of all round objects is its highest point, because all sides are drawn from it. And the meaning of וְחִשֻׁקֵיהֶם, they are the outer circles which bind together חִשֻׁרֵיהֶם which are the thing pieces of wood, resembling arms, which are inserted and placed from the hub to the rim, and this is from the expression, “and their fillets were of silver” (Exodus 27:10), and that is the wheel which rolls on the ground, and we are accustomed to make a circular piece of metal around it and it is called in the language of the Mishna in Chpater XI of the Tractate Kelim סוֹבֵב שֶׁל גַּלְגַל but here the סוֹבֵב was not necessary, because it was all made of copper. And מִסְגָרוֹת means a sort of tablet was made for them above the axles in the four corners in a square, and this is what he said “and their borders were foursquare not round” (7:31) and they enclosed the wagon on its four sides, [and was] therefore called מִסְגָרוֹת, enclosures. And on these borders or enclosures were boards of copper נְסָרִים which the verse called סַרְנֵי נְחוֹשֶׁת and this word סַרְנֵי is a word of disarranged letters. And on them, that is, on the outside and not on top, it was made as the rungs of a ladder; and between one rung and the other [there were] other borders, and on them was the form of oxen (7:29). And the boards went up beyond the borders until it [reached] opposite the height of the wheels, [they were continuously] sloping like a pointy hat and resembling the covering of a covered wagon, until they reached opposite the height of the wheel, and there they were drawn together until they covered it, except above the center they did not cover, but there was a round hole in them. Its diameter was a cubit and a half. This covering was called כּוֹתֶרֶת and the hole which is in it הַכּוֹתֶרֶת פִּי and this is what he said (7:31) “and the mouth thereof was round after the work of a base, a cubit and a half.” And around this hole a partition goes up a half cubit in height, and this is what he said (7:35) “and in the top of the base there was a round compass of half a cubit high.” And into this partition the כֵּן is entered and inserted, for the כֵּן is a receptacle which receives the laver, since the laver is inserted into the כֵּן and the כֵּן is in the midst of this partition which is on the wagon. And the lower half cubit of the כֵּן was round in the same measurement of the height of the partition which is on the round hole which is in the base on top. And the כֵּן rises above this partition one cubit, and this what was said, (7:31) “and the mouth of it within the chapiter and above was a cubit.” And therefore, we have three cubits in the total height of the base, since the wheel was a cubit and a half, and the round partition was a half cubit, and the cubit which the height of the כֵּן protrudes over it, and this cubit is square. And it had four undersetters in its four corners, and this is what the verse said, (7:34) “and there were four undersetters at etc. of each base, the undersetters were of the base itself,” because the lower part of the laver was slanting at the bottom so that it should fit into the כֵּן and in order that it should not fall into it more than the desired amount, therefore these undersetters were made, to carry and support it. This ends the quotation of ‘The Temple Structure.’</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="38">
      <text title="And he made ten lavers: ">It is written in Chron. II (4:6) “such things as belonged to the burnt offering they washed in them.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="39">
      <text title="On the side of the house: ">Against the right side of the house.</text>
      <text title="On the right side of the house: ">It [was in the southeast corner,] extended [along the eastern wall,] from the south side toward the north side. And the following is: קֵדְמָה מוּל נֶגֶב, the northeast corner against the space which is between the northern wall of the house and the wall of the court. And the northern wall [alone,] is called מִמוּל נֶגֶב, extended and removed far away from the south, and מוּל and מִמוּל are not translated the same.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="40">
      <text title="And Hiram made etc.: ">And Rebbi said, the כִּיוֹרוֹת and the סִירוֹת (7:15) are one and the same, [meaning pots or pans,] as we read in the Scriptures, “like a pan of fire among wood” (Zecharia 12:6) and likewise “and he struck it into the pan” (Samuel I 2:14).</text>
      <text title="The lavers: ">They were of copper, [and were used] to remove the ashes therein from the altar.</text>
      <text title="The shovels: ">copper shovels which they call, vedil and shauffel in Germany. They were used to rake the ashes with them into the pots.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="42">
      <text title="Two rows of pomegranates: ">[There were] one hundred pomegranates in each row hanging by chains.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="46">
      <text title="Did the king cast them: ">He melted them and poured them according to their form.</text>
      <text title="In the thick clay: ">[As the Targum renders:] בְּעוֹבֵי גִרְגַשְׁתָּא in the thickness of the clay.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="47">
      <text title="And Solomon left: ">He refrained from weighing the weight of these vessels because there were very many, and [therefore] ceased to count their weight.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="49">
      <text title="Five on the right side and five on the left: ">It is impossible to say [these] five were on the right side of the entrance and [the other] five were on the left of the entrance, for if so, we will find a candlestick on the north side and the Torah states, [specifically, the candlestick should be] on the south side of the tabernacle. Therefore, Moses’ [candlestick] was in the middle, five on its right [side] and five on its left.</text>
      <text title="And the flowers: ">Of the candlestick.</text>
      <text title="And the lamps: ">[These are] the cups into which the oil and wicks are put.</text>
      <text title="And the tongs: ">With which the wick is lifted out of the oil.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="50">
      <text title="And the bowls: ">some type of musical instruments, and similarly, מְזַמְרוֹת [means musical instruments].</text>
      <text title="And the basins: ">To receive the blood.</text>
      <text title="And the spoons: ">[To serve] as the vessels for frankincense.</text>
      <text title="And the censers: ">[These were more in the form of a shovel or rake] to remove the ashes [from the altar], and [to rake] the coals and carry them from the outer altar, the מִזְבֵּח ַהַנְחוֹשֶׁת [in the court of the priests,] to the inner altar, the מִזְבֵּח ַהַזָהָב [in the temple, in order] to burn incense.</text>
      <text title="And the hinges: ">[These were] keys, I heard [that these were used] to open with them the locks [of the temple].</text>
      <text title="For the doors of the inner house: ">Which is the most Holy of Holies [only the hinges were of gold, whereas the doors were of wood overlaid with gold].</text>
      <text title="For the doors of the house: ">which is for the temple, all of their entrances were of gold.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="51">
      <text title="The things which David his father had dedicated: ">That which remained of the silver and gold dedicated by his father [he put into the treasuries of the house of the Lord]. But the Midrash explains that Solomon did not wish to use any of those dedicated materials for the construction of the house. And I heard from scholars of Israel who said [the reason was] because David knew [through prophetic inspiration] that eventually it would be destroyed. [David himself, therefore, begged that his materials should not be used,] so that the idol worshipping nations should not be able to say their idols are mightier for they took their revenge upon the house which was built of the [vast] plunder and destruction which David plundered from them. And others say [that the reason for his refusal was because] Solomon said thus; there was a famine in the days of his father for three consecutive years, and he should have squandered these dedicated materials to sustain therewith the poor people of Israel.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="8">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="The princes of the fathers’ houses of the children of Israel: ">[Literally, to the children of Israel, but translated] of the children of Israel.</text>
      <text title="Out of the city of David: ">David had placed it there when he brought it [back] from the house of Obed-edom (Samuel II 6:12).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="In the Month Ethanim: ">Jonathan rendered [these words] בְּיֶרַח הָאֵיתָנִים בֶּחָג as follows: ‘In the month which the ancients called the first month, on the festival, and at present it is the seventh month,’ i.e., since the Torah was given, and it is written in reference to the month of נִיסָן that it is the first of the months, so תִּשְׁרֵי will then be called the seventh [month].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="And the tabernacle of meeting: ">Which Moses made [in the desert, and was in Gibeon until now], And Solomon stored this away as soon as the first temple was built, [in the upper story which was above the temple and the Sanctuary,] as we have learned in the Tosefta of the tractate Sota (13:1).</text>
      <text title="Which were in the tabernacle: ">which David pitched for the ark.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="Under the wings of the cherubim: ">Those which Solomon made, which are standing on their feet on the ground [and facing the temple.] And these are not the cherubim of the cover which was on the ark.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="Over the place of the ark: ">[Their wings were spread] from wall to wall as he said above on this subject (6:27).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="The ends of the staves were seen: ">In the curtain which was against the entrance [of the sanctuary in the אמה טרקסין. You might think they tore through the curtain and protruded [on the other side]. The text, therefore, states “and they were not seen without.” How is this possible? They were pushing and bulging similar to two breasts of a woman, as it says, “he lies between my breasts” (Song of Songs 1:13).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="When the priests came out of the holy place: ">When the priests who carried the ark into the Sanctuary were leaving, the Divine presence immediately came to rest there.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="Then: ">When he saw the cloud, he said, Now I see that the Divine presence is in the house which I built, for thus did He promise to come and dwell in it from the midst of a cloud and thick darkness. And where did he say this promise? “For in the cloud will I appear upon the ark-cover” (Lev. 16:12). Thus is this taught in the Sifrei.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="For You to dwell in forever: ">And from the time that this [place] was chosen, it would no longer be permissible [to offer sacrifices] on any strange altars, [except those in the temple,] and the Divine presence no longer dwelled in any other place.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="Who spoke with His mouth: ">[He also told him] that he would grant him a son who would build the temple.</text>
      <text title="And has fulfilled it with His hand: ">He has fulfilled His word with His good power, lit. with His good hand.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="… Since the day, etc.: ">This is what He spoke to my father David.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="And Solomon stood before the altar of the Lord: ">[He was not always standing upright but kneeling, nor was he on the ground but on the laver, as] it is written in (Chronicles II 6:13): “for Solomon had made a copper laver, [of five cubits long, and five cubits broad,] and three cubits high, and had set it in the midst of the court, and upon it he stood, and kneeled down upon his knees [in the presence of all the congregation of Israel].”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="Who keeps covenant: ">He waits and stores away [the reward], to keep the covenant, and [which was based on] mercy, to fulfill His promise.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="Who has kept: ">שָּׁמַרְתִּי is an expression meaning fulfilling a promise [a reference to the promise that Solomon would built the temple].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="… will… indeed…?: ">Heb. האמנם, This is an expression of wonder.</text>
      <text title="cannot contain You: ">Heb. יְכַלְכְּלוּ [the root is יכול, to contain].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="If a man sins against his neighbor: ">One who is intimate with a married woman.</text>
      <text title="and an oath be exacted of him: ">curse [rather than oath]. Just as the water inspects her, so does the water inspect him.</text>
      <text title="shall be exacted of him: ">Heb. ונשא בו, an expression of נוֹשֶׁה, a creditor.</text>
      <text title="and he come and swear before your altar: ">As it says, “And the priest shall stand the woman before the Lord” (Num. 5:10).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="To bring his way upon his head: ">“And her belly shall swell, etc.” (ibid. 27).</text>
      <text title="And justifying the righteous: ">[By rewarding those who deserve it, as it says,] “Then she shall be cleared, and shall conceive seed” (ibid. 28). Thus is this explained in the Tosefta of the Tractate Sota (Chap. 1:3).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="And praise Your name: ">For our Sages said that a person is obliged to bless God for the bad as well as the good.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="so that You may answer them: ">The word כי here is used in the context of אשר, “so that.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="yellowing: ">Heb. ירקון, when the wheat does not grow up on the stalk to make an ear [on top].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="43">
      <text title="According to all that the stranger called to you for: ">And by the [request of] the Jew he says (v. 39), “and give to every man according to his ways” [indicating that he may occasionally be refused,] that is because the Jew recognizes and accepts God, the Holy One, may He be blessed, and he knows that He has the ability in His power to respond [favorably to his request, if God so wished;] and if his prayers will not be heard [and fulfilled], he will blame the matter on himself and his sins. But [if] the non-Jew would [experience the same frustrations he would] say, a house whose name and fame reaches to the ends of the world, and I have exhausted myself [traveling] on many roads, and I [finally] came [to this house] and prayed in it and I find no substance [nor significance] in it, just as there is no substance in idol worshipping. Therefore, [I beg You, said Solomon,] “according to all that the stranger called to you for,” but [as for] the Jew, if you see that he uses his wealth to destroy his friend, [then] do not give him [any].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="44">
      <text title="Toward the city: ">[while in the land of the enemy, they shall pray] facing towards Jerusalem.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="45">
      <text title="And maintain their cause: ">their vengeance against their enemy.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="51">
      <text title="The melting furnace of iron: ">An earthenware utensil used to purify gold of its impurities.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="56">
      <text title="According to all that he spoke: ">And where did he speak this? [As it is written], “And He shall give you rest from all your enemies [round about]” (Deuteronomy 12:10).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="59">
      <text title="that He sustain the cause of His servant and the cause of His people Israel: ">to avenge their humiliation from their adversaries.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="64">
      <text title="The same day the king consecrated the middle of the courtyard: ">These words are to be taken literally. This is Rabbi Yehudah’s view. [Solomon] hallowed the pavement of the court with the sanctity of the altar, in order to offer sacrifices on the pavement.</text>
      <text title="For the copper altar: ">[i.e., the stone altar] that Solomon constructed in lieu of the copper altar [of Moses].</text>
      <text title="was too small to contain the burnt offerings and the meal offerings: ">for they brought very many. Rabbi Jose said to him, Is it not already written (Kings 1:3), “One thousand burnt offerings Solomon offered on that altar which Moses had made,” and when one computes the number of cubits and the number of burnt offerings, [he will find that] this one of stones was larger than Moses’, for on Moses’ altar the place of the ‘maarachah,’ the place usually used for the sacrifice, was but one cubit by one cubit, whereas on this one the place of its ‘maarachah’ was twenty- four cubits by twenty-four cubits. Hence Solomon’s was 576 times as large as that of Moses. If so, what is the meaning of “the king consecrated the middle of the court?” It means that he set the stone altar into it, fastened to the floor.</text>
      <text title="was too small to contain: ">[According to Rabbi Jose] he is referring to that of Moses, like one who says to his friend, ‘So-and-so is a dwarf,’ meaning that he is disqualified to perform the sacrificial service.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="65">
      <text title="from the entrance to Hamath: ">which is in the north of Eretz Israel.</text>
      <text title="to the Brook of Egypt: ">which is opposite it in the south, as is delineated in the section entitled אֵלֶה מַסְעֵי (Num. 34:5-8).</text>
      <text title="seven days: ">of the inauguration</text>
      <text title="and seven days: ">of Succoth. It is found that they ate and drank on Yom Kippur.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="66">
      <text title="for David His servant: ">to make known that He had forgiven him his sins, as we find in Moed Katan (9a): When Solomon wished [to bring] the Ark into the Holy of Holies, the gates clung to one another.</text>
      <text title="and for Israel His people: ">that He forgave them the sin of Yom Kippur, and a Bath-Kol [heavenly voice] emanated and declared: All of you are prepared for the life of the World to Come.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="9">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="and My eyes and My heart shall be there at all times: ">Jonathan rendered: And My Shechinah shall dwell there if My will is done.</text>
      <text title="And My eyes and My heart shall be there: ">if My heart and My will are there.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="and this house which I have made sacrosanct for My Name: ">There is a condition between Me and You, “If you heed not…” What is stated there? “I shall make desolate your sanctuaries” (Lev. 26:31).</text>
      <text title="and a byword: ">As the Targum renders: וּלְשׁוּעִי and for a topic of conversation. They will tell [about the] evils [that] have befallen them and will scoff at them. Just as וַיְסַפֵּר“and he told” (Gen. 37:9) the Targum renders וְאִשְׁתָּעֵי. The expression שְׁנִינָה too is an expression of speech, as in וְשִׁנַּנְתָּם לְבָנֶי “And you shall repeat them to your children” (Deut. 5:7).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="And this house will be exalted: ">as long as you have not sinned. And from the time you will sin, every passerby will be astounded and will hiss. And so it is written in Chron II 7:21: “And this house that was exalted by everyone who passed by it…” And this is its interpretation: And this house that was exalted and revered even by the gentiles, as is stated above: “And also to the gentile who is not of Your people…” (Chron. II 6:32), now in its destruction, everyone who passes by it, even the gentiles, will be astounded and will hiss, and will say that the Jews’ sins were the cause.</text>
      <text title="will be astounded: ">יִשֹּׁם in Heb. will wonder, like “… and your enemies will wonder (ושממו) about it.” (Lev. 25:32. Also, “Concerning his day the later ones will wonder (נשמו) ” (Job 18:20).</text>
      <text title="and will hiss: ">siffler in French. Such is the habit of anyone who suddenly sees desolation, to hiss.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="Twenty years: ">i.e., seven years for the Temple, and thirteen years for his own palace, as mentioned above 6:38, 7:1.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="had supplied Solomon: ">An expression of bearing, i.e., he bore his burden in this matter.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="the land of Cabul: ">A land of chains; i.e., a muddy land into which the foot sinks and is entrapped.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="And this is the matter of the tax levy: ">delineated at the end of this topic (below v. 20- 21).“All the remaining people… of them did Solomon raise a levy of forced labor.” This tax levy was to build therewith all these [structures].</text>
      <text title="and the Millo: ">Heb. מלוא, a place that was in Jerusalem, in the city of David, that was called Millo, since it was enclosed by a low wall and was filled (מלא) with dirt.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="a gift: ">a dowry.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="And Tadmor in the desert in the land: ">near civilization.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="the store-cities: ">cities of storehouses.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="These were the commanders of the officers: ">That is to say, those who were appointed subordinate to the officers who were in overall command.</text>
      <text title="five hundred fifty: ">Three hundred of them were proselytes appointed over the 70,000 who bore burdens and the 80,000 hewers in the mountains, and the 3,300 who bore rule over the people, as stated above: “Besides Solomon’s chief officers… three thousand and three hundred” (5:30). And in II Chron. (2:1) it is stated: “six hundred.” These three hundred that are missing here (5:30), he counted there, for they were appointed over all of them. The two hundred and fifty remaining were Israelites appointed over the other laborers. In II Chron. (8:10) he counted them separately: “And these were Solomon’s chief officers two hundred fifty who bore rule over the people who did the work.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="But Pharaoh’s daughter: ">who was originally in the city of David, as it is stated in the beginning of this book (3:1): “and he brought her to the city of David.”</text>
      <text title="came up from the city of David: ">… In Chronicles (II 8:11) Scripture explains: “… for he said, A woman shall not live with me in the city of David (the exact wording is: ”… in the house of David, king of Israel.“) for they [the entire city and all the houses] are holy, for the Ark of the Lord was brought in to them.”</text>
      <text title="then he built up: ">i.e., Solomon.</text>
      <text title="the Millo: ">(See above v. 15) to build within it houses for her manservants and maidservants. Concerning this Jeroboam admonished him, saying: Your father left it open for the pilgrims, and you enclosed it to make a labor force for Pharaoh’s daughter. This is [the inference of] “But” mentioned here. But in this did Solomon sin. So have I heard. I say, however, But Pharaoh’s daughter… i.e., the above mentioned cities were necessary to build for store- cities, for chariots, for riders, and for greatness. But, the Millo he did not build for any greatness, for his father had left it for the pilgrims to pitch their tents therein, but since Pharaoh’s daughter had gone up to her house, and the Millo was adjacent to that house, then he built up the Millo.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="upon the altar: ">i.e., the altar of the Temple.</text>
      <text title="and burning upon it, upon the altar that was before the Lord: ">And that incense altar that was before the Lord for the burning of incense.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="King Solomon made a ship: ">[The usual word is אֳנִיָה] a ship.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="10">
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="and his ascent by which he would go up to the Temple of the Lord: ">A passageway that he had prepared from his house to the Temple, by which he would go up to the house of the Lord.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="almog wood: ">corail in French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="a path to the House of the Lord: ">[lit. a support.] In II Chron. 9:11 it is written, מְסִלּוֹת, paths to the House of the Lord. I, therefore, say that this מִסְעָד, support, is an expression of a pavement.</text>
      <text title="to accompany the vocalists: ">for the Levites.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="And King Solomon gave the queen of Sheba: ">This giving refers only to the teaching of wisdom.</text>
      <text title="all her wish: ">He cohabited with her and Nebuchadnezzar was born to her. He later destroyed the Temple that had stood 410 years in the territory of the twelve tribes.From the Arizal.</text>
      <text title="aside from what he gave her: ">Gifts and delicacies that are found here and are not in her place.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="Six hundred sixty-six: ">Hiram gave him 120 talents (v. 14). The Queen of Sheba, 120 (v. 10), the ships of Tarshish brought from Ophir 420, totaling 660. I do not know from where the other six came. In Chronicles (II 8:18) it stated that the ships brought from Ophir 450 talents, however it does not include the 120 talents of Hiram. We can resolve the contradictions [by saying] that the extra 30 were from the 120 of Hiram. because Hiram’s servants were in Ophir with his [Solomon’s] servants.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="Aside from [that which came through] merchants: ">the merchants who traversed the land on business would bring to him.</text>
      <text title="And the spice peddlers: ">Dealers of spice would carry them from city to city.</text>
      <text title="and all the dependent kings: ">Heb. וכל מלכי הערב. Jonathan Translates: מלכי סומכותא, and all the dependent kings, an expression of guarantee. Kings who granted support and were dependent on him; garantie in French.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="body shields: ">Heb. צנה, a body shield that encircles the person from three sides. This is the meaning of the verse in Psalms (5:13), “You shall encompass him with will like a shield (כַּצִנָּה).”</text>
      <text title="six hundred [dinar of]: ">Six manehs, for a piece of gold (זָהָב) is a dinar [and one hundred dinars total one maneh].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="malleable gold: ">It is soft and easy to flatten out.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="glittering gold: ">Heb. זהב מופז, which sparkles like diamonds.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="six steps: ">steps by which to ascend onto it, and the top of the throne was circular, i.e., the place of the king’s seat.</text>
      <text title="from behind: ">The steps were to the front and to the width. To the back was the seat, a round place, higher than the throne.</text>
      <text title="and arms on both sides: ">on which to support his arms, like two gold rails from corner to corner, extending on the right and on the left.</text>
      <text title="and two lions: ">of gold. The entire plan of the throne is described in the Aggadah of the Book of Esther.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="none was of silver, [since] it was reckoned with as nothing: ">Lit. there was no silver; it was not reckoned… i.e., there was no silver in any of them because it was not reckoned.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="Ships of Tarshish: ">Ships of Africa.</text>
      <text title="ivory and monkeys and peacocks: ">Elephant tusks, monkeys and peacocks.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="one thousand seven hundred chariots: ">It is stated [that Solomon had] one thousand four hundred [chariots]. I say that one thousand four hundred were in the chariot cities and [the remaining] three hundred were with the king in Jerusalem. And this is the explanation [of the verse] in Chron.: “And he stationed them (i.e., the 1,400) in the chariot cities and with the king”; [i.e., with the king] there were other chariots in Jerusalem. While here this is the explanation: And he led them (i.e., the 1,400) in the chariot cities, and with the king; i.e., with the king were some of them in Jerusalem.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="as stones: ">Our Rabbis explained that one refers to the time before Solomon wedded Pharaoh’s daughter, and one refers to the time after Solomon wedded Pharaoh’s daughter.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="The source of Solomon’s horses: ">[was] from Egypt. The assemblage of horse merchants was in Egypt. Solomon’s merchants bid and bought the rights from the king of Egypt, that no person could export horses from there except through them. Therefore, there is a ‘Zakef Gadol’ on the word ‘Mikvei,’ to denote that the word ‘Mikvei’ [stands by itself, and] is not connected with the following words.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="and a horse for one hundred fifty: ">We deduce that a chariot consisted of four horses. And so for these prices to all the kings of the Hittites and to the kings of Aram.</text>
      <text title="through them: ">Through Solomon’s merchants did they export them from Egypt.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="11">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="and Pharaoh’s daughter: ">She too was one of the foreign women, but since she was beloved by him more than all of them, she was counted separately. Similarly, (II Sam. 2: 30) “… and there were missing of David’s servants nineteen men and Asahel.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="Then did Solomon build a high place: ">Our Rabbis said, Since he did not protest against his wives, it is referred to on his name.</text>
      <text title="on the mountain that is before Jerusalem: ">The Mount of Olives.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="For as this has been with you: ">i.e., you knew that you were transgressing My precept.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="And it was when David was in Edom: ">Then Hadad fled before David and Joab.</text>
      <text title="to bury the slain: ">for they buried the slain of Edom. This is what is referred to in the Book of Samuel (II 8:13): “And David made for himself a name when he returned from smiting the Edomites,” for all were praising him as a kind man who buried his slain. And so Scripture says concerning the wars of Gog and Magog: (Ez 39:13) “And they will bury all the people of the land, and it will be for them for a name.” [However,] Jonathan [translated]: לְחַלָצָא יַתקְטִילַיָא, to strip the slain, to take their clothing.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="and assigned then sustenance: ">He said to his attendants, So much bread shall you give him every day.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="the queen: ">Heb. הגבירה, lit. the mistress.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="That David slept with his fathers: ">concerning David who died a natural death, an expression of sleeping is mentioned, whereas concerning Joab who was killed, [an expression of dying is mentioned (Eccles. R. 7:1; Mid. Shmuel)]. Another explanation is that concerning David who was survived by a meritorious son who took his place, an expression of sleeping is mentioned, whereas concerning Joab who was not survived by a meritorious son who took his place, no expression of [sleeping is mentioned, but an expression of dying].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="And God raised up against him an adversary,: ">against Solomon. Now this is what Nathan the prophet said to David (Sam. II 7:14) so that when he goes astray, I will chasten him with the rod of men.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="with the evil that was caused by Hadad: ">Together with the evil that was perpetrated by Hadad, was also this evil of Rezon.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="raised his hand against the king.: ">He rebuked him in public.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="And this was the matter: ">concerning which he rebuked him.</text>
      <text title="Solomon built up the Millo: ">and with this building he closed up the breach behind the Millo. He said to him, Your father made breaches in the wall for the pilgrims to enter, and you fenced it in, to create a labor force for Pharaoh’s daughter, to station there her manservants and maidservants.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="and Solomon saw: ">prior to this.</text>
      <text title="that he was a diligent worker.: ">Lit. that he was doing work. Quick in his work and diligent.</text>
      <text title="Over all the burdens of the house of Joseph: ">Over all the taxpayers of the house of Joseph [Targum Jonathan], Manasseh and Ephraim, since he was from the tribe of Ephraim.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="a kingdom: ">Heb. ניר, a kingdom. ניר is an expression of a yoke.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="39">
      <text title="but not for all times.: ">For in the days of the Messiah the kingdom will be restored to him. In Seder Olam (ch. 15) I found: “I shall afflict David’s descendants because of this. Corresponding to the thirty-six years that Solomon was married to Pharaoh’s daughter, for he married her during the fourth year of his reign. Corresponding to this, the decree was promulgated on the kingdom of the house of David to be divided. The kingdom should have been restored, however, in Asa’s time, in the sixteenth year of his reign, but he sinned by sending a bribe to the king of Aram (below 15:18), and did not depend on the Most Holy, Blessed be He. This is the meaning of that which is stated in Chronicles (II 16:1). In the thirty-sixth year of Asa’s reign Baasha built the high place.” This is impossible, since Asa buried Baasha in the twenty-seventh year of his reign (i.e., Baasha died in the twenty-seventh year of Asa’s reignI Kings 15:33). Rather, the sixteenth year of his reign, Scripture calls “the thirty-sixth,” for they are the end of thirty-six years from the division of the kingdom, and Scripture tells us that in that year Asa sinned. Thus we explain: “But not for all times,” [but thirty-six years].</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="12">
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="My little finger is thicker than my father’s loins: ">Heb. קטני, my little finger.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="scorpions: ">aiguillon in French, a goad or sting [called so] because they sting like scorpions.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="Now see your house: ">The Temple that you built, will be for you alone.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="And King Rehoboam sent Adoram: ">He was Adoniram [mentioned above in 5:28].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="and the tribe of Benjamin: ">Who were situated on the border, for the boundaries of Judah and Benjamin were adjacent.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="When this people goes: ">Sitting in the Temple court is not permitted except for the kings of the house of David only. Therefore, he [Rehoboam] will be seated and I will be standing. Moreover, in the year following the Sabbatical Year, at the time of the Assembly, he will read the portion relating to the king, for he is the king of his province, whereas I will be like the rest of the people, and will, therefore, find myself degraded.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="even until Dan: ">at the end of the boundary of the land.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="in the eighth month: ">He expounded to them that this was the month of ingathering, and was, therefore, the proper time for the festival to be [celebrated].</text>
      <text title="that he had fabricated from his heart: ">Heb. אשר בדא מלבו, an expression of falsehood (controver in O.F., to invent).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="13">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And behold a man of God: ">This was Iddo.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="Altar, altar: ">[Both the one] that is in Beth-El and [the one] that is in Dan.</text>
      <text title="and human bones: ">[This refers to the bones] of Jeroboam, but the prophet dealt him respect.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="And he gave a sign on that day: ">The prophet gave a sign on the day on which he prophesied. This is your sign: the altar will split by itself and the ashes will be spilled to the ground.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="And his hand… became stiff: ">The Holy One, Blessed be He, avenged the honor of a righteous man more than [He avenged] His own honor. [When] he was standing and offering sacrifices to pagan deities, his hand did not become stiff, yet because of the disdain for the righteous man his hand became stiff.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="your God: ">but not my God. He was still in a state of rebellion.</text>
      <text title="and it was as before: ">standing and burning sacrifices to idols.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="and dine: ">and eat.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="And an elderly prophet: ">a false prophet.</text>
      <text title="sojourning in Beth-El: ">He was not from there but from Samaria. So it is stated in the section dealing with Josiah (II Kings 23:18). And they saved his bones with the bones of the prophet who had come from Samaria.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="to the prophet: ">the false prophet.</text>
      <text title="who brought him back: ">Who brought back the man of God. From here they deduced that offering refreshment is a great thing, for it causes the Shechinah to rest on the prophets of the Baal.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="And he called: ">The old prophet called the man of God.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="for the prophet whom he had brought back: ">[i.e., for the prophet] whom this one had brought there, for the man of God to ride upon.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="in his grave: ">[i.e.,] in the graveyard belonging to the false prophet in the city.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="For the thing… will come to be: ">[i.e., the prophecy mentioned above in v. 2] and human bones they will burn upon you. Perhaps his bones will rescue my bones.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="After this thing: ">that he saw this wonder and heard the words of the prophet, he, nevertheless, did not return. And our Rabbis expounded: After the Holy One Blessed be He grasped him by his garment and said to him, Repent and I and you and the son of Jesse will stroll in Paradise.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="14">
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="biscuits: ">Heb. ונקדים. A type of parched grain, dried in an oven. They make flour from it to make it into a dish known in the language of the Gemara as ‘shethitha.’</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="she was disguised: ">as though she were not this one.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="I am sent to you: ">from the Holy One Blessed be He with a harsh message.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="male child: ">Jonathan renders: One who knows knowledge; one who places [wisdom or counsel] into the walls of his heart.</text>
      <text title="those who are restrained and those who are free: ">Heb. עצור ועזוב. עצור is one who has someone restraining his hand, similar to “This one shall rule over (יעצור) My people” (Sam. 9:17). ועזוב means one who has no one restraining his hand.</text>
      <text title="as one expunges: ">As the one who [consumes food to make] it eventually into dung, so will I expunge after him until he is completely consumed.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="a good deed: ">For he absented his watch, for his father had stationed him as a sentry so that no man would go up on the pilgrimage festivals. Instead, he absented his watch and he himself went up.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="who will cut off the house of Jeroboam this day, and also those who will be born from now on.: ">[Those] who are already born to him this day, and those who are destined to be born to him from now on. So did Jonathan render.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="the city that the Lord had chosen: ">Yet, even so…</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="And Judah did what displeased the Lord: ">and they did not pay attention to this.</text>
      <text title="and they angered Him: ">Heb. ויקנאו [usually used in the sense of jealousy or zeal but here is] an expression of angering.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="And they too: ">[like the other] tribes.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="Shishak the king of Egypt: ">We find in Midrash Shir Hashirim: This was Pharaoh Neco. He was called Shishak because all his life he longed for (שוקק) the ivory throne that belonged to Solomon his son-in-law. Now, he went up and took it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="and he took everything: ">the throne that was dearer to him than everything.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="the runners would carry them: ">before him in honor. Afterwards, they would return them to the chamber where the runners were always stationed.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="15">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And in the eighteenth year of King Jeroboam: ">One year after Rehoboam’s death. Now in the twentieth year of Jeroboam, Asa reigned. The third year of Nadab [Abijam] is counted for King Asa as a year, and for him it is also counted.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="and he abolished the adulterers: ">Jonathan renders: And he abolished the prostitutes.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="from being queen: ">Heb. מגבירה, [lit. from queen,] from being queen.</text>
      <text title="for she had made a frightful image: ">Our Rabbis stated: [מפלצת is a combination of] מפליא ליצנותא, it carried lasciviousness to an extreme. She made for it a phallic symbol, and she would copulate with it every day.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="The high places he did not remove: ">The private high places upon which they had become accustomed to sacrifice to Heaven since Shiloh had been destroyed until the Temple was built, when the high places were permissible, were not removed now. Even though they were forbidden when the Temple was built and the people were punished by premature death because of it.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="without exception: ">[lit. no one was exempt.] Even a bridegroom concerning whom it is stated (Deut. 24:5) “He shall be free for his house one year.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="two years: ">the second and the third year of Asa.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="During the third year of Asa, king of Judah, Baasha the son of Ahijah, reigned: ">The third year of Asa is counted for Nadab and Baasha.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="16">
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="Nevertheless, in the hand of Jehu the son of Hanani, the prophet, was the word of the Lord concerning Baasha: ">As though to say: Behold Elah reigned. Nevertheless, the word of the Lord was already in the hand of Jehu that his kingdom would not last.</text>
      <text title="and because he had slain him: ">Since he too, committed the same sins, [lit. went in his sins,] it is found that he should not have slain him. He was, therefore, punished for his murder. So do we find in Hosea (1:4), “And I will visit the blood of Jezreel upon the house of Jehu.” Since they did not turn away from Ahab’s ways, they were punished for their murder.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="captain of half his chariots: ">He and another were captains over the chariots.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="any males: ">nor his kinfolk nor his friends.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="And Tibni died: ">When Asa took Omri’s daughter in marriage for Jehoshaphat his son, they killed Tibni, when they saw Omri’s importance. In Seder Olam (Ch. 17).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="In the thirty-first year of Asa… Omri ruled: ">a complete, [uncontested,] reign. Five years was [the duration] of his conflict with Tibni, from the twenty-seventh year of Asa until the thirty-first.</text>
      <text title="twelve years: ">was the total, five years in conflict and seven with a complete reign. It is impossible to say [that he reigned] twelve years uncontested, for Ahab his son reigned in the thirty-eighth year of Asa.</text>
      <text title="in Tirzah he ruled six years: ">while he had not yet built Samaria.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="and worshipped the Baal: ">in addition to Jeroboam’s calves.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="And Ahab made the Asherah: ">a tree that was worshipped.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="Hiel the Bethelite: ">Heb. ביתהאלי, similar to “Jesse the Bethlehemite (ביתהלחמי)” (I Sam. 16:1), and it does not say הביתלחמי. And so, “Joshua the Bethshemeshite (ביתהשמשי)” in the Book of Sam. (I 6:14), and not הביתשמשי, and so, “In Ofrah of the Abiezerites (אבי העזרי)” (Jud. 6:25), and it does not say, האבי עזרי. Some interpret ביתהאלי [from the word אלה, a curse,] since he accepted upon himself Joshua’s curses, “Cursed be the man… that rises up and builds…” (Jos. 6:26). Our Rabbis stated, Hiel was of the tribe of Benjamin, and Jericho belonged to Jehoshaphat [king of Judea]. Why does Scripture relate him to Ahab [king of Israel]? For a curse is related to a cursed one.</text>
      <text title="with Abiram his firstborn he laid its foundation: ">When he laid its foundation, his firstborn son died, and he buried him and continued to bury all his sons until the last one died when he erected the portals. Now, these were Joshua’s curses, “With [the loss of] his firstborn shall he lay its foundation, and with [the loss of] his youngest son shall he set up its gates” (Jos. 6:26).</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="17">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And Elijah the Tishbite: ">from a land named Toshav.</text>
      <text title="As the Lord… lives: ">Why was this placed here? For Elijah and Ahab went to console Hiel in his mourning. Said Ahab to Elijah, Is it possible that the disciple’s curse was fulfilled while Moses our teacher’s curse was not fulfilled, as it is said: (Deut. 11:15) “And you will turn and worship other gods, and bow down to them, the Lord’s wrath will be kindled against you, and He will shut up the heaven.” Now, all Israel are worshipping idols, and the rains are not being withheld. Immediately, Elijah… said…</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="and hide: ">from Ahab and Jezebel.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="the brook dried up: ">in order that that he know the necessity of rain and trouble himself to go into exile, for it was displeasing to the Holy One, Blessed be He, that Israel should live in hunger.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="to Zarephath: ">the name of a city.</text>
      <text title="Behold I have commanded there: ">in My household that a widow shall feed you there.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="Please take to me a little water: ">He did not recognize the widow concerning whom the Holy One, Blessed be He, had told him. He learned from Eliezer, the servant of Abraham, (Gen. 24:15), and said, The one who gives me water is the widow.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="a cake: ">Heb. מעוג [like עוגה, a cake].</text>
      <text title="[nothing] but a handful: ">Jonathan rendered: the palm of a handful.</text>
      <text title="in a flask: ">bouteille in French, [a bottle,] as it is stated regarding Saul, “the jug (צפחת) of water that was at his head” (I Sam. 26:16).</text>
      <text title="and we will die: ">From then on, we will die of hunger.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="but first make for me a small cake: ">There is a Midrash Agadah in Gen. Rabbah (why he wanted his cake first) on the verse: “And Leah said, ” Good fortune has come" (Gen. 30: 11).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="the son of the woman: ">became ill in order that he should need the key of Resurrection of the dead, as it is stated at the end of the Agadah of chapter Chelek (San. 113a).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="18">
      <text title="to cause my sin to be remembered: ">Before you came, the Heavenly Tribunal would weigh my deeds and the deeds of the people of my city, and I was worthy of a miracle. Since you have come, here, I am not counted as anything since my righteousness is not noticeable And similarly, concerning Lot Scripture states: “And I am not able to flee to the mountain” (Gen. 19:19) to Abraham, for my merit will not be remembered in comparison to his.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="And he prostrated himself: ">Heb. ויתמודד, from an expression of מדה, a measure, i.e., he prostrated himself upon him.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="18">
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="And it was when Jezebel cut off: ">[Scripture] comes to tell [us] how Obadiah feared the Lord.</text>
      <text title="fifty men in a cave: ">[i.e., fifty men in one cave] and fifty men in another cave.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="and we will not lose all our beasts: ">all our beasts will not be cut off from us.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="to kill me: ">as he goes on to explain (v. 12) “And a wind from the Lord will carry you to a place I know not where.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="that they did not find you: ">[i.e., he made them swear] that the nation was unable to find you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="two ideas: ">two thoughts, for you do not know to decide who is God.</text>
      <text title="and if the Baal: ">is God, go after him.</text>
      <text title="And the people did not answer him a word: ">because they did not know to distinguish.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="26">
      <text title="that he gave them: ">For he slipped away from them lest he be offered to the idol. He escaped under the skirt of Elijah’s cloak. He said to him, Go! Through both of you the Omnipresent will be sanctified.</text>
      <text title="and they hopped on the altar that they had made: ">Jonathan renders: And they raved. They were dancing according to their custom, on their altars.</text>
      <text title="and they hopped: ">Heb. ויפסחו, like ויפסעו, and they stepped.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="for he is a god: ">for you say he is one to be feared.</text>
      <text title="Perhaps he is talking or he is pursuing: ">Perhaps he is having a conference with his advisors now, or he is overtaking and pursuing his enemies in war.</text>
      <text title="or he is on a journey: ">to the water closet.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="and gashed themselves: ">an expression of tearing [the flesh] with an instrument. Such was their custom.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="and they feigned to prophesy: ">and they raved.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="and he repaired the torn down altar of the Lord: ">He built an altar and reminded Israel that the altar of the Lord should enter their thoughts and should be spoken of with fluency, for it was torn down and destroyed and its name and its mention had ceased from the mouth of all the ten tribes. Thus I heard its simple interpretation. And its Midrashic interpretation I have heard, that Saul built an altar on Mt. Carmel. That is what [Scripture means when] it states: (I Sam. 15:12) “Saul has come to Carmel, and behold, he is setting up a place,” and there (Gen. 33:20) it says: “And he set up an altar there.” [By a gezerah shavah, analogous expression, we deduce that Saul too, set up an altar]. And the kings of Israel tore down all the altars and high places in their land that were made in the name of Heaven, and Elijah built this altar of Saul that was torn down.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="31">
      <text title="to whom the word of the Lord came, saying, “Israel shall be your name.”: ">Why is this stated here? Because on the day that the Shechinah was revealed to Jacob in Bethel and called him Israel, on that day He said to him, “A nation and a congregation of nations will be from you” (Gen. 35:11). Your children are destined to congregate like other nations and build an altar to burn sacrifices on it during the time when the high places are proscribed. Nevertheless, I will consent to it (Gen. Rabbah 82:6).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="a trench: ">fosse in French.</text>
      <text title="as great as would contain two se’ah: ">Its width was as great as to hold two se’ah, one hundred cubits by fifty cubits like the court of the mishkan.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="pitchers of water: ">to make the miracle greater.</text>
      <text title="and pour: ">Elisha poured on his hands, and his fingers became like springs, and the trench became full. This is the meaning of what is stated (II Kings 3:11): “Here is Elisha the son of Shaphat who poured water on Elijah’s hands, and a miracle took place with the water through him.” He is fit that a miracle should take place with water through him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="36">
      <text title="and at Your word I have done: ">that I sacrificed on a high place at the time of the prohibition of high places.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="Answer me, O Lord, Answer me: ">Answer me with fire, answer me with rain. So did Jonathan render this. Our Rabbis, however, said: Answer me with fire, answer me that they do not say that these deeds were accomplished by sorcery.</text>
      <text title="shall know that You are the Lord: ">and I am Your servant, and when You send me to bring them tidings [of the forthcoming redemption], they will believe me if You answer me today.</text>
      <text title="and You have turned their hearts backwards: ">You have given them a place to turn away from following You, although You were able to direct their hearts toward You. And according to Midrash Agadah, if You do not answer me, I will deny and say, You turned their hearts. And so did Moses say (Num. 16:29), “If these people die the death of all men, I, too, will deny and I will say that the Lord did not send me to speak [the words of] the Torah and the commandments,” and so said Micaiah (below 22:28), “If you return safely, God did not speak through me.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="39">
      <text title="The Lord is God: ">and the Baal is not God.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="42">
      <text title="and he crouched on the ground: ">And he crouched on the ground to pray for rain.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="43">
      <text title="toward the sea: ">If you see a cloud ascending from the sea.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="44">
      <text title="Hitch up and descend: ">Hitch up your chariots and descend quickly from Mt. Carmel, to return to your house, lest the rain oppress you on the way.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="45">
      <text title="Meanwhile: ">While the messenger went, and while he hitched up the chariot, the heavens grew dark.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="46">
      <text title="And a spirit of strength from the Lord: ">A spirit of strength from before the Lord. He became invested with strength to run before the chariot on foot, so that Ahab would not go alone, for he paid regards to royalty.</text>
      <text title="and he girded his loins: ">Heb. וישנס, like ויאזר, yet there is no similar word [in the Bible], and even this one came only to teach us an expression of quickness, i.e., he was as quick as a strong man.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="19">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="So may the gods do: ">as you have done to the prophets of the Baal.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="4">
      <text title="genevrier: ">or genievre in French, a juniper tree.</text>
      <text title="and requested that his soul die: ">He said, EnoughMy long life is enough. Until when will I be confused like this?</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="coals: ">Heb. רצפים, charcoal, and similarly, (Isaiah 6: 6) “and in his hand was a coal (רצפה).”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="to the cave: ">That is the cleft of the rock where Moses stood (Ex. 33:22).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="They have torn down Your altars: ">The private high places that were built in the Name of Heaven, for the altar of the Temple was in Jerusalem.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="and a great… wind: ">A camp of angels of the wind.</text>
      <text title="an earthquake: ">A camp of angels of earthquake.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="a fire: ">A camp of angels of fire.</text>
      <text title="a still small sound: ">A voice of those praising quietly, but concerning the prophets of the nations, Scripture states: (Job 4:16) “Silence and a voice I hear”; there was silence to the praising, but I heard the voice coming out of the silence, retentissement in O.F., resounding, but no one heard the voice itself.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="he wrapped his face: ">Jonathan renders: כריך אפוהי, and so Scripture says: “wrapped in a garment (לוטה בשמלה)” (I Sam. 21:10).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="you shall anoint to be prophet in your stead: ">I do not want your prophecy since you plead for the prosecution of My children.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="Elisha will kill: ">We do not find that Elisha killed anyone except the forty-two children through the bears in Jericho (II Kings 2:24).</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="Go, return: ">from following me.</text>
      <text title="for what have I done to you: ">that you should follow me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="he cooked the meat for them: ">Heb. בִּשְׁלָם הַבָּשָׂר. The mem of bishelam [is usually indicative of the direct object, to be rendered,] he cooked them. [In this case, however, since the object is] habassar, [the meat, we render:] he cooked for them the meat, so Dunash and Menahem (Machbereth Menahem, p. 48) explain, and so did Jonathan render this in two words. [‘bashilu lehon,’ he cooked for them.] I say, however, that it is unnecessary to divide it into two words [i.e., to add the preposition to]. Now what is the meaning of בִּשְׁלָם הַבָּשָׂר ? He cooked the two oxen, their flesh; [i.e., he cooked them, viz. their flesh.] For the yoke is no fewer than two. [Therefore the plural suffix is used.]</text>
      <text title="and he gave the people: ">Out of great joy, he made a feast.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="20">
    <pasuk id="5">
      <text title="As I have sent to you, saying, Your silver… you shall give to me.: ">As I have sent to you… you will give to me I know that you will give to me, but another thing I am decreeing upon you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="6">
      <text title="anything you prize: ">[lit. anything desirable to your eyes.] Now were not the first things desirable things? What, then, is the meaning of “anything you prize” ? This means a prize within a prize [i.e., a possession prized more than any other prized possessions.] This is the sefer Torah, concerning which it is written, “… that are prized more than gold and much fine gold” (Ps. 19:11). Said Ahab to himself, He demands a great thing. This is not mine alone; this belongs to the elders of Israel. He, therefore, summoned all the elders of the land. Even though they worshipped idols, they respected the Torah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="10">
      <text title="if the earth will suffice for the footsteps: ">[Jonathan renders:] To take with the footsteps of all the people who are with me, i.e., earth that adheres to the sole of the feet for the footsteps. לשעלים is an expression of treading with the sole of the foot, similarly, (Num. 22:24) במשעול הכרמים, “in a path between the vineyards.” And similarly (Is. 40:12): מי מדד בשעלו מים, “Who measured the water with his step,” for he trod in the Sea of Reeds, as it is stated: (Hab. 3:15) “You trod in the sea with Your horses.”</text>
      <text title="will suffice: ">Heb. אם ישפק, if there is enough.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="11">
      <text title="Say, One who girds himself with the sword shall not boast as one who unties the sword: ">Say to him, One who girds himself and goes down to war shall not boast like a man who has been victorious and is coming up from it. One who girds his sword to go down to war, who does not know whether he will be victorious or not, should not boast.</text>
      <text title="as one who ungirds the girdle of his sword,: ">who has already come up from the war victorious. Similarly, your master should not boast concerning a future thing.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="12">
      <text title="Lay on: ">the implements of siege against the city.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="a certain prophet: ">That was Micaiah the son of Imlah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="14">
      <text title="With the youths of the governors of the providence.: ">They are the hostages for all the princes of the other nations would give their children into his custody lest they rebel against him.</text>
      <text title="Who will commandeer the war?: ">Who will array [the battle] to command it.</text>
      <text title="You: ">You go forth first and so you shall kill him. [According to Shem Ephraim, the reading is:] And you shall not wait, and you shall array [the battle].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="seven thousand: ">I say that they are the ones concerning whom Scripture stated (above 19:18), “all the knees that did not kneel to the Baal, seven thousand.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="16">
      <text title="in the pavilions: ">that they had made for themselves because of the sun.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="22">
      <text title="at the return of the year: ">at the time of the end of the year.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="and place officers in their place: ">Since they are not of a highborn family, they will endeavor to exert themselves in order to find favor.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="if we will not overpower them: ">i.e., and you will see if we will not overpower them.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="and provisioned: ">provided with supplies for the war; they armed themselves with weapons and all necessities of war.</text>
      <text title="and provisioned: ">they were sustained.</text>
      <text title="like two flocks of goats: ">Heb. עזים חשפי, flocks of goats, although there is no comparison [in the Bible]. Menahem, however, classifies this with the expression of revelation, like (Gen. 30:37) מַחשּׁוף הלבן“laying bare the white”; (Is. 47:2) חשפי שבל “uncover your locks.” The expression of revelation fits with flocks of goats, like (Song of Songs 4:1) “… who bared Mt. Gilead.” When they come down from the mountain, it is bared [or revealed].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="28">
      <text title="and said to the king of Israel. And he said: ">Said R. Johanan: Every place wherein it is stated, And he said… and he said, must be expounded. The first saying [refers to what] he said to him, “… I will deliver all the great multitude into your hand…” The second saying [alludes to an admonition that], “if Ben-Hadad falls into your hands, show him no clemency.” Therefore, when he took pity on him, he said to him (v.42) “Since you released the man I had designated for destruction…”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="33">
      <text title="took it for an omen, and they hastened and caught it from him: ">Heb. יְנַחֲשׁוּ is an expression of divining. They said: Since words of peace fell from his mouth, even inadvertently, it is a good sign, and they hastened to confirm the matter.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="And he said to him: ">i.e., Ben-Hadad said to Ahab, The cities that my father took from your father Omri, I will return to you.</text>
      <text title="and you shall make streets for yourself in Damascus: ">and rule therein, although it is the capital of my kingdom.</text>
      <text title="as my father had made in Samaria: ">your city against your will. He was saying all this out of fear. Said Ahab to him, And I will, with this treaty, release you.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="Strike me now: ">This sign was bad for Ahab, for the prophet said to him by the word of the Lord to kill Ben-Hadad, and he did not kill him. Also, this one to whom the prophet said by the word of the Lord, “Strike me,” and he did not strike him, just as He punished him, he would punish Ahab.</text>
      <text title="By the word of the Lord: ">The Holy One, blessed be He, said that you shall strike me.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="37">
      <text title="and wounding him: ">[He struck him] a wounding blow.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="38">
      <text title="and he disguised himself with his headband: ">He changed his headband so that they would not recognize him. Any change of clothes is an expression of disguise.</text>
      <text title="with his headband: ">Heb. באפר. Jonathan rendered this במעפרה, [that is] a headband.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="39">
      <text title="and behold, a man turned aside: ">from the road to me.</text>
      <text title="and he brought to me a man: ">a prisoner of war.</text>
      <text title="if he will be missing: ">If he escapes, an expression similar to (Num. 31: 49) “and no man was missing from us (ולא נפקדו) ”; an expression of a lack.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="40">
      <text title="and he was gone: ">He ran away.</text>
      <text title="you have pronounced it: ">Either your life or a talent of silver.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="42">
      <text title="the man whom I designated for destruction: ">the man of My war, an expression of חרם, strife. Now, the expression of strife fits with war, and similarly, (Is. 34:5) “… on Edom it will descend and on the nation with whom I war (חרמי).” [Thus we render, “the man with whom I war.” [According to the] Midrash Aggadah: Many traps and nets have I spread for you until he fell into your hand.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="43">
      <text title="sad and upset: ">Heb. סר וזעף. [Jonathan renders:] נסים ודוי, his spirit turned away from him. [These are expressions of sadness.] His spirit turned away from him.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="21">
    <pasuk id="1">
      <text title="And it was after these happenings: ">[lit. after these things,] still another incident to bring his death close.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="its worth: ">[lit. the worth of this, i.e.,] the worth of this vineyard.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="to the elders: ">wicked and ignorant elders, elders of shame.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="9">
      <text title="Proclaim a fast: ">On a fast day it was their custom to search for the sins in their hands.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="13">
      <text title="Naboth cursed: ">Heb. ברך, [lit. blessed, a euphemism for קללה,] curse. The Targum renders: Naboth blasphemed against God and cursed the king.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="Get up and take possession: ">Some of our Sages say that the property of those executed by the king belong to the king. And some of them say that he [Ahab] was the son of his [Naboth’s] father’s brother. He killed him and his children [as well], and was therefore fit to inherit his [property].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="20">
      <text title="you sold yourself: ">You sold yourself to anger your Creator. Heb. התמכרך, you sold yourself [reflexive form] like (Deut. 28:68) והתמכרתם, “and you will sell yourselves there to your enemies.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="23">
      <text title="in the valley of Jezreel: ">Heb. חל, the Aramaic translation of valley.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="25">
      <text title="But there was none like Ahab: ">The Scripture testifies concerning him that there was none among the kings like him, for Jeroboam and all those after him worshipped the calves out of fear that if the people would go up to Jerusalem, the kingdom would return to the house of David, but this one [Ahab] added the Baal and the Asherah to anger God.</text>
      <text title="sold himself: ">was sold to idolatry. I saw in Yerushalmi that Hiel was his counselor, and every day he [Hiel] would estimate his [Ahab’s] value and he [Ahab] would give it to the pagan deities.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="27">
      <text title="and put sackcloth on his flesh, and he fasted: ">he walked barefoot.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="29">
      <text title="I will not bring the disaster: ">i.e., the disaster of his house I will not bring in his days, but the decree that the dogs will lick his blood is impossible to come in the days of his son, but upon him.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
  <chapter id="22">
    <pasuk id="2">
      <text title="in the third year: ">since he had released Ben-Hadad.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="3">
      <text title="and we do nothing: ">We are lazy [siamo pigri in Italian].</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="7">
      <text title="Is there no other prophet of the Lord here?: ">I have a tradition that no two prophets prophesy with one expression, and these are all saying the same expression.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="8">
      <text title="only bad: ">For he said to me, Since you released the man whom I designated for destruction…</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="15">
      <text title="Go up and triumph: ">He did not say it to him in the name of the Lord.</text>
      <text title="and may the Lord deliver it: ">If only the Lord deliver it into the king’s hand.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="17">
      <text title="These have no master: ">You alone will perish in the war, as it is stated below (v. 31), “Do not battle with great or small, except with the king of Israel only.” Even though it was stated, (above 20: 42) “and your people instead of his people,” the drop of blood that came out of the righteous man, Micaiah, whose friend struck him, striking and wounding him, was an atonement for all Israel. So it is explained in the Aggadah.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="19">
      <text title="On His right and on His left: ">Now is there left in Heaven? It is not stated, (Ps. 118:16) “The right hand of the Lord is exalted; the right hand of the Lord does valiantly” ; (Ex. 15:6) “Your right hand, O Lord, is mighty with power; Your right hand, O Lord, dashes the foe” ? But rather, the passage means that these would stand on the right and these would stand on the left. Those who stand on the right present the case for the defense and those who stand on the left present the case for the prosecution.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="21">
      <text title="And a certain spirit came forth: ">The spirit of Naboth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="24">
      <text title="Which did the spirit of the Lord pass: ">Which way did it pass? This is an abbreviated verse. In II Chron. 18:23, it is written: “which way (דרך) did… pass.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="30">
      <text title="And the king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, I will disguise myself and go into battle: ">[lit. disguise and go into battle. He told Jehoshaphat of his plans] to disguise himself and go [into battle]. I will disguise myself I will change my regal garb, lest they recognize me, for if they recognize me, they will turn to me to attack me.</text>
      <text title="and you wear your regal garb: ">that you are wearing, for you are not the king of Israel, but the king of Judah, and with you they have no conflict.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="32">
      <text title="and Jehoshaphat cried out: ">to the Holy One, Blessed be He.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="34">
      <text title="A man drew: ">This was Naaman.</text>
      <text title="innocently: ">not knowing that he was the king of Israel.</text>
      <text title="between the scales and the coat of mail: ">Some coats of mail are made of layers of scales, in the manner it is stated (I Sam. 17:5) “and a coat of mail,” and the scales fall on the holes of the coat and close them, and they are called דבקים.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="35">
      <text title="was standing in the chariot: ">He exerted himself to remain standing so that the Israelites would not become aware of his wound and flee, for flight is the beginning of defeat.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="38">
      <text title="and the dogs licked his blood: ">I say that Naboth was killed there, for the prophet said, “In the place that the dogs have licked the blood of Naboth…” (21:19).</text>
      <text title="and they washed the weapons there of the blood: ">Jonathan rendered it in this manner. Our Rabbis said, [however, rendering ‘zonoth’ as harlots,] “Ahab was a cold person [who disliked sexual relations” (San. 39b)]. Therefore, Jezebel made for him the image of two harlots in his chariot to stimulate him. [When the chariot was washed, these two images were washed in the pool of Samaria.]</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="39">
      <text title="the ivory palace: ">Heb. ביתהשן, lit. the palace of the tooth, i.e.,] elephant tooth.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="45">
      <text title="Jehoshaphat made peace with the king of Israel: ">Since there was war between Assa his father and Baasha the king of Israel, it was necessary to say this.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="47">
      <text title="The remainder of the prostitutes: ">who fornicated in public.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="48">
      <text title="There was no king in Edom: ">Since the time of David, the governor was the king This was written here because in the days of Jehoram his son who sinned, in his days Edom rebelled and crowned a king for themselves, but in the time of Jehoshaphat they were still subordinate to him.</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="49">
      <text title="since the ships were broken: ">Since he joined Ahaziah in this undertaking, therefore, they were broken. And so did the prophet say to him in II Chron. (20:37), “Because you have joined a wicked man (sic), the Lord has caused a breach in your undertaking.”</text>
    </pasuk>
    <pasuk id="52">
      <text title="in the seventeenth year of Jehoshaphat: ">Some wonder about this verse, since it is stated concerning Ahab that he reigned twenty-two, and concerning Jehoshaphat it is stated that he became king in the fourth year of Ahab. It is found that Ahab’s rule ended in the nineteenth year of Jehoshaphat. Yet here [Scripture states that Ahaziah became king in the seventeenth year of Jeohshaphat. However, I searched and found that concerning most kings of Israel [Scripture] is not exact in the number of their years, and if one became king at the end of a year, he counts it at the beginning, but he does not count it elsewhere. Therefore, I say that “in the fourth year of Ahab” (v. 41) that is mentioned in reference to Jehoshaphat’s becoming king, does not count with it Ahab’s first year. And so you find in the majority of cases. Also, the year in which Jehoshaphat became king is not included in these seventeen years.</text>
    </pasuk>
  </chapter>
</book>